<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4927105</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0157754</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-16-09916</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Autoimmune Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Multiple Sclerosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Autoimmune Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Multiple Sclerosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Autoimmune Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Multiple Sclerosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurology</subject><subj-group><subject>Demyelinating Disorders</subject><subj-group><subject>Multiple Sclerosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurology</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurodegenerative Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Multiple Sclerosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Models</subject><subj-group><subject>Mouse Models</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Lipids</subject><subj-group><subject>Cholesterol</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Regulation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Nervous System</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroanatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Spinal Cord</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Nervous System</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroanatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Spinal Cord</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroanatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Spinal Cord</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Studies</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Models of Disease</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzymology</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzyme Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzyme Metabolism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterisation of Transcriptional Changes in the Spinal Cord of the Progressive Experimental Autoimmune Encephalomyelitis Biozzi ABH Mouse Model by RNA Sequencing</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Transcriptional Changes in the Progressive Experimental Encephalomyelitis Biozzi ABH Mouse Model</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4559-2460</contrib-id><name><surname>Sevastou</surname><given-names>Ioanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="currentaff001"><sup>&#x000a4;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pryce</surname><given-names>Gareth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Selwood</surname><given-names>David L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Medicinal Chemistry, UCL Wolfson Institute for Biomedical Science, London, WC1E 6BT, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label><addr-line>Neuroimmmunology Unit, Blizard Institute, Barts and the London School of Medicine and Dentistry, Queen Mary University of London, E1 2AT, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>David R.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Westmead Institute for Medical Research, AUSTRALIA</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>This study was partly funded by Canbex Therapeutics. There are no patents, products in development or marketed products to declare. This does not alter our adherence to PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: IS DLS. Performed the experiments: IS GP DB. Analyzed the data: IS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: IS GP DB DLS. Wrote the paper: IS DB DLS.</p></fn><fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff001"><label>&#x000a4;</label><p>Current address: Translational Research Office, UCL School of Life and Medical Sciences, London, W1T 7DN, United Kingdom</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>d.selwood@ucl.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e0157754</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2016 Sevastou et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sevastou et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0157754.pdf"/><abstract><p>Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a debilitating immune-mediated neurological disorder affecting young adults. MS is primarily relapsing-remitting, but neurodegeneration and disability accumulate from disease onset. The most commonly used mouse MS models exhibit a monophasic immune response with fast accumulation of neurological damage that does not allow the study of progressive neurodegeneration. The chronic relapsing and secondary progressive EAE (pEAE) Biozzi ABH mouse model of MS exhibits a reproducible relapsing-remitting disease course that slowly accumulates permanent neurological deficit and develops a post-relapsing progressive disease that permits the study of demyelination and neurodegeneration. RNA sequencing (RNAseq) was used to explore global gene expression in the pEAE Biozzi ABH mouse. Spinal cord tissue RNA from pEAE Biozzi ABH mice and healthy age-matched controls was sequenced. 2,072 genes were differentially expressed (q&#x0003c;0.05) from which 1,397 were significantly upregulated and 675 were significantly downregulated. This hypothesis-free investigation characterised the genomic changes that describe the pEAE mouse model. The differentially expressed genes revealed a persistent immunoreactant phenotype, combined with downregulation of the cholesterol biosynthesis superpathway and the LXR/RXR activation pathway. Genes differentially expressed include the myelination genes Slc17a7, Ugt8A and Opalin, the neuroprotective genes Sprr1A, Osm and Wisp2, as well as genes identified as MS risk factors, including RGs14 and Scap2. Novel genes with unestablished roles in EAE or MS were also identified. The identification of differentially expressed novel genes and genes involved in MS pathology, opens the door to their functional study in the pEAE mouse model which recapitulates some of the important clinical features of progressive MS.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="award001"><funding-source><institution>Canbex Therapeutics Ltd.</institution></funding-source><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Selwood</surname><given-names>David L.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by a Canbex Therapeutics grant awarded to DLS and the Technology Strategy Board UK/Innovate UK grant no. 25036-166159 awarded to DLS and DB. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="28"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All sequencing FASTQ files are available from the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database (accession number GSE78996).</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All sequencing FASTQ files are available from the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database (accession number GSE78996).</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a central nervous system disease that primarily affects young adults. MS has a median survival expectancy of 40 years after diagnosis [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], while patients start accumulating significant levels of disability early in disease progression, which adds a substantial burden to their everyday lives. MS is an immune-mediated disorder, characterised by demyelination and neurodegeneration [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The clinical presentation of MS is most commonly relapsing-remitting, but can also be primary progressive, where neurodegeneration and disability accumulate from disease onset. Over time relapsing remitting MS acquires a secondary progressive phenotype, with pathology accumulating between relapses [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Neurological symptoms in MS reflect focal inflammatory demyelinating lesions in the central nervous system that affect saltatory conduction in the affected sites [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Accumulating neurological disability is accompanied by disabling symptoms such as spasticity, tremor and muscle stiffness [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>The most commonly used mouse model for the study of MS is the experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE) model. This model has been extensively used in research, primarily in C57BL/6 mice immunised with myelin oligodendrocyte glycoprotein (MOG) peptide 35&#x02013;55. These mice exhibit a monophasic immune response with fast accumulation of neurological damage, rendering them as perhaps not the most suitable EAE model to study progressive neurodegeneration [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The SJL mouse strain is a strain that develops relapsing-remitting disease following active immunisation, and is thus useful for the study of immune responses that more closely compare to the human disease [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, the severe clinical disease and the low incidence of relapse in these mice makes it hard to study accumulating neurological disability. Thus existing mouse models do not always address the neurodegenerative processes that underlie primary or secondary progressive MS. The neurodegenerative component of MS remains a challenge and is currently untreated [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], in contrast to significant advances in controlling relapsing-remitting MS, which responds to immunosuppressive treatments [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Although the adaptive immune response drives relapsing disease and is sensitive to immune modifying drugs that act in the periphery to prevent new lesion formation and active attacks [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], progressive neurodegenerative disease is probably driven by innate inflammatory responses within the CNS, which are insensitive to current peripheral immunomodulatory drugs in both progressive EAE and MS [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Additionally, it has been demonstrated that neurodegeneration can persist beyond the elimination of clinical relapses in EAE [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], as occurs in relapsing MS also [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Therefore there is a need to develop novel neuroprotective therapeutic approaches to complement current immunomodulatory approaches. To address this challenge, the study of chronic progressive EAE models, where the underlying pathological chronic neurodegenerative mechanisms are present, is expected to provide valuable insight in disease pathophysiology and potential therapeutic targets.</p><p>The chronic relapsing and secondary progressive EAE Biozzi ABH mouse model of MS exhibits a reproducible relapsing-remitting disease course that slowly accumulates permanent neurological deficit, which is followed by progressive neurodegeneration and disability (pEAE), with associated residual signs of disease such as spasticity and tremor [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Histological studies of Biozzi ABH mouse spinal cord tissue reveal immune-mediated relapsing disease episodes that prime the CNS-microenvironment for persistent demyelination, gliosis, glial cell activation, axonal and neuronal loss [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Thus, the pEAE mouse model permits the study of mechanisms involved in the accumulation of neurological damage. Treatment of neurodegeneration is likely to be critical in the treatment of progressive MS so this Biozzi ABH mouse chronic model may provide a platform where strategies for neuroprotection and neurorepair can be evaluated.</p><p>In this study we used RNA sequencing (RNAseq) to explore gene expression in the spinal cord of the post-relapsing secondary progressive pEAE Biozzi ABH mouse model. During the post-relapsing pEAE disease stage the spinal cord is characterised by widespread demyelination, astrocytic gliosis, microglial activation and little to none immune infiltration [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. This hypothesis-free investigation of global gene expression aimed to characterise the genomic changes that describe this pEAE mouse model and to generate the complete transcriptome of the chronic, neurodegenerative EAE state. By studying the individual genes that were differentially expressed, as well as the pathways that were differentially regulated, we were able to better characterise the immunological, neurodegenerative and remyelinating components of the disease, as well as to propose genes and processes worth investigating further as potential therapeutic targets.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Animals</title><p>Adult (6&#x02013;8 weeks), pathogen-free male Biozzi ABH mice were bred at Queen Mary University of London. Methods of housing and other reporting elements relevant to the ARRIVE guidelines have been reported previously [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. All procedures were approved by the Queen Mary University of London Animal Welfare and Ethical Review Body and the United Kingdom Government Home Office Inspectorate. These studies where performed under Licence from the UK Home Office and conformed to the United Kingdom Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act 1986 for the use of animals in research and Directive 2010/63/EU.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>pEAE Induction</title><p>pEAE was induced in Biozzi ABH mice as described previously [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Briefly, young adult mice were injected subcutaneously with 1 mg freeze-dried mouse spinal cord homogenate in Freund&#x02019;s adjuvant on days 0 and 7. Animals developed relapsing-remitting episodes of limb paralysis with remission. Spasticity and slow deterioration of movement typically developed after 2&#x02013;3 relapses, &#x0223c;80&#x02013;100 d post-induction [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Pathology in this model is largely restricted to the spinal cord [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], so animal spinal cords were sampled during remission from active paralytic episodes associated with hindlimb paralysis and weight loss [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>RNA Extraction and Sequencing</title><p>Three post-relapsing chronic pEAE animals were sacrificed following the development of spasticity and tremor, at least 3 months after disease induction and after at least 3 clinical attacks as indicated previously [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Three age-matched control mice that did not receive an injection with spinal cord homogenate in Freunds adjuvant were also sacrificed. The spinal cord tissue was removed, snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at -80&#x000b0;C. Frozen tissue was disrupted in TRIzol<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Reagent on ice, using a rotor-stator homogeniser. Following 5 min incubation at room temperature, chloroform was added to the samples, which were shaken, left to rest and then centrifuged at 12000 g for 15 minutes. The resulting upper aqueous phase was washed with 70% ethanol, mixed well and loaded on an RNeasy column. Thereafter the Qiagen RNeasy<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Mini Kit protocol was followed to extract and purify mRNA. mRNA integrity was assessed by microfluidic capillary electrophoresis using the Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer. All samples had a 260/280 ratio &#x0003e; 1.8 with RNA integrity number (RIN) &#x0003e; 9. RNA samples were processed and sequenced at the UCL Genomics facility (UCL Institute of Child Health) using the Illumina NextSeq 500 platform. Library preparation was performed using the TruSeq Stranded Total RNA Library Prep Kit. 43 bp <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://topics.sciencedirect.com/topics/page/Shotgun_sequencing">paired-end sequencing</ext-link> was performed and approximately 18&#x02013;25 million reads were obtained per sample. The dataset can be found in the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO), accession number GSE78996.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>The FASTQ files generated for each sample were aligned to the UCSC <italic>Mus musculus</italic> mm10 reference genome using the TopHat2 software (Illumina). Downstream analysis of these alignments was performed using Cufflinks software (Illumina). Cufflinks computes normalised fragments per kilobase of exon per million fragments mapped (FPKM) which reflect the expression levels of each mRNA molecule [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The reads were mapped to a total of 23,352 genes and 30,608 transcripts. To calculate <italic>p</italic> values, Cufflinks uses the Cuffdiff 2 algorithm that estimates expression at transcript-level resolution and controls for variability across replicate libraries. The Cuffdiff 2 statistical algorithm is described in depth in [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The Cuffdiff 2 algorithm statistically analysed gene expression and produced a list of differentially expressed genes in the pEAE tissue samples. The statistical analysis resulted in <italic>p</italic> values corrected for multiple testing with a default false discovery rate (FDR) of q &#x0003c;0.05.</p><p>To generate a heatmap for comparison of gene expression between all samples the UCL Genomics facility (UCL Institute of Child Health) R-based pipeline was used. To compare the lists of differentially expressed genes in pEAE with other published sets of genes, publically available Venn analysis software was used (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfogp.cnb.csic.es/tools/venny/index.html">http://bioinfogp.cnb.csic.es/tools/venny/index.html</ext-link>).</p><sec id="sec007"><title>Ingenuity Pathway Analysis</title><p>Ingenuity pathway analysis (IPA, Ingenuity Systems<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ingenuity.com">www.ingenuity.com</ext-link>) was used to identify biological and molecular networks differentially regulated in the pEAE model. IPA is a source of gene-interaction based pathway analysis including canonical pathways and a knowledge database based on scientific findings. Statistically significant differentially expressed genes at least 2-fold upregulated or downregulated were imported and analysed in the IPA database. Based on the direct or indirect connectivity of genes as disclosed in the literature, genes were mapped onto biological pathways and disease networks. Fisher&#x02019;s exact test was performed to validate assignation of a biological function or disease to a network. Canonical pathway analysis was based on the identification of molecular pathways that are most significant for the dataset.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec008"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec009"><title>Differential Gene Expression Levels</title><p>The spinal cord tissue RNA sequencing resulted in approximately 18&#x02013;25 million reads per sample, which were aligned on the <italic>Mus musculus</italic> mm10 reference genome. This resulted in the identification of 23,352 annotated genes. Downstream statistical analysis of gene expression between control and pEAE samples (Cuffdiff) resulted in 14,373 genes successfully tested for differential expression (test status OK). Genes that were omitted from the analysis included genes with insufficient alignments for testing (NOTEST), too shallowly sequenced genes (LOWDATA), or genes with too many fragments aligned on the locus (HIDATA). It should be noted here that two genes, <italic>Mbp</italic> and <italic>Plp1</italic>, were not successfully tested due to a HIDATA return. These two genes are constituents of myelin, thus their involvement in this EAE model cannot be overlooked. They both had O FPKM in the control mice, but very high average fragment numbers (7939.56 and 2639.63 respectively) in the pEAE samples. Thus even though these genes are not included in the statistical analysis and the Ingenuity pathway analysis, they are included in the lists of highly upregulated genes. From the mapped genes, 2,072 were differentially expressed with a default false discovery rate (FDR) of q &#x0003c;0.05 (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c;0.0072). More specifically 1,397 genes were significantly upregulated (q &#x0003c;0.05) and 675 genes were significantly downregulated (q &#x0003c;0.05) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s002">S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s003">S2</xref> Tables). The differential gene expression in the pEAE samples compared with the control samples is visualised in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g001">Fig 1A</xref>. The MA plot presents the ratio of FPKM expression values between the two conditions. All 14,373 genes are presented in the plot with differentially regulated genes highlighted in colour. The volcano plot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g001">Fig 1B</xref>) presents the 14,373 genes, with genes with FDR &#x0003c;0.05 (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c;0.0072, -log <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c;2.1426) visualised in colour. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g001">Fig 1B</xref> the statistically significant genes with a larger that 2-fold change in expression are presented in red and are the genes selected for further analysis. The heatmap in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s001">S1 Fig</xref> demonstrates the hierarchical clustering within the three control and three pEAE spinal cord samples which represents the differential expression of significantly regulated genes between the control and pEAE groups.</p><fig id="pone.0157754.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0157754.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Identification of differentially expressed genes.</title><p>(A) MA plot representing the ratio of FPKM expression values between chronic relapsing secondary progressive EAE samples and control samples plotted against their average. All 14,373 genes are plotted with significantly regulated genes (q&#x0003c;0.05) plotted in red. (B) Volcano plot presenting the 14,373 genes, with genes over the significance cut off at <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c;0.0072 (-log <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c;2.1426) plotted in grey. The statistically significant genes with &#x0003e;2-fold change in expression are plotted in red.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0157754.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Differential Gene Expression Analysis</title><p>The list of highly upregulated genes with a fold change of more than 16 (log<sub>2</sub>&#x0003e;4) reveals a number of genes with established roles in inflammatory processes, such as antigen processing and presentation, cell chemotaxis and cell adhesion (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s002">S1 Table</xref>). This reveals a sustained inflammatory response in the spinal cord of the post-relapsing pEAE model, consistent with sustained microglial activity that remains following relapsing disease induced by the adaptive immune response [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. These findings are in line with the histological spinal cord studies during the progressive remitting stage of this EAE model, which have shown that the extensive immunoglobulin deposition and infiltration of macrophages, CD4<sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes, B lymphocytes and leucocytes described during relapses is greatly diminished [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and the remitting spinal cord tissue is characterised by widespread demyelination, astrocytic gliosis and persistent low grade microglial activation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>Additionally, a number of highly upregulated genes are genes involved in non-inflammatory biological functions, for example cell differentiation, proliferation, or ion transport. This list of genes is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0157754.t001">Table 1</xref>. The Gene Ontology biological processes that are implicated in neurodegeneration, remyelination and related functions for each gene are also listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0157754.t001">Table 1</xref>. Some genes with cell adhesion properties may also be implicated in regenerative, remyelinating processes so they are included in the list. Associations with chronic EAE processes, differentiation, de/remyelination, neurodegeneration and neuroprotection are also referenced in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0157754.t001">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0157754.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0157754.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Most significantly upregulated genes (&#x0003e;16 fold change) with non-immunological functions.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0157754.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0157754.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entrez Gene</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entrez Name</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">log<sub>2</sub> fold change</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic> value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene ontology processes associated with EAE</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association with chronic EAE processes, differentiation, de/remyelination, neurodegeneration, neuroprotection</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Mbp</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">myelin basic protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inf</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myelination</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myelin constituent. Highly upregulated during oligodendrocyte differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Plp1</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">proteolipid protein (myelin) 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inf</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myelination</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myelin constituent. Highly upregulated during oligodendrocyte differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Mmp12</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">matrix metallopeptidase 12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inf</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive regulation of epithelial cell proliferation involved in wound healing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extracellular protease expressed in active macrophages in MS lesions [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Involved in the pathogenesis of Theiler&#x02019;s murine encephalopathy, induces demyelination and neurotoxicity [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Mcoln3</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mucolipin 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inf</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auditory receptor cell differentiation, ion transport</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transient receptor potential channel (TRPML3) involved in endocytosis [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], localized to lysosomes and initiates neutralised lysosome exocytosis [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Atp6v0d2</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATPase, H+ transporting, lysosomal V0 subunit D2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inf</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP hydrolysis coupled proton transport</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulator of bone formation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], no identified role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Gpnmb</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycoprotein (transmembrane) nmb</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.09385</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell adhesion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upregulated in Lewis rat EAE [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and in an amyotrophic lateral sclerosis mouse model, proposed neuroprotective role [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Wisp2</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WNT1 inducible signaling pathway protein 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.21785</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell adhesion, cell growth regulation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Promotes neurite outgrowth in ganglioside deficient mice [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Plin4</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">perilipin 4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.82633</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipid storage regulation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein present in spinal cord, involved in lipid droplet storage [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Steap4</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STEAP family member 4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.37493</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ion transport</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Involved in osteoclast differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], no identified role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Ms4a7</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">membrane-spanning 4-domains, subfamily A, member 7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.34068</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No identified role. Associated with late-onset Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Gm4841</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>predicted gene 4841</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20993</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0007</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No identified role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Cybb</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome b-245, beta polypeptide</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.02298</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immune response, ion transport</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superoxide generating enzyme Nox2, implicated in microglial induced neurodegeneration [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Gpr65</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G-protein coupled receptor 65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.94688</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0026</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G-protein coupled receptor signaling pathway</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proton sensing TDAG8 receptor, involved in osteoclast regulation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Ch25h</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cholesterol 25-hydroxylase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.91766</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol metabolism</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed susceptibility gene for Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Proinflammatory enzyme, ch25h deletion attenuates EAE [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Sprr1a</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">small proline-rich protein 1A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60697</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0026</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Keratinocyte differentiation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein expressed after neuronal injury, involved in neuronal regeneration processes [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Ppl</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">periplakin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.55594</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0026</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abundant in the brain, opioid receptor interacting protein [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], no identified role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Xdh</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">xanthine dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4114</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell differentiation/apoptosis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xanthine oxidase, the metabolic product of xanthine dehydrogenase, is Implicated in EAE pathogenesis, axonal and myelin loss [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Wfdc17</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WAP four-disulfide core domain 17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.38813</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-neuroinflammatory microglial protein [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Osm</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">oncostatin M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30594</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0026</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immune response, peripheral nervous system development</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upregulated in relapsing-remitting MS patients [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], protective against demyelination in the Cuprizone-induced demyelination model [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Ms4a6d</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">membrane-spanning 4-domains, subfamily A, member 6D</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.26213</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No identified role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Rnf186</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ring finger protein 186</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0977</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0007</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No identified role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Gpr114</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adhesion G protein-coupled receptor G5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.09084</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00345</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G-protein coupled receptor signaling pathway</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No identified role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Tnfsf11</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tumor necrosis factor (ligand) superfamily, member 11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07763</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00275</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immune response, cell differentiation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoprotegerin ligand RANKL, important osteoclast differentiation factor [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Upregulated in MS patients [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Serpina3i</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">serine (or cysteine) peptidase inhibitor, clade A, member 3I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.05241</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No identified role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>B430306N03Rik</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RIKEN cDNA B430306N03 gene</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04922</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown protein.</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The list of most significantly downregulated genes with a fold change of more than 4 (log<sub>2</sub>&#x0003e;2), reveals that no genes are directly involved in inflammatory processes. Most of the genes downregulated are involved in the cholesterol biosynthesis and metabolism superpathway. The list of the downregulated genes and their possible involvement in pEAE is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0157754.t002">Table 2</xref>. The Gene Ontology biological processes that are implicated in neurodegeneration, remyelination and related functions for each gene are also listed, as well as associations with chronic EAE processes, differentiation, de/remyelination, neurodegeneration and neuroprotection.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0157754.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0157754.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Most significantly downregulated genes (&#x0003e;4 fold change).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0157754.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0157754.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entrez Gene</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entrez Name</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">log<sub>2</sub> fold change</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic> value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene ontology processes associated with EAE</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association with chronic EAE processes, differentiation, de/remyelination, neurodegeneration, neuroprotection</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Ttr</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transthyretin</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.43828</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00265</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retinol metabolic process, thyroid hormone transport</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Involvement in thyroxin transport, thyroxin promotes OPC differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], is protective in experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Slc17a7</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">solute carrier family 17 (sodium-dependent inorganic phosphate cotransporter), member 7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.25294</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport, synaptic transmission</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vesicle bound glutamate transporter (VGLUT1) localised in glutamatergic axon-OPC synapses and involved in myelination processes [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>A930006I01Rik</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RIKEN cDNA A930006I01 gene</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.47535</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown protein.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Idi1</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">isopentenyl-diphosphate delta isomerase</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.70827</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isoprenoid biosynthetic process</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol synthesizing enzyme, downregulated in A&#x003b2; treated neurons [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and rat spinal cord injury [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Hmgcs1</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-Coenzyme A synthase 1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.61103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol metabolism</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol rate limiting enzyme, negatively regulated in rat spinal cord injury [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] and in a dysmyelinating mouse model [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Induces OPC migration and myelination failure [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Fam216b</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">family with sequence similarity 216, member B</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.45922</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No identified role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Ugt8a</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDP galactosyltransferase 8A</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.40356</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myelination, lipid metabolism</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enzyme essential for myelination [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Depdc1b</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DEP domain containing 1B</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.403</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell migration</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Promotes cellular de-adhesion and mitosis [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>9630013A20Rik</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RIKEN cDNA 9630013A20 gene</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.34667</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0025</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-coding RNA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Mvd</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mevalonate (diphospho) decarboxylase</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.30806</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol metabolism</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enzyme involved in cholesterol metabolism.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Sc4mol</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">methylsterol monoxygenase 1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.25635</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipid metabolism</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enzyme involved in cholesterol metabolism and LXR signaling [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Opalin</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">oligodendrocytic myelin paranodal and inner loop protein</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.23362</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myelination</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myelin protein, located in paranodal loop membrane [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Cyp51</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome P450, family 51</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.17764</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol metabolism</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enzyme involved in cholesterol metabolism.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Slc5a11</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">solute carrier family 5 (sodium/glucose cotransporter), member 11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.13978</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ion transport</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose transporter implicated in immune modulation and apoptosis [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Ldlr</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">low density lipoprotein receptor</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.13576</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol metabolism</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Involvement in LXR-induced myelination in oligodendrocytes [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Aqp6</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aquaporin 6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.13396</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No identified role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Hmgcr</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-Coenzyme A reductase</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.12073</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol metabolism</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate controlling enzyme in cholesterol metabolism, upregulated in myelination [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], negatively regulated in a dysmyelinating mouse model [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Sqle</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">squalene epoxidase</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.11207</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol metabolism</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate limiting enzyme in sterol biosynthesis.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Smyd1</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SET and MYND domain containing 1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.10952</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of transcription</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key factor in myogenic differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], no identified role.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>4930452G13Rik</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RIKEN cDNA 4930452G13 gene</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.03768</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00025</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-coding RNA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown role.</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Gene Network Construction</title><p>The gene network construction performed using the IPA platform aimed at creating a visual tool to assess connections between differentially expressed genes. The direct or indirect connectivity of genes as disclosed in the literature allows the assessment of connections between any two given genes. A network was constructed for the upregulated genes with &#x0003e;3-fold increase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g002">Fig 2</xref>). A large number of functional direct and indirect connections can be seen between membrane receptors that take part in the response and maturation processes of the immune system. Membrane receptors that belong to the major histocompatibility complex (<italic>H2</italic> gene family receptors) group together since they directly interact with each other to orchestrate the autoimmune response. The constructed network illustrates the secreted chemokines <italic>Ccl3l3</italic>, <italic>Ccl4</italic> and <italic>Ccl5</italic> as hubs for multiple signaling connections. The connections between the upregulated members of the complement system, <italic>C2</italic>, <italic>C3</italic>, <italic>C4a/C4b</italic>, <italic>C1s</italic>, <italic>C1r</italic>, <italic>C1qa</italic> and <italic>C1qb</italic> are also depicted. Secreted <italic>Tnfsf11</italic> that encodes for the receptor activator of nuclear factor kappa-B ligand (<italic>RANKL</italic>) also acts as a hub for multiple gene connections. RANKL, encoded by Tnfsf11, and its receptor RANK are central in regulating the function of dendritic cells and are critically involved in the maintenance of the number and function of CD4<sup>+</sup>CD25<sup>+</sup> regulatory T cells [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] (also see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec016">discussion</xref>). The multiple indirect connections of the putative neuroprotectant oncostatin M (<italic>Osm</italic>; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec016">discussion</xref>) are also presented. <italic>Ptpn6</italic>, a tyrosine phosphatase with a role in inflammatory disease also forms many direct and indirect connections with the upregulated gene population.</p><fig id="pone.0157754.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0157754.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Network of direct and indirect gene connections between &#x0003e;3-fold upregulated genes.</title><p>Network of direct and indirect gene connections as predicted by Ingenuity Pathway Analysis software. &#x0003e;3-fold upregulated mouse genes were uploaded on the IPA platform to establish a network of their published connections.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0157754.g002"/></fig><p>The number of significantly downregulated genes that were involved in direct or indirect connections was small, so this allowed for the construction of a network using all the significantly downregulated genes with &#x0003e;2-fold increase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g003">Fig 3</xref>). Interestingly but not surprisingly, the gene that formed the most connections in the network was Insig1, an endoplasmic reticulum receptor that plays an important role in the downregulation of cholesterol biosynthesis. The connections between <italic>Hmgcr</italic> and <italic>Cyp51a1</italic>, both enzymes involved in cholesterol metabolism (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec016">discussion</xref>), and other downregulated genes are also depicted in the constructed network.</p><fig id="pone.0157754.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0157754.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Network of direct and indirect gene connections between &#x0003e;2-fold downregulated genes.</title><p>Network of direct and indirect gene connections as predicted by Ingenuity Pathway Analysis software. &#x0003e;2-fold downregulated mouse genes were uploaded on the IPA platform to establish a network of their published connections.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0157754.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Canonical Pathway Analysis</title><p>For the canonical pathway analysis, differentially expressed genes with a FDR of q &#x0003c;0.05 and a fold change of at least 2 were selected (visualised in red in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g001">Fig 1B</xref>). This set of genes, comprising of 851 upregulated and 150 downregulated genes was imported into the Ingenuity pathway analysis platform (IPA, Ingenuity Systems<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ingenuity.com">www.ingenuity.com</ext-link>). The list of the 10 most significantly regulated canonical pathways is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0157754.t003">Table 3</xref>. As expected from the gene analysis, the cholesterol biosynthesis superpathway was the most significantly downregulated pathway, with 17/27 genes downregulated. The LXR/RXR regulation pathway, a pathway emerging as a critical pathway in oligodendrocyte precursor cell (OPC) differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] was significantly regulated, with 23/121 genes upregulated and 4/121 genes downregulated. The rest of the significantly regulated canonical pathways were all upregulated pathways involved in immune processes, namely the dendritic cell maturation pathway, the T helper cell differentiation pathway, the pathway of hepatic fibrosis and hepatic stellate cell activation, the pathway of altered T and B cell signaling in rheumatoid arthritis, the acute phase response signaling pathway, the antigen presentation pathway, the complement system pathway and the pattern recognition receptors in recognition of bacteria and viruses. All the above pathways in many instances overlap, with upregulated genes involved in tumour necrosis factor signaling, toll receptor signaling or antigen presentation processes involved in more than one upregulated pathway. The upregulation of pathways involved in immune processes further supports the presence of persistently activated microglia in pEAE mice.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0157754.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0157754.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Ten most significantly altered canonical pathways.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0157754.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0157754.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ingenuity Canonical Pathways</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-log(<italic>p</italic> value)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ratio</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down-regulated</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No change</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up-regulated</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No overlap with dataset</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molecules</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Superpathway of Cholesterol Biosynthesis</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59E01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3E-01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/27 (63%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/27 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/27 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/27 (37%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HMGCS1, NSDHL, ACAT2, FDPS, HMGCR, SC5D, MSMO1, LSS, SQLE, IDI1, DHCR24, MVK, TM7SF2, HSD17B7, CYP51A1, MVD, DHCR7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dendritic Cell Maturation</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53E01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25E-01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/169 (1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/169 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36/169 (21%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131/169 (78%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLCB2, H-2-AHLA-DQA1, FCGR1A, TNFRSF1A, PIK3R5, PLCE1, TLR9, FCER1G, NFKBIA, TREM2, TLR4, IL23A, IRF8, HLA-DMA, STAT1, TYROBP, HLA-DRB5, HLA-DMB, IL1RL2, CD80, TLR2, CD86, IL33, LTB, HLA-DQB1, TNFRSF1B, MAP3K14, HLA-DOB, B2M, FCGR2A, PIK3CG, PLCG2, HLA-A, FCGR2B, IL1A, COL2A1, ICAM1, IKBKE</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>T Helper Cell Differentiation</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48E01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.58E-01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/67 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/67 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/67 (36%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43/67 (64%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL21R, TGFB1, TNFRSF1A, HLA-DQA1, HLA-DQB1, TNFRSF1B, IL6R, ICOSLG/LOC102723996, HLA-DOB, FCER1G, IL2RG, IL10RA, TGFBR2, IL10RB, HLA-DMA, STAT1, HLA-DRB5, STAT6, HLA-DMB, CD80, IL4R, RORC, CD86, IL12RB1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hepatic Fibrosis / Hepatic Stellate Cell Activation</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31E01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94E-01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/196 (1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/196 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36/196 (18%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158/196 (81%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGFB1, TNFRSF1A, IL6R, TNFSF8, LBP, TNFSF13, IL10RA, TLR4, A2M, CCR5, IL1R1, STAT1, EDN1, IL1RL2, LTB, CCL5, TNFSF11, COL6A3, KDR, TNFRSF1B, CD14, IGFBP5, FGF2, COL5A1, IGF1, IGF2, AGT, TGFBR2, COL23A1, CCL2, IL1A, IL4R, COL2A1, SERPINE1, FAS, COL13A1, ICAM1, HGF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Altered T Cell and B Cell Signaling in Rheumatoid Arthritis</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27E01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96E-01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/81 (1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/81 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/81 (28%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57/81 (70%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TLR7, TNFSF11, TGFB1, HLA-DQA1, HLA-DQB1, TLR1, MAP3K14, TLR9, FCER1G, TNFSF13, TLR4, IL23A, HLA-DMA, HLA-DRB5, IL1A, HLA-DMB, CD80, TLR6, FAS, TLR2, CD86, IL33, LTB</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Acute Phase Response Signaling</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16E01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96E-01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/168 (1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/168 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/168 (19%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135/168 (80%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CFB, OSM, C3, SOCS3, TNFRSF1A, IL6R, LBP, C1R, NFKBIA, A2M, C4A/C4B, C2, IL1R1, VWF, ITIH2, IL33, CP, TNFRSF1B, RBP1, MAP3K14, SERPINA3, HMOX1, PIK3CG, OSMR, AGT, CEBPB, IL1A, FTL, SERPINE1, C1S, SERPING1, TTR, IKBKE</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Antigen Presentation Pathway</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16E01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.32E-01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/37 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/37 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/37 (43%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21/37 (57%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA-E, CD74, HLA-DQA1, NLRC5, HLA-G, HLA-DOB, B2M, TAP1, HLA-A, TAP2, HLA-DMA, HLA-DRB5, HLA-DMB, MR1, PSMB9, PSMB8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>LXR/RXR Activation</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1E01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23E-01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/121 (3%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/121 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/121 (19%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94/121 (78%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C3, TNFRSF1A, HMGCR, LBP, PON3, TLR4, C4A/C4B, LDLR, IL1R1, IL1RL2, IL33, MYLIP, S100A8, SREBF1, TNFRSF1B, CD14, APOD, ABCA1, MSR1, AGT, LYZ, CCL2, IL1A, LPL, CYP51A1, APOE, TTR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Complement System</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06E01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17E-01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/36 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/36 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/36 (42%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21/36 (58%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITGAM, CFB, C3, C1QB, ITGAX, ITGB2, C1R, CFH, C3AR1, C1QA, C1QC, C4A/C4B, C2, C1S, SERPING1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Role of Pattern Recognition Receptors in Recognition of Bacteria and Viruses</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04E01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18E-01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/119 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/119 (0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/119 (22%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93/119 (78%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSM, TGFB1, C3, TLR1, PIK3R5, TLR9, C3AR1, C1QA, TLR4, SYK, IRF7, TLR6, TLR2, PTX3, TLR7, CCL5, C1QB, CASP1, PIK3CG, PLCG2, C1QC, PRKCD, NLRP3, IFIH1, IL1A, CLEC7A</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Comparison between pEAE and Microarray EAE Studies</title><p>To dissect the unique molecular characteristics of the pEAE mouse model, its comparison with transcriptional studies of other EAE rodent models can provide valuable information about genes and pathways that may be similarly or differently regulated between different models. The comparison of the present pEAE study with other transcriptomic studies of EAE models proved difficult, since lack of publicly available data, especially from older studies, as well as differences in the methodology used, in animal species, strain and immunisation antigens selected, in most cases did not allow direct comparison of the studies. In absence of MOG-induced mouse EAE transcriptional data, the lists of differentially expressed genes from two EAE microarray studies re-analysed in a meta-analysis performed by Raddatz et al. [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] were selected to compare with the pEAE mouse data.</p><p>The first study was a MOG-induced relapsing EAE study performed on Dark Agouti rat spinal cord tissue, where healthy rats were compared to the acute, remitting and relapsing states of the disease [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. The comparison of the differentially expressed pEAE genes with the differentially upregulated or downregulated genes in the different disease states revealed some overlap between the two models (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g004">Fig 4</xref>). In the relapsing disease stage a large percentage of genes overlapped with the pEAE gene dataset. This supports higher similarities between the relapsing EAE phenotype and the progressive phenotype. All the lists of different or common genes at all disease stages can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s004">S3 Table</xref>.</p><fig id="pone.0157754.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0157754.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Comparison of the differentially expressed pEAE genes with differentially expressed genes in MOG-induced EAE in Dark Agouti rats at different disease stages.</title><p>(A) Venn diagrams of upregulated and downregulated pEAE genes compared with acute MOG-induced EAE. (B) Venn diagrams of upregulated and downregulated pEAE genes compared with remitting MOG-induced EAE. (C) Venn diagrams of upregulated and downregulated pEAE genes compared with relapsing MOG-induced EAE.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0157754.g004"/></fig><p>The second study was a PLP-induced acute EAE study of spinal cord tissue performed in SJL/J mice [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The comparison of the two different mouse EAE models revealed some similarities in gene expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g005">Fig 5</xref>). Since this comparison was performed between the acute disease stage of a monophasic EAE mouse model and the progressive EAE model, the lists of unique pEAE genes are informative in regards to the nature of genes differentially regulated in the chronic disease phase. The lists of different or common genes upregulated and downregulated in the two mouse EAE models can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s005">S4 Table</xref>.</p><fig id="pone.0157754.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0157754.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Comparison of the differentially expressed pEAE genes with differentially expressed genes in PLP-induced EAE in SJL/J mice during the acute disease phase.</title><p>Venn diagrams of the comparisons between the upregulated and the downregulated gene datasets.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0157754.g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>Comparison between pEAE and Other RNAseq EAE Studies</title><p>RNAseq is a relatively new transcriptomic analysis technology and so far only very few RNAseq studies have addressed MS and EAE models. An advantage of RNAseq is that the very small amounts of RNA required allow the identification of the transcriptome of cellular populations rather than whole tissue. The single RNAseq study that investigated the whole transcriptome in an EAE mouse model was performed on spinal cord microglia and monocyte-derived macrophages isolated from different stages of MOG-induced EAE in C57BL/6 mice [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. The differentially regulated canonical pathways identified in microglia and monocyte derived microglia during different disease stages were compared with our pEAE study. This comparison allowed us to identify the microglial and macrophage pathways that overlap with our dataset. It also allowed us to isolate pathways that are not enriched in microglial lineage cells and that can be related to monocyte/microglial independent disease mechanisms such as T-cell mediated immune processes, neurodegeneration, demyelination and remyelination. All canonical pathways in our dataset with 3 or more genes identified within the pathway were compared with the canonical pathways regulated in pre-symptomatic and active EAE (clinical score 3) monocyte derived macrophages, as well as with pre-symptomatic and active EAE microglial derived macrophages. As seen in the Venn diagrams in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g006">Fig 6A</xref> the majority of the canonical pathways enriched in each macrophage population were common with the pEAE dataset while some pathways were unique for the macrophage populations (all data in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s006">S5 Table</xref>). The unique canonical pathways in the pEAE dataset were plotted on a Venn diagram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g006">Fig 6B</xref>) to isolate the 71 canonical pathways consistently unique to our dataset between all comparisons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s007">S6 Table</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0157754.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0157754.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>Comparison between the regulated pathways of the pEAE dataset with presymptomatic and active EAE (clinical score 3) monocyte derived macrophages, as well as with presymptomatic and active EAE microglial derived macrophages.</title><p>(A) Venn diagrams of each comparison set. (B) Venn diagram of the unique canonical pathways regulated only in pEAE mice identified from the comparison of the chronic relapsing and secondary progressive EAE dataset with the macrophage populations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0157754.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Comparison between Differentially Regulated Genes and MS Susceptibility Genes</title><p>During the last years, genome-wide association studies (GWAS) and other large-scale genotyping projects have revealed that only a few common genetic variants exist that exert relatively large MS risk, all of which are located in the <italic>HLA</italic> (human leucocyte antigen) locus. The remainder of the genetic risk spectrum comprises of a number of susceptibility variants exerting much smaller effects. So far, 110 independent SNPs outside the <italic>HLA</italic> locus have been identified to contribute to MS risk [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. A comparison between the published MS susceptibility genes and the differentially regulated genes in the pEAE mouse spinal cord tissue could reveal genes of specific interest to MS that also contribute to EAE pathology. Hoppmann et al. [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>] recently produced a list of 209 human genes mapped in proximity to the 110 MS susceptibility loci. This list of mapped genes was compared with our set of upregulated and downregulated genes to identify MS susceptibility genes that overlap with our dataset. 34/209 MS susceptibility genes were significantly upregulated in the pEAE gene dataset, and 4/209 MS susceptibility genes were downregulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g007">Fig 7</xref>). These 38 MS susceptibility genes are of particular interest since their involvement in pEAE can highlight common disease processes.</p><fig id="pone.0157754.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0157754.g007</object-id><label>Fig 7</label><caption><title>Comparison between the differentially upregulated and downregulated genes in the pEAE mice and MS susceptibility genes.</title><p>(A) Venn diagram depicting the common genes between MS susceptibility genes (Hoppmann et al., [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]) and upregulated EAE genes (34) and the common genes between the MS susceptibility genes and downregulated EAE genes (4). (B) List of the common genes as identified in the Venn diagram.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0157754.g007"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec016"><title>Discussion</title><p>The aim of this RNAseq study was to transcriptionally characterise the pEAE Biozzi ABH mouse model, to identify genes and molecular processes that may be specifically regulated in the chronic progressive phase of this disease model and to identify novel MS targets. The spinal cord transcriptional analysis revealed that a persistent immune response underlies the disease with immune pathways and genes highly upregulated (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s002">S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s003">S2</xref> Tables, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0157754.t003">Table 3</xref>). Immune pathways and responses established in EAE pathology are involved in the pEAE model, such as the dendritic cell maturation pathway, the T helper cell differentiation pathway, the antigen presentation pathway and the complement system. However, it is clear that the adaptive immune response driven by T cells that induces relapsing disease is reduced during progressive EAE, which is more associated with chronic microglial activation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] as also appears to be the case in neurodegeneration in MS that is associated with chronic microglial activation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Additionally, pathways and genes that seem to play an important role in the chronic disease progression were also revealed, such as the highly downregulated cholesterol biosynthesis and the RXR/LXR activation pathways. Genes that increase susceptibility to MS were found up- or downregulated in this model, providing insights into the relevance of this model for the study of MS processes.</p><sec id="sec017"><title>Genes Involved in Cellular Differentiation</title><p>Remyelination is a frequent event in MS lesions [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Shadow plaques, which are completely remyelinated lesions, account for 10&#x02013;20% of all lesions [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Remyelination was histopathologically described in pEAE mice [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and characterises the secondary progressive phenotype of this disease model. Here, the remarkable upregulation of <italic>Mbp</italic> and <italic>Plp1</italic> expression in the pEAE model confirms that active remyelination takes place during the progressive phase of the disease model. <italic>Mbp</italic> and <italic>Plp1</italic> encode for myelin basic protein and proteolipid protein 1, both constituent proteins of the myelin membrane, with a documented upregulation during oligodendrocyte differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Remyelination in progressive EAE as well as MS is limited. The reduced ability for lesion remyelination has been attributed to neuronal loss, but also the inability of OPCs to switch from a proliferating and migrating phenotype to a differentiating one. Genes involved in myelination significantly downregulated in the pEAE transcriptome reveal significant clues to remyelination failure processes. Vesicle bound glutamate transporter (VGLUT1), encoded by <italic>Slc17a7</italic> is an axon terminal glutamate transporter required in neuronal&#x02013;OPC synapses to promote myelination processes [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. <italic>Slc17a7</italic> downregulation in pEAE reflects how neurodegeneration may inhibit myelination processes. <italic>Ugt8a</italic> was significantly downregulated in the pEAE mouse. <italic>Ugt8a</italic> encodes for the enzyme ceramide glucosyltransferase, which is essential for galactosylceramide production and myelin integrity [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Opalin is a myelin membrane protein present in paranodal loops [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] which was also significantly downregulated in the pEAE mouse. These dowregulated genes involved in myelination present as promising targets for new remyelination strategies.</p><p>Attention should also be drawn to some regulated genes involved in cellular differentiation processes with no identified role in EAE or MS. <italic>Smyd1</italic> for example is a downregulated transcriptional regulator identified as a key factor in myogenic differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] but with no known role in EAE or MS. Another example of a highly upregulated gene is <italic>Mcoln3</italic>, that encodes a transient Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel, (TRPML3), which is involved in auditory receptor cell differentiation in mice [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Recently TRPML3 emerged as a transient receptor potential channel (TRP) located in lysosomes responsible for lysosomal extrusion following their neutralisation by bacterial infection [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. The involvement of <italic>Mcoln3</italic> in lysosomal homeostasis could implicate it in autophagosomal processes that may be related to neurodegeneration. Another group of upregulated genes involved in cellular differentiation include the H<sup>+</sup> transporting ATPase <italic>Atp6v0d2</italic>, the ion transporter <italic>Steap4</italic>, the proton sensing receptor <italic>Gpr65</italic> (TDAG8) and the Nf-&#x003ba;B ligand RANKL, encoded by <italic>Tnfsf11</italic> (tumour necrosis factor superfamily member 11), all involved in the regulation of osteoclast differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The upregulation of osteoclast differentiation molecules may reflect defects in bone remodelling in pEAE and MS, or may reflect a yet unidentified involvement of this differentiation pathway in disease progression. It is interesting to note that RANKL is significantly upregulated in MS patient serum [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. RANKL and its receptor RANK have a critical role in regulating the function of dendritic cells and in maintaining the number and function of CD4<sup>+</sup>CD25<sup>+</sup> regulatory T cells [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The involvement of RANKL in T cell regulation in active EAE was demonstrated in a recent study where RANKL depletion prevented EAE development due to impaired T cell infiltration into the CNS [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Thus the upregulation of RANKL in our dataset and the upregulated protein levels in MS patient serum may reflect the involvement of RANKL in T cell regulation in EAE and MS.</p></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>Genes Involved in Neurodegeneration and Neuroprotection</title><p>Some genes upregulated in the pEAE model that are involved in immune processes have been reported to also be involved in neurodegenerative processes. Matrix metallopeptidase 12 (<italic>Mmp12</italic>) is expressed in macrophages but has also been involved in inducing demyelination and neurodegeneration before macrophage infiltration in Theiler&#x02019;s murine encephalopathy [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. <italic>Mmp12</italic> was highly upregulated in pEAE highlighting the possibility that regulation of <italic>Mmp12</italic> levels could have a neuroprotective effect. Reactive oxygen species generating enzymes such as <italic>Cybb</italic>, encoding for the superoxide-generating microglial enzyme <italic>Nox2</italic> and xanthine dehydrogenase (<italic>Xdh</italic>) were also upregulated in pEAE. Both enzymes have been implicated in neurodegenerative processes [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p><p>A gene with a well-documented role in neuroprotection was upregulated in the pEAE dataset. <italic>Sprr1a</italic>, the small proline-rich protein A1, is a protein involved in keratinocyte differentiation which is upregulated in neurons following experimental brain injury [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], and in sciatic nerve and spinal cord sensory neurons following axotomy [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. <italic>Sprr1a</italic> promotes neuronal outgrowth and is expressed soon after neuronal injury. Thus the upregulation of this gene indicates the activation of a neuroprotective mechanism in the pEAE spinal cord and highlights a potential therapeutic avenue that deserves further investigation. The transient channel TRPML3, encoded by the <italic>Mcoln3</italic> gene and also known as cornifin-A, is a channel involved in keratinocyte differentiation. An additional gene involved in keratinocyte complex formation, Ppl which encodes periplakin was also upregulated in the pEAE mouse. It is possible that Ppl may be part of the pathway that promotes axonal regeneration together with Sprr1A, so further investigation of the involvement of <italic>Plp</italic> in neuroprotection would be of interest. Additional genes with neuroprotective roles were also upregulated in the pEAE mouse model. Oncostatin M, encoded by the <italic>Osm</italic> gene was found upregulated in the serum of a cohort of people with relapsing-remitting MS [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], while oncostatin treatment protected against demyelination in the Cuprizone-induced demyelination model [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. <italic>Gpnmb</italic> is a transmembrane glycoprotein also found upregulated in Lewis rat EAE [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and in a mouse model of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. A neuroprotective <italic>in vitro</italic> role has been proposed [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In a ganglioside deficient mouse model <italic>Wisp2</italic>, a protein with cell adhesion and cell growth regulation properties upregulated in our dataset was also found to be neuroprotective and promote neurite outgrowth <italic>in vitro</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The upregulation of neuroprotective genes in the pEAE mouse model suggests that this model can be used to investigate neuroprotective pathways in the progressive disease stage.</p></sec><sec id="sec019"><title>The Cholesterol Biosynthesis Pathway</title><p>The cholesterol biosynthesis pathway was identified as the most significantly regulated canonical pathway in the Ingenuity pathway analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0157754.t003">Table 3</xref>), with 17/27 genes assigned to this pathway significantly downregulated. Importantly, some of the cholesterol biosynthesis pathway genes, such as the genes encoding the cholesterol synthesising enzymes isopentenyl-diphosphate delta isomerase (<italic>Idi1</italic>), 3-hydroxy-3-methyglutaryl-coenzyme A synthase 1 (HMG-CoA reductase, Hmgcs1), methylsterol monoxygenase 1 (Sc4mol), 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase (<italic>Hmgcr</italic>) and squalene epoxidase (<italic>Sqle</italic>) are in the list of the most significantly downregulated genes in this analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0157754.t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>Significant downregulation of the cholesterol biosynthesis genes during relapsing disease has also been reported in MOG-induced EAE in Dark Agouti rats [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], as well as in the spinal cord of MBP-induced EAE in Lewis rats [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. In contrast to the MOG-induced EAE study though, where only cholesterol biosynthesis genes were downregulated, in our model cholesterol transport genes were also downregulated, indicating downregulation of additional components of cholesterol metabolism in the pEAE model. HMG-CoA reductase, a cholesterol rate-limiting enzyme has also been found downregulated in people with MS [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. In the dysmyelinating peroxisome-proliferator-activated receptor gamma coactivator 1 (PGC1&#x003b1;) knock-out mouse model, brain cholesterol, its precursors, and the rate-limiting enzymes HMG CoA synthase (<italic>Mcoln3</italic>) and HMG CoA reductase (<italic>Hmgcr</italic>), were downregulated [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. There are two possible mechanisms that may result in cholesterol biosynthesis downregulation in EAE. One mechanism may involve the presence of cholesterol at lesions due to the breakdown of the cholesterol-rich myelin membranes, leading to inhibition of its biosynthesising pathway and contributing to remyelination inhibition. Cholesterol negatively regulates the transcription of cholesterol biosynthesis genes [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Another mechanism involved in cholesterol biosynthesis downregulation involves the activation of the immune system. It was recently shown that metabolic factors involved in cholesterol biosynthesis are downregulated to promote the expansion and reorganisation of pro-inflammatory CD4<sup>+</sup> Th17 cells <italic>in vivo</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>].</p><p>The involvement of cholesterol synthesis rate-limiting enzymes in MS and EAE pathology is also highlighted by the fact that HMG-CoA inhibitors ameliorate EAE and MS relapses by inhibiting immune cell activation and migration through the blood-brain barrier [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Lovastatin and simvastatin are HMG-CoA inhibitors taken to clinical studies for relapsing remitting MS [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. However, more importantly, high dose simvastatin has recently been shown to inhibit neurogeneration in secondary progressive MS [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>], which is a disease stage that is not typically responsive to immune activation or blockage of peripheral immune responses entering the brain [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The finding here that cholesterol biosynthesis pathways are highly dysregulated in pEAE, which is mostly unresponsive to peripheral immunomodulation, may support the value of HMG-CoA inhibitors in progressive MS and provide a tool for mechanistic studies to understand the neuroprotective effects of statins. The transcriptomic data available clearly indicate a downregulation of this pathway but further investigation is needed to determine the physiological consequences of this downregulation.</p><p>Additionally <italic>Ch25h</italic>, a gene involved in cholesterol metabolism, was upregulated in the pEAE mouse. Cholesterol 25-hydroxylase is involved in lipid metabolism, catalyses the formation of 25-hydroxycholesterol from cholesterol and represses cholesterol biosynthetic enzymes [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Thus its upregulation agrees with the preferential downregulation of the cholesterol biosynthesis pathway. <italic>Ch25h</italic> has also been proposed as a susceptibility gene for Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and its deletion can significantly attenuate EAE disease course by limiting trafficking of pathogenic CD4<sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes to the central nervous system [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Lastly a lipid storage regulator, <italic>Plin4</italic> is upregulated in pEAE and with no identified role in EAE or MS pathology its potential role in cholesterol or LXR/RXR metabolism (see below) would be worth investigating.</p></sec><sec id="sec020"><title>The LXR/RXR Activation Pathway</title><p>The LXR/RXR activation pathway was also significantly regulated in the pEAE model with 23/121 genes involved in this pathway downregulated and 4/121 upregulated. Genes involved in this pathway include <italic>Ttr</italic> (transthyretin), the most significantly downregulated gene in this study (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0157754.t002">Table 2</xref>), the HMG-CoA reductase gene, as well as the highly downregulated genes S<italic>c4mol</italic> and <italic>Ldlr</italic>. The liver X receptors (LXRs) and the retinoid X receptors (RXRs) are obligate heterodimers that form ligand-activated nuclear transcription factors that regulate lipid homeostasis, including cholesterol metabolism [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. The LXR pathway is emerging as a critical pathway in oligodendrocyte precursor cell (OPC) differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. It was found that the RXR-&#x003b3; receptor was significantly upregulated in the regenerative phase of remyelination in a toxin-induced demyelination model in rats, while the LXR/RXR activation pathway was significantly regulated [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. This positive regulation of remyelination is a promising pharmaceutical target. The suppression of the LXR/RXR activation pathway identified in the pEAE model, may contribute to the limited remyelination observed in this model and suggests that upregulation of relevant components of the LXR/RXR pathway may promote remyelination.</p><p>Interestingly and perhaps not surprisingly, the LXR/RXR activation pathway was also highly regulated in the transcriptomic analysis of T cells isolated from acute mouse EAE [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>], implicating LXR/RXR signaling in immune cell responses. In addition to genes such as <italic>Srebf1</italic>, <italic>Hmgcr</italic>, or <italic>Cyp51a1</italic> which are involved in cholesterol biosynthesis, genes such as <italic>Abca1</italic>, <italic>Srebf1</italic> and <italic>Lpl</italic> which are involved in cholesterol transport were also found regulated in Th17 cells, as well as in our dataset, implicating cholesterol transport in the disease progression. mRNA levels of LXR-&#x003b2; were also found increased in MS patient peripheral blood mononuclear cells [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Additionally, combination of LXR and RXR or PPAR&#x003b3; and RXR agonists can inhibit microglial and astrocyte inflammatory responses <italic>in vitro</italic> and in EAE models [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. LXR/RXR signaling provides promising therapeutic options in MS, but much is still unclear about the role of this signaling pathway in specific cell populations and different phases of disease progression. Transcriptomic analysis of acute and chronic models can help with the elucidation of LXR/RXR signaling in MS.</p><p>Transthyretin, encoded by the <italic>Ttr</italic> gene is associated with the LXR/RXR activation pathway and is highly downregulated in our dataset. Transthyretin transfers thyroxin from the blood to the brain, where thyroxin is essential for oligodendrocyte maturation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Thus the low transcripts of transthyretin in EAE spinal cord may be one factor contributing to remyelination failure. Transthyretin is highly expressed in MS patient serum [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>], suggesting that there may be a failure in transthyretin transfer from the blood to the CSF and the brain and that pharmacological enhancement of that pathway may increase thyroxin availability in the brain and spinal cord and promote remyelination in MS patients.</p></sec><sec id="sec021"><title>The pEAE Mouse Model Transcriptome Compared to Other EAE Models</title><p>The pEAE Biozzi ABH mouse model exhibits a reproducible relapsing-remitting disease accompanied by demyelination, gliosis, glial cell activation, axonal and neuronal loss, followed by a slowly accumulating permanent neurological deficit [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0157754.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], which was examined here. The pEAE mouse model has been used for the study of mechanisms involved in the accumulation of neurological damage. Genes and pathways relevant to MS pathology are identified in this model, but its comparison to other EAE models can provide a lot of information about genes and processes unique to this model or common with other progressive phenotypes. The comparison of pEAE with a MOG-induced relapsing EAE study in Dark Agouti rats during the acute, remitting and relapsing stages of the disease [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>] revealed some similarities between the two models, and especially similarities between upregulated genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g004">Fig 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s004">S3 Table</xref>). 66% of the upregulated genes in the relapsing phase of the MOG-EAE model were common with the pEAE model, opposed to 42% in the acute phase and 33% in the remitting phase. This supports higher similarities between the relapsing EAE phenotype and the pEAE phenotype, as such active inflammation and progressive lesions co-exist in progressive MS, although the equilibrium is shifted to chronic glial cell lesions [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. A limitation of our study was that only tissue from the secondary progressive phase of the disease was studied. Additional studies of different disease stages of the pEAE mouse model would help identify the molecular pathways unique in the progressive stage, as well as give even more information regarding similarities and differences between relapsing-remitting EAE models. On the other hand, our study identified a larger number of differentially expressed genes in comparison to older microarray studies.</p><p>Another interesting subject for further investigation would be the identification of the transcriptome of the different cellular populations of the pEAE spinal cord. RNAseq analysis has made it possible to collect small amounts of RNA and perform transcriptomic analysis. The comparison of our study with an RNAseq study of the transcriptome of monocyte derived or resident CNS microglia [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] in MOG-induced EAE revealed a wealth of information about macrophage-specific pathways regulated in pEAE, as well as pathways uniquely identified in pEAE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g006">Fig 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0157754.s007">S6 Table</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec022"><title>MS Susceptibility Genes Significantly Regulated in Progressive EAE</title><p>pEAE is an experimental autoimmune mouse model that recapitulates key pathological features of secondary progressive MS, such as demyelination, remyelination, gliosis, axonal and neuronal loss [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Genes significantly modulated in pEAE are involved in disease mechanisms that are similar to MS pathology. To identify molecules in pEAE that may point to molecular pathways specifically relevant to MS pathology, we compared the pEAE transcriptome with 209 MS susceptibility genes [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>] and identified 39 significantly regulated genes that are MS susceptibility genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g007">Fig 7</xref>). This list of genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0157754.g007">Fig 7B</xref>) comprises of immune-related genes such as the ligand <italic>C3</italic>, the cell surface proteins <italic>Cd37</italic>, <italic>Cd48</italic>, <italic>Cd86</italic>, <italic>Fcrls</italic>, <italic>Ltbr</italic>, <italic>Vcam1</italic>, <italic>Ccdc88b</italic> and the cytoplasmic proteins <italic>Coro1a</italic>, <italic>Ifi30</italic>, <italic>Plek</italic>, <italic>MertK and Dab2</italic>. <italic>Tnfaip3</italic>, <italic>Tnfrsf14</italic>, <italic>Tnfrsf1a</italic> and <italic>Traf3a</italic> are genes that are involved in the tumor necrosis factor signaling processes. TNF signaling is central to MS and EAE pathology. Thus it comes as no surprise that in the pEAE mouse model TNF was identified as the most significantly regulated upstream regulator in the IPA analysis (data not shown, available on request). The transcription factors <italic>Hhex</italic>, <italic>Irf8</italic>, <italic>Maf</italic>, <italic>Stat3</italic>, <italic>Zfp36l1</italic>, <italic>Zfp36l2</italic> and the transcription regulators <italic>Ikzf1</italic>, <italic>Ptrf Sp110</italic> were also upregulated in pEAE and although most of them are involved in immune-pathway transcription, their careful investigation could reveal additional functions. <italic>Sox8</italic>, the only transcription factor in the list which was downregulated in the pEAE mouse, promotes cellular differentiation and has a possible role in nervous system development.</p><p>MS susceptibility genes regulated in the pEAE without a clearly identified role in MS include the non-voltage gated sodium channel <italic>Scnn1a</italic>, the solute carrier <italic>Slc44a2</italic>, the lysosomal cysteine proteinase <italic>Ctsh</italic>, the serine biosynthesis enzyme <italic>Phgdh</italic>, and the mitochondrial <italic>Hmgsc2</italic>, an enzyme which controls ketogenesis. The proton sensing receptor <italic>Gpr65</italic>, involved in osteoclast differentiation, which is one of the most upregulated genes in the pEAE mouse model is also an MS susceptibility gene. <italic>Iqgap1</italic> is a scaffolding protein recognised as instrumental in cytoskeletal organisation and cell signaling [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. <italic>Rgs14</italic>, a regulator of G protein signaling found upregulated in pEAE was identified as a gene differentially regulated in pathogenic CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Interestingly it is also recognised as a neuronal suppressor of long-term potentiation of synaptic transmission in the hippocampus [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. The neuronal role of <italic>Rgs14</italic> opens a question as to whether its upregulation in pEAE may involve neuronal processes. Quantification of <italic>Rgs14</italic> levels in neuronal cells in MS or EAE will help to resolve this question. The same applies to <italic>Scap2</italic>, a gene with documented expression in both neurones and immune cells. <italic>Scap2</italic> is a Src kinase-associated phosphoprotein involved in integrin-stimulated cytoskeleton rearrangement [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>], but it is also involved in neuronal differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. A glioblastoma susceptibility locus, <italic>Phldb1</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0157754.ref098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>] was also present in the list of MS susceptibility genes downregulated in the pEAE mouse. The identification of these MS susceptibility genes in the pEAE mouse model opens the door to their functional study in a mouse model which recapitulates some of the important clinical features of MS.</p></sec><sec id="sec023"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The aim of this study was to transcriptionally characterise the progressive Biozzi ABH EAE mouse model in an unbiased manner and identify genes and disease processes that may be specific to this mouse model and that may recapitulate some of the MS features more adequately than other disease models. Importantly, genes specifically regulated in the chronic phenotype of EAE were identified and their role in the chronic disease phase as well as their potential as therapeutic targets can be studied further.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec024"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0157754.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>Heatmap of gene expression between samples.</title><p>Heatmap of significantly regulated gene expression demonstrating the hierarchical clustering within the three control (1CTR - 3CTR) and three pEAE (1EAE&#x02013; 3EAE) spinal cord samples (top dendrogram). The left hand side dendrogram demonstrates clustering between genes as predicted in the R arlgorithm. Scale: Yellow indicates high expression and red demonstrates low expression.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0157754.s001.tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0157754.s002"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Significantly upregulated genes.</title><p>(XLSX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0157754.s002.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0157754.s003"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title>Significantly downregulated genes.</title><p>(XLSX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0157754.s003.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0157754.s004"><label>S3 Table</label><caption><title>Comparison between gene expression in MOG EAE and pEAE.</title><p>(XLSX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0157754.s004.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0157754.s005"><label>S4 Table</label><caption><title>Comparison between gene expression in EAE and pEAE.</title><p>(XLSX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0157754.s005.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0157754.s006"><label>S5 Table</label><caption><title>Comparisons between pEAE pathways and Macrophage RNAseq pathways.</title><p>(XLSX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0157754.s006.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0157754.s007"><label>S6 Table</label><caption><title>All unique pEAE pathways after comparison with Macrophage RNAseq.</title><p>(XLSX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0157754.s007.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are grateful for the support of Canbex Therapeutics and the Technology Strategy Board UK/Innovate UK grant no. 25036-166159.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0157754.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Multiple sclerosis&#x02014;a global disorder and still poorly managed</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1078</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. Epub 2008/11/15. S1474-4422(08)70246-1 [pii] <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S1474-4422(08)70246-1">10.1016/S1474-4422(08)70246-1</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 19007729?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19007729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Compston</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>372</volume>(<issue>9648</issue>):<fpage>1502</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. Epub 2008/10/31. S0140-6736(08)61620-7 [pii] <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61620-7">10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61620-7</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 18970977?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18970977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weinshenker</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>. <article-title>The natural history of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Neurol Clin</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. Epub 1995/02/01. .<?supplied-pmid 7739500?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7739500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bardos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broughton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>The high cost of spasticity in multiple sclerosis to individuals and society</article-title>. <source>Multiple sclerosis</source>. <year>2015</year> Epub 2015/01/28. 1352458514566416 [pii] <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/1352458514566416">10.1177/1352458514566416</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 25623252?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25623252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuerten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gruppe</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laurentius</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tary-Lehmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Differential patterns of spinal cord pathology induced by MP4, MOG peptide 35&#x02013;55, and PLP peptide 178&#x02013;191 in C57BL/6 mice</article-title>. <source>APMIS</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>119</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>336</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. Epub 2011/05/17. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-0463.2011.02744.x">10.1111/j.1600-0463.2011.02744.x</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 21569091?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21569091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McFarlin</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Relapsing experimental allergic encephalomyelitis in the SJL/J mouse</article-title>. <source>Lab Invest</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>278</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>. Epub 1981/09/01. .<?supplied-pmid 6792424?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6792424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Al-Izki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pryce</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Immunosuppression with FTY720 is insufficient to prevent secondary progressive neurodegeneration in experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis</article-title>. <source>Multiple sclerosis</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>939</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>. Epub 2011/04/05. 1352458511400476 [pii] <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/1352458511400476">10.1177/1352458511400476</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 21459808?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21459808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Molyneux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paolillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davie</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Monoclonal antibody treatment exposes three mechanisms underlying the clinical course of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Annals of neurology</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>296</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304</lpage>. Epub 1999/09/11. .<?supplied-pmid 10482259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10482259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pryce</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Croxford</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hankey</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>East</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Autoimmune tolerance eliminates relapses but fails to halt progression in a model of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroimmunology</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. Epub 2005/06/09. S0165-5728(05)00133-5 [pii] <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jneuroim.2005.04.009">10.1016/j.jneuroim.2005.04.009</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 15939483?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15939483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Comi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rammohan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rieckmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soelberg Sorensen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A placebo-controlled trial of oral cladribine for relapsing multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>362</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>416</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. Epub 2010/01/22. NEJMoa0902533 [pii] <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa0902533">10.1056/NEJMoa0902533</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 20089960?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20089960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Compston</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>359</volume>(<issue>9313</issue>):<fpage>1221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(02)08220-X">10.1016/S0140-6736(02)08220-X</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 11955556?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11955556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hampton</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Serio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pryce</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al-Izki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Neurodegeneration progresses despite complete elimination of clinical relapses in a mouse model of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Acta Neuropathol Commun</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>84</fpage> Epub 2013/12/25. 2051-5960-1-84 [pii] <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/2051-5960-1-84">10.1186/2051-5960-1-84</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3895761.<?supplied-pmid 24364862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24364862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gschmeissner</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Butter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Induction of chronic relapsing experimental allergic encephalomyelitis in Biozzi mice</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroimmunology</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. Epub 1990/08/01. .<?supplied-pmid 2373763?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2373763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heremans</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dillen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Groenen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Billiau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Chronic relapsing experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (CREAE) in mice: enhancement by monoclonal antibodies against interferon-gamma</article-title>. <source>Eur J Immunol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2393</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. Epub 1996/10/01. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/eji.1830261019">10.1002/eji.1830261019</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 8898951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8898951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Al-Izki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pryce</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluating potential therapies for bladder dysfunction in a mouse model of multiple sclerosis with high-resolution ultrasonography</article-title>. <source>Multiple sclerosis</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>795</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>801</lpage>. Epub 2009/05/26. 1352458509104594 [pii] <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/1352458509104594">10.1177/1352458509104594</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 19465448?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19465448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nikodemova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fabry</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantification of myelin and axon pathology during relapsing progressive experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis in the Biozzi ABH mouse</article-title>. <source>J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>616</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. Epub 2009/05/22. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/NEN.0b013e3181a41d23">10.1097/NEN.0b013e3181a41d23</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 19458548?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19458548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hampton</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pryce</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fawcett</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>An experimental model of secondary progressive multiple sclerosis that shows regional variation in gliosis, remyelination, axonal and neuronal loss</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroimmunology</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>201&#x02013;202</volume>:<fpage>200</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. Epub 2008/08/02. S0165-5728(08)00225-7 [pii] <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jneuroim.2008.05.034">10.1016/j.jneuroim.2008.05.034</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 18672298?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18672298</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Al-Izki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pryce</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Butter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Practical guide to the induction of relapsing progressive experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis in the Biozzi ABH mouse</article-title>. <source>Multiple Sclerosis and Related disorders</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.msard.2011.09.001">10.1016/j.msard.2011.09.001</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 25876448?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25876448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Models of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>ACNR</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Differential gene and transcript expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with TopHat and Cufflinks</article-title>. <source>Nature protocols</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>562</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>. Epub 2012/03/03. nprot.2012.016 [pii] <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2012.016">10.1038/nprot.2012.016</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3334321.<?supplied-pmid 22383036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sauvageau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rinn</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Differential analysis of gene regulation at transcript resolution with RNA-seq</article-title>. <source>Nature biotechnology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>46</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nbt.2450">10.1038/nbt.2450</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3869392.<?supplied-pmid 23222703?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23222703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Speed</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ngai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barres</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Functional genomic analysis of oligodendrocyte differentiation</article-title>. <source>The Journal of neuroscience: the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>43</issue>):<fpage>10967</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2572-06.2006">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2572-06.2006</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 17065439?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17065439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Haastert</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Groot</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van der Valk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Matrix metalloproteinase-12 is expressed in phagocytotic macrophages in active multiple sclerosis lesions</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroimmunology</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. .<?supplied-pmid 12742660?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12742660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hansmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herder</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalkuhl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haist</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaudien</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Matrix metalloproteinase-12 deficiency ameliorates the clinical course and demyelination in Theiler's murine encephalomyelitis</article-title>. <source>Acta neuropathologica</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00401-012-0942-3">10.1007/s00401-012-0942-3</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 22271152?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22271152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Noben-Trauth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>The TRPML3 channel: from gene to function</article-title>. <source>Advances in experimental medicine and biology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>704</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-0265-3_13">10.1007/978-94-007-0265-3_13</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 21290299?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21290299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>. <article-title>A TRP Channel Senses Lysosome Neutralization by Pathogens to Trigger Their Expulsion</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>161</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1306</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2015.05.009">10.1016/j.cell.2015.05.009</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4458218.<?supplied-pmid 26027738?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26027738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sul</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>v-ATPase V0 subunit d2-deficient mice exhibit impaired osteoclast fusion and increased bone formation</article-title>. <source>Nature medicine</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nm1514">10.1038/nm1514</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 17128270?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17128270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Inglis</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCombe</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gene expression in the spinal cord in female lewis rats with experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis induced with myelin basic protein</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e48555</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0048555">10.1371/journal.pone.0048555</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3491034.<?supplied-pmid 23139791?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23139791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimazawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsuruma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The potential of GPNMB as novel neuroprotective factor in amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Scientific reports</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/srep00573">10.1038/srep00573</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3417778.<?supplied-pmid 22891158?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22891158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ohkawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohmi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Wisp2/CCN5 up-regulated in the central nervous system of GM3-only mice facilitates neurite formation in Neuro2a cells via integrin-Akt signaling</article-title>. <source>Biochemical and biophysical research communications</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>411</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bbrc.2011.06.118">10.1016/j.bbrc.2011.06.118</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 21723256?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21723256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Azizov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stehning</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kedersha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Auburger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dysregulated expression of lipid storage and membrane dynamics factors in Tia1 knockout mouse nervous tissue</article-title>. <source>Neurogenetics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10048-014-0397-x">10.1007/s10048-014-0397-x</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3994287.<?supplied-pmid 24659297?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24659297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manolagas</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Steap4 plays a critical role in osteoclastogenesis in vitro by regulating cellular iron/reactive oxygen species (ROS) levels and cAMP response element-binding protein (CREB) activation</article-title>. <source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>288</volume>(<issue>42</issue>):<fpage>30064</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M113.478750">10.1074/jbc.M113.478750</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3798475.<?supplied-pmid 23990467?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23990467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Naj</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beecham</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vardarajan</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Common variants at MS4A4/MS4A6E, CD2AP, CD33 and EPHA1 are associated with late-onset Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Nature genetics</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>436</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.801">10.1038/ng.801</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3090745.<?supplied-pmid 21460841?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21460841</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Surace</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>Targeting microglia-mediated neurotoxicity: the potential of NOX2 inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Cellular and molecular life sciences: CMLS</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>2409</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00018-012-1015-4">10.1007/s00018-012-1015-4</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3677079.<?supplied-pmid 22581365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22581365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hikiji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Horie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akahoshi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>TDAG8 activation inhibits osteoclastic bone resorption</article-title>. <source>FASEB journal: official publication of the Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>871</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1096/fj.13-233106">10.1096/fj.13-233106</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 24221084?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24221084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Papassotiropoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wavrant-De Vrieze</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wollmer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von der Kammer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Streffer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Cholesterol 25-hydroxylase on chromosome 10q is a susceptibility gene for sporadic Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Neuro-degenerative diseases</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1159/000090362">10.1159/000090362</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 16909003?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16909003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chalmin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rochemont</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lippens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clottu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sailer</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Merkler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Oxysterols regulate encephalitogenic CD4(+) T cell trafficking during central nervous system autoimmunity</article-title>. <source>Journal of autoimmunity</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jaut.2014.10.001">10.1016/j.jaut.2014.10.001</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 25456971?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25456971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marklund</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fulp</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strittmatter</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Selective temporal and regional alterations of Nogo-A and small proline-rich repeat protein 1A (SPRR1A) but not Nogo-66 receptor (NgR) occur following traumatic brain injury in the rat</article-title>. <source>Experimental neurology</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>197</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>70</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.expneurol.2005.08.029">10.1016/j.expneurol.2005.08.029</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2849132.<?supplied-pmid 16321384?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16321384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonilla</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strittmatter</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Small proline-rich repeat protein 1A is expressed by axotomized neurons and promotes axonal outgrowth</article-title>. <source>The Journal of neuroscience: the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>. .<?supplied-pmid 11850458?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11850458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Starkey</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Expression of the regeneration-associated protein SPRR1A in primary sensory neurons and spinal cord of the adult mouse following peripheral and central injury</article-title>. <source>The Journal of comparative neurology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>513</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/cne.21944">10.1002/cne.21944</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3339437.<?supplied-pmid 19107756?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19107756</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kellett</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scorer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milligan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Selective interactions between helix VIII of the human mu-opioid receptors and the C terminus of periplakin disrupt G protein activation</article-title>. <source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>278</volume>(<issue>35</issue>):<fpage>33400</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M305866200">10.1074/jbc.M305866200</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 12810704?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12810704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Honorat</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Xanthine oxidase mediates axonal and myelin loss in a murine model of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e71329</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0071329">10.1371/journal.pone.0071329</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3738596.<?supplied-pmid 23951137?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23951137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karlstetter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walczak</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weigelt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van den Brulle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schwer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The novel activated microglia/macrophage WAP domain protein, AMWAP, acts as a counter-regulator of proinflammatory response</article-title>. <source>Journal of immunology</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>185</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>3379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.0903300">10.4049/jimmunol.0903300</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 20709948?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20709948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alikhani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alsahebfosoul</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shajarian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Investigation of Oncostatin M protein expression in Iranian relapsing remitting multiple sclerosis patients</article-title>. <source>Multiple sclerosis and related disorders</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>747</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.msard.2014.09.172">10.1016/j.msard.2014.09.172</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Janssens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maheshwari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van den Haute</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baekelandt</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stinissen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Oncostatin M protects against demyelination by inducing a protective microglial phenotype</article-title>. <source>Glia</source>. <year>2015</year>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/glia.22840">10.1002/glia.22840</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 25921393?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25921393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lacey</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timms</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dunstan</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Osteoprotegerin ligand is a cytokine that regulates osteoclast differentiation and activation</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. .<?supplied-pmid 9568710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9568710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alatab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maghbooli</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hossein-Nezhad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Khosrofar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mokhtari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cytokine profile, Foxp3 and nuclear factor-kB ligand levels in multiple sclerosis subtypes</article-title>. <source>Minerva medica</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>102</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>461</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. .<?supplied-pmid 22193377?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22193377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kurban</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akpinar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mehmetoglu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Receptor activator of nuclear factor kappaB ligand (RANKL) and osteoprotegerin levels in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Multiple sclerosis</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/1352458507084028">10.1177/1352458507084028</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 18208894?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18208894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Calza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giardino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellular approaches to central nervous system remyelination stimulation: thyroid hormone to promote myelin repair via endogenous stem and precursor cells</article-title>. <source>Journal of molecular endocrinology</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1677/JME-09-0067">10.1677/JME-09-0067</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 19578096?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19578096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dell'Acqua</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lorenzini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D'Intino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sivilia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pasqualetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Panetta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Functional and molecular evidence of myelin- and neuroprotection by thyroid hormone administration in experimental allergic encephalomyelitis</article-title>. <source>Neuropathology and applied neurobiology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>454</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2990.2011.01228.x">10.1111/j.1365-2990.2011.01228.x</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 22007951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22007951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pleasure</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Axon-glia synapses are highly vulnerable to white matter injury in the developing brain</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroscience research</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>90</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jnr.22722">10.1002/jnr.22722</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3209489.<?supplied-pmid 21812016?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21812016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sahel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kerninon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Angulo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nait-Oumesmar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Alteration of synaptic connectivity of oligodendrocyte precursor cells following demyelination</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in cellular neuroscience</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3389/fncel.2015.00077">10.3389/fncel.2015.00077</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4362325.<?supplied-pmid 25852473?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25852473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Killick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wroe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Usardi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Oligomeric amyloid-beta peptide affects the expression of genes involved in steroid and lipid metabolism in primary neurons</article-title>. <source>Neurochemistry international</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neuint.2012.05.006">10.1016/j.neuint.2012.05.006</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 22579571?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22579571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of gene expression in rats with spinal cord injury based on microarray data</article-title>. <source>Molecular medicine reports</source>. <year>2015</year>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3892/mmr.2015.3670">10.3892/mmr.2015.3670</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 25936407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25936407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valenza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leoni</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brilli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Peroxisome-proliferator-activated receptor gamma coactivator 1 alpha contributes to dysmyelination in experimental models of Huntington's disease</article-title>. <source>The Journal of neuroscience: the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>26</issue>):<fpage>9544</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1291-11.2011">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1291-11.2011</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3132810.<?supplied-pmid 21715619?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21715619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mawdsley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hines</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pozzoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mutation of 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl CoA synthase I reveals requirements for isoprenoid and cholesterol synthesis in oligodendrocyte migration arrest, axon wrapping, and myelin gene expression</article-title>. <source>The Journal of neuroscience: the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>3402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4587-13.2014">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4587-13.2014</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3935092.<?supplied-pmid 24573296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24573296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bosio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Binczek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stoffel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Functional breakdown of the lipid bilayer of the myelin membrane in central and peripheral nervous system by disrupted galactocerebroside synthesis</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>13280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC24084.<?supplied-pmid 8917582?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8917582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marchesi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deflorian</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D'Antuono</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cuomo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bologna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>DEPDC1B coordinates de-adhesion events and cell-cycle progression at mitosis</article-title>. <source>Developmental cell</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>420</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2014.09.009">10.1016/j.devcel.2014.09.009</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4250264.<?supplied-pmid 25458010?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25458010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kratz</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vallejo</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Mutations in the human SC4MOL gene encoding a methyl sterol oxidase cause psoriasiform dermatitis, microcephaly, and developmental delay</article-title>. <source>The Journal of clinical investigation</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>976</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1172/JCI42650">10.1172/JCI42650</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3049385.<?supplied-pmid 21285510?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21285510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tohyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hashikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagakura-Takagi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Opalin, a transmembrane sialylglycoprotein located in the central nervous system myelin paranodal loop membrane</article-title>. <source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>283</volume>(<issue>30</issue>):<fpage>20830</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M801314200">10.1074/jbc.M801314200</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3258930.<?supplied-pmid 18490449?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18490449</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liou</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The sodium-dependent glucose cotransporter SLC5A11 as an autoimmune modifier gene in SLE</article-title>. <source>Tissue antigens</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1399-0039.2007.00975.x">10.1111/j.1399-0039.2007.00975.x</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 18069935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18069935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nelissen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smets</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timmermans</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smeets</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ameloot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Liver X receptors regulate cholesterol homeostasis in oligodendrocytes</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroscience research</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>90</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>60</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jnr.22743">10.1002/jnr.22743</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 21972082?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21972082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duhamel-Clerin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Villarroya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mehtali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lapie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Besnard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gumpel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Cellular expression of an HMGCR promoter-CAT fusion gene in transgenic mouse brain: evidence for a developmental regulation in oligodendrocytes</article-title>. <source>Glia</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/glia.440110106">10.1002/glia.440110106</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 8070893?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8070893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>SMYD1, the myogenic activator, is a direct target of serum response factor and myogenin</article-title>. <source>Nucleic acids research</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>7059</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkp773">10.1093/nar/gkp773</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2790895.<?supplied-pmid 19783823?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19783823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Loser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mehling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loeser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Apelt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grabbe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Epidermal RANKL controls regulatory T-cell numbers via activation of dendritic cells</article-title>. <source>Nature medicine</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1372</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nm1518">10.1038/nm1518</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 17143276?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17143276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Totsuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nemoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>RANK-RANKL signaling pathway is critically involved in the function of CD4+CD25+ regulatory T cells in chronic colitis</article-title>. <source>Journal of immunology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>182</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>6079</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.0711823">10.4049/jimmunol.0711823</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 19414759?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19414759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jarjour</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nait Oumesmar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kerninon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krezel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Retinoid X receptor gamma signaling accelerates CNS remyelination</article-title>. <source>Nature neuroscience</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nn.2702">10.1038/nn.2702</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4013508.<?supplied-pmid 21131950?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21131950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Raddatz</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hansmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spitzbarth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalkuhl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deschl</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Transcriptomic meta-analysis of multiple sclerosis and its experimental models</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e86643</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0086643">10.1371/journal.pone.0086643</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3903571.<?supplied-pmid 24475162?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24475162</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pedre</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stempfl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kleiter</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Couillard-Despres</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aigner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Novel role for SLPI in MOG-induced EAE revealed by spinal cord expression analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroinflammation</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1742-2094-5-20">10.1186/1742-2094-5-20</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2438345.<?supplied-pmid 18501024?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18501024</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/</ext-link> [Internet].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Juchem</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stefanopoulos</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Modis</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>. <article-title>RNA sequencing of microglia and monocyte-derived macrophages from mice with experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis illustrates a changing phenotype with disease course</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroimmunology</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>277</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jneuroim.2014.09.014">10.1016/j.jneuroim.2014.09.014</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 25270668?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25270668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>International Multiple Sclerosis Genetics C</collab>, <name><surname>Beecham</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Patsopoulos</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xifara</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kemppinen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Analysis of immune-related loci identifies 48 new susceptibility variants for multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Nature genetics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.2770">10.1038/ng.2770</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3832895.<?supplied-pmid 24076602?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24076602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>International Multiple Sclerosis Genetics C</collab>, <collab>Wellcome Trust Case Control C</collab>, <name><surname>Sawcer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hellenthal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pirinen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Genetic risk and a primary role for cell-mediated immune mechanisms in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>476</volume>(<issue>7359</issue>):<fpage>214</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature10251">10.1038/nature10251</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3182531.<?supplied-pmid 21833088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21833088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoppmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Graetz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paterka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poisa-Beiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larochelle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>New candidates for CD4 T cell pathogenicity in experimental neuroinflammation and multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Brain: a journal of neurology</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>Pt 4</issue>):<fpage>902</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/brain/awu408">10.1093/brain/awu408</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 25665584?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25665584</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frischer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weigand</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kale</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pirko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Clinical and pathological insights into the dynamic nature of the white matter multiple sclerosis plaque</article-title>. <source>Annals of neurology</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>710</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ana.24497">10.1002/ana.24497</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4623970.<?supplied-pmid 26239536?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26239536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Patrikios</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stadelmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kutzelnigg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rauschka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmidbauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laursen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Remyelination is extensive in a subset of multiple sclerosis patients</article-title>. <source>Brain: a journal of neurology</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>Pt 12</issue>):<fpage>3165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/brain/awl217">10.1093/brain/awl217</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 16921173?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16921173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Patani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balaratnam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Remyelination can be extensive in multiple sclerosis despite a long disease course</article-title>. <source>Neuropathology and applied neurobiology</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>277</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2990.2007.00805.x">10.1111/j.1365-2990.2007.00805.x</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 17442065?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17442065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Di Palma</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Belyantseva</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kachar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Noben-Trauth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mutations in Mcoln3 associated with deafness and pigmentation defects in varitint-waddler (Va) mice</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>14994</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.222425399">10.1073/pnas.222425399</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC137533.<?supplied-pmid 12403827?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12403827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guerrini</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Danks</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Penninger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Inhibition of the TNF Family Cytokine RANKL Prevents Autoimmune Inflammation in the Central Nervous System</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2015.10.017">10.1016/j.immuni.2015.10.017</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 26680207?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26680207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lock</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hermans</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pedotti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brendolan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schadt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garren</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Gene-microarray analysis of multiple sclerosis lesions yields new targets validated in autoimmune encephalomyelitis</article-title>. <source>Nature medicine</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>500</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nm0502-500">10.1038/nm0502-500</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 11984595?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11984595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of the mevalonate pathway</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>343</volume>(<issue>6257</issue>):<fpage>425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/343425a0">10.1038/343425a0</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 1967820?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1967820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zipp</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waiczies</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aktas</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hemmer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schraven</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Impact of HMG-CoA reductase inhibition on brain pathology</article-title>. <source>Trends in pharmacological sciences</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>342</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2007.05.001">10.1016/j.tips.2007.05.001</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 17573124?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17573124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sena</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pedrosa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Graca Morais</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Therapeutic potential of lovastatin in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Journal of neurology</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>250</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. .<?supplied-pmid 12862032?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12862032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vollmer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Key</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durkalski</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tyor</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Corboy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Markovic-Plese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Oral simvastatin treatment in relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>363</volume>(<issue>9421</issue>):<fpage>1607</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(04)16205-3">10.1016/S0140-6736(04)16205-3</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 15145635?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15145635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chataway</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schuerer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alsanousi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacManus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Effect of high-dose simvastatin on brain atrophy and disability in secondary progressive multiple sclerosis (MS-STAT): a randomised, placebo-controlled, phase 2 trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>383</volume>(<issue>9936</issue>):<fpage>2213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(13)62242-4">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)62242-4</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 24655729?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24655729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref086"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>. <article-title>cDNA cloning of mouse and human cholesterol 25-hydroxylases, polytopic membrane proteins that synthesize a potent oxysterol regulator of lipid metabolism</article-title>. <source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>273</volume>(<issue>51</issue>):<fpage>34316</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>. .<?supplied-pmid 9852097?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9852097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref087"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tontonoz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Liver X receptors in lipid metabolism: opportunities for drug discovery</article-title>. <source>Nature reviews Drug discovery</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrd4280">10.1038/nrd4280</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 24833295?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24833295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref088"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Giorelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Livrea</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Minervini</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trojano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Immunomodulatory properties of increased levels of liver X receptor beta in peripheral blood mononuclear cells from multiple sclerosis patients</article-title>. <source>Experimental neurology</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>204</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>759</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.expneurol.2007.01.013">10.1016/j.expneurol.2007.01.013</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 17337267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17337267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref089"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Diab</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lovett-Racke</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chavis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Racke</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ligands for the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma and the retinoid X receptor exert additive anti-inflammatory effects on experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroimmunology</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>148</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>116</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jneuroim.2003.11.010">10.1016/j.jneuroim.2003.11.010</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 14975592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14975592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref090"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chavis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Racke</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-alpha and retinoid X receptor agonists inhibit inflammatory responses of astrocytes</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroimmunology</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>176</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jneuroim.2006.04.019">10.1016/j.jneuroim.2006.04.019</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 16764943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16764943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref091"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Storer</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chavis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Racke</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Agonists for the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-alpha and the retinoid X receptor inhibit inflammatory responses of microglia</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroscience research</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jnr.20518">10.1002/jnr.20518</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 15968640?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15968640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref092"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang-Gandhi</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Liver X receptor and retinoid X receptor agonists inhibit inflammatory responses of microglia and astrocytes</article-title>. <source>Journal of neuroimmunology</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>183</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jneuroim.2006.11.007">10.1016/j.jneuroim.2006.11.007</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2080645.<?supplied-pmid 17175031?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17175031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref093"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Voelter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Melms</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalbacher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>New poteintial serum biomarkers in multiple sclerosis identified by proteomic strategies</article-title>. <source>Current medicinal chemistry</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>1544</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. .<?supplied-pmid 24180278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24180278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref094"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schuldt</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rajasekaran</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riese</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>IQGAP1: insights into the function of a molecular puppeteer</article-title>. <source>Molecular immunology</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>336</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molimm.2015.02.012">10.1016/j.molimm.2015.02.012</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4480615.<?supplied-pmid 25733387?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25733387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref095"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dudek</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hepler</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulator of G Protein Signaling 14: A Molecular Brake on Synaptic Plasticity Linked to Learning and Memory</article-title>. <source>Progress in molecular biology and translational science</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>206</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/bs.pmbts.2015.03.006">10.1016/bs.pmbts.2015.03.006</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 26123307?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26123307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref096"><label>96</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alenghat</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baca</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pao</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matozaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lowell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Macrophages require Skap2 and Sirpalpha for integrin-stimulated cytoskeletal rearrangement</article-title>. <source>Journal of cell science</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>Pt 22</issue>):<fpage>5535</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1242/jcs.111260">10.1242/jcs.111260</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3561861.<?supplied-pmid 22976304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22976304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref097"><label>97</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shiota</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kouroku-Murakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujita-Jimbo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Urase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Spatial and temporal expression of RA70/Scap2 in the developing neural tube</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience letters</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>576</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neulet.2014.05.013">10.1016/j.neulet.2014.05.013</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 24846415?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24846415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0157754.ref098"><label>98</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shete</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Houlston</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Claus</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barnholtz-Sloan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Genome-wide high-density SNP linkage search for glioma susceptibility loci: results from the Gliogene Consortium</article-title>. <source>Cancer research</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>7568</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-11-0013">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-11-0013</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3242820.<?supplied-pmid 22037877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22037877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>