<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3749233</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-20915</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073586</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Complete <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> Transcriptome during Colonization of a Natural Host Determined by RNAseq</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">The In Vivo Transcriptome of <italic>C. jejuni</italic> by RNAseq</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taveirne</surname><given-names>Michael E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Theriot</surname><given-names>Casey M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Livny</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>DiRita</surname><given-names>Victor J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of Michigan Medical School, Ann Arbor, Michigan, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Pulmonary and Critical Care, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Genome Sequencing and Analysis Program, Broad Institute, Cambridge, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Rasko</surname><given-names>David&#x000a0;A</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Maryland School of Medicine, United States of America</addr-line></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>vdirita@umich.edu</email> (VJD); <email>livny@broadinstitute.org</email> (JL)</corresp><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MET CMT JL VJD. Performed the experiments: MET CMT JL. Analyzed the data: MET CMT JL VJD. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MET CMT JL VJD. Wrote the manuscript: MET CMT JL VJD. </p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e73586</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Taveirne et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter jejuni</named-content></italic> is a major human pathogen and a leading cause of bacterial derived gastroenteritis worldwide. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> regulates gene expression under various environmental conditions and stresses, indicative of its ability to survive in diverse niches. Despite this ability to highly regulate gene transcription, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> encodes few transcription factors and its genome lacks many canonical transcriptional regulators. High throughput deep sequencing of mRNA transcripts (termed RNAseq) has been used to study the transcriptome of many different organisms, including <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>; however, this technology has yet to be applied to defining the transcriptome of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> during <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization of its natural host, the chicken. In addition to its use in profiling the abundance of annotated genes, RNAseq is a powerful tool for identifying and quantifying, as-of-yet, unknown transcripts including non-coding regulatory RNAs, 5&#x02019; untranslated regulatory elements, and anti-sense transcripts. Here we report the complete transcriptome of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> during colonization of the chicken cecum and in two different <italic>in vitro</italic> growth phases using strand-specific RNAseq. Through this study, we identified over 250 genes differentially expressed <italic>in vivo</italic> in addition to numerous putative regulatory RNAs, including trans-acting non-coding RNAs and anti-sense transcripts. These latter potential regulatory elements were not identified in two prior studies using ORF-based microarrays, highlighting the power and value of the RNAseq approach. Our results provide new insights into how <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> responds and adapts to the cecal environment and reveals new functions involved in colonization of its natural host.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This project was supported in part with federal funds from the USDA to MET [Grant Number: 2012- 67012-19704], the NIAID to VJD [Grant Number: AI-076608] and from the NHLBI to CMT [Grant Number: T32-HL007749]. Additionally, this project has been funded in whole or in part with Federal funds from the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Department of Health and Human Services, under Contract No.: HHSN272200900018C to JL. Its contents are solely the responsibility of the authors and do not necessarily represent the official views of the USDA, the NIAID, the DHHS or the NIH. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter jejuni</named-content></italic> is an important human pathogen and a leading cause of bacterial derived gastroenteritis worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Human <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> infections are sporadic foodborne diseases commonly associated with foods of animal origin, with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> being the predominant species associated with human illness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Preventative measures to limit human exposure have focused on identifying genes and loci required for colonization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] as these represent targets for anti-<named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> strategies. Although much research has been carried out characterizing regulatory mechanisms in this human pathogen, most of this work has focused on <italic>in vitro</italic> studies with little knowledge generated towards understanding the mechanisms of global gene expression during colonization.</p><p>The five <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> strains sequenced to date contain approximately 1,650 to 1,800 protein-encoding genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> highly regulates gene expression under various stresses and environmental conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Despite its ability to rapidly alter gene expression, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> encodes only three sigma factors and a total of 34 other identified transcriptional regulators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Furthermore, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> lacks homologues of many canonical transcriptional regulators such as FNR, CRP, OxyR, RpoS, SoxRS and ArcA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Although there appears to be a paucity of encoded transcription factors, other mechanisms of gene regulation have been identified in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>. Slip-strand mispairing, leading to phase variation gene expression, has been demonstrated to be a regulatory mechanism of flagella biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], lipooligosaccharide glycosylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], and capsule production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Furthermore, genome rearrangements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], interspecies genetic exchange [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] and modification of RNA polymerase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] are alternative mechanisms of genetic regulation employed by <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>.</p><p>Regulatory networks in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> have been characterized principally through <italic>in vitro</italic> methods including quantitative reverse transcriptase PCR (qRT-PCR), transcriptional reporter strains and microarray studies. These have yielded tremendous amounts of information as to how this organism regulates gene expression; however, many of these studies focused on regulatory mechanisms of specific genes and loci in response to specific substrates and culture conditions <italic>in vitro</italic>. Only two studies have evaluated the transcriptome of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> during <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization of an animal model, including the day-of-hatch chicken model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] and the rabbit ileal loop model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. These studies, utilizing microarray approaches, determined that there are marked differences in gene expression profiles between <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> samples, illustrating the importance for continued research into how <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> regulates gene expression during colonization.</p><p>High throughput sequencing of cDNA libraries (RNAseq) has emerged as a powerful approach for mapping transcriptomes and profiling gene expression in diverse bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. RNAseq has several key advantages over microarray analysis, including 1) the ability to detect and quantify transcripts derived from all regions of the genome, 2) a large dynamic range that affords high sensitivity for low-abundance transcripts, and 3) single nucleotide resolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>].</p><p>Regulatory mechanisms involving small, non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs), or riboswitches have not been well-characterized in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>. Recently, two <italic>in vitro</italic> RNAseq studies mapped the transcriptome of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> and other <named-content content-type="genus-species"><named-content content-type="genus">Campylobacter</named-content> species</named-content> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. One study characterized the regulon of the sigma factor RpoN and correlated transcriptome expression data with protein expression profiles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. In the other study, RNAseq was used to map and compare transcriptional start sites, characterize promoter structures and analyze CRISPR RNAs in multiple <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> strains and species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Moreover, both studies identified a wide repertoire of potential non-coding RNA species. These <italic>in vitro</italic> RNAseq studies have yielded much information into regulatory mechanisms encoded by <named-content content-type="genus-species"><named-content content-type="genus">Campylobacter</named-content> species</named-content>; however, this powerful tool has yet to be applied to characterizing the transcriptome of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> during colonization of its natural host. Although, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> encodes non-coding RNA species, it does not encode the conserved RNA binding protein Hfq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], a key component of sRNA regulatory mechanisms in other organisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> does, however, encode another conserved RNA binding protein CsrA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] which, in other organisms, plays a role in regulating many processes including motility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>], virulence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>], biofilm formation and central carbon metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. The <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> CsrA homologue is involved in the oxidative stress response, biofilm formation, and host cell invasion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Unlike other microbes that use CsrA, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> does not encode any obvious homologue of the CsrA-antagonizing small RNA <italic>csrB</italic>; thus the mechanism of CsrA regulation in this pathogen is unknown. Although the regulatory mechanisms of non-coding RNAs have yet to be characterized in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>, the genome of the closely related organism <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Helicobacter pylori</named-content></italic> (which like <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> encodes CsrA but not Hfq), encodes non-coding RNAs as well as riboswitches and antisense transcripts involved in regulatory processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>], suggesting <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> may also regulate gene expression with non-coding RNAs.</p><p>Here we report the first complete transcriptome of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> during <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization of the chicken cecum using RNAseq. We used a strand-specific, library construction protocol to identify both sense and antisense transcripts. Through this study we identified 272 genes that are differentially expressed <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-log and stationary phase grown cultures and identified 51 potential RNA regulators including small, non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs), anti-sense transcripts and probable riboswitches. We also identified the structure of the chick cecal microbiome and identified differences in microbiome structure in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> colonized chicks compared to mock infected controls. Overall, we identified <italic>in vivo</italic> expression patterns and possible uncharacterized regulatory mechanisms that provide insight into how <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> is able to adapt to diverse environments.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="s2.1"><title>Mapping the in vivo and in vitro transcriptome of <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content> using Illumina-based RNAseq</title><p><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> gene expression is highly regulated; however, the mechanisms of this regulation are still largely uncharacterized. To profile the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> transcriptome <italic>in vivo</italic>, RNA was isolated from the cecal contents of chicks seven days post colonization with an average of ~7.5 x 10<sup>8</sup><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> CFU/g cecal contents. To generate enough starting RNA for library construction (5 &#x000b5;g of DNA-free RNA), RNA isolated from five separate chicks housed in the same brooder, was pooled together. In total, three pools of RNA were isolated from three separate sets of chicks. <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> strand specific, bar-coded cDNA libraries were generated using methods described by Mandlik et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Bar-coded cDNA libraries were also generated from three independent cultures of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> grown in Mueller Hinton Broth (MHB) to mid-log and stationary phase, respectively. The six <italic>in vitro</italic> libraries were sequenced on a total of two lanes of the Illumina HiSeq2000 platform; each of the three <italic>in vivo</italic> samples was sequenced in its own lane. The average number of reads obtained for <italic>in vitro</italic> samples was ~125.4 million reads per sample, with ~87.2% of reads mapping to the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> 81-176 chromosome and two plasmids, pVir and pTet (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>). Sequencing of the <italic>in vivo</italic> samples resulted in ~378.8 million reads per sample, in which ~14.6% of reads mapped to the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> chromosome and plasmids (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>). Most reads mapped to open reading frames; however, many reads mapped to intergenic non-coding regions on the chromosome as well as locations anti-sense to open reading frames (ORFs), suggesting that <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> encodes ncRNAs that could be involved in uncharacterized regulatory mechanisms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g001">Figure 1A</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Summary of sequencing results of <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> Illumina based cDNA libraries.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth Condition</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample #</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Reads (in millions)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Reads Aligned to Genome</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Reads Aligned in Pairs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mid-Log</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.52</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Stationary</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.51</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">389.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.58</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Chick</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">379.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">367.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.56</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="pone-0073586-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073586.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Mapping and expression profiles of <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> sequence reads to the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> 81-176 genome.</title><p>A. Distribution of reads (as percent of total reads) that mapped back to specific locations of the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> 81-176 genome. B. Venn diagram of genes with increased and decreased abundance <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> samples. ORF: open reading frame, IGR: intergenic region, rRNA: ribosomal RNA, tRNA: transfer RNA, ncRNA: non-coding RNA, Anti-sense: anti-sense RNA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0073586.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2.2"><title>Structural differences in the chicken microbiome do not correlate to changes in <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content> global gene expression during colonization</title><p>To determine the relative abundance of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> in the chick ceca during colonization, we performed 454-pyrosequencing of the 16S rRNA gene isolated from the same <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> colonized chicks used in RNAseq experiments, as well as PBS (mock) infected chicks. DNA based 454-pyrosequencing analysis of the V3-V5 region of the 16S rRNA gene yielded a total of 87,663 sequences, which after trimming and chimera removal by the analysis program mothur [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>], yielded 48,571 sequences with minimum read length of 250 base pairs. On average, <italic>Campylobacters</italic> represented between 5&#x02013;10% of the total number of sequences identified in the ceca of brooder 1 (10%), 2 (5%) and 3 (5%), (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). We identified differences in the structure of the cecal microbiota at the phylum, family and OTU (Operational Taxonomic Unit) level between brooder sets and PBS control chicks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s001">S1</xref>). Previous studies investigating the cecal microbiota of pathogen free and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> colonized chicks showed a difference in phylotype distribution; however, no changes in the microbiota functional gene content was identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. In this study, chicks colonized with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> had microbiome structures distinct from the PBS control group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). The structure of the cecal microbiota of chicks colonized with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> housed in brooder 1 was statistically different from chicks housed in brooders 2 and 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). Moreover, at the family level, chicks in brooder 1 showed an increase (compared to the other brooders) in the relative abundance of Ruminococcaceae, <named-content content-type="family">Leuconostocaceae</named-content> and <named-content content-type="family">Enterococcaceae</named-content> families and a decrease in members of the <named-content content-type="family">Lachnospiraceae</named-content> family (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Brooder 1 chicks also had an increase in the relative abundance of <named-content content-type="family">Campylobacteraceae</named-content> (~10%) compared to brooders 2 and 3 (~5%). This poses questions as to whether the indigenous cecal microbiota dictates the level of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> colonization, or if the level of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> colonization results in distinct shifts in the microbiota. Although there was a significant difference in the bacterial community structure between brooders, there was no significant difference (avg. R-value of 0.979) in the global transcriptome profiles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s002">Figure S2</xref>, G-I), indicating that changes in the cecal microbiota, observed in this study, did not result in changes in the global gene expression of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>. This is in agreement with the result that changes in the microbiota of chicks colonized with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> did not alter functional gene content of the microbiome within the chick cecum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. In this study, we observed no changes in transcriptome profiles between animal replicates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s002">Figure S2 G&#x02013;I</xref>); in contrast, a previous transcriptome study of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>, using the rabbit illeal loop model (RIL), showed wide variances in transcript abundance between animals (R value of 0.49) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. The difference between the two sets of findings could be due to differences in animal models (RIL v. 1-day-old chicks), including host immune response and the host microbiota structure and function, and/or the result of differences in transcriptomic technologies (microarray v. RNAseq).</p><fig id="pone-0073586-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073586.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>The cecal microbiota of chickens colonized with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>.</title><p>A. Defining members of the cecal microbiota by relative rank abundance plots (&#x0003e;1%) at the bacterial family level. The average relative abundance for each treatment group (PBS control n=5; brooder 1 n=5; brooder 2 n=5; brooder 3 n=5) is represented in the bar plot. B. Principle coordinates analysis (PCoA) illustrating the community structure relationship between chicks from different treatment groups. This ordination was generated using a Yue and Clayton-based distance matrix representing the relative abundance of OTUs in each community at a 3% OTU definition level. The community of each chick is indicated by a colored symbol (PBS control = blue; brooder 1 = black; brooder 2 = green; brooder 3 = red). All brooder bacterial communities were significantly different from PBS controls (<italic>p</italic>=0.008 for brooder1 and <italic>p</italic>=0.007 for brooder 2 and 3; AMOVA). Brooder 1 was significantly different from Brooder 2 and 3 (<italic>p</italic>=0.003 and <italic>p</italic>=0.015, respectively; AMOVA).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0073586.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2.3"><title>Differential gene expression during colonization of the chicken cecum and validation of RNAseq</title><p>To analyze differential expression of transcripts between <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> samples we utilized the variance analysis package DESeq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. A substantial number of genes were significantly differentially expressed (&#x0003e;4-fold, p<sub>adj</sub> &#x0003c;0.05) <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to both <italic>in vitro</italic> conditions. Differential expression profiles of chick samples compared to mid-log samples identified 149 genes that were differentially expressed; 135 transcripts showed increased abundance <italic>in vivo</italic> while 14 genes had decreased abundance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g001">Figure 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s003">Tables S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s004">S2</xref>). Comparing DESeq of chick samples to stationary samples, 152 genes were significantly differentially expressed (&#x0003e;4-fold, p<sub>adj</sub> &#x0003c;0.05); 95 transcripts with increased abundance compared to 57 with decreased abundance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g001">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s005">Tables S3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s006">S4</xref>). Of the genes with increased abundance <italic>in vivo</italic>, 29 were increased in comparison to both <italic>in vitro</italic> conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g001">Figure 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2</xref>). No transcripts were found to be decreased in abundance in both conditions with a &#x0003e;4-fold cutoff. All genes significantly differentially expressed (&#x0003e;4-fold, p<sub>adj</sub> &#x0003c;0.05) during <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> growth, and those differentially expressed between <italic>in vitro</italic> growth conditions, are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s003">Tables S1-S6</xref>. Expression profiles of every gene, under all growth conditions, are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s011">Table S9</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Genes increased in abundance <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to both <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-log and stationary phase cultures.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ Locus Number</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Name / Function</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Change (ML)<xref rid="ngtab2.1">*</xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold Change (Stat)<xref rid="ngtab2.1">*</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Energy and Metabolism</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0044</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dsbB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome c Fmaily</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0403</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sulphite Oxidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0880</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dsbA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Stress Response</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1387</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>katA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">320.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1574</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cgb</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.72</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Transport</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0642</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pstS</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.54</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0643</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pstA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0644</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pstC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.74</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0750</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transporter periplasmic substrate binding protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.95</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0753</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transporter periplasmic substrate binding protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0754</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transporter periplasmic substrate binding protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1601</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>chuA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.54</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>chuB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1603</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>chuC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.79</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1604</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>chuD</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1619</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>exbB-2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1620</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>exbD</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Other</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1388</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ankyrin repeat protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.96</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hypothetical</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.76</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0063</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.74</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0065</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.66</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0522</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0751</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0752</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0954</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1386</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1746</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.06</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ngtab2.1"><label>*</label><p>p<sub>adj</sub> &#x0003c; 0.05, a corrected p-value analogous to a false detection rate of &#x0003c; 5%.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To validate expression patterns identified by RNAseq, we performed qRT-PCR on RNA isolated from <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> grown cultures. RNA used in qRT-PCR experiments was isolated independent from samples used in RNAseq library construction. Primers were designed to amplify genes with increased, decreased or unchanged levels of transcript abundance <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> samples (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s010">Table S8</xref>). RNAseq identified <italic>katA</italic> as one of the highest abundant transcripts during colonization compared to both <italic>in vitro</italic> growth conditions, and this increase in abundance was confirmed by qRT-PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Furthermore, genes identified as having decreased transcript abundance (<italic>Cjj0315</italic> and <italic>Cjj0067</italic>) or no changes in transcript abundance (<italic>cjaC</italic> and <italic>ccoN</italic>) during colonization, compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> grown cultures, were also confirmed by qRT-PCR, validating the RNAseq expression profiles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Because differential expression analysis (DESeq) combined and averaged sequencing results from the three biological replicates, we wanted to confirm that transcript abundance between replicates was similar. Expression profiles between each biological replicate were compared by plotting the abundance (log<sub>2</sub>) of each ORF between all replicates of each growth condition. Transcript abundance between replicates, of all three growth conditions, showed no statistical differences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s002">Figure S2</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0073586-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073586.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Validation of RNAseq expression analysis by qRT-PCR.</title><p>Relative expression levels of genes determined by RNAseq to be differentially expressed <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to A. <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-log cultures and B. <italic>in vitro</italic> stationary phase cultures. Relative expression was assessed using the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) method, error bars represent standard deviation of three independent biological replicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0073586.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2.4"><title>Insights into the intestinal environment during <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content> colonization derived from global transcript regulatory patterns</title><p>To identify global regulation patterns occurring <italic>in vivo</italic>, we graphed DESeq analyses on MA plots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g004">Figure 4</xref>). MA plots represent the log<sub>2</sub> of the ratio of abundances of each ORF between the indicated conditions [M], plotted against the average log<sub>2</sub> abundance of that ORF in all conditions [A]. Three functional gene groups were identified as increased in abundance during colonization including iron transport, phosphate transport and oxidative and nitrosative stress responses. Iron has been consistently identified as a critical micronutrient for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> growth and colonization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. Increased expression of the heme transport genes <italic>chuA</italic> and <italic>chuB</italic> were previously identified in an <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content> in vivo</italic> microarray transcriptome study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Utilizing RNAseq, we confirmed the increased abundance of <italic>chuA</italic> and <italic>chuB</italic> transcripts along with <italic>chuC</italic> and <italic>chuD</italic> of the heme transport operon (<italic>chuABCD</italic>). Additionally, we identified two other iron transporters with increased expression <italic>in vivo</italic>, including the outer membrane TonB-dependent energy transduction system <italic>exbB-exbD</italic>-<italic>tonB</italic> and the ferric transport system FTR1-<italic>p19</italic>. The increased abundance of three iron transport systems suggests that the chicken cecum is an extremely iron-limiting environment.</p><fig id="pone-0073586-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073586.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Differential gene expression (DESeq) of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> during <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization and <italic>in vitro</italic> growth.</title><p>(A&#x02013;C) The log<sub>2</sub> of the ratio of abundances of each gene between the indicated conditions [M] plotted against the average log<sub>2</sub> of abundance of that gene in all conditions [A]. For each plot, [M] and [A] values were generated with DESeq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] using data from three biological replicates of each <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> growth condition. Genes significantly differentially expressed (&#x0003e;4-fold p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05) as well genes of specific functional groups are highlighted (see legend for functional group highlight annotation). Grey regions highlight expression differences greater-than and less-than 4-fold.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0073586.g004"/></fig><p>Transcripts from the phosphate transport system (<italic>pstSCAB</italic>) were increased in abundance <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to both <italic>in vitro</italic> conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g005">Figure 5B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s003">Tables S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s005">S3</xref>); however, in contrast to the iron transport systems noted above, increased expression of this locus was not observed in either previous <italic>in vivo</italic> microarray transcriptome study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. In addition to this ABC-type transport system, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> encodes a low affinity non-specific phosphate transport system <italic>pitAB</italic> (<italic>Cjj1208, Cjj1209</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], which was not differentially expressed to any significant extent in our studies. In response to phosphate limitation, the <italic>pst</italic> transport system is activated by the two-component system PhoSR; <italic>pst</italic> is required for growth in phosphate-limited media [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] while the <italic>pitAB</italic> locus has yet to be characterized. A role for <italic>pitAB</italic> and <italic>pstSCAB in vivo</italic> has yet to be determined in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>, but increased abundance of the <italic>pst</italic> system <italic>in vivo</italic> suggests that the chick cecum is limited in phosphate and that this system could be required for colonization based on its importance <italic>in vitro</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>].</p><fig id="pone-0073586-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073586.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Gene expression profiles of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> during <italic>in vitro</italic> growth and <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization.</title><p>Histograms illustrating strand-specific coverage per nucleotide across multiple loci on the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> chromosome. Red lines represent reads sequenced and mapped from <italic>in vivo</italic> chick libraries. Blue (mid-log) and green (stationary) lines represent reads sequenced and mapped from <italic>in vitro</italic> libraries. ORF&#x02019;s are labeled below each histogram in blue. Specific loci A) <italic>katA</italic>, B) <italic>pstSCAB</italic>, C) <italic>cgb</italic>, which were increased in abundance during <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization, are highlighted in red.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0073586.g005"/></fig><p>Furthermore, increased <italic>in vivo</italic> transcript abundance (compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> growth) was observed from genes involved in oxidative and nitrosative stress responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g004">Figure 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g005">Figure 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s003">Tables S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s005">S3</xref>). The second highest differentially expressed gene <italic>in vivo</italic>, <italic>katA</italic> (encoding catalase), is critical for the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> response to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and is required for colonization of the chicken cecum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g005">Figure 5A</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. Additionally, the truncated flavohemoprotein (<italic>cgb</italic>), involved in the nitrosative stress response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>], was highly expressed <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). The high level of expression of these two important stress response genes during <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization corresponds with studies demonstrating that <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> induces a host immune response in the chicken [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]. Specifically, RNAseq analysis of chicken cecal tissue during colonization with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> showed increased expression of NOXO1, (NADPH oxidase organizer 1) which regulates respiratory burst [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. Moreover, infection of human HCT-8 intestinal epithelial cells with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> activated host Nox1 and Duox2, resulting in increased H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production and consequent inactivation of CjtK. CjtK, a tyrosine kinase encoded by <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>, activates GalE, required for glycosylation and capsule formation, important factors in adherence and invasion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. The high level of catalase gene expression during <italic>in vivo</italic> growth suggests that <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> is responding to host H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production, which might be a mechanism to avoid inactivation of CjtK allowing for adherence and invasion. Furthermore, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> elicits a TLR response in chicks, specifically activating TLR-2, TLR-4 and TLR-21 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. Most importantly, TLR signaling was shown to be induced when using <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> cell lysates compared to whole cells, proposing that bacterial lysis (evoking a hostile host environment) is required for full TLR activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. Although <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> is considered a commensal that does not induce human-like disease symptoms in chicks, it does elicit an immune response; therefore, increasing expression of stress response genes could possibly result in a mechanism for <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> to postpone lysis, preventing a robust immune response, resulting in persistent colonization.</p><p>Overall, we identified 272 transcripts that were differentially expressed <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s003">Tables S1-S4</xref>). Many of the genes whose abundance increased <italic>in vivo</italic> contribute to cellular processes including central carbon metabolism, electron transport, biosynthetic processes and transport systems, indicative of a nutrient-restricted environment in the chick cecum compared to the rich <italic>in vitro</italic> growth medium MHB. We observed that <italic>in vivo</italic> abundance of RNA transcripts from the pTet plasmid were extremely low, with some transcripts never detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g004">Figure 4</xref>). This suggests either that <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> strongly down-regulates expression of this plasmid <italic>in vivo</italic>, or that the plasmid is lost at a high rate during colonization. Both pTet and pVir are conjugative plasmids in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> 81-176 and both contain type-4 secretion system (T4SS) genes, with only genes encoded on pVir functionally characterized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>]. Involvement of pVir in attachment, invasion and disease during colonization of ferrets has been demonstrated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>]; however, no mechanism by which pTet might contribute to colonization has been uncovered. Genes involved in histidine biosynthesis and nitrogen metabolism (<italic>hisH</italic> and <italic>hisF</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>] were decreased <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s004">Table S2</xref>), suggesting that the chick cecum could be replete with histidine and/or glutamate. In <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>, <italic>hisH</italic> and <italic>hisF</italic> have been implicated in the biosynthesis of intermediates of the flagellar glyscosylation pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>]; however, no role in chick colonization has been determined. Similarly, the major antigenic peptide (PEB3) was also determined to be decreased in abundance <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s004">Table S2</xref>). This glycoprotein is immunoreactive [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>] suggesting that decreased expression could be a mechanism to evade host recognition leading to persistent colonization.</p><p>Comparison of RNAseq expression profiles to those of a previous <italic>in vivo</italic> transcriptome study using microarrays revealed many differences in expression patterns along with some similarities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Most evident are the total number of differentially regulated genes between the two experiments, with microarray identifying only 68 differentially expressed genes (&#x0003e;2-fold), while RNAseq identified 272 differentially expressed genes, even using a higher stringency cutoff (&#x0003e;4-fold). Functional groups identified as differentially expressed in both experiments included components of electron transport, central carbon metabolism and transport systems. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> encodes a highly branched electron transport chain allowing for adaptation to specific environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>]. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> is considered a microaerophile but has been shown to grow anaerobically in the presence of alternative electron acceptors including DMSO and nitrate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. RNAseq identified increased abundance of many transcripts associated with electron transport, including DMSO reductase, sulphite oxidase, the low-affinity oxidase (<italic>cioAB</italic>) and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> biogenesis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s003">Tables S1-S4</xref>). Alternatively, there was decreased <italic>in vivo</italic> abundance of NADH: ubiquinone oxidoreductase transcripts (~2-3-fold), which encode proteins responsible for using reduced flavodixin as an electron donor instead of NADH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>], and there was no change in the abundance of the high-affinity oxidase CcoN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). Taken together, and as previously hypothesized, <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> most likely encounters a limited oxygen environment in the cecum, as CioAB is a low-affinity oxidase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>], and <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> has been shown to be able to respire off substrates such as sulphite and DMSO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>]. We did not observe an increase in expression of the nitrate reductase genes (<italic>napAB</italic>) as identified in the previous chick <italic>in vivo</italic> microarray study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. This difference in expression of <italic>napAB</italic> could be a result of growth temperature variation of <italic>in vitro</italic> grown cultures. The nitrate reductase locus is up-regulated at 42&#x000b0;C, compared to 37&#x000b0;C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>]. <italic>In vitro</italic> cultures for RNAseq experiments, reported here, were grown at 42&#x000b0;C in an effort to identify genes that were differentially regulated based on host colonization factors and the host nutritional environment, not differences in temperature, as the internal temperature of the chicken is 42&#x000b0;C. Additionally, expression differences could be due to different colonization conditions (including strain differences, inoculum load, duration of colonization and <italic>in vitro</italic> growth conditions). Finally, these differences could also be attributed to differences in transcriptome mapping technologies, as RNAseq affords direct quantification of transcripts and high sensitivity for low-abundance transcripts. As transcriptome studies are snapshots of gene expression, it would be interesting to determine <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> gene expression profiles over time during the course of colonization. This would allow for a more in-depth profile of the transcriptome during initial colonization through persistent colonization.</p></sec><sec id="s2.5"><title>Identification of non-coding and anti-sense RNA species</title><p>We next mined our RNAseq data for non-coding RNAs and identified 51 putative ncRNA candidates on the chromosome (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab3">Table 3</xref>) and on plasmid pTet (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s009">Table S7</xref>), including transcripts derived from intergenic regions and anti-sense to open reading frames (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g006">Figure 6</xref>). Our analysis identified nearly all the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> ncRNAs annotated in the Rfam database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>], including the thiamin pyrophosphate (TPP) riboswitch, the bacterial signal recognition particle (SRP), tmRNA and the RNA component of RNase P [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>]. Similarly, we detected expression of 17 of the 25 ncRNAs identified in previous <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> RNAseq studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. In several cases, expression of ncRNAs previously identified in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> strain NCTC11168 were not detected in our analysis of strain 81-176, despite the conservation of these loci in both strains, an observation consistent with recent studies in <named-content content-type="genus-species"><named-content content-type="genus">Campylobacter</named-content> sp.</named-content> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] and <named-content content-type="genus-species"><named-content content-type="genus">Listeria</named-content> sp.</named-content> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>] showing that expression of conserved ncRNAs may diverge significantly even among strains of the same species. Additionally, several ncRNAs previously identified in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> 81-176 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] were not identified in our study, likely reflecting differences in growth temperatures, RNA library construction protocols, and/or ncRNA prediction algorithms.</p><table-wrap id="tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Non-coding RNAs identified by RNAseq and their differential expression under different growth conditions.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncRNA ID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome Location</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>DESeq</p></list-item><list-item><p><chem-struct><break/>Chick:ML</chem-struct></p></list-item></list></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>DESeq</p></list-item><list-item><p><chem-struct><break/>Chick:Stat</chem-struct></p></list-item></list></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>DESeq</p></list-item><list-item><p><chem-struct><break/>ML:Stat</chem-struct></p></list-item></list></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 1</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100050.100258</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 2</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104909.105040</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 3</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">913140.913278</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 4</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">940044.940212</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 5</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1032051.1032145</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 6</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1190593.1190723</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 7</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1278300.1278473</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 8</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1536244.1536387</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 9</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1566220.1566328</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 10</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77586.77846</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 11</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93760.93891</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 12</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">227132.227266</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 13</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176680.176901</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 14</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250947.251049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 15</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">506475.506785</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 16</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">578796.579113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 17</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">622442.622594</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 18</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">667317.667510</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 19</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">874073.874227</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 20</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">878326.878438</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 21</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">924301.924469</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 22</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1036626.1036898</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 23</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1075868.1076095</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 24</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">361854.361960</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 25</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1248138.1248316</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 26</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1502121.1502247</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 27</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1551155.1551721</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 28</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">457707.457860</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 29</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">459841.460022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 30</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">473652.473826</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 31</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">789226.789789</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 32</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">878386.878507</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc 33</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">910988.911157</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="pone-0073586-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073586.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Expression profiles of non-coding RNA species during <italic>in vitro</italic> growth and <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization.</title><p>Histograms illustrating strand-specific coverage per nucleotide across multiple loci identifying non-coding RNA species. Red lines represent reads sequenced and mapped from <italic>in vivo</italic> chick libraries. Blue (mid-log) and green (stationary) lines represent reads sequenced and mapped from <italic>in vitro</italic> libraries. ORF&#x02019;s are labeled below each histogram in blue. Specific ncRNAs, A. anti-sense nc4, B. intergenic nc18, C. anti-sense nc21, are highlighted by grey boxes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0073586.g006"/></fig><p>The abundance of most of these candidate ncRNAs increased during stationary phase compared to mid-log phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g007">Figure 7A</xref>), suggesting they are likely induced in response to increased stress and/or nutrient limitation. The abundance of these putative ncRNAs was also induced <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to mid-log cultures, though not as much as in stationary phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0073586-g007">Figure 7B and 7C</xref>), again suggesting their expression is likely regulated by similar stimuli and conditions encountered by <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> during its transition from log to stationary growth in culture.</p><fig id="pone-0073586-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073586.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Differential expression of putative non-coding RNA species identified by RNAseq and Rfam analyses.</title><p>(A&#x02013;C) The log<sub>2</sub> of the ratio of abundances of each gene between the indicated conditions [M] plotted against the average log<sub>2</sub> of abundance of that gene in all conditions [A]. For each plot, [M] and [A] values were based on data from three biological replicates from each <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> growth condition. ORFs are marked as dark grey circles. Non-coding RNAs are highlighted in red. Grey regions highlight expression differences greater-than and less-than 4-fold.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0073586.g007"/></fig><p>To investigate possible regulatory mechanisms of the newly identified ncRNAs we utilized the sRNA target prediction program TargetRNA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>]. Non-coding RNAs are a unique class of regulators that can regulate gene expression by different mechanisms, including altering mRNA interactions with the ribosome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>] and modulating mRNA stability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>]. Additionally, ncRNAs can act as cis-regulatory elements or as trans-regulatory elements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>]. We chose to focus on the intergenic ncRNAs for TargetRNA analysis, as these are more likely to act as trans-regulatory elements and potentially have multiple targets. TargetRNA identified at least 4 targets (p-value &#x0003c; 0.01) for eight intergenic encoded ncRNAs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab4">Table 4</xref>). The pattern of abundance of many of these targets was the same or opposite of their cognate ncRNAs among the conditions tested (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab4">Table 4</xref>), suggesting their stability may be regulated by the ncRNA and lending further credence to the TargetRNA predictions. Those targets whose expression patterns were not well correlated with their cognate ncRNA may represent false predictions or correspond to ncRNA: mRNA interactions that do not significantly alter message stability. Further characterization of these putative ncRNAs and target mRNAs will likely yield key insights into <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> regulatory mechanisms and pathways.</p><table-wrap id="tab4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>mRNA targets of ncRNAs analyzed by TargetRNA and their differential expression in different growth conditions.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellpadding="3 "><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncRNA ID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Name / locus number</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TargetRNA Score</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">DESeq of mRNA Target<hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Chick:ML</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Chick:Stat</bold></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>ML:Stat</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc3</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0481</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mviN</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0193</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.08</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.96</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-6.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-13.98</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc5</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1304</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.79</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0289</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1389</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>porA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.02</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc6</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0565</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-112</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tuf</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rpsG</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>flgB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-4.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-11.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc9</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>chuA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.75</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">10.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pgk</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.15</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>neuB1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.31</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>fliN</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-2.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.67</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc14</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>argC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.65</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mutY</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.75</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">2.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0579</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.78</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-2.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0213</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.21</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc18</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1193</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0481</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>secF</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.71</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0973</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.79</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc29</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0193</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.96</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nuoM</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.07</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">2.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0481</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mviN</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc32</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1746</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.01</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">7.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mobB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-2.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_1370</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.06</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nspC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.97</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>nc33</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cutE</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">4.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tlyA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.57</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CJJ81176_0076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">2.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>napL</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.08</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">-1.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The small size of its genome, its lack of an Hfq homologue, and the relatively limited success of genomics-based approaches for identifying ncRNAs in <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>] have led to speculations that <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> does not encode the sizeable arsenal of ncRNAs found in many other bacteria. However, the discovery of numerous putative <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> ncRNAs in this study, and in other recent RNAseq-based studies, suggests that <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> does indeed possess a robust RNA-mediated regulation system and provides insights into the mechanisms by which this organism, which encodes so few canonical transcription factors, is able to effectively adapt to rapidly changing environmental conditions and niches.</p></sec><sec id="s2.6"><title>The&#x000a0;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter jejuni</named-content></italic> RNAseq transcriptome browser</title><p>The RNAseq data generated during the course of this study contains a wealth of information that will be a valuable resource to the numerous researchers studying <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>. To make these data readily accessible to this community, we have generated coverage plots for each RNAseq dataset that can be visualized in the GenomeView browser [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">86</xref>] using the following link:</p><p>http://www.broadinstitute.org/software/genomeview/supplemental/CjVJD13/. This browser allows visualization of expression profiles of all annotated ORFs (under all growth conditions), as well as non-coding RNA species; including 5&#x02019;-UTRs, anti-sense transcripts and intergenic ncRNAs.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Summary</title><p>This is the first report of the complete transcriptome of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> during colonization of the chicken cecum using RNAseq. Through our strand specific library preparation, we identified 51 probable non-coding RNA species, 29 of which were not previously annotated. We also determined the expression profile of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> during colonization, identifying 272 genes that are significantly differentially expressed <italic>in vivo</italic>. Additionally, we characterized the microbiota of the chick cecum during <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> colonization. It was shown that <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> represents ~5-10% of the bacterial population and that structural differences in microbiota profiles do not result in changes in the global <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> transcriptome. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> must rapidly regulate gene expression in response to diverse environmental conditions; however, the regulatory mechanisms underpinning these responses are poorly understood. This work provides key insights into the genes and functions involved in the transition of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> from logarithmic to stationary growth and during its adaption to the chicken cecal environment, as well as revealing a number of putative regulatory ncRNAs that may play key roles in these adaptations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4.1"><title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title><p><italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>&#x000a0;strain DRH212 (an 81-176 streptomycin resistant derivative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>]) was grown on Mueller Hinton agar (BD, Sparks, MD) supplemented with 10% sheep blood (BA) or in Mueller Hinton Broth (MHB) (BD, Sparks, MD). <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>&#x000a0;was cultured at 42&#x000b0;C microaerobically in a tri-gas incubator, constantly maintained at 5% O<sub>2</sub>, 10% CO<sub>2</sub>, balanced with N<sub>2</sub>. Liquid cultures of&#x000a0;<italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic>&#x000a0;were grown in MHB to mid-log or stationary phase (as monitored by optical density Ab<sub>600</sub>).</p></sec><sec id="s4.2"><title>Chicken Colonization</title><p>Animal work carried out in this study followed the recommendations of the National Institutes of Health in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. This protocol was approved by the University Committee on Use and Care of Animals at the University of Michigan (Protocol 10462-1). All efforts were made to minimize suffering of animals throughout the course of the experiment.</p><p>One-day-old chicks were inoculated orally with 1x10<sup>3</sup> CFU of <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> in PBS. Cells used in the inoculum were grown on BA for ~16 h, washed and resuspended in PBS to 10<sup>4</sup> CFU/mL. Chicks were inoculated with 100 &#x000b5;l of cell suspension via oral gavage. Seven days post inoculation, chicks were sacrificed and cecal contents were removed. For RNA isolation, cecal contents were immediately suspended in 1 mL of RNAlater (Qiagen, Valencia CA) and frozen at -80&#x000b0;C. For colonization load and DNA extraction for 454-pyrosequencing, a subsample of cecal contents was removed and diluted in PBS. Colonization load was determined by serially diluting cecal contents and plating on <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> selective media (BA supplemented with Vancomycin [40 &#x000b5;g/ml], Cefoparazone [40 &#x000b5;g/ml], Trimethoprim [10 &#x000b5;g/ml] and Cycloheximide [100 &#x000b5;g/ml]). Plates were incubated at 42&#x000b0;C under microaerobic conditions until countable colonies appeared (~2-3 days). CFU counts were standardized to gram wet weight of cecal content.</p></sec><sec id="s4.3"><title>RNA isolation</title><p><italic>In vitro</italic> RNA was isolated from <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> grown in MHB under microaerobic conditions to mid-log and stationary phase (as monitored by optical density Ab<sub>600</sub>). An equal volume of RNA stop solution (95% EtOH, 5% phenol) was added to the cultures immediately after removal from microaerobic conditions and cells were harvested by centrifugation at 4&#x000b0;C. RNA was extracted with TRIzol&#x000ae; (Invitrogen, Grand Island, NY) as per manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Contaminating DNA was removed with two treatments of TURBO&#x02122; DNase (Invitrogen) per manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. DNase treated RNA was cleaned with RNA clean and concentrate 25 columns after each DNase treatment step (Zymo Research, Irvine, CA). Conformation of DNA removal was assessed by PCR with three sets of primers ranging in amplification products of 100, 150, 250 bp and the Qubit dsDNA high sensitivity assay kit (Life Technologies) (data not shown).</p><p>For <italic>in vivo</italic> RNA isolation, cecal contents were harvested from individual birds and immediately submerged in 1 ml of RNAlater/cecum. <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> was enriched from cecal contents as performed by Jerome et al. in an effort to deplete contaminating eukaryotic cells and cecal debris [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">88</xref>]. After <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> enrichment, RNA was extracted with TRIzol&#x000ae; and contaminating DNA was removed with TURBO&#x02122; DNase as described previously. Purified DNA-free RNA from 5 birds (housed in the same brooder) was pooled to create enough starting DNA-free RNA for Illumina cDNA library construction.</p></sec><sec id="s4.4"><title>Illumina Library Construction</title><p>Illumina cDNA libraries were constructed in a similar manner to Mandlik et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Five micrograms of RNA was depleted of 16S and 23S rRNA species using the Gram Negative Ribo-Zero&#x02122; rRNA Removal Kit (Epicentre, Madison, WI). Removal of contaminating RNA species was assessed with the Agilent Bioanalyzer RNA 6000 nano chip (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA). Depleted mRNA was fragmented into 100-500 bp species with fragmentation buffer from the GeneChip&#x000ae; clean up module kit (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA). First-strand cDNA was synthesized with random hexamers, Actinomycin D and SuperScript III (Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY). Second strand cDNA was synthesized with dUTP replacing dTTP as described by Levin et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>]. Double stranded cDNA ends were repaired and adenylated as described in the Illumina Truseq&#x02122; RNA sample preparation low throughput (LT) protocol (Illumina, San Diego, CA). Bar-coded Illumina adapters were ligated to the ends of the cDNA libraries and adapter-cDNA libraries were treated with Uracil-N-glycosylase (UNG) for 15 min at 37&#x000b0;C, followed by 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min. UNG-treaded cDNA was enriched by low-cycle PCR (8-cylces) with Illumina adapter specific primers. Final cDNA libraries were cleaned with two treatments of AMPureXP beads (Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA), and sequenced using 50 bp paired-end reads on an Illumina HiSeq2000 platform at the University of Michigan Sequencing Core.</p></sec><sec id="s4.5"><title>Quantitative reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction</title><p>PCR primers used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0073586.s010">Table S8</xref> and were used to amplify nucleotide fragments of genes of interest between 100 and 150&#x000a0;bp. Isolation of RNA from&#x000a0;<italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> cultures (independent from RNAseq library preparations) was performed as mentioned previously. qRT-PCR was performed by using the Quantitect Sybr, Green RT-PCR kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA) as by Taveirne et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] and analyzed using the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4.6"><title>RNAseq analysis</title><p>Reads were aligned to the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> chromosome, pTet, and pVir sequence files (RefSeq NC_008787, NC_008770, and NC_008790) using BWA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">91</xref>] version 5.9. Gene annotations were obtained from RefSeq and Rfam [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>]. The overall fragment coverage of genomic regions corresponding to features such as ORFs and rRNAs was conducted as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Differential expression analysis was conducted using DESeq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4.7"><title>Chick ceca microbiota analysis</title><p>DNA extraction was done on untreated chick cecal content, in PBS, using Roche MagNA Pure Compact system according to the Roche MagNA Pure Nucleic Acid Isolation Kit I protocol instructions (Roche, Madison, WI). Amplification of the V3-V5 region of the 16S rRNA gene was accomplished using the Broad HMP protocol (HMP MDG Default Protocol v 4.2). Briefly, extracted DNA was used to construct DNA libraries targeting the V3-V5 hypervariable regions of the 16S rRNA gene using primers 357F (<named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02019;-CCTACGGGAGGCAGCAG-3&#x02019;</named-content>) with a B adaptor (<named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02019;-CCTATCCCCTGTGTGCCTTGGCAGTCTCAG-3&#x02019;</named-content>) and 926R (<named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02019;-CCGTCAATTCMTTTRAGT-3&#x02019;</named-content>) with a unique bar code to identify the target and an A adaptor (<named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02019;-CCATCTCATCCCTGCGTGTCTCCGACTCAG-3&#x02019;</named-content>). A PCR reaction mixture of 1X AccuPrime PCR Buffer II (Invitrogen), 0.15 &#x000b5;l AccuPrime Taq DNA Polymerase High Fidelity, 0.2 &#x000b5;M Primer B, 0.2 &#x000b5;M uniquely bar-coded Primer A was used. DNA was amplified using the following conditions: 95&#x000b0;C for 2 min, 30 cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 20 sec, 50&#x000b0;C for 30 sec and 72&#x000b0;C for 5 min. Amplicons were cleaned with the Agencourt AMPure XP and quantified using the Quant-it PicoGreen dsDNA kit (Invitrogen). Samples were pooled in equal proportion, cleaned again with AMPureXP, and sequenced on the Roche 454 GS Junior Titanium platform according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s specifications. Analysis of 454 Pyrosequencing data was done using mothur (version 1.30.2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Mothur was used to group or assign bacterial 16S rRNA gene sequences into Operational Taxonomic Units (OTUs) using a 3% species level definition. Classifications were determined by comparing sequences to the Ribosomal Database Project [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B92">92</xref>]. Classified OTUs were used to determine the relative abundance of bacterial phyla and family in each sample. Principal coordinates analysis (PCoA) was used to assess community similarity among all samples and was calculated based on Yue and Clayton-based distance matrix [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B93">93</xref>]. An AMOVA (analysis of molecular variance) was performed to determine statistical differences between the community structures of each treatment group. Heatmaps of microbiome data (OTUs) were made using the <italic>heatmap</italic> command in R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">94</xref>]. The <italic>heatmap</italic> command re-orders the data in the rows and the columns separately, so that similar data are grouped together by hierarchical clustering, as shown by dendrograms for the rows and the columns. The Euclidean distance was used in the clustering [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B95">95</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0073586.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><bold>Structural changes to the chicken cecal microbiota.</bold>
A heatmap of the top 25 (&#x0003e;1%) operational taxonomic units (OTUs) found in the chick cecal microbiome shows differences between the four-treatment groups (PBS control n=5; brooder 1 n=5; brooder 2 n=5; brooder 3 n=5). The distance between treatment groups was measured by a dendrogram in R statistical program. The PBS controls (blue bars) group very distinctly from chicks colonized with <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> in brooder 1 (black bars) and brooders 2 and 3 (green and red bars). Bacterial phylum, family and OTU number are listed on the heatmap. The heatmap scale ranges from 0 to 100% relative OTU abundance.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0073586.s001.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0073586.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><bold>Comparison of gene expression between biological replicates used in DESeq analysis.</bold>
Scatter plots of the log<sub>2</sub> (FPKMO) abundance of open reading frames obtained from RNAseq libraries created from <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-log samples (A&#x02013;C), <italic>in vitro</italic> stationary phase samples (D&#x02013;F) and <italic>in vivo</italic> chick samples (G&#x02013;I). R<sup>2</sup> (coefficient of determination) was determined by linear regression, represented by the sold line.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0073586.s002.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0073586.s003"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><bold>Genes increased in abundance <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-log phase cultures.</bold>
Listed are genes with increased abundance during <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-exponential phase broth grown cultures, as determined by DESeq analysis (materials and methods). Only genes significantly differentially regulated (&#x0003e;4-fold difference in abundance, p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05) are listed. p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05, is a corrected p-value analogous to a false detection rate of &#x0003c; 5%. Genes are grouped by functional classification and by their <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> 81-176 locus numbers and gene name or function.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0073586.s003.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0073586.s004"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><bold>Genes decreased in abundance <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-log phase cultures.</bold>
Listed are genes with decreased abundance during <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-exponential phase broth grown cultures, as determined by DESeq analysis (materials and methods). Only genes significantly differentially regulated (&#x0003e;4-fold difference in abundance, p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05) are listed. p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05, is a corrected p-value analogous to a false detection rate of &#x0003c; 5%. Genes are grouped by functional classification and by their <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> 81-176 locus numbers and gene name or function.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0073586.s004.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0073586.s005"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><bold>Genes increased in abundance <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> stationary phase cultures.</bold>
Listed are genes with increased abundance during <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> stationary phase broth grown cultures, as determined by DESeq analysis (materials and methods). Only genes significantly differentially regulated (&#x0003e;4-fold difference in abundance, p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05) are listed. p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05, is a corrected p-value analogous to a false detection rate of &#x0003c; 5%. Genes are grouped by functional classification and by their <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> 81-176 locus numbers and gene name or function.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0073586.s005.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0073586.s006"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p><bold>Genes decreased in abundance <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> stationary phase cultures.</bold>
Listed are genes with decreased abundance during <italic>in vivo</italic> colonization compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> stationary phase broth grown cultures, as determined by DESeq analysis (materials and methods). Only genes significantly differentially regulated (&#x0003e;4-fold difference in abundance, p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05) are listed. p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05, is a corrected p-value analogous to a false detection rate of &#x0003c; 5%. Genes are grouped by functional classification and by their <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> 81-176 locus numbers and gene name or function.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0073586.s006.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0073586.s007"><label>Table S5</label><caption><p><bold>Genes increased in abundance <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-log compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> stationary phase cultures.</bold>
Listed are genes with increased abundance during <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-exponential phase broth grown cultures compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> stationary phase broth grown cultures, as determined by DESeq analysis (materials and methods). Only genes significantly differentially regulated (&#x0003e;4-fold difference in abundance, p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05) are listed. p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05, is a corrected p-value analogous to a false detection rate of &#x0003c; 5%. Genes are grouped by functional classification and by their <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> 81-176 locus numbers and gene name or function.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0073586.s007.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0073586.s008"><label>Table S6</label><caption><p><bold>Genes decreased in abundance <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-log compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> stationary phase cultures.</bold>
Listed are genes with decreased abundance during <italic>in vitro</italic> mid-exponential phase broth grown cultures compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> stationary phase broth grown cultures, as determined by DESeq analysis (materials and methods). Only genes significantly differentially regulated (&#x0003e;4-fold difference in abundance, p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05) are listed. p<sub>adj</sub>&#x0003c;0.05, is a corrected p-value analogous to a false detection rate of &#x0003c; 5%. Genes are grouped by functional classification and by their <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> 81-176 locus numbers and gene name or function.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0073586.s008.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0073586.s009"><label>Table S7</label><caption><p><bold>Non-coding RNAs that align to pTet.</bold>
Location of non-coding RNA species identified by RNAseq that map to the pTET plasmid.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0073586.s009.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0073586.s010"><label>Table S8</label><caption><p><bold>Primers used in qRT-PCR experiments.</bold>
Listed are the primer sets, along with their sequence, used in qRT-PCR experiments. Each primer set is annotated by which gene it will amplify.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0073586.s010.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0073586.s011"><label>Table S9</label><caption><p><bold>Results of DEseq analysis of RNAseq data for all annotated <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> ORFs.</bold>
Each annotated gene in the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> genome, and two plasmids, is listed in locus number order. DESeq analysis for each gene under each growth condition comparison is given, including the base mean reads for each growth condition and the fold change (and log<sub>2</sub> fold change) between each condition. p<sub>adj</sub> is the adjusted P values for each gene and resVarA/B are the variance values within each set of biological replicates.</p><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0073586.s011.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank Bob Lyons and his staff at the University of Michigan DNA Sequencing Core for their help and guidance with the sequencing of RNAseq libraries. We would also like to thank Susan Foltin at the University of Michigan for her help and guidance with the 454-pysrocequencing. Finally we would like to thank Thomas Abeel from the Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard and the VIB Department of Plant Systems Biology at Ghent University for his help in creating the <italic><named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content></italic> RNAseq transcriptome browser.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Altekruse</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Swerdlow</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title><italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic>--an emerging foodborne pathogen</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>-<lpage>35</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3201/eid0501.990104">10.3201/eid0501.990104</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10081669">10081669</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10081669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The physiology of <italic>Campylobacter</italic> species and its relevance to their role as foodborne pathogens</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><volume>74</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0168-1605(01)00678-X">10.1016/S0168-1605(01)00678-X</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11981968">11981968</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11981968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Jacobs-Reitsma</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>[!(surname)!]</surname></name>, <name><surname>Wagenaar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title><italic>Campylobacter</italic> in the Food Supply</article-title>; <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Nachamkin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Szymanski</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaser</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kakuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DiRita</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A <italic>Campylobacter jejuni znuA</italic> orthologue is essential for growth in low-zinc environments and chick colonization</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>191</volume>: <fpage>1631</fpage>-<lpage>1640</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.01394-08">10.1128/JB.01394-08</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19103921">19103921</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19103921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hendrixson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DiRita</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Identification of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> genes involved in commensal colonization of the chick gastrointestinal tract</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>52</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>-<lpage>484</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.03988.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.03988.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15066034">15066034</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15066034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wassenaar</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van der Zeijst</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ayling</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Colonization of chicks by motility mutants of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> demonstrates the importance of flagellin A expression</article-title>. <source>J Gen Microbiol</source><volume>139</volume><issue-id>6</issue-id>: <fpage>1171</fpage>-<lpage>1175</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1099/00221287-139-6-1171">10.1099/00221287-139-6-1171</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8360610">8360610</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8360610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weerakoon</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borden</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goodson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The role of respiratory donor enzymes in Campylobacter jejuni host colonization and physiology</article-title>. <source>Microb Pathog</source><volume>47</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.micpath.2009.04.009">10.1016/j.micpath.2009.04.009</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19397993">19397993</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19397993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weingarten</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Role of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> respiratory oxidases and reductases in host colonization</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>74</volume>: <fpage>1367</fpage>-<lpage>1375</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/AEM.02261-07">10.1128/AEM.02261-07</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18192421">18192421</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18192421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wren</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mungall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ketley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The genome sequence of the food-borne pathogen <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> reveals hypervariable sequences</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>403</volume>: <fpage>665</fpage>-<lpage>668</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/35001088">10.1038/35001088</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10688204">10688204</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gaskin</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Segers</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nuijten</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The complete genome sequence of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> strain 81116 (NCTC11828)</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>189</volume>: <fpage>8402</fpage>-<lpage>8403</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.01404-07">10.1128/JB.01404-07</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17873037">17873037</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17873037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fouts</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mongodin</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mandrell</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rasko</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Major structural differences and novel potential virulence mechanisms from the genomes of multiple <italic>Campylobacter</italic> species</article-title>. <source>PLOS Biol</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e15</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.0030015">10.1371/journal.pbio.0030015</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15660156">15660156</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15660156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Br&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wren</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ketley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>A novel <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> two-component regulatory system important for temperature-dependent growth and colonization</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>181</volume>: <fpage>3298</fpage>-<lpage>3302</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10322038">10322038</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10322038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burans</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Reversible expression of flagella in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>50</volume>: <fpage>941</fpage>-<lpage>943</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/4066041">4066041</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4066041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Palyada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Threadgill</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stintzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Iron acquisition and regulation in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>186</volume>: <fpage>4714</fpage>-<lpage>4729</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.186.14.4714-4729.2004">10.1128/JB.186.14.4714-4729.2004</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15231804">15231804</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15231804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sampathkumar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Napper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carrillo</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Willson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taboada</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional and translational expression patterns associated with immobilized growth of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>152</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>-<lpage>577</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1099/mic.0.28405-0">10.1099/mic.0.28405-0</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16436444">16436444</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16436444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stintzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Gene expression profile of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> in response to growth temperature variation</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>185</volume>: <fpage>2009</fpage>-<lpage>2016</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.185.6.2009-2016.2003">10.1128/JB.185.6.2009-2016.2003</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12618466">12618466</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12618466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Taveirne</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sikes</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Molybdenum and tungsten in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic>: their physiological role and identification of separate transporters regulated by a single ModE-like protein</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>74</volume>: <fpage>758</fpage>-<lpage>771</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06901.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06901.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19919002">19919002</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19919002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Woodall</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barrow</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marsden</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> gene expression in the chick cecum: evidence for adaptation to a low-oxygen environment</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>73</volume>: <fpage>5278</fpage>-<lpage>5285</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/IAI.73.8.5278-5285.2005">10.1128/IAI.73.8.5278-5285.2005</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16041056">16041056</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16041056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hendrixson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A phase-variable mechanism controlling the <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> FlgR response regulator influences commensalism</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1646</fpage>-<lpage>1659</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05336.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05336.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16899076">16899076</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16899076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karlyshev</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gregson</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wren</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A novel paralogous gene family involved in phase-variable flagella-mediated motility in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>148</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>-<lpage>480</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11832511">11832511</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11832511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guerry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Szymanski</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prendergast</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Phase variation of Campylobacter jejuni 81-176 lipooligosaccharide affects ganglioside mimicry and invasiveness <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>70</volume>: <fpage>787</fpage>-<lpage>793</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/IAI.70.2.787-793.2002">10.1128/IAI.70.2.787-793.2002</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11796612">11796612</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11796612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Szymanski</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alm</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A phase-variable capsule is involved in virulence of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> 81-176</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>40</volume>: <fpage>769</fpage>-<lpage>777</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02431.x">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02431.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11359581">11359581</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11359581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>H&#x000e4;nninen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hakkinen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rautelin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Stability of related human and chicken <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> genotypes after passage through chick intestine studied by pulsed-field gel electrophoresis</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>65</volume>: <fpage>2272</fpage>-<lpage>2275</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10224037">10224037</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10224037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wagenaar</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Achterberg</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Putten</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schouls</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Generation of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> genetic diversity in vivo</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>44</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>-<lpage>359</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2958.2002.02930.x">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2002.02930.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11972775">11972775</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972775</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gaynor</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacKichan</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Falkow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> stringent response controls specific stress survival and virulence-associated phenotypes</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>56</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>27</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2005.04525.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2005.04525.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15773975">15773975</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15773975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Role of the DksA-like protein in the pathogenesis and diverse metabolic activity of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>190</volume>: <fpage>4512</fpage>-<lpage>4520</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.00105-08">10.1128/JB.00105-08</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18456813">18456813</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18456813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stintzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marlow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palyada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naikare</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Panciera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Use of genome-wide expression profiling and mutagenesis to study the intestinal lifestyle of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>73</volume>: <fpage>1797</fpage>-<lpage>1810</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/IAI.73.3.1797-1810.2005">10.1128/IAI.73.3.1797-1810.2005</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15731081">15731081</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15731081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cattoir</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skurnik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aschard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional response of mucoid <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> to human respiratory mucus</article-title>. <source>mBio</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e00410-00412</fpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23143799">23143799</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23143799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanji</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Quantitative RNA-seq analysis of the <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> transcriptome</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>157</volume>: <fpage>2922</fpage>-<lpage>2932</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1099/mic.0.050278-0">10.1099/mic.0.050278-0</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21816880">21816880</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dugar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herbig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>F&#x000f6;rstner</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heidrich</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reinhardt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>High-Resolution Transcriptome Maps Reveal Strain- Specific Regulatory Features of Multiple <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> Isolates</article-title>. <source>PLOS Genet</source><volume>9</volume></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mandlik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Livny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robins</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mekalanos</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>RNA-Seq-based monitoring of infection-linked changes in <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> gene expression</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>174</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2011.07.007">10.1016/j.chom.2011.07.007</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21843873">21843873</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21843873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Darfeuille</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reignier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Findeiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The primary transcriptome of the major human pathogen <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>464</volume>: <fpage>250</fpage>-<lpage>255</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature08756">10.1038/nature08756</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20164839">20164839</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20164839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>RNA-Seq: a revolutionary tool for transcriptomics</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrg2484">10.1038/nrg2484</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19015660">19015660</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Efficient translation of the RpoS sigma factor in <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> requires host factor I, an RNA-binding protein encoded by the <italic>hfq</italic> gene</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>178</volume>: <fpage>3763</fpage>-<lpage>3770</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8682778">8682778</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8682778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hajnsdorf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>R&#x000e9;gnier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Host factor Hfq of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> stimulates elongation of poly(A) tails by poly(A) polymerase I</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>97</volume>: <fpage>1501</fpage>-<lpage>1505</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.040549897">10.1073/pnas.040549897</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10677490">10677490</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10677490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Muffler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hengge-Aronis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The RNA-binding protein HF-I, known as a host factor for phage Qbeta RNA replication, is essential for <italic>rpoS</italic> translation in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1143</fpage>-<lpage>1151</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gad.10.9.1143">10.1101/gad.10.9.1143</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8654929">8654929</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8654929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Muffler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Traulsen</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hengge-Aronis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The RNA-binding protein HF-I plays a global regulatory role which is largely, but not exclusively, due to its role in expression of the sigmaS subunit of RNA polymerase in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>179</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>-<lpage>300</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8982015">8982015</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8982015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brun-Zinkernagel</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simecka</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pr&#x000fc;ss</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Babitzke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Positive regulation of motility and <italic>flhDC</italic> expression by the RNA-binding protein CsrA of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>40</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>256</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02380.x">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02380.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11298291">11298291</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11298291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loughlin</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fainberg</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Messenger</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ussery</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Global regulation of virulence and the stress response by CsrA in the highly adapted human gastric pathogen <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>51</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14651608">14651608</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14651608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Romeo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brun-Zinkernagel</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Identification and molecular characterization of <italic>csrA</italic>, a pleiotropic gene from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> that affects glycogen biosynthesis, gluconeogenesis, cell size, and surface properties</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>175</volume>: <fpage>4744</fpage>-<lpage>4755</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8393005">8393005</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8393005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title><italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> CsrA mediates oxidative stress responses, biofilm formation, and host cell invasion</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>190</volume>: <fpage>3411</fpage>-<lpage>3416</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.01928-07">10.1128/JB.01928-07</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18310331">18310331</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18310331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A cis-encoded antisense small RNA regulated by the HP0165-HP0166 two-component system controls expression of <italic>ureB</italic> in <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>193</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.00800-10">10.1128/JB.00800-10</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20971914">20971914</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20971914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schloss</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Westcott</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ryabin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Introducing mothur: open-source, platform-independent, community-supported software for describing and comparing microbial communities</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>75</volume>: <fpage>7537</fpage>-<lpage>7541</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/AEM.01541-09">10.1128/AEM.01541-09</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19801464">19801464</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19801464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brulc</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, Theoret JR, et al (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Comparative metagenomics reveals host specific metavirulomes and horizontal gene transfer elements in the chicken cecum microbiome</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e2945</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0002945">10.1371/journal.pone.0002945</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18698407">18698407</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18698407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>R106</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20979621">20979621</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Headley</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Influence of iron on growth, morphology, outer membrane protein composition, and synthesis of siderophores in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>54</volume>: <fpage>126</fpage>-<lpage>132</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2944843">2944843</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2944843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mulholland</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McNicholl-Kennedy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> gene expression in response to iron limitation and the role of Fur</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>151</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>-<lpage>257</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1099/mic.0.27412-0">10.1099/mic.0.27412-0</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15632442">15632442</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15632442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Palyada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Threadgill</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stintzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Iron acquisition and regulation in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>186</volume>: <fpage>4714</fpage>-<lpage>4729</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.186.14.4714-4729.2004">10.1128/JB.186.14.4714-4729.2004</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15231804">15231804</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15231804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haigh</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ketley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of a new ferric enterobactin receptor, CfrB, in <italic>Campylobacter</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>192</volume>: <fpage>4425</fpage>-<lpage>4435</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.00478-10">10.1128/JB.00478-10</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20585060">20585060</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20585060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Vliet</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wooldridge</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ketley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Iron-responsive gene regulation in a <italic>Campylobacter jejuni fur</italic> mutant</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>180</volume>: <fpage>5291</fpage>-<lpage>5298</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9765558">9765558</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9765558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Veen</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Phosphate transport in prokaryotes: molecules, mediators and mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source><volume>72</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>315</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1000530927928">10.1023/A:1000530927928</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9442271">9442271</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9442271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>W&#x000f6;sten</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Mourik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guilhabert</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> PhosS/PhosR operon represents a non-classical phosphate-sensitive two-component system</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>62</volume>: <fpage>278</fpage>-<lpage>291</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05372.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05372.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16956379">16956379</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16956379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Palyada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Butcher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naikare</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Characterization of the oxidative stress stimulon and PerR regulon of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>481</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-10-481">10.1186/1471-2164-10-481</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19835633">19835633</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19835633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>WA</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Sajecki</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joens</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Role of catalase in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> intracellular survival</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>68</volume>: <fpage>6337</fpage>-<lpage>6345</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/IAI.68.11.6337-6345.2000">10.1128/IAI.68.11.6337-6345.2000</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11035743">11035743</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11035743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of <italic>katA</italic> from <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> and generation of a catalase-deficient mutant of <italic>Campylobacter coli</italic> by interspecific allelic exchange</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>141</volume>(<issue-id>6</issue-id>): <fpage>1369</fpage>-<lpage>1376</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1099/13500872-141-6-1369">10.1099/13500872-141-6-1369</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7670638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Elvers</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gilberthorpe</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Role of an inducible single-domain hemoglobin in mediating resistance to nitric oxide and nitrosative stress in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> and <italic>Campylobacter coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>186</volume>: <fpage>5332</fpage>-<lpage>5341</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.186.16.5332-5341.2004">10.1128/JB.186.16.5332-5341.2004</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15292134">15292134</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15292134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abuoun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cawthraw</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rothwell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title><italic>Campylobacter</italic> colonization of the chicken induces a proinflammatory response in mucosal tissues</article-title>. <source>FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol</source><volume>54</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>-<lpage>121</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-695X.2008.00458.x">10.1111/j.1574-695X.2008.00458.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18647351">18647351</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18647351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rothwell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barrow</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic>-induced cytokine responses in avian cells</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>73</volume>: <fpage>2094</fpage>-<lpage>2100</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/IAI.73.4.2094-2100.2005">10.1128/IAI.73.4.2094-2100.2005</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15784550">15784550</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15784550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Deun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pasmans</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ducatelle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flahou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vissenberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Colonization strategy of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> results in persistent infection of the chicken gut</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol</source><volume>130</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>-<lpage>297</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.vetmic.2007.11.027">10.1016/j.vetmic.2007.11.027</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18187272">18187272</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18187272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Connell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meade</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Avian resistance to <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> colonization is associated with an intestinal immunogene expression signature identified by mRNA sequencing</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e40409</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0040409">10.1371/journal.pone.0040409</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22870198">22870198</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22870198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Corcionivoschi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strengert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alemka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Mucosal reactive oxygen species decrease virulence by disrupting <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> phosphotyrosine signaling</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2012.05.018">10.1016/j.chom.2012.05.018</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22817987">22817987</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22817987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Zoete</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keestra</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roszczenko</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Putten</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Activation of human and chicken toll-like receptors by <italic>Campylobacter</italic> spp</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>78</volume>: <fpage>1229</fpage>-<lpage>1238</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/IAI.00897-09">10.1128/IAI.00897-09</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20038539">20038539</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20038539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Batchelor</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Friis</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Nucleotide sequences and comparison of two large conjugative plasmids from different <italic>Campylobacter</italic> species</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>150</volume>: <fpage>3507</fpage>-<lpage>3517</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1099/mic.0.27112-0">10.1099/mic.0.27112-0</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15470128">15470128</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15470128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guerry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leifer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Development and characterization of <italic>recA</italic> mutants of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> for inclusion in attenuated vaccines</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>62</volume>: <fpage>426</fpage>-<lpage>432</lpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8300203">8300203</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8300203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alm</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kopecko</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Involvement of a plasmid in virulence of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> 81-176</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>68</volume>: <fpage>4384</fpage>-<lpage>4390</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/IAI.68.8.4384-4390.2000">10.1128/IAI.68.8.4384-4390.2000</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10899834">10899834</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10899834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brilli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fondi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The role of gene fusions in the evolution of metabolic pathways: the histidine biosynthesis case</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source><volume>7</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue>: <fpage>S4</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-7-S1-S4">10.1186/1471-2148-7-S1-S4</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17767732">17767732</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17767732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aubry</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mui</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guerry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Functional characterization of the flagellar glycosylation locus in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> 81-176 using a focused metabolomics approach</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>281</volume>: <fpage>18489</fpage>-<lpage>18498</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M603777200">10.1074/jbc.M603777200</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16684771">16684771</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16684771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ellison3rd</surname></name>, <article-title>Blaser MJ</article-title> (<year>1991</year>) <comment>Identification, purification, and characterization of major antigenic proteins of Campylobacter jejuni. The Journal of biological chemistry 266: 16363-16369</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Linton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karlyshev</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cronshaw</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wren</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Identification of N-acetylgalactosamine-containing glycoproteins PEB3 and CgpA in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>43</volume>: <fpage>497</fpage>-<lpage>508</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2958.2002.02762.x">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2002.02762.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11985725">11985725</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11985725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sellars</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Growth of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> supported by respiration of fumarate, nitrate, nitrite, trimethylamine-N-oxide, or dimethyl sulfoxide requires oxygen</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>184</volume>: <fpage>4187</fpage>-<lpage>4196</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.184.15.4187-4196.2002">10.1128/JB.184.15.4187-4196.2002</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12107136">12107136</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12107136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weerakoon</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> NADH:ubiquinone oxidoreductase (complex I) utilizes flavodoxin rather than NADH</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>190</volume>: <fpage>915</fpage>-<lpage>925</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.01647-07">10.1128/JB.01647-07</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18065531">18065531</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18065531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elvers</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gidley</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wainwright</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Oxygen reactivity of both respiratory oxidases in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic>: the <italic>cydAB</italic> genes encode a cyanide-resistant, low-affinity oxidase that is not of the cytochrome bd type</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>189</volume>: <fpage>1604</fpage>-<lpage>1615</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.00897-06">10.1128/JB.00897-06</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17172349">17172349</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17172349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A sulphite respiration system in the chemoheterotrophic human pathogen <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>151</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>-<lpage>242</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1099/mic.0.27573-0">10.1099/mic.0.27573-0</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15632441">15632441</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15632441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stintzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Gene expression profile of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> in response to growth temperature variation</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>185</volume>: <fpage>2009</fpage>-<lpage>2016</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.185.6.2009-2016.2003">10.1128/JB.185.6.2009-2016.2003</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12618466">12618466</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12618466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daub</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nawrocki</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kolbe</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Rfam: updates to the RNA families database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>37</volume>: <fpage>D136</fpage>-<lpage>D140</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkp725">10.1093/nar/gkp725</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18953034">18953034</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18953034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gundogdu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dorrell</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Re-annotation and re-analysis of the <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 genome sequence</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>162</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-8-162">10.1186/1471-2164-8-162</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17565669">17565669</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17565669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wurtzel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sesto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mellin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karunker</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edelheit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Comparative transcriptomics of pathogenic and non-pathogenic <italic>Listeria</italic> species</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22617957">22617957</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22617957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tjaden</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>TargetRNA: a tool for predicting targets of small RNA action in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>36</volume>: <fpage>W109</fpage>-<lpage>W113</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkn264">10.1093/nar/gkn264</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18477632">18477632</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18477632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mika</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nierhaus</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Small RNA binding to 5' mRNA coding region inhibits translational initiation</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source><volume>32</volume>: <fpage>827</fpage>-<lpage>837</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2008.10.027">10.1016/j.molcel.2008.10.027</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19111662">19111662</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19111662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mass&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Escorcia</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Coupled degradation of a small regulatory RNA and its mRNA targets in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source><volume>17</volume>: <fpage>2374</fpage>-<lpage>2383</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gad.1127103">10.1101/gad.1127103</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12975324">12975324</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12975324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aiba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>RNase E-based ribonucleoprotein complexes: mechanical basis of mRNA destabilization mediated by bacterial noncoding RNAs</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2176</fpage>-<lpage>2186</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gad.1330405">10.1101/gad.1330405</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16166379">16166379</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pr&#x000e9;vost</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salvail</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Desnoyers</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacques</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phaneuf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The small RNA RyhB activates the translation of <italic>shiA</italic> mRNA encoding a permease of shikimate, a compound involved in siderophore synthesis</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>64</volume>: <fpage>1260</fpage>-<lpage>1273</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2007.05733.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2007.05733.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17542919">17542919</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17542919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Two seemingly homologous noncoding RNAs act hierarchically to activate <italic>glmS</italic> mRNA translation</article-title>. <source>PLOS Biol</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e64</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.0060064">10.1371/journal.pbio.0060064</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18351803">18351803</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18351803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Storz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Regulatory RNAs in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>136</volume>: <fpage>615</fpage>-<lpage>628</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2009.01.043">10.1016/j.cell.2009.01.043</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19239884">19239884</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19239884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Livny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teonadi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Livny</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waldor</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>High-throughput, kingdom-wide prediction and annotation of bacterial non-coding RNAs</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e3197</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0003197">10.1371/journal.pone.0003197</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18787707">18787707</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18787707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abeel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Parys</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saeys</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galagan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van de Peer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>GenomeView: a next-generation genome browser</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>40</volume>: <fpage>e12</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkr995">10.1093/nar/gkr995</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22102585">22102585</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22102585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hendrixson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akerley</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DiRita</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Transposon mutagenesis of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> identifies a bipartite energy taxis system required for motility</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>40</volume>: <fpage>214</fpage>-<lpage>224</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02376.x">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02376.x</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11298288">11298288</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11298288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jerome</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plovanich-Jones</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barrick</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Standing genetic variation in contingency loci drives the rapid adaptation of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> to a novel host</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e16399</fpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0016399">10.1371/journal.pone.0016399</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21283682">21283682</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21283682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adiconis</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nusbaum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive comparative analysis of strand-specific RNA sequencing methods</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>709</fpage>-<lpage>715</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.1491">10.1038/nmeth.1491</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20711195">20711195</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20711195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>-<lpage>408</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/meth.2001.1262">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11846609">11846609</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1754</fpage>-<lpage>1760</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp324">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp324</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19451168">19451168</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cardenas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Ribosomal Database Project: improved alignments and new tools for rRNA analysis</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>37</volume>: <fpage>D141</fpage>-<lpage>D145</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkp353">10.1093/nar/gkp353</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19004872">19004872</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19004872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A similarity measure based on species proportions</article-title>. <source>Commun Stat Theor Methods</source><volume>34</volume>: <fpage>2123</fpage>-<lpage>2131</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/STA-200066418">10.1080/STA-200066418</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>R Development Core Team</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>R: A language and environment for statisitcal programing</source>. <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spellman</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Cluster analysis and display of genome-wide expression patterns</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>95</volume>: <fpage>14863</fpage>-<lpage>14868</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.95.25.14863">10.1073/pnas.95.25.14863</ext-link> PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9843981">9843981</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>