<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Microbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2180</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4236580</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">s12866-014-0206-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25085508</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-014-0206-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterization and analysis of the <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> BsaN virulence regulon</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Yahua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>yahua_chen@nuhs.edu.sg</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Schr&#x000f6;der</surname><given-names>Imke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>ischroeder@ehs.ucla.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>Christopher T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>ctfrench@icloud.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Jaroszewicz</surname><given-names>Artur</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>arturtjaro@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>Xiao Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>xiaojiey@miltenyibiotec.com.sg</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name><surname>Teh</surname><given-names>Boon-Eng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>a0019137j@alumni.nus.edu.sg</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7"><name><surname>Toesca</surname><given-names>Isabelle J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>toesca@hotmail.fr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Jeff F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>jfmiller@ucla.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A9"><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>Yunn-Hwen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref><email>yunn_hwen_gan@nuhs.edu.sg</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Biochemistry, Yong Loo Lin School of Medicine, National University of Singapore, Singapore 117597, Singapore</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Microbiology, Immunology and Molecular Genetics, The University of California Los Angeles, Los Angeles 90095, CA, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Molecular, Cell and Developmental Biology, The University of California Los Angeles, Los Angeles 90095, CA, USA</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>California NanoSystems Institute, The University of California Los Angeles, Los Angeles 90095, CA, USA</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Molecular Biology Institute, The University of California Los Angeles, Los Angeles 90095, CA, USA</aff><aff id="I6"><label>6</label>Immunology Program, Yong Loo Lin School of Medicine, National University of Singapore, Singapore 117597, Singapore</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Chen et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chen et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/14/206"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> is a facultative intracellular pathogen and the causative agent of melioidosis. A conserved type III secretion system (T3SS3) and type VI secretion system (T6SS1) are critical for intracellular survival and growth. The T3SS3 and T6SS1 genes are coordinately and hierarchically regulated by a TetR-type regulator, BspR. A central transcriptional regulator of the BspR regulatory cascade, BsaN, activates a subset of T3SS3 and T6SS1 loci.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>To elucidate the scope of the BsaN regulon, we used RNAseq analysis to compare the transcriptomes of wild-type <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW and a <italic>bsaN</italic> deletion mutant. The 60 genes positively-regulated by BsaN include those that we had previously identified in addition to a polyketide biosynthesis locus and genes involved in amino acid biosynthesis. BsaN was also found to repress the transcription of 51 genes including flagellar motility loci and those encoding components of the T3SS3 apparatus. Using a promoter-<italic>lacZ</italic> fusion assay in <italic>E. coli</italic>, we show that BsaN together with the chaperone BicA directly control the expression of the T3SS3 translocon, effector and associated regulatory genes that are organized into at least five operons (<italic>BPSS1516-BPSS1552</italic>). Using a mutagenesis approach, a consensus regulatory motif in the promoter regions of BsaN-regulated genes was shown to be essential for transcriptional activation.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>BsaN/BicA functions as a central regulator of key virulence clusters in <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> within a more extensive network of genetic regulation. We propose that BsaN/BicA controls a gene expression program that facilitates the adaption and intracellular survival of the pathogen within eukaryotic hosts.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Melioidosis is a serious and often fatal infectious disease common to Southeast Asia and Northern Australia caused by the Gram-negative soil bacterium <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei. B. pseudomallei</italic> is a highly versatile pathogen capable of surviving inside mammalian cells and in many environmental niches. The bacterium can infect numerous animal species, amoebae, nematodes, and tomato plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]&#x02013;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], and has been previously found within the tissues of exotic grasses in Australia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The environmental origin of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> and its promiscuous host range have shaped the hypothesis that some of its genetic loci evolved in the rhizosphere as anti-predation determinants that subsequently promote &#x0201c;accidental&#x0201d; virulence in humans and animals. In recent years, important advances have been made in understanding the pathogenic mechanisms of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> including the roles of the Type III and Type VI Secretion Systems (T3SS, T6SS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]&#x02013;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> contains three T3SSs and six T6SSs, but only T3SS3 (also referred to as the <italic>Burkholderia</italic> secretion apparatus, or T3SS<sub>Bsa</sub>) and T6SS1 are critical for pathogenesis in mice and hamsters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p><p>Expression of the T3SS3 and T6SS1 gene clusters is tightly controlled, both temporally and spatially, during the <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> intracellular lifecycle. We have identified a regulatory cascade that coordinately activates T3SS3 and T6SS1 gene expression in growth medium and in infected mammalian cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. At the top of the cascade is the TetR-type regulator BspR that stimulates the expression of <italic>bprP</italic>. The <italic>bspR</italic> gene is located on chromosome 1 of the <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> genome whereas <italic>bprP</italic> is part of the T3SS3 gene cluster on chromosome 2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. The ToxR-like BprP in turn activates genes encoding the structural components of T3SS3, including the <italic>araC</italic>-type regulatory gene <italic>bsaN</italic>. BsaN is important for the activation of T3SS3 effector and translocon gene expression, and several regulatory genes including <italic>bprC</italic> and <italic>virAG</italic>, whose gene products control T6SS1 expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The mechanisms through which these transcriptional regulators control the expression of their target genes are not understood. It is also unclear whether these regulators are acting directly on the identified target genes or through as yet undiscovered intermediary regulators, and whether additional host cell cofactors are involved that may serve as intracellular signals.</p><p>Compared to T3SSs in other pathogens such as <italic>Pseudomonas, Salmonella</italic> and <italic>Shigella</italic>, only a limited number of effectors have been identified for <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> T3SS3. One of the effector proteins secreted by T3SS3 is BopE, which is annotated to exhibit guanine nucleotide exchange factor activity and has been reported to facilitate invasion of epithelial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. <italic>bopA</italic> is generally assumed to encode a T3SS3 effector since it is located adjacent to <italic>bopE</italic>, although T3SS3-dependent secretion of BopA has never been verified. Functionally, BopA has been described to promote resistance to LC3-associated autophagy and a <italic>bopA</italic> mutation results in an intracellular replication defect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. A third effector protein, BopC (BPSS1516), was recently shown to be secreted via T3SS3, and <italic>bopC</italic> mutants were reported to be less invasive in epithelial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] and to exhibit delayed endosome escape and reduced intracellular growth in J774 murine macrophages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p><p>To determine the full extent of the BsaN regulon and examine whether BsaN activates the expression of additional effector genes, we performed global transcriptome analysis of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW wildtype (WT) and a &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> mutant strain using RNAseq. Our analysis shows that 111 genes are under the direct or indirect transcriptional control of BsaN. In addition to activating loci associated with T3SS3, we demonstrate that BsaN functions to repress transcription of other loci. Thus, BsaN functions as a central regulatory factor within a more extensive network to facilitate the intracellular lifecycle of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Identification of the BsaN regulon through RNAseq analysis</title><p>BsaN (<italic>BPSS1546</italic> in the reference <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> K96243 genome) was previously shown to function as a central regulator of a hierarchical cascade that activates effector and translocon genes of T3SS3 as well as several associated regulatory genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Furthermore, BsaN was shown to activate the expression of certain T6SS1-associated genes including the two-component regulatory system locus <italic>virAG</italic> (<italic>BPSS1494, 1495</italic>), and the <italic>bim</italic> actin motility genes (<italic>BPSS1490-1493</italic>). To gain further insight into the BsaN regulon, massive parallel sequencing was performed on cDNA prepared from RNA isolated from wild-type and &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> mutant strains. We had previously shown that complementation of our &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> mutant with a <italic>bsaN</italic> plasmid could restore the secretion of the BopE effector [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], showing that our complementation restored protein expression of the effectors and that the mutation was specific to <italic>bsaN</italic> and not due to off target effects.</p><p>Between 16 and 56 million reads (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;2 from 3 combined cultures) were obtained that aligned to non-ribosomal genes in the KHW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] genome (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S1). Reads of the technical replicates displayed high reproducibility (R-value) (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S1) demonstrating that variability was not introduced through sample preparation or sequencing errors. The K96243 reference genome was co-aligned for ease of gene annotation. The nucleotide sequences of chromosomes I and II are 99.3 and 99.1% identical, respectively.</p><p>Comparison between wild-type and &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> transcriptomes identified 111 genes that were differentially regulated using 3-fold or more (adjusted p-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) as the cut off. Of these, 60 genes were expressed more highly in wild-type KHW compared to the &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> strain, indicating that BsaN directly or indirectly activates their transcription (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). However, 51 genes were expressed more highly in the &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> mutant suggesting that BsaN can function directly or indirectly as a repressor (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). RNAseq results were validated using quantitative real time-PCR (qRT-PCR) analysis for select loci. RNAseq analysis identified all genes that we had previously shown to be activated by BsaN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>B, Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The effector and chaperone genes <italic>bopE</italic>, <italic>bopA</italic> and <italic>bicP</italic> together with the regulatory gene <italic>bprD</italic> were amongst the highest activated genes (50-270-fold). In addition, two putative transposase genes separating the T3SS3 genes and the T6SS1 gene clusters were highly activated by BsaN (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Genes activated at lower levels (3-4-fold) include a hybrid non-ribosomal peptide synthase (NRPS)/polyketide synthase (PKS) locus consisting of 22 genes (<italic>BPSL0472-BPSL0493</italic>) unique to <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>B. mallei</italic>. NRPS/PKS systems are found in microbes and fungi, and are generally responsible for the production of complex natural compounds such as antibiotics and siderophores. <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species are rich in NRPS/PKS loci that contain multiple metabolic genes or encode large multidomain synthases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Although the precise function of this NRPS/PKS locus is not currently known, the presence of a diaminobutyrate-2-oxoglutarate amino transferase gene (<italic>BPSL0476</italic>) suggests that 2,4-diaminobutrate is one of the polyketide&#x02019;s component. Loci for methionine and threonine biosynthesis, as well as ribose uptake (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), were activated at similar levels. Representative BsaN-activated genes were confirmed by qRT-PCR (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>C-D).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>List of 60 genes that are expressed 3-fold and higher in the wild-type versus &#x00394;</bold><bold><italic>bsaN</italic>
</bold><bold>mutant strains (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01)</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr valign="top"><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Gene locus ID</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Gene</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Protein description</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Fold activation</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">T3SS3 associated<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1512<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>tssM</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">ubiquitin-specific proteinase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">9.3<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1513<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">7.5<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1514<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>folE</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">GTP hydrolase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">5.1<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1515<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">9.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1516<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bopC</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 effector<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">48.2<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1518<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">transposase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">44.3<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1519<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">transposase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">10.1<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1523<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bicP</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 chaperone<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">149.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1524<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bopA</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 effector<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">269.4<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1525<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bopE</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 effector<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">51.7<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1526<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bapC</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 effector<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">5.9<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1527<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bapB</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 effector<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">6.8<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1528<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bapA</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 effector<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">7.6<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1529<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bipD</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 translocon<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">7.6<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1531<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bipC</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 translocon<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">6.3<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1532<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bipB</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 translocon<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">6.6<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1533<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bicA</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 chaperone<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">9.4<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">T6SS1 apparatus<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1497<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>tssB</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T6SS-1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">3.1<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1498<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>hcp</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T6SS-1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">11.3<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Actin based motility<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1490<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">N-acetylmuramoyl-L-Ala-amidase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">13.5<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1491<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">ADP-heptose:LPS transferase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">8.8<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1492<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bimA</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Bim actin polymerization protein<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">7.8<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1493<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">14.5<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Polyketide biosynthesis<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL0472-BPSL0493<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">NRPKS/PKS biosynthesis locus<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">3.0-4.3<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL2883<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Glyoxalase/bleomycin resistance protein/dioxygenase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">4.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Amino acid biosynthesis and sugar uptake<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL0196<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>metW</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">methionine biosynthesis protein MetW<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">4.2<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL0197<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>metX</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">homoserine O-acetyltransferase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">3.4<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1691<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>metZ</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">O-succinylhomoserine sulfhydrylase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">3.2<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0005<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>kbl</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">2-amino-3-ketobutyrate CoA ligase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">6.3<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0006<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>tdh</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">L-threonine dehydrogenase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">5.5<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL1793<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Periplasmic binding protein (ribose binding)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">3.4<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Regulatory<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1494<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>virG</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T6SS-1 response regulator<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">22.4<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1495<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>virA</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T6SS-1 His kinase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">15.8<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1520<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bprC</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 AraC-type regulator<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">24.5<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1521<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bprD</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 regulator<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">151.5<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1522<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bprB</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 response regulator<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">89.5<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1530<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bprA</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">T3SS-3 HNS-type regulator<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">6.9<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL0480</td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>syrP</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top">NPKS/PKS regulator</td><td align="left" valign="top">3.9</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>List of 51 genes that are expressed 3-fold and lower in the wild-type versus &#x00394;</bold><bold>
<italic>bsaN</italic>
</bold><bold>mutant strains (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01)</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr valign="top"><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Gene locus ID</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Gene</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Protein description</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Fold repression</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">T3SS3 apparatus<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1545<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bsaO</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.3<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1547<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bsaM</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;5.6<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1548<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bsaL</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;5.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1549<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bsaK</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;4.7<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1550<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>bsaJ</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.9<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1551<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>orgA</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Flagella-dependent motility<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL0281<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>flgL</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Flagellar hook-associated protein<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.3<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL3319<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>fliC</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Flagellin<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.7<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL3320<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>fliD</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Flagellin<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL3321<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Unknown<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.1<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Polyketide biosynthesis<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0130<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Non-ribosomal peptide synthase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.1<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0303-BPSS0311<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PKS biosynthesis locus<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.0 - (&#x02212;6.1)<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0328<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Malate/L-lactate dehydrogenase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;7.8<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0329<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Fatty aldehyde dehydrogenase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;9.6<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0330<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Amino acid transporter<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;19.7<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0331<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Dihydrodipicolinate synthase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;19.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0332<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Hydroxyproline-2-epimerase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;21.7<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0333<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Deaminating oxidase subunit<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;18.8<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0334<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Deaminating oxidase subunit<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;24.7<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0335<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Deaminating oxidase subunit<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;20.1<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0337<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0338<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Transposase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;12.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0339<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">4-Hydroxyphenylpyruvate<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;8.2<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Lipid metabolism<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS2037<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Inner membrane fatty acid desaturase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS2038<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Acyl carrier protein<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.4<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS2039<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Cyclopropane-fatty-acyl-phospholipid synthase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.6<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS2040<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Inner membrane fatty acid desaturase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.2<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Energy metabolism<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL1744<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>arcB</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Ornithine carbamoyltransferase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.4<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL1745<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>arcC</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Carbamate kinase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.2<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL2404<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Periplasmic ligand binding protein<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;7.3<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL2405<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">FAD-dependent deaminase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;5.4<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1885<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Aromatic hydrocarbons catabolism-related reductase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.1<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1886<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Aromatic hydrocarbons catabolism-related dioxygenase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;4.2<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1887<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Aromatic oxygenase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.1<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS1888<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Aromatic oxygenase<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL2380<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>cyoC</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Cytochrome <italic>bo</italic> oxidase subunit<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.4<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL2381<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>cyoD</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Cytochrome <italic>bo</italic> oxidase subunit<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;3.0<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Regulatory<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSS0336<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">AraC-type regulator, adjacent to polyketide genes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;8.1<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Adaptation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">BPSL3369</td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>acoD</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top">Glycine betaine aldehyde dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x02212;4.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Regulation of selected genes by BsaN as analyzed by RNAseq and qRT-PCR. A</bold>. Activation and repression of T3SS3 cluster genes as analyzed by RNAseq. The adjusted p value for all genes is less than 0.01 with the exception of three genes denoted with ^. <bold>B</bold>. Activation of BsaN regulated T6SS1 and <italic>bim</italic> motility genes as analyzed by RNAseq. <bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold> qRT-PCR validation of selected activated genes. Expression of each in wild-type <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW gene is set to 1; transcription was normalized to that of the <italic>recA</italic> reference gene. <bold>E</bold>. qRT-PCR validation of repressed genes. Expression of each in wild-type <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW gene is set to 1; transcription was normalized to that of the 16S rRNA reference gene. The <italic>flgL</italic> gene is located upstream and in the same transcriptional unit as <italic>flgK</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="s12866-014-0206-6-1"/></fig><p>Intriguingly, genes encoding the T3SS3 apparatus components were found to be repressed in the wildtype compared with the &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> mutant, suggesting a role for BsaN in limiting apparatus synthesis when translocon and effector genes are transcribed (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A, 1E, Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Also repressed are polar flagellar motility loci on chromosome 1 including the flagellin genes <italic>fliC</italic> and <italic>fliD,</italic> as well as flagellar hook proteins <italic>flgL</italic> and <italic>flgK.</italic> Repression of these genes as well as <italic>motA</italic> (<italic>BPSL3309</italic>) and <italic>cheD</italic> (<italic>BPSS3302</italic>) were validated by qRT-PCR (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>E). In <italic>Salmonella</italic> and other bacteria, <italic>motAB</italic> are key components of the flagellar motor complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. <italic>motAB</italic> in KHW are part of a chemotaxis (<italic>che</italic>) locus, which is repressed 2&#x02013;2.9-fold (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) as assessed by RNAseq. In addition, expression of a second polyketide biosynthesis locus (<italic>BPSS0303-BPSS0311</italic>) was reduced in a <italic>&#x00394;bsaN</italic> mutant, possibly by repression of a co-localized <italic>araC</italic>-type regulatory gene, <italic>BPSS0336</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). However, down-regulation of this cluster could not be verified by qRT-PCR (data not shown). We were likewise unable to validate repression of <italic>BPSL2404-2405</italic>, which putatively encode transport and energy metabolism functions, respectively, in addition to <italic>BPSS1887-1888</italic>, which are postulated to encode oxidative enzymes for energy metabolism.</p><p>Additional loci implicated in lipid and energy metabolism are also repressed (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Catabolic genes encode a cytochrome <italic>o</italic> oxidase typically used by bacteria in an oxygen-rich environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], along with enzymes involved in the aerobic degradation of aromatic compounds and in the degradation of arginine. A gene involved in the synthesis of betaine, an osmoprotectant which serves to adapt Gram-negative bacteria to conditions of high osmolarity, is also repressed by BsaN.</p></sec><sec><title>BsaN together with chaperone BicA directly activate T3SS3 effector and T6SS1 regulatory genes</title><p>We have previously shown that expression of the two component regulatory system <italic>virAG</italic> and the genes from <italic>BPSS1520</italic> (<italic>bprC</italic>) to <italic>BPSS1533</italic> (<italic>bicA</italic>) in the T3SS3 cluster were regulated by BsaN in concert with the chaperone BicA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. To determine whether BsaN/BicA activate these genes directly, <italic>bsaN</italic> and <italic>bicA</italic> open reading frames (orfs) from <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> strain KHW were inserted into a plasmid downstream of an arabinose-inducible promoter on pMLBAD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. These constructs were introduced into <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] along with an additional construct containing putative promoter regions of several BsaN target genes transcriptionally fused to <italic>lacZ</italic> on pRW50 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] or pRW50mob, which contains the oriT fragment for pOT182 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. The effect of BsaN/BicA on promoter activity was then assessed by &#x003b2;-galactosidase activities.</p><p>The putative <italic>bsaN</italic> orf is annotated in the <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> genome database to initiate from a GTG start codon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. We identified a second potential start codon (ATG) and ribosome binding site 117 nucleotides (nt) upstream of GTG (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A, B). <italic>bsaN/bicA</italic> expression constructs (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A) that were initiated from GTG were unable to activate transcription of <italic>bicA, bopA</italic> and <italic>bopE</italic> in <italic>E. coli</italic> (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S2), supporting the notion that the ATG was the actual start codon for BsaN. Furthermore, a transcriptional start site was identified 56 nucleotide upstream of the ATG codon via RNA ligase-mediated rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RLM-RACE) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>B). A putative Ribosomal Binding Site (RBS) is located in front of the ATG condon. Replacing the GTG-initiated <italic>bsaN</italic> orf with the longer version containing the ATG start site resulted in activation of the <italic>bicA, bopA</italic> and <italic>bopE</italic> promoters as well as those for <italic>BPSS1521</italic> (<italic>bprD</italic>)<italic>, BPSS 1495</italic> (<italic>virA</italic>) and the putative transposase <italic>BPSS1518</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>A-F). Expression of BsaN alone was not sufficient to activate these promoters (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S2), demonstrating the co-requirement for BicA. No apparent BsaN/BicA-dependent promoter activity was obtained for <italic>BPSS1528</italic> (<italic>bapA</italic>)<italic>, BPSS1523</italic> (<italic>bicP</italic>)<italic>, BPSS1530</italic> (<italic>bprA</italic>)<italic>,</italic> or <italic>BPSS1520 (bprC)</italic> (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S2) (refer to Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C for gene location). Furthermore, BsaN/BicA could not activate transcription of a <italic>BPSS1512</italic> (<italic>tssM)-lacZ</italic> fusion in <italic>E. coli</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>G). Thus, BsaN/BicA drives the expression of <italic>bprDC</italic> and the <italic>BPSS1518-1516</italic> operons directly, whereas <italic>bicP</italic> and <italic>bprB</italic> gene expression is likely driven by the upstream-located <italic>bopA</italic> promoter. Transcription of the <italic>bapABC</italic> and <italic>bprA</italic> genes could be driven from the <italic>bicA</italic> promoter. Collectively, these results are represented in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C where the five validated promoters and operon structures controlled directly by BsaN/BicA are depicted by black solid line arrows.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Transcriptional analysis of</bold><bold><italic>bsaN</italic></bold><bold>and BsaN/BicA-regulated genes. A</bold>. Schematic diagram of the <italic>bsaN</italic> gene. Arrow above +1 indicates the transcriptional start site and direction. Double-headed arrows indicated the DNA fragments used for the reconstitution of BsaN-mediated promoter activation experiments. <bold>B</bold>. Promoter region indicating the transcriptional start site and start codon of <italic>bsaN</italic>. Bold and underlined letter G indicates the transcriptional start site (+1 in 2A). Bold and underlined agga indicate the putative RBS. Bold and underlined ATG and GTG indicate the actual and wrongly annotated start codons of <italic>bsaN</italic>, respectively. <bold>C</bold>. Genetic and transcriptional organization of T3SS3 genes. Arrows indicate transcriptional units. Putative promoter regions are depicted as shaded spheres at the beginning of line arrows. Red line arrows denote operons regulated by BprP. Black line arrows indicate operons regulated by BsaN. Black dotted arrows with shaded diamonds represent putative promoters that were analyzed for direct activation by BsaN/BicA, however, no expression was found (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S2).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="s12866-014-0206-6-2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Activation of promoters by BsaN/BicA in</bold><bold><italic>E. coli.</italic></bold> The ability of BsaN and BicA to directly activate the expression of promoters was examined by providing regulatory genes in <italic>trans</italic> and measuring &#x003b2;-galactosidase activities arising from the expression of transcriptional promoter<italic>-lacZ</italic> fusions in <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1;. Effect of BsaN/BicA on the expression of <bold>A</bold>. P<italic>bicA-lacZ</italic> fusion, <bold>B</bold>. P<italic>bopA-lacZ</italic> fusion, <bold>C</bold>. P<italic>bopE-lacZ</italic> fusion, <bold>D</bold>. P<italic>bprD-lacZ</italic> fusion and <bold>E</bold>. Ps1518<italic>-lacZ</italic> fusions; Ps1518 denotes the promoter region of BPSS1518. Effect of BsaN/BicA on the expression of <bold>F</bold>. P<italic>virA-lacZ</italic> fusion and <bold>G</bold>. P<italic>tssM</italic>-<italic>lacZ</italic> fusion. *p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="s12866-014-0206-6-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Identification of transcriptional start sites and the sequence motif for BsaN/BicA activation</title><p>Similarities between BsaN/BicA regulated promoters were examined by first determining their transcriptional start sites using RLM-RACE. One transcriptional start site was identified for the <italic>bicA, bprD</italic> and <italic>BPSS1518</italic> promoters, and two start sites were detected for the <italic>bopA</italic> and <italic>virA</italic> promoters. We were unable to identify a transcriptional start site for <italic>bopE</italic>, which is divergently transcribed from <italic>bopA</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C). A 150-bp sequence upstream of each transcriptional start site was submitted to MEME (Motif Elicitation for Prediction of DNA Motifs), which identified a 15&#x000a0;bp motif that we designated as the putative BsaN box (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>A). The distance from the transcriptional start site varied from 24&#x000a0;bp (<italic>virA</italic>) to 35&#x000a0;bp (<italic>bicA</italic> and <italic>bopA</italic>) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>B). When the motif was submitted to Motif Alignment &#x00026; Search Tool (MAST) to search for other potential BsaN/BicA-regulated promoters in the <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> genome (strain K96243), BsaN boxes were also found upstream of <italic>tssM</italic> and <italic>BPSS1889</italic>, a putative gene encoding an AraC family protein, in addition to those already identified. However, qRT- PCR analysis of <italic>BPSS1889</italic> expression in &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>bicA</italic> mutants did not reveal a decrease in expression compared to wild-type bacteria (data not shown). <italic>BPSS1889</italic> is located adjacent but transcribed in the opposite direction to the operon <italic>BPSS1884-1888,</italic> which was shown by RNAseq to be repressed by BsaN (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Although we could not confirm BsaN-dependent regulation of <italic>BPSS1889</italic> by qRT-PCR, the upstream BsaN box suggests the possible involvement of this putative regulator in repression of the operon <italic>in vivo</italic>. It is likely that conditions for BsaN-dependent repression are difficult to establish <italic>in vitro</italic> resulting in variability and lack of validation. We also could not identify any &#x02212;10 and &#x02212;35 sequences for prokaryotic housekeeping sigma factor in these promoters. It is likely that the BsaN/BicA-regulated promoters are transcribed by one or more alternative sigma factors. Unfortunately, <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> genome harbours more than 10 alternative sigma factors that have not been systematically studied. Therefore, their recognition sequences are currently unknown.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Sequence motifs in promoter regions of BsaN/BicA-regulated genes. A</bold>. The sequence motif for the BsaN box as indicated in bold, capital letters was identified using the bioinformatics tool MEME. <bold>B</bold>. The sequence of the BsaN box generated by MEME from the 5 BsaN-activating promoters as denoted in capital letters. The 3&#x02019;capitalized letters denote the start of transcription with the exception of P<italic>tssM,</italic> which is the translational start codon of TssM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="s12866-014-0206-6-4"/></fig><p><italic>tssM</italic> is one of the highly activated genes in our RNAseq analysis (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) confirming previous <italic>in vivo</italic> expression studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. However, despite the presence of the BsaN box upstream of the putative <italic>tssM</italic> operon (<italic>BPSS1512-1514</italic>), BsaN/BicA alone is not sufficient to activate <italic>tssM</italic> transcription in <italic>E. coli</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>G). This suggests that <italic>tssM</italic> regulation is more complex and likely requires additional cis and/or trans-acting regulatory elements for activation.</p></sec><sec><title>Determining the sequence motif requirement for BsaN/BicA activation</title><p>To determine whether the putative BsaN box motif was required and sufficient for the other genes regulated by BsaN/BicA, we constructed two types of truncated promoter-<italic>lacZ</italic> fusions. The &#x0201c;type 1&#x0201d; deletion contained only the BsaN motif and lacked all upstream sequences. The &#x0201c;type 2&#x0201d; deletion lacked all upstream sequences in addition to the first six bp of the putative BsaN box motif. We assayed the ability of these truncated promoters to drive <italic>lacZ</italic> expression in the presence of BsaN/BicA. All truncated versions of the promoter regions for <italic>bicA</italic>, <italic>virA</italic> and <italic>BPSS1518</italic> lost promoter activity (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>A-C). In contrast, versions containing the intact BsaN box for <italic>bprD</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>D) and <italic>bopA</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>E) were still functional, but further truncation eliminated their activation. The type 1 truncated version of the <italic>bprD</italic> promoter (P<italic>bprD1-lacZ</italic>) had three-fold higher &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity than the full length promoter- <italic>lacZ</italic> fusion (P<italic>bprD-lacZ)</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>D)<italic>,</italic> whereas deletion of sequences upstream of the <italic>bopA</italic> promoter did not have a significant effect on the level of activation (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>E).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Analysis of BsaN box requirements for transcription activation by BsaN/BicA.</bold> The ability of BsaN/BicA to directly activate the expression of truncated promoters was examined by providing regulatory genes in <italic>trans</italic> and measuring &#x003b2;-galactosidase activities arising from the expression of transcriptional promoter<italic>-lacZ</italic> fusions in <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1;. The top sequence of each gene includes the intact promoter region; sequence 1 is deleted up to the BsaN box; sequence 2 also includes a 6 nucleotide deletion of the BsaN box. Effect of BsaN/BicA on the expression of <bold>A</bold>. P<italic>bicA-lacZ</italic> fusion, <bold>B</bold>. P<italic>virA-lacZ</italic> fusion and <bold>C</bold>. Ps1518<italic>-lacZ</italic> fusion; Ps1518 denotes the promoter region of BPSS1518. Effect of BsaN/BicA on the expression of <bold>D</bold>. P<italic>bprD-lacZ</italic> fusion and <bold>E</bold>. P<italic>bopA-lacZ</italic> fusion.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="s12866-014-0206-6-5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>BprP directly activates <italic>bsaN</italic> and <italic>bsaM</italic></title><p>In the hierarchical control of T3SS3 and T6SS1 expression, BspR was suggested to activate the expression of <italic>bprP</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Previously, BprP was shown to bind sequences upstream of <italic>bsaM</italic> and <italic>bsaN</italic> (refer to Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C for gene location) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], suggesting that it directly activates their transcription. <italic>bsaN</italic> is the first orf of the putative operon that encodes structural components of T3SS3 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C) and is divergently transcribed from <italic>bsaM</italic>. To better understand how <italic>bsaN</italic> expression itself is controlled, we examined the relationships to its upstream regulators BspR and BprP using the LacZ fusion assay as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Plasmids with either <italic>bspR</italic> or <italic>bprP</italic> under arabinose induction control were introduced into <italic>E. coli</italic> containing plasmids with either a <italic>bsaN</italic>-<italic>lacZ</italic> fusion or a <italic>bsaM</italic>-<italic>lacZ</italic> fusion. A <italic>bprP-lacZ</italic> fusion served as control for BspR regulation. The ability of BspR and BprP to directly activate <italic>bsaN-lacZ, bsaM-lacZ</italic> and <italic>bprP-lacZ</italic> expression was determined by measuring &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity. As expected, BprP activated both the <italic>bsaM</italic> and <italic>bsaN</italic> promoters in <italic>E. coli</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>A, B). The presence of <italic>bprQ</italic>, a gene immediate downstream from <italic>bprP</italic>, had no effect on the activity of BprP. Furthermore, BprP did not activate its own promoter in <italic>E. coli</italic> (data not shown). However, BspR was not able to activate the promoter of <italic>bprP</italic> demonstrating that this regulator is not active in <italic>E. coli</italic> or that additional factors are required for activation (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>C).</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Activation of</bold><bold><italic>bsaM</italic></bold><bold>and</bold><bold><italic>bsaN</italic></bold><bold>promoters by BprP in</bold><bold><italic>E. coli.</italic></bold> The ability of BprP to directly activate the expression of promoters in the presence and absence of BprQ was examined by providing the <italic>bprP</italic> and <italic>bprQ</italic> genes in <italic>trans</italic> and measuring &#x003b2;-galactosidase activities arising from the expression of transcriptional promoter<italic>-lacZ</italic> fusions in <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1;. <bold>A</bold>. Effect of BprP and BprQ on the expression of P<italic>bsaN-lacZ</italic> fusion. <bold>B</bold>. Effect of BprP and BprQ on the expression of P<italic>bsaM-lacZ</italic> fusion. <bold>C</bold>. Effect of BspR on the expression of P<italic>bprP-lacZ</italic> fusion. *p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="s12866-014-0206-6-6"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Analysis of BsaN/BicA-regulated virulence loci</title><p>BsaN/BicA directly induces the expression of three known T3SS3 effector loci, <italic>bopA</italic>, <italic>bopC</italic> and <italic>bopE</italic>. Recent studies suggest that the T3SS3 effectors BopC and BopE are involved in invasion of epithelial cells and endosome escape [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], while BopA has been implicated in escape from autophagy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. BopC was recently shown to be secreted via T3SS3 in <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> K96243 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>], and our data confirm this (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S1). In <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW, mutation of <italic>bopA</italic>, <italic>bopC</italic> or <italic>bopE</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] individually resulted in no detectable difference in numbers of bacteria inside RAW264.7 mouse macrophages when measured 2&#x000a0;hr. after infection (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S2A). Upon extended incubation times, however, the &#x00394;<italic>bopA</italic> and the &#x00394;<italic>bopACE</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] strains exhibited an intracellular replication defect that was intermediate between levels observed for wildtype KHW and the &#x00394;<italic>bsaM</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] or &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> mutant derivatives. No differences in intracellular growth or host cell cytotoxicity were observed for the <italic>bopC</italic> or <italic>bopE</italic> mutant strains, although infection with the <italic>bopA</italic> or <italic>bopACE</italic> triple deletion mutants resulted in a decrease in cytotoxicity (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S2B) that coincided with a reduction in the rate of intracellular replication (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S2A), suggesting that intracellular replication results in host cell toxicity. This is in contrast to the T3SS3 &#x00394;<italic>bsaM</italic> and the &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> regulatory mutants in strain KHW, which are limited in their ability to multiply intracellularly as previously reported (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S2A).</p><p>Three BsaN/BicA-activated orfs are located between the T3SS3 and T6SS1 loci, and upstream of the T3SS3 effector gene <italic>bopC.</italic> We analyzed these orfs for potential roles in intracellular replication and cell-to-cell spread. <italic>BPSS1512</italic> encodes TssM, was previously shown to be secreted independently of T3SS3 and T6SS1 and functions as a broad-base deubiquitinase, with activity on TNFR-associated factor-3, TNFR-associated factor-6, and I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. <italic>BPSS1513</italic> is predicted to encode a short (97 aa) protein of unknown function and was not secreted under our assay conditions (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S3A). <italic>folE (BPSS1514)</italic> encodes a putative GTP cyclohydrolase I, suggesting a role in tetrahydrofolate biosynthesis rather than in virulence. Consistent with this notion, &#x00394;(<italic>BPSS1513</italic>-<italic>folE)</italic> mutant did not exhibit defects in cell-based virulence assays (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S3B-E).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>T3SSs and T6SSs play important roles in bacterial-host cell interactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. As each system is a complex structure encoded by 20 or more genes, it is expected that their expression and assembly would be tightly regulated. In <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>, T3SS3 and T6SS1 gene clusters are highly induced following host cell infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], and their function is critical for virulence in animal models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. T3SS3 has been shown to promote escape from endocytic vesicles, and T6SS1 plays a key role in promoting intercellular spread by fusion of adjacent cell membranes, leading to the formation of MNGCs that can be found in melioidosis patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Upregulation of T3SS3 is mediated by a signalling cascade initiating from BspR through BprP, which in turn increases the expression of the AraC-type regulator BsaN. Using global transcriptome and promoter activation analysis, we have shown that the BsaN regulon occupies a central position in modulating the expression of T3SS3, T6SS1 and several additional loci that are likely involved in promoting virulence and intracellular survival.</p><p>Regulatory factors may act to control expression by acting directly on a given gene, or indirectly by modulating a regulatory intermediate. We found that BsaN in complex with the T3SS3 chaperone BicA directly controls the expression of 19 loci in a region of chromosome 2 containing T6SS1 and T3SS3 accessory genes (<italic>BPSS1494-BPSS1533</italic>). BsaN/BicA activated transcription of the operons encoding T3SS3 effector proteins, the BipBCD translocon complex, chaperones, and other transcriptional regulators, as well as two genes of unknown function (<italic>BPSS1513-1514</italic>). BsaN/BicA upregulates expression of T6SS1 by activating the transcription of the two component regulatory system loci <italic>virAG</italic> and <italic>bprC,</italic> which in turn induce the <italic>hcp</italic> and <italic>tssAB</italic> loci, encoding T6SS1 tube and sheath proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. Interestingly, our RNAseq and qRT-PCR analyses revealed that BsaN also acts to repress transcription of T3SS3 apparatus genes in the <italic>bsaM</italic> and <italic>bsaN</italic> operons that are otherwise directly activated by the upstream regulator BprP. It is possible that BsaN mediates repression indirectly as the <italic>bsaM</italic> and <italic>bsaN</italic> intergenic region lacks a recognizable BsaN binding motif (see below). It is unlikely, however, that repression occurs due to decreased expression of <italic>bprP</italic> since its transcription is unchanged in a &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> mutant. Taken together, these findings demonstrate that BsaN plays a dual role in the regulation of T3SS3; one in coordinating translocon and effector transcription, and a second in preventing costly synthesis of T3SS3 apparatus components that are no longer required. Given the critical role of T3SS3 and T6SS1 in causing disease, BsaN/BicA could be considered a central regulator of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> mammalian virulence. Virulence studies in mice support this notion, since the &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> mutant was unable to cause disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] in contrast to the &#x00394;<italic>bspR</italic> mutant, which produced a more chronic infection in mice compared to wildtype bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p><p>In addition to loci associated with T3SS3 and T6SS1, 41 other genes with potential roles in virulence were also found by RNAseq to be positively regulated by BsaN, most notably the <italic>bimBCAD</italic> intracellular motility operon and <italic>tssM</italic>. Regulation of <italic>bimA</italic> has been shown to be through <italic>virAG</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], explaining why no BsaN motif was identified for the operon. While <italic>bimA</italic> encodes an autotransporter protein that nucleates and polymerizes host cell actin to facilitate intracellular motility and cell-cell spread by the bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>], the functions of the other loci in the <italic>bim</italic> operon are unknown. TssM has been shown to suppress host NF&#x003ba;B and Type I interferon pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. TssM is expressed and secreted inside cells following infection with <italic>B. mallei</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], however, secretion occurs independently of T3SS3 and T6SS1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. BsaN was also found to activate expression of a putative non-ribosomal peptide synthase (NRPS)/polyketide synthase (PKS) biosynthesis locus. The diversity of polyketides, PKSs and NRPS/PKS hybrid systems was recently reviewed by Hertweck [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. The <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> locus is similar in gene content to that of a recently described plasmid encoded NRPS/PKS system in the marine bacterium <italic>Alteromonas macleodii</italic>, which was suggested to produce a bleomycin-related antibiotic Unlike <italic>A. macleodii</italic>, the gene encoding the putative bleomycin-family resistance protein (<italic>BPSL2883</italic>) is not co-localized with the NRPS/PKS gene cluster, although they are similarly regulated by BsaN (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><p>BsaN is homologous to the <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> InvF, <italic>Shigella flexneri</italic> MxiE and the <italic>Yersinia enterocholitica</italic> YsaB transcriptional regulators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]&#x02013;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. All belong to the AraC/XylS family of transcriptional regulators, which act in complex with a chaperone to activate their respective T3SS genes. The chaperones not only serve as cognate partners to the transcriptional activators but also pair with T3SS translocase proteins, which are secreted into the host membrane to facilitate the injection of effector proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. We currently, have no understanding of the timed mechanism that frees BicA and allows it to partner with BsaN. The <italic>S. typhimurium</italic> chaperone SicA was shown to partition the translocase SipB and SipC, and it is sequestered by SipB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Once apparatus assembly is complete, translocases are secreted and SicA is free to complex and thus activate InvF. The InvF-SicA split feedback regulatory loop, which includes positive autoregulation of <italic>invF</italic>, is conserved in <italic>Y. enterocholitica</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. However, in <italic>S. flexneri</italic> MxiE-dependent activity is inhibited via sequestration by the T3SS substrate OspD1 when the apparatus is inactive [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Only when OspD1 is secreted, can MxiE partner with its chaperone IpgC to activated transcription of effector genes.</p><p>Regulation by BsaN-BicA is distinct from the previously described systems. The designation of BsaN-BicA as a dual-function regulatory protein complex is illustrated by its role in activating T3SS effector and accessory genes while repressing the system&#x02019;s structural and secretion components as summarized in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>. BsaN was also found to suppress the transcription of 51 additional genes in the <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> genome including those belonging to the <italic>fla1</italic> flagellar and chemotaxis locus on chromosome 1 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>E). Fla1 is the sole flagellar system in Southeast Asian <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> strains such as KHW, in contrast to Australian <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> isolates which possess a complete second system encoded on chromosome 2 (Fla2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. The conserved <italic>fla1</italic> locus encodes polar flagella and was shown to be responsible for swimming in liquid medium and swarming in soft agar, but played no role in intracellular motility following infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Moreover, we were intrigued to find that BsaN suppresses a second PKS/NRPS cluster (<italic>BPSS0130, BPSS0303-BPSS0311, BPSS0328-BPSS0339</italic>) (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), where almost identical homologs were identified in <italic>B. mallei</italic> and <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> by Biggins <italic>et al.</italic> and shown to produce an iron-chelating siderophore called malleilactone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. Disruption of the MAL cluster in <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> reduced lethality following infection of <italic>C. elegans</italic>, and purified malleilactone was toxic to mammalian cells at micromolar concentrations. How the function of MAL fits within an overall regulatory framework that promotes virulence is not clear, although it is conceivable that BsaN-mediated suppression of MAL reduces the production of toxic products during infection, thereby promoting long term survival within eukaryotic hosts. Alternatively, malleilactone itself may regulate virulence factor production similar to that reported for the <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> siderophore pyoverdine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>].</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Diagram of BsaN regulon.</bold> The BsaN regulon is shown as part of a regulatory network, which is superseded by BprP activating transcriptions of T3SS3 apparatus genes (blue) including <italic>bsaN</italic>. The <italic>bicA</italic> gene is likely initially transcribed via read through of apparatus genes. BsaN-BicA function as a complex to activate T3SS3 translocon (purple), effector (yellow), accessory (grey) and regulatory (red) genes. Transcriptional activation is indicated by green arrows. BsaN-BicA also activate <italic>virAG</italic>, which in turn activates the <italic>bimA</italic> motility genes and the T6SS1 locus. BprC activates the T6SS1 <italic>tssAB</italic> apparatus genes. BsaN-BicA also activate a non-ribosomal polyketide synthesis locus and several metabolic genes. BsaN-repressed genes as indicated by red, blunted lines include T3SS3 apparatus genes and flagellar motility genes. Only genes which have been validated by qRT-PCR are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="s12866-014-0206-6-7"/></fig><p>Until recently, BopA and BopE were the only two known T3SS effector proteins in <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>. The dearth of effectors is surprising when compared to other intracellular pathogens such as <italic>Shigella</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> that are known to possess numerous effectors. We have independently identified BopC (BPSS1516) as a new T3SS3 effector based on its regulatory control by BsaN/BicA. <italic>bopC</italic> is transcribed in an operon encoding its chaperone (<italic>BPSS1517</italic>) and a transposase (<italic>BPSS1518</italic>) that are also activated by BsaN/BicA. Incidentally, we had previously predicted by a genome-wide screen that <italic>BPSS1516</italic> would encode a T3SS effector based on genomic colocalization with T3SS chaperones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. The BsaN regulatory motif we found in the promoters of the effectors was also recently reported to be associated with T3SS3 in a condition-dependent transcriptome study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. Of the T3SS3-linked effector proteins; BopA, BopC and BopE, our results suggest that BopA is the most critical for promoting cellular infection, consistent with prior studies linking BopA to intracellular survival of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>B. mallei</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>],[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. No cellular phenotype was evident following infection with &#x00394;<italic>bopC</italic> or &#x00394;<italic>bopE</italic> deletion mutants, and the <italic>&#x00394;bopACE</italic> triple effector mutant was indistinguishable from the &#x00394;<italic>bopA</italic> single deletion strain. As with <italic>bopE</italic> and <italic>bopC</italic>, no roles were observed for the BsaN-regulated effector candidate loci <italic>BPSS1513-1514</italic> in cell-based virulence assays. <italic>BPSS1513</italic> encodes a hypothetical protein and <italic>BPSS1514</italic> is annotated as <italic>folE</italic>, a predicted GTP cyclohydrolase. Based on their genomic organization, the transcription of these loci is likely driven from the promoter upstream of <italic>BPSS1512 tssM</italic>. The secretion of HA-tagged BPSS1513 was not detected in <italic>in vitro</italic> secretion assays, although it is possible that the epitope tag could have interfered with secretion of BPSS1513, or that the assay was not performed at conditions permissive for secretion. It is intriguing why these three genes are placed under BsaN/BicA regulation by the bacterium. One possibility could be that they are important under specific stress conditions or during chronic infection.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Elucidating the scope of the BsaN regulon significantly enhances our understanding of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> pathogenic mechanisms. BsaN orchestrates the temporal and spatial expression of virulence determinants during progression through the intracellular lifecycle, promoting endosome escape and possibly evasion of autophagy through activation of T3SS3 effector loci, facilitating cell-cell spread by activation of T6SS1 and the <italic>bim</italic> intracellular motility loci, and suppressing cellular immunity via the action of the TssM ubiquitin hydrolase. BsaN also suppresses other loci that are potentially counterproductive following intracellular localization, such as the <italic>fla1</italic> flagellar motility and chemotaxis locus, which could lead to activation of cellular immunity pathways through PAMP recognition. It is likely that the BsaN regulon and other virulence determinants that promote pathogenesis in higher mammals have been shaped primarily as a result of interactions with free-living protozoa, similar to what is believed to be the case for <italic>L. pneumophila</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. Indeed, many of the same BsaN-regulated systems, namely T3SS and T6SS, are thought to act as &#x0201c;anti-predation determinants&#x0201d; that facilitate endosome escape and promote survival within bacteriovorus amoebae by manipulating eukaryotic pathways that are conserved from protists to humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The dual regulatory roles of BsaN &#x02013; that of an activator and a suppressor &#x02013; indicate that it is a key node in a regulatory program that successfully enables an environmental saprophyte to transition from the soil to surviving intracellularly.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Bacterial strains and culture conditions</title><p>Bacterial strains are listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>. Plasmids are listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S2. The <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> wild-type strains used in this study are clinical isolates KHW. Plasmids were introduced into <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1; and S17-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>] strains by electro- or chemical-transformation. Plasmids were transferred into <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> by conjugation from <italic>E. coli</italic> S17-1 on membrane filters. <italic>E. coli</italic> donors and <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> recipients were first mixed on filters and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C on non-selective Luria-Bertani (LB) agar for 3&#x000a0;hours before transferring the filters onto selective media. In our RNA isolation for transcriptome analysis and qRT-PCR, <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> wild-type and mutant strains were cultured in acidic (pH&#x000a0;5.0) RPMI medium containing 10% fetal bovine serum at 37&#x000b0;C for 4&#x000a0;hours, when bacteria were in their mid exponential growth phase (OD600&#x02009;~&#x02009;1.0). Acidification results in higher T3SS3 expression without affecting cell growth.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>List of strains used in this study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr valign="top"><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Strain</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Relevant characteristic(s)</bold><sup>
<bold>
<italic>a</italic>
</bold>
</sup></th><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Source or reference</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top"><bold>
<italic>E. coli</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">DH5&#x003b1;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>lacZ</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">S17-1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Donor strain for conjugation<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top"><bold>
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">KHW<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Clinical strain<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">&#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">KHW, <italic>bsaN</italic> orf was deleted<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">&#x00394;<italic>bsaM</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">KHW, <italic>bsaM</italic> orf was deleted<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">&#x00394;<italic>bopA</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">KHW, <italic>bopA</italic> orf was replaced by zeocin resistance gene, Zeo<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">&#x00394;<italic>bopE</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">KHW, <italic>bopE</italic> orf was deleted<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">&#x00394;<italic>bopC</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">KHW, <italic>bopC</italic> orf was replaced by zeocin resistance gene, Zeo<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">&#x00394;<italic>bopACE</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">KHW, <italic>bopA</italic> and <italic>bopE</italic> orfs were deleted, <italic>bopC</italic> orf was replaced by zeocin resistance gene, Zeo<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">&#x00394;<italic>BPSS1513-folE</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top">KHW, <italic>BPSS1513</italic> and <italic>folE</italic> orfs were deleted</td><td align="left" valign="top">This study</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>Abbreviations: <italic>Zeo</italic><sup><italic>r</italic></sup> zeocin resistant.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>List of plasmids used in this study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr valign="top"><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Plasmid</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Relevant characteristic(s)</bold><sup>
<bold>
<italic>a</italic>
</bold>
</sup></th><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Source or reference</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pMLBAD<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Broad host range vector containing inducible promoter P<sub>bad</sub>, Tm<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRW50<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Low copy-number vector containing a promoter-less <italic>lacZ</italic> gene, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pOT182<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Source of oriT sequence, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pK18mobsac<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Conjugative, suicide vector containing sacB gene, Km<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRW50mob<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">pRW50 containing oriT sequence from pOT182, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pMLbspR<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">pMLBAD containing <italic>bspR</italic> orf from KHW, Tm<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pMLbprP<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">pMLBAD containing <italic>bprP</italic> orf from KHW, Tm<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pMLbprQ<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">pMLBAD containing <italic>bprQ</italic> orf from KHW, Tm<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pMLbprPQ<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">pMLBAD containing <italic>bprP</italic> and <italic>bprQ</italic> orfs from KHW, Tm<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pMLbsaNs/bicA<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">pMLBAD containing shorter <italic>bsaN</italic> orf (GTG start) and <italic>bicA</italic> orf from KHW, Tm<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pMLbsaN<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">pMLBAD containing longer <italic>bsaN</italic> orf (ATG start) from KHW, Tm<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pMLbsaN/bicA<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">pMLBAD containing longer <italic>bsaN</italic> orf (ATG start) and <italic>bicA</italic> orf from KHW, Tm<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbsaM<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbsaM<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing <italic>bsaM</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbsaN<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbsaN<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing <italic>bsaN</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbicA<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbicA<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing <italic>bicA</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbicA1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbicA1<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing truncated <italic>bicA</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, type 1 deletion, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbicA2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbicA2<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing truncated <italic>bicA</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, type 2 deletion, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbopE<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbopE<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing <italic>bopE</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbopA<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbopA<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing <italic>bopA</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbopA1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbopA1<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing truncated <italic>bopA</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, type 1 deletion, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbopA2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbopA2<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing truncated <italic>bopA</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, type 2 deletion, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbprB<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbprC<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing <italic>bprB</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbprD<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbprD<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing <italic>bprD</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbprD1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbprD1<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing truncated <italic>bprD</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, type 1 deletion, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbprD2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbicA2<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing truncated <italic>bicA</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, type 2 deletion, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWbprC<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PbprC<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50mob containing <italic>bprC</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWs1518<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Ps1518<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50 containing BPSS1518 upstream sequence from KHW, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWs1518a<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Ps1518a<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50 containing truncated BPSS1518 upstream sequence from KHW, type 1 deletion, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWs1518b<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">Ps1518b<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50 containing truncated BPSS1518 upstream sequence from KHW, type 2 deletion, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWvirA<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PvirA<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50 containing <italic>virA</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWvirA1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">PvirA1<italic>-lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50 containing truncated <italic>virA</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, type 1 deletion, Tc<sup>r</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" valign="top">pRWtssM</td><td align="left" valign="top">PtssM-<italic>lacZ</italic> transcriptional fusion, pRW50 containing <italic>tssM</italic> upstream sequence from KHW, Tc<sup>r</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top">This study</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>Abbreviations: <italic>Ap</italic><sup><italic>r</italic></sup> ampicillin resistant, <italic>Km</italic><sup><italic>r</italic></sup> kanamycin resistant, <italic>Tc</italic><sup><italic>r</italic></sup> tetracycline resistant, <italic>Tm</italic><sup><italic>r</italic></sup> trimethoprim resistant.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Bacterial mutant construction</title><p><italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> gene deletions were generated by allelic exchange. Approximately 1&#x000a0;kb fragments upstream and downstream of the target gene were amplified from genomic DNA and cloned into pK18mobsacB vector [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] simultaneously using In-Fusion PCR cloning kit (Clontech). The plasmids were introduced into <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> strains by conjugation. Homologous recombination was then selected for by growing bacteria in LB&#x02009;+&#x02009;15% sucrose to counter select the <italic>sacB</italic> gene in the pK18mobsacB plasmid backbone. Successful double cross-over clones were screened by colony PCR from kanamycin sensitive colonies.</p></sec><sec><title>Activation of potential promoters by regulators</title><p>The ability of regulators to directly activate the expression of promoters was examined in <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1; as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Briefly, upstream regions of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> genes encompassing at least 100&#x000a0;bp of non-coding sequence upstream of the start codon were amplified from KHW genomic DNA and fused to the <italic>lacZ</italic> gene in pRW50 or pRW50mob to generate transcriptional fusions (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). Coding sequences of regulators were amplified from KHW genomic DNA and cloned into the arabinose-inducible expression vector pMLBAD. The <italic>lacZ</italic> fusion plasmid and arabinose-inducible regulator plasmid were introduced into the <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1;. &#x003b2;-galactosidase activities arising from the expression of promoter<italic>-lacZ</italic> fusions were assessed. &#x003b2;-Galactosidase assays were performed and values were calculated as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Transcriptome analysis by RNAseq</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from three independently grown bacterial cultures that were combined at equal cell density in their exponential growth phase and quick frozen in dry ice-ethanol slurry. Approximately 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup> ice cold cells were centrifuged at 3000 &#x000d7; g for 45&#x000a0;sec and 4&#x000b0;C and RNA was isolated from cell pellets using the RiboPure&#x02122;-Bacteria Kit (Ambion). Stable RNAs were removed from 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g RNA using the MICROBExpress kit from Ambion. Absence of genomic DNA contamination was confirmed by PCR. Paired-end libraries for Illumina sequencing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>] were prepared using the TruSeq RNA sample preparation kit version 2.0 (Illumina) according to manufacturer's High Sample (HS) protocol albeit omitting the initial poly A selection step. Libraries were generated from 2 technical replicates using 350&#x02013;500&#x000a0;ng enriched RNA from wildtype and &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> mutant strains as the starting material. Library preparation and sequencing was done by the UCLA Neuroscience Genomics Core (UNGC). Reads were aligned to chromosomes I and II of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW (also called BP22) (RefSeq identification numbers NZ_CM001156.1 and NZ_CM001157.1) and <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> K96243 (RefSeq identification numbers NC_006350.1 and NC_006351.1) as the annotated reference genome. The number of reads aligning to each genomic position on each strand was calculated and normalized using RPKM ([reads/kb of gene]/[million reads aligning to genome]). Differentially expressed genes identified by the log2 ratio of the differential between the wildtype and &#x00394;<italic>bsaN</italic> RPKMs. Only, genes with a &#x00394;log2 value of &#x0003e;1.5 and&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;&#x02212;1.5 corresponding to 3-fold up or down regulated genes with an adjusted p value (padj) of &#x0003c;0.01 were considered for this study.</p></sec><sec><title>Measurement of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> gene expression by qRT- PCR</title><p>Expression of activated genes was confirmed by qRT-PCR of RNA prepared from bacteria grown in acidified RPMI. Gene repression was difficult to observe under these conditions; RNA for qRT-PCR analysis was therefore prepared from infected RAW264.7 cells using the following procedure: RAW264.7 cells (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> cells/well) were seeded and grown overnight in DMEM medium in 12 well plates. RAW264.7 cells were transferred to RPMI medium prior to infection and infected at MOI of 100:1. Bacterial RNA was isolated from infected RAW264.7 cells 4&#x000a0;hours post infection using TRIzol and PureLink RNA mini-kit (Invitrogen). cDNA was synthesized using 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g of RNA and the High Capacity Reverse Transcription Reagent Kit (Applied Biosystems). Transcripts were quantified using GoTaq qPCR Master Mix (Promega) in a BioRad iQ5 machine. Real-time PCR primers are listed in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S4. Relative RNA level of a particular gene in mutant strains was normalized to that of wild type using the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;</sup>Ct method with 16S rRNA or <italic>recA</italic> as reference gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Mapping transcriptional start sites</title><p>The transcriptional start (+1) sites of the promoters were mapped by RNA ligase-mediated rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RLM-RACE) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. The RLM-RACE was performed using GeneRacer Kit (Invitrogen) according to manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> RNA was isolated as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence motif predication and database search of motifs in the <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW genome</title><p>150 base pairs of nucleotide sequence upstream of the transcriptional starts of each gene was submitted to the bioinformatics tool &#x02013; MEME (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://meme.nbcr.net/meme/cgi-bin/meme.cgi">http://meme.nbcr.net/meme/cgi-bin/meme.cgi</ext-link>) for prediction of DNA motifs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. The motif with the highest statistical significance (lowest E-value) was chosen and its data &#x02013; in Position-Specific Probability Matrix format was submitted to MAST (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://meme.nbcr.net/meme/cgi-bin/mast.cgi">http://meme.nbcr.net/meme/cgi-bin/mast.cgi</ext-link>) to search for the best matching positions in the upstream sequences of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Results were presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation. Student&#x02019;s t-test was used to find the significant differences between the means, defined as when p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 (*) and p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 (**).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>YC, IS and YHG designed the experiments. YC, IS, CTF, XJY, BET and IJT performed the experiments. YC, IS, CTF, AJ and YHG analyzed the results. YC and YHG conceived the study and together with IS and JFM wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Additional file</title></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>Materials and Methods. Table S1.</bold> Summary of Illumina sequencing. <bold>Table S2.</bold> &#x003b2;-galactosidase activities in <italic>E coli</italic> DH5&#x003b1; strain containing transcriptional promoter-<italic>lacZ</italic> fusions and arabinose-inducible <italic>bsaN</italic> and <italic>bicA</italic> or empty vector. <bold>Table S3.</bold> List of additional plasmids used in this study. <bold>Table S4.</bold> List of Real-Time PCR primers for this study. <bold>Figure S1.</bold> Secretion of BopC. KHW and &#x00394;<italic>bsaM</italic> mutant were grown in acidic LB broth for 3&#x000a0;hours. Total protein from the bacterial culture supernatant was precipitated and protein concentration was normalized with respect to the optical density (OD600) of the bacterial cultures. Proteins on membranes were probed with rabbit polyclonal antibodies to BopC and BopE. <bold>Figure S2.</bold> (A) Intracellular replication of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW and mutants in RAW264.7 cells. Cells were infected at an MOI of 0.1:1. Intracellular bacterial loads were quantified at 2 and 8&#x000a0;h post infection by plate counting. (B) Cytotoxicity of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW and mutants against RAW264.7 cells. Cells were infected at an MOI of 100:1. Cytotoxicity was quantified at 8&#x000a0;h post infection by LDH release assay. *p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. <bold>Figure S3.</bold> Secretion and function of BsaN controlled proteins. <bold>A</bold>. Secretion of BPSS1513 in strain KHW. Proteins were separated on 12% polyacrylamide gels, transferred to PVDF membranes and probed with a mouse monoclonal antibody to HA or rabbit polyclonal antibody to BopE. P: pellet; S: supernatant. <bold>B</bold>. Intracellular replication of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW and &#x00394;(<italic>BPSS1513-folE)</italic> mutant in RAW264.7 cells at 2&#x000a0;h and 8&#x000a0;h (MOI of 10:1) or <bold>C</bold>. 2&#x000a0;h and 24&#x000a0;h after infection at an MOI of 0.1:1. Intracellular bacterial loads were quantified by plate counting. <bold>D</bold>. Cytotoxicity of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> KHW and &#x00394;(<italic>BPSS1513-folE</italic>) mutant against RAW264.7 cells. Cells were infected at an MOI of 100:1. Cytotoxicity was quantified at 8&#x000a0;h post infection by LDH release assay. E. MNGC formation of cells infected with <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> wild-type (WT) strain KHW and F. &#x00394;(<italic>BPSS1513-1514</italic>) mutant at an MOI of 10:1.</p></caption><media xlink:href="s12866-014-0206-6-S1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank M. A. Valvano (University of Western Ontario) for pMLBAD plasmid, S.J. Busby (University of Birmingham) for pRW50 plasmid, S. Korbsrisate (Mahidol University) for BopC antibody, and M.P. Stevens (University of Edinburgh) for BopE antibody. This work is supported by grants T208A3105 from the Ministry of Education to YHG, NMRC/1221/2009 from the National Medical Research Council to YHG, an award from the Pacific Southwest Regional Center of Excellence in Biodefense and Emerging Infectious Diseases (NIH U54 A1065359) to JFM, and grant HDTRA1-11-1-0003 from the Defense Threat Reduction Agency to JFM. We would like to thank Isabelle Chen for her technical assistance.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Galyov</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>DeShazer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular insights into Burkholderia pseudomallei and Burkholderia mallei pathogenesis</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.micro.112408.134030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20528691?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20528691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wiersinga</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Poll</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><article-title>Melioidosis: insights into the pathogenicity of Burkholderia pseudomallei</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1385</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16541135?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16541135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hasselbring</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>Dictyostelium discoideum as a model system for identification of Burkholderia pseudomallei virulence factors</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2011</year><volume>79</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2079</fpage><lpage>2088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01233-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21402765?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21402765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Inglis</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutton</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><article-title>Interaction between Burkholderia pseudomallei and Acanthamoeba species results in coiling phagocytosis, endamebic bacterial survival, and escape</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2000</year><volume>68</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1681</fpage><lpage>1686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.68.3.1681-1686.2000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10678988?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10678988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of tomato plant as a novel host model for Burkholderia pseudomallei</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>28</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-10-28</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20109238?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20109238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaestli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothballer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuanyok</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Keim</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><article-title>Out of the ground: aerial and exotic habitats of the melioidosis bacterium Burkholderia pseudomallei in grasses in Australia</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>14</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2058</fpage><lpage>2070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2011.02671.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22176696?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22176696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Burtnick</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngugi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribot</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chantratita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Scorpio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Deshazer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>The Cluster 1 Type VI Secretion System is a Major Virulence Determinant in Burkholderia pseudomallei</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2011</year><volume>79</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1512</fpage><lpage>1525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01218-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21300775?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300775</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><article-title>Regulation of type VI secretion system during Burkholderia pseudomallei infection</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2011</year><volume>79</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3064</fpage><lpage>3073</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.05148-11</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21670170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21670170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Toesca</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Teslaa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaty</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schr&#x000f6;der</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiou</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Teitell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><article-title>Dissection of the Burkholderia intracellular life cycle using a photothermal nanoblade</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><issue>29</issue><fpage>12095</fpage><lpage>12100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1107183108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21730143?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21730143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Galyov</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><article-title>An Inv/Mxi-Spa-like type III protein secretion system in Burkholderia pseudomallei modulates intracellular behaviour of the pathogen</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2002.03190.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12410823?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12410823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pervaiz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><article-title>Caspase-1 dependent macrophage death induced by Burkholderia pseudomallei</article-title><source>Cell Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1447</fpage><lpage>1458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-5822.2005.00569.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16153244?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16153244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Easton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Underwood-Fowler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Titball</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bancroft</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Galyov</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><article-title>Attenuated virulence and protective efficacy of a Burkholderia pseudomallei bsa type III secretion mutant in murine models of melioidosis</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2004</year><volume>150</volume><issue>Pt 8</issue><fpage>2669</fpage><lpage>2676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.27146-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15289563?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15289563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Warawa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><article-title>Type III secretion system cluster 3 is required for maximal virulence of Burkholderia pseudomallei in a hamster infection model</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2005</year><volume>242</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.femsle.2004.10.045</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15621426?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15621426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of a regulatory cascade controlling Type III Secretion System 3 gene expression in Burkholderia pseudomallei</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>76</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07124.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20345664?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20345664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Friebel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardt</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Galyov</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><article-title>A Burkholderia pseudomallei type III secreted protein, BopE, facilitates bacterial invasion of epithelial cells and exhibits guanine nucleotide exchange factor activity</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2003</year><volume>185</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>4992</fpage><lpage>4996</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.185.16.4992-4996.2003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12897019?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12897019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cullinane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazar-Adler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tra</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolvetang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Devenish</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Stimulation of autophagy suppresses the intracellular survival of Burkholderia pseudomallei in mammalian cell lines</article-title><source>Autophagy</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/auto.6246</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18483470?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18483470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cullinane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Treerat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramm</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Devenish</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><article-title>The Burkholderia pseudomallei type III secretion system and BopA are required for evasion of LC3-associated phagocytosis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e17852</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017852</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21412437?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21412437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Muangman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Korbsrisate</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Muangsombut</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Galyov</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><article-title>BopC is a type III secreted effector protein of Burkholderia pseudomallei</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2011</year><volume>323</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2011.02359.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22092682?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22092682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Srinon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Muangman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Imyaem</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Muangsombut</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazar Adler</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Galyov</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Korbsrisate</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Comparative assessment of the intracellular survival of the Burkholderia pseudomallei bopC mutant</article-title><source>J Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>51</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>522</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12275-013-2557-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23990305?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23990305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><article-title>Model of differential susceptibility to mucosal Burkholderia pseudomallei infection</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2002</year><volume>70</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.70.2.504-511.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11796576?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11796576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Biggins</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><article-title>Metabolites from the induced expression of cryptic single operons found in the genome of Burkholderia pseudomallei</article-title><source>J Am Chem Soc</source><year>2011</year><volume>133</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1638</fpage><lpage>1641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja1087369</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21247113?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21247113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><article-title>Motility protein complexes in the bacterial flagellar motor</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>261</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.1996.0453</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8757288?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8757288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Melville</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunsalus</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><article-title>Aerobic regulation of cytochrome d oxidase (cydAB) operon expression in Escherichia coli: roles of Fnr and ArcA in repression and activation</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1997.5031860.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9302022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9302022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lefebre</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Valvano</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>Construction and evaluation of plasmid vectors optimized for constitutive and regulated gene expression in Burkholderia cepacia complex isolates</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>68</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>5956</fpage><lpage>5964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.12.5956-5964.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12450816?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12450816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritsch</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><source>Molecular cloning : a laboratory manual</source><year>1989</year><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lodge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fear</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunasekaran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamini</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><article-title>Broad host range plasmids carrying the Escherichia coli lactose and galactose operons</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>1992</year><volume>74</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1992.tb05378.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1526459?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1526459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>DeShazer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlyon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><article-title>Mutagenesis of Burkholderia pseudomallei with Tn5-OT182: isolation of motility mutants and molecular characterization of the flagellin structural gene</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1997</year><volume>179</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2116</fpage><lpage>2125</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9079894?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9079894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Titball</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerde&#x000f1;o-T&#x000e1;rraga</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossman</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mungall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebaihia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bason</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Beacham</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name><surname>Challis</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherevach</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chillingworth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>DeShazer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Feltwell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hance</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Holroyd</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagels</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Genomic plasticity of the causative agent of melioidosis, Burkholderia pseudomallei</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><issue>39</issue><fpage>14240</fpage><lpage>14245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0403302101</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15377794?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15377794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shanks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Burtnick</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Waag</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Spurgers</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribot</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Panchal</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gherardini</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Deshazer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Burkholderia mallei tssM encodes a putative deubiquitinase that is secreted and expressed inside infected RAW 264.7 murine macrophages</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2009</year><volume>77</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1636</fpage><lpage>1648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01339-08</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19168747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19168747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teh</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagullo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiou</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Teitell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><article-title>Type three secretion system-mediated escape of Burkholderia pseudomallei into the host cytosol is critical for the activation of NFkappaB</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>115</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-14-115</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24884837?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24884837</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Macary</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><article-title>Suppression of host innate immune response by Burkholderia pseudomallei through the virulence factor TssM</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2010</year><volume>184</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>5160</fpage><lpage>5171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.0902663</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20335533?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20335533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Endres</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Subversion of trafficking, apoptosis, and innate immunity by type III secretion system effectors</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>21</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2013.06.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23870533?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23870533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jani</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><article-title>Type VI secretion: not just for pathogenesis anymore</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2010.06.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20638635?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20638635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Puthucheary</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Vadivelu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>The histopathology of human melioidosis</article-title><source>Histopathology</source><year>1995</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2559.1995.tb00620.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7713483?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7713483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cascales</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambillau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Structural biology of type VI secretion systems</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>367</volume><issue>1592</issue><fpage>1102</fpage><lpage>1111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2011.0209</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22411981?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22411981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeng</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Galyov</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of a bacterial factor required for actin-based motility of Burkholderia pseudomallei</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04528.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15773977?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15773977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hertweck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>The biosynthetic logic of polyketide diversity</article-title><source>Angew Chem Int Ed Engl</source><year>2009</year><volume>48</volume><issue>26</issue><fpage>4688</fpage><lpage>4716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.200806121</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19514004?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19514004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Darwin</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><article-title>Type III secretion chaperone-dependent regulation: activation of virulence genes by SicA and InvF in Salmonella typhimurium</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1850</fpage><lpage>1862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/20.8.1850</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11296219?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11296219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>WA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Maurelli</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><article-title>MxiE regulates intracellular expression of factors secreted by the Shigella flexneri 2a type III secretion system</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2002</year><volume>184</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>4409</fpage><lpage>4419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.184.16.4409-4419.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12142411?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12142411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><article-title>Regulation of the Ysa type III secretion system of Yersinia enterocolitica by YsaE/SycB and YsrS/YsrR</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>4056</fpage><lpage>4066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.186.13.4056-4066.2004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15205407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15205407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Deane</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrusci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><article-title>Timing is everything: the regulation of type III secretion</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>67</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1065</fpage><lpage>1075</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-009-0230-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20043184?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20043184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><article-title>Complex function for SicA, a Salmonella enterica serovar typhimurium type III secretion-associated chaperone</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2000</year><volume>182</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2262</fpage><lpage>2268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.182.8.2262-2268.2000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10735870?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10735870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Parsot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ageron</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Penno</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mavris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamoussi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>d'Hauteville</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sansonetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Demers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>A secreted anti-activator, OspD1, and its chaperone, Spa15, are involved in the control of transcription by the type III secretion apparatus activity in Shigella flexneri</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1627</fpage><lpage>1635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2005.04645.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15916611?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15916611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tuanyok</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Auerbach</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Brettin</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Munk</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Detter</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornstra</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sermswan</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wuthiekanun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Keim</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><article-title>A horizontal gene transfer event defines two distinct groups within Burkholderia pseudomallei that have dissimilar geographic distributions</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2007</year><volume>189</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>9044</fpage><lpage>9049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01264-07</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17933898?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17933898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Biggins</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ternei</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><article-title>Malleilactone, a polyketide synthase-derived virulence factor encoded by the cryptic secondary metabolome of Burkholderia pseudomallei group pathogens</article-title><source>J Am Chem Soc</source><year>2012</year><volume>134</volume><issue>32</issue><fpage>13192</fpage><lpage>13195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja3052156</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22765305?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22765305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lamont</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Beare</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochsner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasil</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasil</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><article-title>Siderophore-mediated signaling regulates virulence factor production in Pseudomonasaeruginosa</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>7072</fpage><lpage>7077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.092016999</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11997446?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11997446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Panina</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozak</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuk</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><article-title>A genome-wide screen identifies a Bordetella type III secretion effector and candidate effectors in other species</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>58</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2005.04823.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16164564?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16164564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nandi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreisberg</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Conejero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshaghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ang</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobral</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Korbsrisate</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Titball</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bancroft</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Valade</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>The condition-dependent transcriptional landscape of Burkholderia pseudomallei</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e1003795</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003795</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24068961?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24068961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Whitlock</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Estes</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><article-title>Construction of a reporter system to study Burkholderia mallei type III secretion and identification of the BopA effector protein function in intracellular survival</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><year>2008</year><volume>102</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>S127</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0035-9203(08)70029-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19121674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19121674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Escoll</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolando</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Valero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchrieser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>From Amoeba to Macrophages: Exploring the Molecular Mechanisms of Legionella pneumophila Infection in Both Hosts</article-title><source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source><year>2013</year><volume>376</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23949285?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23949285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Priefer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000fc;hler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>A broad range mobilization system for in vitro genetic engineering: Transposon mutagenesis in Gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>Bio/Technology</source><year>1983</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>784</fpage><lpage>791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt1183-784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tauch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalinowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thierbach</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Puhler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Small mobilizable multi-purpose cloning vectors derived from the Escherichia coli plasmids pK18 and pK19: selection of defined deletions in the chromosome of Corynebacterium glutamicum</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1994</year><volume>145</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1119(94)90324-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8045426?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8045426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Control of the Escherichia coli rrnB P1 promoter strength by ppGpp</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>11181</fpage><lpage>11189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.270.19.11181</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7538113?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7538113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adiconis</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusbaum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnirke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Regev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Comprehensive comparative analysis of strand-specific RNA sequencing methods</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1491</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20711195?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20711195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11846609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bensing</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunny</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><article-title>Sensitive detection of bacterial transcription initiation sites and differentiation from RNA processing sites in the pheromone-induced plasmid transfer system of Enterococcus faecalis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>7794</fpage><lpage>7799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.15.7794</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8755555?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8755555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Elkan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Fitting a mixture model by expectation maximization to discover motifs in biopolymers</article-title><source>Proc Int Conf Intell Syst Mol Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><?supplied-pmid 7584402?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7584402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gribskov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Combining evidence using p-values: application to sequence homology searches</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>1998</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/14.1.48</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9520501?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9520501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>