<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Development</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Development</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DEV</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">develop</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Development (Cambridge, England)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0950-1991</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1477-9129</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Company of Biologists Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4725341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26657768</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.126326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">DEV126326</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>102</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Stem Cells and Regeneration</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genes implicated in stem cell identity and temporal programme are directly targeted by Notch in neuroblast tumours</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zacharioudaki</surname><given-names>Evanthia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Housden</surname><given-names>Benjamin E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="AN1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garinis</surname><given-names>George</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stojnic</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Delidakis</surname><given-names>Christos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>Sarah J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x02021;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Physiology, Development and Neuroscience</addr-line>, <institution>University of Cambridge</institution>, <addr-line>Cambridge CB2 3DY</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><institution>Institute of Molecular Biology and Biotechnology, FORTH-Hellas</institution>, <addr-line>Heraklion, Crete 70013</addr-line>, <country>Greece</country></aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Biology</addr-line>, <institution>University of Crete, Heraklion</institution>, <country>Greece GR71409</country></aff><aff id="af4"><label>4</label><institution>Cambridge Systems Biology Centre, University of Cambridge</institution>, <addr-line>Cambridge CB2 1QR</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><author-notes><fn id="AN1" fn-type="present-address"><label>*</label><p>Present address: Department of Genetics, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02021;</label>Authors for correspondence (<email>delidaki@imbb.forth.gr</email>; <email>sjb32@cam.ac.uk</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. --><volume>143</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2016. Published by The Company of Biologists Ltd</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0</uri>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium provided that the original work is properly attributed.</license-p></license><?release-delay 0|0?></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="develop-143-126326.pdf"/><abstract><p>Notch signalling is involved in a multitude of developmental decisions and its aberrant activation is linked to many diseases, including cancers. One example is the neural stem cell tumours that arise from constitutive Notch activity in <italic>Drosophila</italic> neuroblasts. To investigate how hyperactivation of Notch in larval neuroblasts leads to tumours, we combined results from profiling the upregulated mRNAs and mapping the regions bound by the core Notch pathway transcription factor Su(H). This identified 246 putative direct Notch targets. These genes were highly enriched for transcription factors and overlapped significantly with a previously identified regulatory programme dependent on the proneural transcription factor Asense. Included were genes associated with the neuroblast maintenance and self-renewal programme that we validated as Notch regulated <italic>in vivo</italic>. Another group were the so-called temporal transcription factors, which have been implicated in neuroblast maturation. Normally expressed in specific time windows, several temporal transcription factors were ectopically expressed in the stem cell tumours, suggesting that Notch had reprogrammed their normal temporal regulation. Indeed, the Notch-induced hyperplasia was reduced by mutations affecting two of the temporal factors, which, conversely, were sufficient to induce mild hyperplasia on their own. Altogether, the results suggest that Notch induces neuroblast tumours by directly promoting the expression of genes that contribute to stem cell identity and by reprogramming the expression of factors that could regulate maturity.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><bold>Summary:</bold> Genome-wide screens identify direct targets of Notch involved in promoting neural stem cell tumours in <italic>Drosophila,</italic> tying Notch into the transcription factor network coordinating these stem cells.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEY WORDS</title><kwd><italic>Drosophila</italic></kwd><kwd>Neuroblast</kwd><kwd>Notch</kwd><kwd>Gene regulation</kwd><kwd>Stem cell</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Medical Research Council</institution><institution-id>http://search.crossref.org/fundref?q=501100001322</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>G0800034</award-id><award-id>MR/L007177/1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Herakleitos</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NSRF 2007-2013</award-id></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The Notch pathway is a cell communication mechanism that is involved in many developmental decisions and in stem cell homeostasis of adult tissues. Furthermore, abnormal Notch activity is linked to various diseases, including several forms of cancer. Indeed, in some cancers Notch is thought to have a role in the initiation and maintenance of cancer stem cells (CSCs) (<xref rid="DEV126326C16" ref-type="bibr">Capaccione and Pine, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C44" ref-type="bibr">Ntziachristos et al., 2014</xref>). One context in which high Notch activity causes stem cell hyperplasia, with similarities to CSCs, is in <italic>Drosophila</italic> neural stem cells, the so-called neuroblasts (NBs). Notch is normally active in NBs but is rapidly inactivated in their progeny. Sustained activity of the pathway in the NB lineages results in brain tumours, where the overproliferation of NBs at the expense of neurons gives rise to large NB masses in the brain that compromise the survival of the animals to adulthood (<xref rid="DEV126326C13" ref-type="bibr">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C58" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C60" ref-type="bibr">Weng et al., 2010</xref>). It is therefore important to understand how sustained Notch activity alters the balance between self-renewal and differentiation to result in tissue tumorigenesis.</p><p>In normal circumstances, the larval NBs undergo repeated rounds of asymmetric division to generate neurons appropriate for the adult CNS. At each division the larger cell maintains NB properties and regrows to sustain many rounds of division (<xref rid="DEV126326C33" ref-type="bibr">Knoblich, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C52" ref-type="bibr">Sousa-Nunes and Somers, 2013</xref>). The majority are Type I NBs, identified by expression of the transcription factors (TFs) Deadpan (Dpn) and Asense (Ase), whose small daughter cell, the ganglion mother cell (GMC), divides terminally to produce two neurons and/or glia. A small number of NBs, the so-called Type II NBs (eight per brain lobe), express Dpn but not Ase and follow a more complex pattern of division. When these divide asymmetrically, their smaller daughter is an immature intermediate neural progenitor (INP), which reaches maturation within a few hours and then itself divides asymmetrically a few times. In this case, the daughter is a GMC similar to that of Type I NBs. The existence of INPs enables Type II NBs to generate a large number of progeny in a short period of time (<xref rid="DEV126326C5" ref-type="bibr">Bayraktar and Doe, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C6" ref-type="bibr">Bello et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C10" ref-type="bibr">Boone and Doe, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C13" ref-type="bibr">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C28" ref-type="bibr">Izergina et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C30" ref-type="bibr">Kang and Reichert, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C33" ref-type="bibr">Knoblich, 2008</xref>). At the end of larval life, both Type I and Type II NBs exit the cell cycle and cease proliferation, under the influence of temporal factors (<xref rid="DEV126326C18" ref-type="bibr">Chai et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C41" ref-type="bibr">Maurange et al., 2008</xref>), the steroid hormone ecdysone (<xref rid="DEV126326C24" ref-type="bibr">Homem et al., 2014</xref>) and other cues (<xref rid="DEV126326C18" ref-type="bibr">Chai et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>Notch pathway activity is detected in NBs and contributes to their maintenance. During mitosis, one of the key determinants that is segregated asymmetrically into the GMC daughter is Numb, a potent inhibitor of Notch signalling (<xref rid="DEV126326C2" ref-type="bibr">Babaoglan et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C19" ref-type="bibr">Connor-giles et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C21" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C38" ref-type="bibr">Le Borgne et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C47" ref-type="bibr">Rhyu et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C55" ref-type="bibr">Spana and Doe, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C58" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2006</xref>). Perturbations in Numb function lead to uncontrolled proliferation of NBs and the formation of brain tumours. This is largely caused by the ectopic Notch activity that ensues, a condition that is mimicked by expression of a constitutively active Notch fragment (<xref rid="DEV126326C13" ref-type="bibr">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C58" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C60" ref-type="bibr">Weng et al., 2010</xref>). Upon interaction with its ligands [Delta (Dl) or Serrate (Ser)], the Notch receptor undergoes two proteolytic cleavages to release the Notch intracellular domain (Nicd), which translocates into the nucleus where it interacts with the CSL (also known as RBPJ) DNA-binding protein {Suppressor of Hairless [Su(H)] in <italic>Drosophila</italic>} and activates the transcription of target genes (<xref rid="DEV126326C14" ref-type="bibr">Bray, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C34" ref-type="bibr">Kopan and Ilagan, 2009</xref>). Expression of Nicd or of a transmembrane fragment mimicking the first ligand-activated cleavage (N&#x00394;ecd), results in similar brain tumours to those caused by loss of Numb.</p><p>One significant target of Notch activity in NBs is <italic>Enhancer of spilt m&#x003b3;</italic> [<italic>E(spl)m&#x003b3;-HLH</italic>], a HES family gene that is dependent on Notch for expression (<xref rid="DEV126326C1" ref-type="bibr">Almeida and Bray, 2005</xref>). However, mutations removing the entire <italic>E(spl)</italic> complex [<italic>E(spl)-C</italic>] of Notch-responsive genes have only minor effects on NB maintenance, suggesting that additional targets exist. Indeed, <italic>E(spl)m&#x003b3;-HLH</italic> appears to function semi-redundantly with <italic>dpn</italic>, another HES family gene, which has both Notch-dependent and Notch-independent modes of regulation in NBs (<xref rid="DEV126326C48" ref-type="bibr">San-Ju&#x000e1;n and Baonza, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C64" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2012</xref>). In addition, expression of the zinc-finger protein Klumpfuss (Klu) may also be Notch regulated in this context (<xref rid="DEV126326C8" ref-type="bibr">Berger et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C62" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2012</xref>). Overexpression of <italic>E(spl)m&#x003b3;-HLH</italic>, <italic>dpn</italic> or <italic>klu</italic> can cause NB hyperplasia (<xref rid="DEV126326C8" ref-type="bibr">Berger et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C48" ref-type="bibr">San-Ju&#x000e1;n and Baonza, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C62" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>); however, their effects are generally weaker or more spatially limited than that of Nicd or N&#x00394;ecd. It therefore appears that these Notch targets do not account for the full scope of Notch functions in normal NBs, nor in the hyperactive Notch-induced NB tumours.</p><p>To characterise the repertoire of genes activated by Notch in overproliferating NB tumours we compared the transcriptional profiles from the CNS of Notch-induced NB hyperplasia with wild type (WT) and integrated these data with maps of the regions bound by Su(H) in the Notch hyperplasia. The Notch targets identified in this way were highly enriched in genes encoding TFs associated with NB maintenance and the self-renewal programme, as well as TFs that are implicated in the temporal programming of the stem cells. Validating these targets and their functions <italic>in vivo</italic> suggests that stemness and temporal TFs might cooperate to sustain Notch-induced hyperplasias. Furthermore, the redundancy between the identified targets potentially gives a robustness to the signalling output that could explain why the previously known targets are insufficient to account for the Notch activation phenotype.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s2"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Identification of Notch target genes involved in NB hyperplasia</title><p>Constitutively active Notch (N&#x00394;ecd) results in NB overproliferation at the expense of neurons (<xref rid="DEV126326C13" ref-type="bibr">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C58" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2006</xref>). To identify genes acting downstream of Notch to produce NB hyperplasia, we first characterised the population of RNAs showing elevated expression, since the Nicd complex results in transcriptional activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>A). N&#x00394;ecd was expressed for 24&#x02005;h in larval NBs (via <italic>grhNB-Gal4 Gal80ts</italic>) to produce CNS dominated by Dpn-expressing NBs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>A), which included many Ase<sup>&#x02212;</sup> Type II NB-like cells as well as Ase<sup>+</sup> Type I NB-like cells (<uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S1A</uri>). A comparison of their RNA expression profile with that of control CNS of a similar stage identified 1576 upregulated transcripts in N&#x00394;ecd hyperplastic CNS (FDR&#x02264;0.1) (<uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Table&#x000a0;S1</uri>). We note that, as this reflects changes in the entire CNS transcriptome, the effects of N&#x00394;ecd will be attenuated by the non-NB cells and there will be indirect effects from the altered ratios of cell types in the hyperplastic brains.
<fig id="DEV126326F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p><bold>Identification of target genes in Notch-induced NB hyperplasia.</bold> (A) Wild-type (WT) and hyperplastic (N&#x00394;ecd; expressed using <italic>grhNB-Gal4</italic>) <italic>Drosophila</italic> CNS. Dpn marks NBs in brain lobes (top) and VNC (bottom). Scale bars: 50 &#x000b5;m. (B) GSEA plot of enrichment scores (classic scoring approach) for Su(H)-bound genes [defined as genes within 20&#x02005;kb of an Su(H) peak] relative to genes showing expression changes, pre-ranked by log<sub>2</sub> fold change (FC) (3717 genes, FDR&#x02264;0.1) indicates that the Su(H) gene set is significantly enriched in the upregulated genes. ES, enrichment score, which indicates the degree of overrepresentation at the top of the ranked list; NES, normalised enrichment score; <italic>P</italic>-value, nominal <italic>P</italic>-value; FDR, false discovery rate. (C) The proportion of upregulated genes (1576 genes, FDR&#x02264;0.1) with Su(H) binding (red, 246 genes) and their relationship to genes with known expression in NBs and to Notch targets in wing hyperplasia. NB expression was determined by RNAseq of FACS sorted cells [F (<xref rid="DEV126326C8" ref-type="bibr">Berger et al., 2012</xref>)] or by targeted DamID with PolII [T (<xref rid="DEV126326C54" ref-type="bibr">Southall et al., 2013</xref>)], or both (F+T). (D) Sequence logo of motifs enriched in Su(H)-bound fragments. Enrichment for the Su(H) motif is more significant than in related ChIP datasets (e.g. <xref rid="DEV126326C49" ref-type="bibr">Skalska et al., 2015</xref>). (E) Functional characteristics of 246 putative NB Notch target genes. GO categories are ranked by enrichment (&#x02265;2-fold enrichment, <italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.05; overlapping processes were grouped and the most enriched selected). (F) Examples of Notch-regulated genes in genomic regions spanning <italic>E(spl)-C</italic> (top) and <italic>dpn</italic> (bottom). Graphs depict Su(H)-bound regions (enrichment relative to input AvgM, scale log<sub>2</sub> 0-4) in N&#x00394;ecd brains (red) and in N&#x00394;ecd wing discs (green). Blue bars, conserved Su(H) binding motifs identified using Patser; bar height represents the Patser score, scale 5-9.79 (<xref rid="DEV126326C22" ref-type="bibr">Hertz and Stormo, 1999</xref>). Gene models are depicted in black.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="develop-143-126326-g1"/></fig></p><p>To distinguish which genes may be directly regulated by Notch activity, genomic regions occupied by Su(H) in hyperplastic brains were identified by ChIP. The 595 bound regions were significantly enriched for sequences matching the consensus Su(H) binding motif YGTGRGAA (<italic>P</italic>=4.11&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;43</sup>), strengthening the likelihood that they represent bona fide binding sites. Other enriched motifs included those for Tramtrack (Ttk), which is expressed in glial cells (<xref rid="DEV126326C4" ref-type="bibr">Badenhorst, 2001</xref>) and may thus repress the enhancers in those lineages, for bHLH repressor proteins (CRCGTG) and for the homeodomain protein Homothorax (Hth) (TGACA), which is discussed further below (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>D, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S1C</uri>).</p><p>Our criteria for direct Notch-regulated genes are that they should be both upregulated in the Notch-induced hyperplasia and associated with Su(H)-occupied regions. This implies that Su(H)-bound genes should be enriched among those that are upregulated by N&#x00394;ecd, which we confirmed by two approaches. First, gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) (<xref rid="DEV126326C43" ref-type="bibr">Mootha et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C57" ref-type="bibr">Subramanian et al., 2005</xref>) using a pre-ranked gene list from the expression analysis (3717 genes, FDR&#x02264;0.1) indicated a significant enrichment of Su(H)-bound genes among those with upregulated mRNAs (normalised enrichment score=1.68, <italic>P</italic>=0.037; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>B). Second, a comparison of the Su(H)-bound genes with gene lists generated from 10,000 randomly generated ChIP peak sets demonstrated that the former were preferentially enriched among the more highly upregulated genes [log<sub>2</sub> fold change (FC)&#x0003e;0.5; see Materials and Methods and <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Table&#x000a0;S3</uri>].</p><p>By intersecting the 1576 upregulated genes with those located within 20&#x02005;kb of Su(H) peaks, we identified a set of 246 candidates for direct Notch targets in the CNS stem cells, of which 185 had log<sub>2</sub> FC&#x0003e;0.5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>C, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Table&#x000a0;S2</uri>). These included <italic>E(spl)m</italic><italic>&#x003b3;-HLH</italic> and <italic>dpn</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>F), two genes previously associated with Notch regulation in larval NBs. Furthermore, the gene set was significantly enriched in NB-expressed genes (<italic>P</italic>=5.47&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup>), based on two different experiments in which NB transcription profiles were analysed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>C) (<xref rid="DEV126326C8" ref-type="bibr">Berger et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C54" ref-type="bibr">Southall et al., 2013</xref>). Conversely, the gene set was not enriched for genes expressed in sensory organ proneural clusters (<xref rid="DEV126326C46" ref-type="bibr">Reeves and Posakony, 2005</xref>), where Notch has an opposing function and is off in the neural precursor.</p><p>Functional characteristics of the 246 putative direct Notch targets were assessed using gene ontology (GO) and protein domain annotations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>E). Besides general development-related categories (&#x02018;post-embryonic organ morphogenesis&#x02019;, &#x02018;cell fate determination&#x02019;), enriched categories included &#x02018;regulation of transcription&#x02019; and &#x02018;DNA binding&#x02019;, along with three neurogenesis-related categories (&#x02018;neuron differentiation&#x02019;, &#x02018;sensory organ development&#x02019;, &#x02018;compound eye development&#x02019;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>E). Several targets in the transcription category have been implicated in NB maintenance [<italic>E(spl)m</italic><italic>&#x003b3;-HLH</italic>, <italic>dpn</italic>, <italic>klu</italic>, <italic>wor</italic>, <italic>grh</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C1" ref-type="bibr">Almeida and Bray, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C8" ref-type="bibr">Berger et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C17" ref-type="bibr">Cenci and Gould, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C48" ref-type="bibr">San-Ju&#x000e1;n and Baonza, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C51" ref-type="bibr">Song and Lu, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C62" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C64" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2012</xref>)] or in their temporal regulation [<italic>cas</italic>, <italic>svp</italic>, <italic>hth</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C39" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C41" ref-type="bibr">Maurange et al., 2008</xref>)].</p><p>Strikingly, Notch-regulated genes in NB hyperplasia were generally different from those in an epithelial hyperplasia caused by excessive Notch activity in wing imaginal discs (<xref rid="DEV126326C20" ref-type="bibr">Djiane et al., 2013</xref>). First, the overall functional characteristics differed: in NB hyperplasia the target genes were associated with cell fate commitment and transcription (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>E), whereas in epithelial hyperplasia they were enriched for signalling pathways and proliferation control (<xref rid="DEV126326C20" ref-type="bibr">Djiane et al., 2013</xref>). Second, only nine genes appeared to be directly Notch induced in both conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>C; <italic>P</italic>=0.028). Even when genes from a similar Su(H)-induced wing disc hyperplasia were added, the overlap only increased to 18 genes, although this is a significant enrichment demonstrating that the responses are related (<italic>P</italic>=1.091&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>). Besides <italic>E(spl)m</italic><italic>&#x003b3;-HLH</italic>, the overlap included <italic>dpn</italic> (also HES related) and <italic>M</italic><italic>yc</italic>. The latter is widely regulated by Notch in many contexts both in flies and mammals (<xref rid="DEV126326C20" ref-type="bibr">Djiane et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C32" ref-type="bibr">Klinakis et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C35" ref-type="bibr">Krejc&#x000ed; et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C59" ref-type="bibr">Weng et al., 2006</xref>). Finally, even for those genes that were regulated in both tissues, the Su(H) binding profiles differed (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>F). For example, in CNS, Su(H) was detected at a region 5&#x02032; of the <italic>dpn</italic> gene body, which overlapped with a previously identified NB enhancer (<xref rid="DEV126326C48" ref-type="bibr">San-Ju&#x000e1;n and Baonza, 2011</xref>), whereas in wing-discs it was predominantly bound at an intronic enhancer (<xref rid="DEV126326C3" ref-type="bibr">Babao&#x0011f;lan et al., 2013</xref>). These results demonstrate that Notch responses can differ extensively, even in circumstances when the eventual outcomes for the tissue are similar (i.e. tissue overgrowth).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Notch regulates genes linked to stem cell identity</title><p>Two previous studies have investigated gene networks involved in regulating NBs. One evaluated the enrichment of RNAs in NBs compared with neurons in the larval CNS and then proposed a regulatory network of TFs (<xref rid="DEV126326C8" ref-type="bibr">Berger et al., 2012</xref>). This TF network is significantly represented amongst our CNS direct Notch targets (<italic>P</italic>=7.278&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;17</sup>; <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S1B</uri>). Indeed, our results confirm Notch regulation of a core network of these genes. The second used the binding profile of the proneural protein Ase to identify genes involved in NB programming in the embryo (<xref rid="DEV126326C53" ref-type="bibr">Southall and Brand, 2009</xref>). Again, the Notch target genes were highly enriched in these Ase-bound genes: 69/246 were identified targets of Ase (<italic>P</italic>=4.75&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;16</sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>A). This subset of Notch targets was also enriched in genes bound by two other TFs involved in regulating NB lineages, namely Dpn and Pros (<italic>P</italic>=7.794&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;26</sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>A) (<xref rid="DEV126326C53" ref-type="bibr">Southall and Brand, 2009</xref>). By contrast, the 177 genes that were not Ase targets showed less overlap with Dpn/Pros regulation (<italic>P</italic>=0.005; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>A). Nevertheless, both Ase<sup>+</sup> and Ase<sup>&#x02212;</sup> subsets were similarly enriched in NB-expressed genes, suggesting that the latter are also important in NBs.
<fig id="DEV126326F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p><bold>Notch regulates the NB stem cell network as well as temporal genes.</bold> (A) A significant proportion of Notch NB targets overlap with Ase-regulated genes (black; <italic>P</italic>=4.747&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;16</sup>). This subset is enriched in Dpn (light green), Dpn and Pros (dark green), and Pros (mid-green) regulated genes (<italic>P</italic>=7.794&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;26</sup>) compared with the Ase<sup>&#x02212;</sup> subset (<italic>P</italic>=0.005). Both subsets show similar enrichments for NB-expressed genes (data not shown). (B) Examples of NB-specific genes upregulated in Notch-induced hyperplasia and associated with Su(H) peaks; log<sub>2</sub> FC relative to controls. All are in the Ase<sup>+</sup> subset of NB targets. (C) Grh and Mira are upregulated by ectopic Notch activity. Expression of Grh (top row; red, white) and Mira (bottom row; red, white) in WT (control) and N&#x00394;ecd-expressing NBs, marked by CD8-GFP (green). In this and subsequent figures Dpn or Ase marks NBs as indicated (Ase also labels GMCs). (D) Sensitivity of Grh and Mira expression to disruption of the Notch pathway. Grh (left panels; red, white) or Mira (right panels; red, white) expression in GFP-marked clones mutant for <italic>Dl<sup>rev10</sup> Ser<sup>RX106</sup></italic> (top two rows; green) or WT (bottom row; green). Yellow arrows indicate NBs from mutant Type I lineages; yellow outlines mark mutant or control Type II lineages. Insets are Dpn only, to show INP numbers in mutant lineages. Type II lineages were scored as having altered expression if levels in NBs or INPs were reduced and/or if fewer Dpn<sup>+</sup> INPs expressed the gene of interest. (E) Temporal genes included among the Notch targets; log<sub>2</sub> FC relative to controls. (F) Sporadic upregulation of Hth, Svp and Cas (red or white as indicated) in NBs expressing N&#x00394;ecd (right panels; marked by CD8-GFP, green) compared with controls (left panels; CD8-GFP, green). Only Hth is detectable in some control NBs, where levels are low. With N&#x00394;ecd expression, Hth is present at high levels in all supernumerary NB-like cells; Svp and Cas are expressed <italic>de novo</italic> in ectopic NB-like cells. (G) Disruption of Notch activity (<italic>Dl<sup>rev10</sup> Ser<sup>RX106</sup></italic>) does not perturb Hth or Cas expression in Type I (yellow arrows) or Type II lineages (yellow outline). GFP-marked clones (green) are stained for Cas or Hth (red or white). Insets are Dpn only, to show INP numbers in mutant lineages. Scale bars: 50&#x02005;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="develop-143-126326-g2"/></fig></p><p>Altogether, these comparisons reveal that a significant proportion of the Notch targets have been implicated in regulatory networks coordinating the NB stem cell programme (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>B). We therefore sought to verify their response to Notch signalling by testing whether expression from a subset (<italic>grh</italic>, <italic>wor</italic>, <italic>mira</italic>, <italic>numb</italic>) was modified when NBs were subjected to a pulse of N&#x00394;ecd for 24&#x02005;h. All four genes were expressed in overproliferating NB-like cells generated under these conditions (<italic>grh</italic>, <italic>mira</italic>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>C; <italic>wor</italic>, <italic>n</italic><italic>umb</italic>, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S2A</uri>). Indeed, Mira levels were significantly higher in the N&#x00394;ecd lineages (<uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S2C,D</uri>), although we note that, in general, the major effect is one of more cells expressing these genes rather than a large increase in expression levels per cell. Nevertheless, there is widespread expression of the stem cell genes in response to ectopic Notch activity <italic>in vivo</italic>, in agreement with the expression array results.</p><p>To test whether stem cell network genes are sensitive to reduced Notch function, we generated marked clones of cells mutant for <italic>Dl</italic>, <italic>Ser</italic> [which compromises Notch activity in NBs (<xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>)] or for <italic>mastermind</italic> (<italic>mam</italic>) (to prevent the transcriptional activation of targets). Such manipulations led to significantly altered expression of <italic>mira</italic> (100% of lineages, <italic>n</italic>=8; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>D), <italic>grh</italic> (85.72% of lineages, <italic>n</italic>=7; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>D), <italic>wor</italic> (60% of lineages, <italic>n</italic>=5) and <italic>numb</italic> (100% of lineages, <italic>n</italic>=7) in Type II lineages (<uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S2B, Table&#x000a0;S4</uri>). The effects in Type I lineages were more subtle, as <italic>mira</italic> was the only gene that was significantly reduced in expression (16.2% of lineages, <italic>n</italic>=99; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>D, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Table&#x000a0;S4</uri>), although the levels of Numb and Wor were also reduced in some clones. Altogether, these data are consistent with these genes being under Notch regulation in some NB lineages. The fact that their expression is not abolished upon Notch loss of function in Type I NBs might be the consequence of additional, compensatory regulatory inputs, as has been shown for <italic>dpn</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C48" ref-type="bibr">San-Ju&#x000e1;n and Baonza, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>), or of Type I NBs being more resilient to reductions in Notch activity (<xref rid="DEV126326C13" ref-type="bibr">Bowman et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C58" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Notch regulates the expression of TFs implicated in temporal programming</title><p>In addition to genes implicated in NB identity, which are expressed consistently and specifically in NBs, Notch targets also included genes with more dynamic NB expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>E). Several of these are involved in temporal programming of NBs and their progeny (<xref rid="DEV126326C41" ref-type="bibr">Maurange et al., 2008</xref>). In particular, <italic>svp</italic> and <italic>cas</italic> are expressed in NBs at mid-larval stages and regulate a change in the size and identity of the neurons produced, as well as determining the time that NBs will undergo cell cycle exit or Reaper/Hid/Grim-dependent apoptosis (<xref rid="DEV126326C41" ref-type="bibr">Maurange et al., 2008</xref>). <italic>hth</italic> has a similar role in programming optic lobe NBs (<xref rid="DEV126326C39" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>) and exhibits dynamic expression in central brain NBs (data not shown), although its function there is not known. The fact that such genes have increased expression in Notch-induced NB tumours suggests a disruption to the temporal programme such that early expressed genes are transcribed at later times.</p><p>To substantiate the expression array results we compared the expression of <italic>svp</italic>, <italic>cas</italic> and <italic>hth</italic> in WT CNS with that in which N&#x00394;ecd was induced for 24&#x02005;h. No expression of Cas or Svp was detected in NBs in late WT CNS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>F, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S3A</uri>); their expression was entirely complementary to that of Dpn, suggesting that they were predominantly neuronal. Expression of Hth was more complex, with variable levels in NBs as well as in GMCs and in neuronal progeny (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>F). In the presence of N&#x00394;ecd, all three proteins were detected in the ectopic NB-like cells. Many Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells expressed Svp and Cas and they exhibited greatly enhanced Hth levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>F, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S3A,B</uri>). Thus, unexpectedly, sustained Notch activity results in ectopic expression of temporal genes in late stage NBs.</p><p>By contrast, reductions in Notch function had relatively little impact on <italic>cas</italic>, <italic>hth</italic> or <italic>svp</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>G). In Type I lineages mutant for <italic>Dl Ser</italic>, Cas and Svp were still present, both at L3 in neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>G, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Table&#x000a0;S4</uri>) and at earlier stages when these proteins are normally expressed in NBs (L2, 30-50&#x02005;h after larval hatching; <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S3C</uri>). In <italic>Dl Ser</italic> mutant Type II lineages Hth and Svp were absent, suggesting that their expression might be dependent on Notch in these NBs. Thus, similar to the NB-specific genes, temporal programming genes are responsive to Notch overactivation but are largely resistant to Notch downregulation, except in Type II NBs, suggesting that compensatory mechanisms might be involved in regulating their NB expression.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Su(H)-bound regions identify NB enhancers</title><p>If Notch coordinates the expression of stem cell and temporal programming genes, the regions occupied by Su(H) should correspond to Notch-regulated enhancers that direct expression in NBs. To test this, we first measured the activity of fragments encompassing the Su(H)-bound regions in <italic>grh</italic>, <italic>wor</italic> and <italic>mira</italic> using luciferase reporter assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>A,B). All three enhancers were upregulated by Nicd, and the responses of <italic>grh</italic> and <italic>wor</italic> were compromised when sequences corresponding to Su(H) recognition motifs were mutated, consistent with these being direct Notch-regulated enhancers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>B). Subsequently, we focused on <italic>grh</italic>, where Su(H) binding was detected in an intronic region that was adjacent to, but not overlapping, a previously identified NB enhancer (<xref rid="DEV126326C45" ref-type="bibr">Prokop et al., 1998</xref>). When placed upstream of a <italic>lacZ</italic> reporter, this fragment (<italic>grh[NRE]</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>A) was sufficient to direct expression in NBs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>C,E). We therefore tested whether the enhancer was responsive to Notch signalling. First, expression of <italic>grh[NRE]-lacZ</italic> was detected in the ectopic NB-like cells in the presence of N&#x00394;ecd (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>C). Its expression was also elevated within N&#x00394;ecd NB-like cells as compared with neighbouring WT NBs in the dorsal brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>D). Second, <italic>grh[NRE]-lacZ</italic> expression was significantly reduced in NB lineages in which Notch signalling was compromised by mutations in <italic>Dl</italic> and <italic>Ser</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>E,G). Thus, the Su(H)-bound region within <italic>grh</italic> corresponds to an enhancer that specifically directs expression in NBs and that is responsive to Notch signalling, supporting the proposal that <italic>grh</italic> has a direct input from Notch activity.
<fig id="DEV126326F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p><bold>Su(H)-bound regions identify NB enhancers.</bold> (A) Genomic region spanning <italic>grh</italic>, <italic>svp</italic> and <italic>cas</italic> with graphs depicting Su(H)-bound regions (enrichment relative to input, AvgM, scale log<sub>2</sub> 0-4) in N&#x00394;ecd brains (red) and in N&#x00394;ecd wing discs (green). Grey bars indicate regions tested for enhancer activity, and the purple bar indicates a previously identified <italic>grh</italic> NB enhancer. Details as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>F. (B) Su(H)-bound regions from <italic>grh</italic>, <italic>wor</italic> and <italic>mira</italic> respond to Nicd in transient transfection assays. Fold change in expression from WT enhancers was significantly different from those with Su(H) binding motifs mutated. *<italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.001, <italic>t</italic>-test. Average of three biological replicates; error bars indicate s.e.m. (C) Su(H)-bound region from <italic>grh</italic>, <italic>cas</italic> and <italic>svp</italic> direct NB-specific expression and respond to ectopic Notch activity. Expression from the indicated enhancers (red, white) in WT and N&#x00394;ecd-expressing brain regions. Pros (blue) marks GMCs and neurons, and Mira (blue) marks NBs. (D) Intensity of expression from <italic>grh[NRE]</italic> in control and N&#x00394;ecd-expressing dorsal brain NBs (20 NBs per brain lobe, five brains) was significantly different (*<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, <italic>t</italic>-test). Box represents the interquartile range (IQR), orange/grey interface indicates median and whiskers indicate &#x000b1;1.5&#x000d7;IQR. (E) <italic>grh[NRE]</italic> is sensitive to reduced Notch signalling. <italic>grh[NRE]-lacZ</italic> (red, white) in WT (green, left) or <italic>Dl<sup>rev10</sup> Ser<sup>RX106</sup></italic> (green, right). Yellow arrows indicate NBs from GFP-marked WT or mutant Type I and Type II lineages. (F) Enhancers from <italic>cas</italic> show differing sensitivity to reduced Notch signalling. Expression from the indicated enhancers (red, white) in WT (green, left) or <italic>Dl<sup>rev10</sup> Ser<sup>RX106</sup></italic> (green, right) clones. Yellow arrows indicate NBs from clonally marked WT or mutant Type I and Type II lineages. (G) Percentages of Type I NBs with high (blue), medium (orange) or low/no (grey) levels of expression of the indicated reporters in control versus <italic>Dl<sup>rev10</sup> Ser<sup>RX106</sup></italic> lineages. Scale bars: 50&#x02005;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="develop-143-126326-g3"/></fig></p><p>A similar strategy was taken with the temporal factors <italic>svp</italic> and <italic>cas</italic>. Of three fragments bound by Su(H) in the vicinity of <italic>cas</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>A), two directed expression in NBs. <italic>cas-prox[NRE]</italic> generated high levels of <italic>lacZ</italic> expression in NBs, even at late larval stages, whereas <italic>cas-med[NRE]</italic> yielded lower levels of expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>C). The third region overlaps a previously defined NB enhancer (<xref rid="DEV126326C36" ref-type="bibr">Kuzin et al., 2012</xref>), although it was inactive in our assays. Similarly, the <italic>svp[NRE]</italic> fragment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>A) generated high levels of <italic>lacZ</italic> expression in a subset of NBs and lower levels in others (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>C). Thus, as with <italic>grh</italic>, the Su(H)-bound regions correspond to NB enhancers. Notably, however, these were still active in late NBs, a developmental stage when the corresponding genes would be shut off. This suggests either that these enhancers lack sequences necessary for their inactivation at later stages or that there is an enhancer handover mechanism (<xref rid="DEV126326C12" ref-type="bibr">Boukhatmi et al., 2012</xref>), with a distinct region involved in mediating the repression at late stages.</p><p>The <italic>svp</italic> and <italic>cas</italic> enhancers all responded positively to ectopic Notch activity. Thus, the ectopic NB-like cells exhibited robust expression from <italic>cas-prox[NRE]</italic>, <italic>cas-med[NRE]</italic> and <italic>svp[NRE]</italic> in the presence of N&#x00394;ecd (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>C). Conversely, many NBs had reduced levels of <italic>cas-med[NRE]</italic> and <italic>svp[NRE]</italic> when Notch activity was compromised, although the effects on <italic>cas-med[NRE]</italic> were subtle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>F,G). By contrast, a high proportion of NBs retained high levels of <italic>cas-prox[NRE]</italic> expression in <italic>Dl Ser</italic> mutant lineages. Nevertheless, both <italic>cas</italic> and <italic>svp</italic> are associated with at least one enhancer that exhibits a consistent response to Notch activity, in agreement with these genes having direct regulatory input. In addition, Su(H)-bound regions for eight other genes were similarly tested <italic>in vivo</italic>, of which seven yielded NB expression (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Role of stem cell identity genes in Notch-induced NB hyperplasia</title><p>Possible roles for Notch-regulated NB-expressed genes might be to inhibit pro-differentiation factors and/or to maintain the self-renewal characteristics of NBs. One candidate for the former is <italic>mira</italic>, which encodes a protein required to retain key factors at the cytoplasmic cortex of NBs. In Type I NBs these include Pros, a transcriptional regulator of proliferation/differentiation, which can drive proliferating larval NBs into quiescence (<xref rid="DEV126326C37" ref-type="bibr">Lai and Doe, 2014</xref>). By upregulating the expression of <italic>mira</italic>, Notch activity could favour the sequestration of Pros and so promote self-renewal. To test whether Mira is important for Notch-induced hyperplasia, we analysed the consequences of Mira depletion (by RNAi) in the background of Nicd overexpression (via <italic>inscGal4;UAS-Nicd</italic>, a combination that induces weaker hyperplasia than the N&#x00394;ecd used in earlier experiments; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F4">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>A). Under these conditions, Pros was detectable in the nuclei of NBs, consistent with perturbation of Mira function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F4">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>A). However, there was no reduction in hyperplasia; instead, the extent of hyperplasia was exacerbated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F4">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>A,B, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S4</uri>). Thus, the hyperplasia cannot be explained by Mira-mediated sequestration of factors such as Pros.
<fig id="DEV126326F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p><bold>Moderate consequences of removal of NB target genes on Notch-induced overproliferation.</bold> (A) Depletion of Mira leads to Pros accumulation in NBs. Distribution of Pros (blue, white) in VNC NB lineages expressing control RNAi (controlRi) or <italic>mira</italic> RNAi (miraRi) with and without Nicd. Arrowheads mark NBs where Pros is detected in the nucleus. (B) Depletion of Mira exacerbates overproliferation. Number of Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells in dorsal brains (db) and VNC (vc) of the genotypes indicated. Box represents IQR, orange/grey interface indicates median and whiskers indicate &#x000b1;1.5&#x000d7;IQR. *<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 versus equivalent control (<italic>t</italic>-test). (C) Hyperplasia induced by Nicd in lineages lacking <italic>grh</italic> function. MARCM clones (green) overexpressing Nicd in WT and in <italic>grh[B37]</italic>, showing examples from Type I and Type II lineages. (Bottom row) Single channel showing Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells; yellow arrows indicate NBs from marked clones, and yellow lines outline labelled lineages in some panels. (D) Percentage of Type I and Type II lineages exhibiting hyperplasia in the indicated genotypes. Hyperplasia is defined as &#x0003e;2 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells in Type I lineages and &#x0003e;28 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells in Type II lineages. (E) Number of Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells present in overproliferating lineages (scored as in D) of the genotypes indicated. Box represents the IQR, orange/grey interface indicates median and whiskers indicate &#x000b1;1.5&#x000d7;IQR. The reduced proliferation was only significant for lola[5D2]. Scale bars: 50&#x02005;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="develop-143-126326-g4"/></fig></p><p>We then tested whether hyperplasia is reduced when the NB-specific TFs are depleted, since previous studies showed that deletion of <italic>E(spl)m8-HLH</italic> from <italic>N&#x00394;ecd</italic>-overexpressing clones drastically reduces overproliferation (<xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F5">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>A). However, little rescue of the overproliferation occurred in Type I lineages when <italic>grh</italic> or <italic>dpn</italic> were mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F4">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>C-E, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Table&#x000a0;S5</uri>), nor when <italic>wor</italic> was depleted (<uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S5B</uri>). The number and extent of overproliferating Nicd-expressing lineages that were mutant for <italic>dpn</italic> (28.2% of lineages, median of 2 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, <italic>n</italic>=234) or <italic>grh</italic> (16.6% of lineages, median of 3 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, <italic>n</italic>=229) was similar to Nicd alone (13% of lineages, median of 3 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, <italic>n</italic>=355).
<fig id="DEV126326F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p><bold>Removal of temporal genes suppresses Notch-induced overproliferation.</bold> (A) Hyperproliferation induced by N&#x00394;ecd is suppressed in lineages lacking <italic>svp</italic> or <italic>hth</italic> function. Effects of <italic>hth<sup>C1</sup></italic>, <italic>svp</italic><sup>e22</sup> and <italic>E(spl)<sup>b32.2</sup></italic> on WT or N&#x00394;ecd-expressing NB clones (green, MARCM; yellow lines in single-channel images outline marked lineages); examples are from Type II lineages. (B) Proportion of Type I and Type II lineages exhibiting hyperplasia in the indicated genotypes. (C) Number of Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells in overproliferating lineages of the genotypes indicated. Box represents IQR, orange/grey interface indicates median and whiskers indicate &#x000b1;1.5&#x000d7;IQR. *<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01, **<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 versus N&#x00394;ecd alone (Wilcoxon rank-sum test). Scale bars: 50&#x02005;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="develop-143-126326-g5"/></fig></p><p>We also tested the effects of eliminating the widely expressed TF Lola, since several of its isoforms were upregulated by N&#x00394;ecd. A strong hypomorphic mutation affecting all <italic>lola</italic> isoforms (<italic>lola<sup>5D2</sup></italic>) had little impact on Type I lineage overproliferation (8.4% of lineages overproliferating, median of 6 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, <italic>n</italic>=143). By contrast, the phenotypes in Type II lineages were partially suppressed by mutations affecting these genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F4">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>C-E, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Table&#x000a0;S5</uri>). For example, loss of <italic>grh</italic> decreased the Nicd-induced overproliferation phenotype from 158 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells per Type II lineage (<italic>n</italic>=21) to 114 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells per lineage (<italic>n</italic>=15), and <italic>lola<sup>5D2</sup></italic> significantly rescued the Nicd phenotype (33 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, <italic>n</italic>=8; WT lineages have 27 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells). A <italic>dpn</italic> allele also decreased overproliferation of Type II NBs, as observed previously (<xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>), yielding a median of 84 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells (<italic>n</italic>=7), but as there was considerable variability the effect was not statistically significant in these experiments.</p><p>Mutations in the NB-specific genes might not alter Notch-induced hyperplasia if they have overlapping functions in stem cell renewal, as previously shown for <italic>dpn</italic> and <italic>E(spl)-C</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>). We therefore examined whether removal of &#x02018;stemness&#x02019; regulators, alone or in pairs, results in any defects in a normal background. We generated NB lineages that were double mutant for different combinations of TFs [<italic>grh E(spl)-C</italic>, <italic>wor E(spl)-C</italic>, <italic>grh dpn</italic>, <italic>wor dpn</italic> and <italic>grh wor</italic>] and measured changes in the number of progeny for both Type I and Type II NBs. Of those tested, only <italic>grh wor</italic> double-mutant lineages showed significant differences in the number of INPs and GMCs compared with either single mutant alone (<uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S5</uri>). In addition, the <italic>grh wor</italic> Type I NBs had smaller nuclei (<uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S5</uri>). Thus, these two NB-specific TFs have overlapping roles in maintaining NB size and proliferative rate. This suggests a robustness in the transcriptional network regulating stem cell characteristics, which might explain why removal of a single factor is insufficient to fully suppress Notch-induced hyperplasia.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Role of temporal genes in Notch-induced hyperplasia</title><p>To decipher whether persistent expression of the temporal programming factors <italic>svp</italic>, <italic>cas</italic> and <italic>hth</italic> is important for NB hyperplasia, we used mutations to compromise their function while at the same time expressing N&#x00394;ecd. Results showed that the hyperplasia in Type II lineages was highly susceptible to depletion of these TFs. Thus, the N&#x00394;ecd-induced hyperplasia in Type II lineages (median of 135 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells/lineage, <italic>n</italic>=13) was rescued by removing either of the temporal genes <italic>svp</italic> or <italic>hth</italic> as well as by removing <italic>E(spl)-C</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F5">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>A-C, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Table&#x000a0;S5</uri>). The effects of removing <italic>svp</italic> were most dramatic: none of the lineages showed residual overproliferation and most lineages even had fewer Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells (median 13 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, <italic>n</italic>=8; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F5">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>C) than WT (median 28 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells). One way to reconcile this highly penetrant phenotype with the observation that only a subset of NB-like cells exhibit Svp expression is that the immunofluorescence only gives a snapshot of the expression at any given moment; many more NB-like cells might switch <italic>svp</italic> on at some stage to prompt the overproliferation. Alternatively, as we were only able to recover a relatively small number of clones of this genotype, it is possible that the phenotypic effects are overestimated. Eliminating <italic>hth</italic> in lineages expressing N&#x00394;ecd also ameliorated the hyperplasia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F5">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>B,C), with the median number of Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells reduced by both <italic>hth<sup>B2</sup></italic> (64.5 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, <italic>n</italic>=8) and <italic>hth<sup>C1</sup></italic> (58 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, <italic>n</italic>=19). Finally, mutations affecting <italic>cas</italic> also resulted in decreased numbers of Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells per Type II lineage (89 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, <italic>n</italic>=25; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F5">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>C) although, because of the high variability, the effects were not statistically significant.</p><p>The effects on Type I lineages were less pronounced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F5">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>B,C, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig.&#x000a0;S6</uri>). In these lineages, which were scored as hyperplastic when they contained two or more Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, the overexpression of <italic>N&#x00394;ecd</italic> caused hyperplasia in 61.6% of lineages (<italic>n</italic>=86), with a median of 13 Dpn<sup>+</sup> NB-like cells (which were usually intermediate in size between a normal NB and a GMC). Of the genes tested, only mutations in <italic>svp</italic> significantly rescued the Type I hyperplasia, although to a smaller extent than removing <italic>E(spl)-C</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F5">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>B,C). Specifically, only 13.5% of <italic>svp</italic> lineages (<italic>n</italic>=654) remained overgrown, with a median of 2 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, although there was considerable variability. In addition, in a few lineages (1.7%) the NBs appeared to have undergone apoptosis. By contrast, mutations in <italic>cas</italic> or <italic>hth</italic> failed to significantly alter Type I NB hyperplasia; 47% <italic>cas</italic> (<italic>n</italic>=228), 40.8% <italic>hth<sup>C1</sup></italic> (<italic>n</italic>=94) and 58.5% <italic>hth<sup>B12</sup></italic> (<italic>n</italic>=174) lineages exhibited hyperplasia, with medians of 12, 14 and 11 Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Expression of <italic>wor</italic> and of temporal genes is sufficient to induce mild hyperplasia</title><p>From the loss-of-function experiments it appears that several Notch-regulated genes contribute to the hyperplasia. To investigate whether any of these targets is sufficient to induce excess NBs, we assessed the consequences of their overexpression in larval lineages by scoring the numbers of Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>). We note that in some cases [<italic>grh</italic>, <italic>E(spl)m&#x003b3;-HLH</italic>, <italic>wor</italic>] these manipulations would augment existing expression levels, whereas for <italic>svp</italic> they would result in ectopic expression.
<fig id="DEV126326F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p><bold>Expression of <italic>wor</italic> or of temporal genes is sufficient to induce mild hyperplasia.</bold> (A) <italic>wor</italic> expression (via <italic>inscGal4</italic>) induces hyperplasia in all regions (dorsal brain, top two rows; VNC, bottom two rows). Ase (green), Dpn (red or white). (B) Phenotypes from expression of <italic>wor</italic> or <italic>cas</italic> compared with control (<italic>UAS-lacZ</italic>). Total numbers of Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells were scored in dorsal brain and VNC. **<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 versus equivalent control (<italic>t</italic>-test). Similar results were obtained in ventral brains (data not shown). (C) Dorsal brain from the indicated genotypes, where transgenes were ectopically expressed via <italic>inscGal4</italic>. Anterior is inferior, lateral is leftwards; Ase, green; Dpn, red or white; Pros, blue. E(spl)m&#x003b3;-HLH leads to a large increase in Dpn<sup>+</sup> Ase<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells; Svp or En-Hth leads to an increase in the number of Dpn<sup>+</sup> Ase<sup>+</sup> cells. (D) Number of Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells in dorsal brains overexpressing the proteins indicated, with &#x003b2;-galactosidase as control (con). *<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 versus equivalent control (<italic>t</italic>-test). (E) Summary of the Notch response in NBs. (F) Diagram illustrating the phenotypes (imINP, immature INP; mINP, mature INP) in Type II NB lineages caused by Notch and how these are influenced by manipulating the identified Notch targets (summarised in <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Table&#x000a0;S5</uri>). Scale bars: 50&#x02005;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="develop-143-126326-g6"/></fig></p><p>Two of the three NB-specific genes tested resulted in significant hyperplasia. Notably, expression of <italic>wor</italic> was sufficient to promote an increase in NB-like cells both in the dorso-posterior brain, where Type II lineages reside, and in the ventral nerve cord (VNC), where Type I lineages occur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>A,B). As previously shown, overexpression of <italic>E(spl)m&#x003b3;-HLH</italic> also caused hyperplasia, primarily in the dorso-posterior brain, where it generated regions of contiguous Dpn<sup>+</sup> Ase<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells. Their size was intermediate between an INP and an NB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>C) and they most likely arose from Type II lineages. By contrast, <italic>grh</italic> overexpression failed to cause any increase in NB numbers, even in these more susceptible Type II lineages (data not shown).</p><p>Whereas expression of Cas had no effect on NB lineages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>B, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig. S7A</uri>), overexpression of Svp did elicit supernumerary Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells in Type II lineages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>C,D, <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">Fig. S7B</uri>). These were Ase<sup>+</sup> and generally smaller than NBs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>C). Excess Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells were also produced following expression of a chimeric Hth, in which Hth is fused to the Engrailed (En) repressor domain to create a constitutive Hth repressor. These excess Dpn<sup>+</sup> cells were Ase<sup>+</sup> and were similar to, or smaller than, mature INPs. In addition, some hyperplasia was present in Type I NB lineages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DEV126326F6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>C,D). As Hth has been reported to have both activator and repressor functions (<xref rid="DEV126326C27" ref-type="bibr">Inbal et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C61" ref-type="bibr">Wernet and Desplan, 2014</xref>), we cannot predict whether En-Hth would act as a positive or a dominant-negative factor in the conditions tested. Regardless of the mechanisms involved, altered activity of Svp and Hth is nevertheless sufficient to induce a modest level of hyperplasia, especially in Type II lineages.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Notch activity is sustained in post-embryonic NBs throughout their lifetime and, when activated inappropriately, is sufficient to confer NB-like properties on the progeny. Our analysis of the genes regulated by Notch under these circumstances reveals that it is likely to achieve its functions through multi-pronged regulation of the stem cell programme. Of the 246 putative direct Notch target genes that we identified in hyperplastic CNS, the majority (&#x0003e;55%) are enriched in the NB transcriptome and 28% are assigned to the NB network regulated by Ase. Many of these encode TFs that have been implicated in stem cell regulation, such as <italic>grh</italic>, <italic>klu</italic>, <italic>wor</italic>, <italic>dpn</italic> and <italic>E(spl)m&#x003b3;-HLH</italic>, and others encode proteins involved in regulating asymmetric stem cell divisions, including <italic>mira</italic> and <italic>numb</italic>. An unexpected constituent of the Notch-upregulated genes were those implicated in the temporal programming of NBs, represented by <italic>svp</italic>, <italic>cas</italic> and <italic>hth</italic>. Such genes are thought to confer stage-specific NB characteristics and determine the ultimate timing of their cell cycle exit. For example, in larval NBs, <italic>svp</italic> and <italic>cas</italic> are expressed early in L2 and, if absent, a switch in neuronal identities fails to occur and the NBs fail to cease proliferating appropriately (<xref rid="DEV126326C41" ref-type="bibr">Maurange et al., 2008</xref>). Similarly, <italic>hth</italic> has been implicated in the temporal cascade of optic lobe larval NBs (<xref rid="DEV126326C39" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>). By promoting the re-expression or extended expression of factors that are normally present transiently, Notch activity is likely to change the NB developmental clock. Sustained expression of such factors may perturb the ability of NBs to exit the cell cycle correctly. This would imply that persistent expression of such factors has similarly disruptive consequences to their total removal (<xref rid="DEV126326C41" ref-type="bibr">Maurange et al., 2008</xref>). As Notch-regulated enhancers were enriched in target motifs for both E(spl)m&#x003b3;-HLH and Hth, feed-forward regulatory loops might also be important in the regulation of NB maintenance and progression by Notch, although the mechanisms remain to be deciphered.</p><p>With the exception of <italic>mira</italic>, all of the Notch targets tested were found to contribute to Notch-induced hyperplasia. Type II NB hyperplasia was more sensitive to the attenuation of target genes, with all mutations reducing the overgrowth to a greater or lesser extent, whereas Type I NB hyperplasia was only ameliorated by <italic>E(spl)-C</italic> and <italic>svp</italic>. Furthermore, a subset, notably <italic>wor</italic>, <italic>svp</italic>, <italic>hth</italic>, <italic>dpn</italic>, <italic>E(spl)m&#x003b3;-HLH</italic> and <italic>klu</italic>, were themselves sufficient to drive mild hyperplasia, especially in Type II lineages (see also <xref rid="DEV126326C8" ref-type="bibr">Berger et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C48" ref-type="bibr">San-Ju&#x000e1;n and Baonza, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C62" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>). Thus, both stemness and temporal TFs cooperate to sustain Notch-induced hyperplasia. Furthermore, although individual factors each make some unique contribution to NB maintenance, several [E(spl)m&#x003b3;-HLH and Dpn, Grh and Wor] appear to have overlapping functions, which confers robustness on the regulatory network.</p><p>The regions bound by Su(H) identified NB enhancers, in agreement with the nearby genes being targets of Notch in NBs. However, an unexpected feature was that the NB expression of these genes did not appear to be strictly dependent on Notch activity. This might in part be explained by the regulated genes having multiple NB enhancers; for example, at least two further NB-specific enhancers have been identified for <italic>grh</italic>, besides <italic>grh[NRE]</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C15" ref-type="bibr">Brody et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C45" ref-type="bibr">Prokop et al., 1998</xref>). However, this cannot fully account for the lack of Notch dependency. Even when we focused on individual enhancers, loss of Notch signalling did not always eliminate their expression, although in most cases it did reduce it, as observed previously for <italic>E(spl)m8-HLH</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>). The only target gene tested that is fully dependent on Notch for expression in NBs, being undetectable upon Notch loss of function, is <italic>E(spl)m&#x003b3;-HLH</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C1" ref-type="bibr">Almeida and Bray, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C63" ref-type="bibr">Zacharioudaki et al., 2012</xref>). It thus appears that in NBs many of the Notch targets respond to additional transcriptional cues that can partially compensate for the absence of Notch. It will be interesting to determine whether this is also true for the majority of Notch target enhancers in other tissues.</p><p>Persistent Notch activity in several other tissues also causes extreme hyperplasia. Surprisingly, however, only 18 of the genes upregulated in the NB hyperplasia are also targeted in an epithelial hyperplasia caused by ectopic activity of Notch in wing discs. These include HES/<italic>E(spl)</italic> genes, which respond robustly to Notch signalling in most cellular contexts, and the growth regulator <italic>M</italic><italic>yc</italic>, which is also a common target even in human pathologies, such as T-ALL (<xref rid="DEV126326C32" ref-type="bibr">Klinakis et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C59" ref-type="bibr">Weng et al., 2006</xref>). Thus, the mechanisms through which Notch induces hyperplasia differ in the two contexts. It is possible that this relates to the fact that the hyperplasia originates from a stem cell lineage in one case and an epithelium in the other. Indeed, comparisons between the genes regulated in the epithelial model and those regulated by Notch1 in a breast cancer cell line revealed a surprising extent of overlap (<xref rid="DEV126326C20" ref-type="bibr">Djiane et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="DEV126326C42" ref-type="bibr">Mazzone et al., 2010</xref>). It will therefore be important in future to make comparisons with different stem cell-related hyperplasias in mammals, to ask whether the Notch-regulated genes exhibit similar characteristics to those observed for NBs. Such comparisons will help to ascertain whether there are indeed common themes in the transcriptional outputs from Notch activation that reflect the different cellular contexts.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s4a"><title><italic>Drosophila</italic> genetics</title><p><italic>Drosophila</italic> stocks are described in FlyBase and were obtained from the Bloomington Stock Center unless otherwise indicated. Overproliferating third instar larval CNS was generated by crossing <italic>tubGal80ts; UASN&#x00394;ecd</italic> flies with <italic>UASCD8GFP; grhNB-Gal4</italic> flies to drive expression in most NBs (<xref rid="DEV126326C45" ref-type="bibr">Prokop et al., 1998</xref>). Crosses were kept at 18&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02005;days, then transferred to 30&#x000b0;C for 24&#x02005;h prior to dissection.</p><p>Stocks for generating Notch loss of function, loss-of-function mutants coupled with hyperactivation of Notch, and double-mutant combinations are detailed in the <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">supplementary Materials and Methods</uri> and were crossed to appropriate <italic>FRT aTub-Gal80</italic> counter-chromosomes combined with <italic>hs-FLP</italic>, <italic>aTub-Gal4</italic>, <italic>UAS-GFP</italic> for generating clones. WT <italic>FRT</italic> chromosomes (e.g. <italic>FRT82B &#x003c0;Myc</italic> or <italic>FRTG13</italic>) were used for control clones. Progeny underwent heatshock for 1&#x02005;h at 37&#x000b0;C at &#x0223c;72&#x02005;h after egg lay (AEL). For experiments involving RNAi, progeny were transferred to 30&#x000b0;C for 72&#x02005;h prior to dissection (to enhance RNAi activity). Phenotypes were analysed at late L3 (&#x0223c;110-120&#x02005;h AEL).</p><p>For overexpression of genes in NBs, the UAS-lines <italic>U</italic><italic>AS-lacZ</italic> (control), <italic>UAS-E(spl)m&#x003b3;</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C40" ref-type="bibr">Ligoxygakis et al., 1998</xref>), <italic>UAS-svp</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C31" ref-type="bibr">Kerber et al., 1998</xref>), <italic>UAS-EN::Hth</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C27" ref-type="bibr">Inbal et al., 2001</xref>), <italic>UAS-Wor</italic> (<xref rid="DEV126326C8" ref-type="bibr">Berger et al., 2012</xref>) were crossed to <italic>inscGal4; tubGal80ts</italic> and the progeny were transferred to 30&#x000b0;C for 72&#x02005;h prior to dissection.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Expression arrays and genome-wide ChIP</title><p>For each expression array, RNA was isolated from the CNS of 300 flies using the RNeasy Plus Mini Kit (Qiagen) and reverse transcribed using standard procedures before hybridising to Affymetrix GeneChip <italic>Drosophila</italic> Genome 2.0 Array 3 (see the <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">supplementary Materials and Methods</uri> for details). Four replicate arrays were analysed for each genotype. Quantile normalised data were analysed using Limma (<xref rid="DEV126326C50" ref-type="bibr">Smyth, 2004</xref>) to estimate the log<sub>2</sub> FC in Notch versus control samples and the Benjamini-Hochberg adjusted <italic>P</italic>-values (FDR). Data from expression arrays have been deposited in ArrayExpress (E-MTAB-3561).</p><p>For each ChIP, chromatin was prepared from the CNS of 50 flies and the Su(H) ChIP performed as described previously (<xref rid="DEV126326C35" ref-type="bibr">Krejc&#x000ed; et al., 2009</xref>). The products were amplified and hybridised to NimbleGen <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> 2.1 M Whole-Genome Tiling Arrays. Three biological replicates were performed and quantile normalisation was applied to replicates for each genotype. Bound regions (peaks) were identified using Tamalpais at T02P005 stringency [top 2%, <italic>P</italic>&#x02264;0.005 (<xref rid="DEV126326C9" ref-type="bibr">Bieda et al., 2006</xref>)]. Genes in proximity to ChIP peaks were identified by the nearest genes upstream and downstream of each peak (using coordinates for the gene body) with a distance cutoff of 20&#x02005;kb. ChIP data have been deposited in Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO series GSE68614).</p><p>Gene set enrichment analysis (<xref rid="DEV126326C57" ref-type="bibr">Subramanian et al., 2005</xref>) was performed using the &#x02018;pre-ranked&#x02019; option to analyse the gene list ranked by log<sub>2</sub> FC from the mRNA expression data (3717 genes, FDR&#x02264;0.1) for enrichment of Su(H)-bound genes. As recommended, the more conservative &#x02018;classic&#x02019; scoring approach was used, which computes enrichment using only the gene&#x02019;s ranking (with no increment for the absolute value of the ranking metric).</p><p>GO analysis was performed using the DAVID bioinformatics resource (<xref rid="DEV126326C26" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2009</xref>). Motif enrichment analysis utilised the Bioconductor package PWMEnrich, which assesses the enrichment of each motif from a library of 650 experimentally derived <italic>Drosophila</italic> TF DNA motifs (<xref rid="DEV126326C56" ref-type="bibr">Stojnic and Diez, 2014</xref>). Enrichments for NB-expressed genes, Ase targets, and NB stem cell networks were assessed using Fisher's exact test, with the Benjamini-Hochberg method (<xref rid="DEV126326C7" ref-type="bibr">Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995</xref>) to correct for multiple sampling.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>NRE reporters</title><p>Putative Notch-regulated enhancers (NREs) in <italic>grh</italic>, <italic>svp</italic> and <italic>cas</italic> (coordinates are provided in the <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">supplementary Materials and Methods</uri>) were cloned in pBlueRabbit (pBR) (<xref rid="DEV126326C25" ref-type="bibr">Housden et al., 2012</xref>). Flies carrying the pBR transgenes were generated by &#x00278;C31-mediated site-directed integration in the attP40 landing site.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p>Fixation and immunohistochemistry of larval tissues were performed according to standard protocols. Details of primary antibodies are provided in the <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">supplementary Materials and Methods</uri>. Mouse, rabbit, guinea pig or rat secondary antibodies were conjugated to Alexa 488, 555, 568, 633 or 647 (Molecular Probes) or to FiTC, Cy3 or Cy5 (Jackson ImmunoResearch). Samples were imaged on a Leica SP2 or TCS SP8 confocal microscope (Confocal Facility, University of Crete or CAIC, University of Cambridge).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank George Papagiannakis for microarray hybridisations; Bettina Fischer (FlyChip) for help with genome-wide data processing; Leila Muresan (CAIC) for image data analysis; Electra Vitsakis and Ioannis Livadaras for help with NRE reporter constructs; Hadi Boukhatmi for comments on the manuscript; and other members of the S.J.B. and C.D. labs for valuable discussions. We acknowledge A. Gould, F. Casares, R. Carthew, S. Thor, W. Odenwald, Y. Hiromi, E. Giniger, A. Salzberg, the Bloomington Stock Center, the DGRC Kyoto Stock Center, the VDRC Stock Center, and the Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank for flies and antibodies.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p>The authors declare no competing or financial interests.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Author contributions</bold></p><p>E.Z. and B.E.H. performed experiments; E.Z., R.S., G.G., C.D. and S.J.B. analysed data; E.Z., C.D. and S.J.B. designed experiments; E.Z., C.D. and S.J.B. wrote the manuscript; B.E.H., R.S. and G.G. edited the manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding</bold></p><p>This work was supported by MRC programme grants to S.J.B. [G0800034; MR/L007177/1] and by scholarships to E.Z. from Thanassis and Marina Martinos and from the &#x02018;Herakleitos&#x02019; operational programme for Education and Lifelong Learning co-financed by Greece and the European Union [NSRF 2007-2013]. Deposited in PMC for immediate release.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold></p><p>Supplementary information available online at <uri xlink:href="http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1">http://dev.biologists.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1242/dev.126326/-/DC1</uri></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="DEV126326C1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Regulation of post-embryonic neuroblasts by Drosophila Grainyhead</article-title>. <source><italic>Mech. Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>122</volume>, <fpage>1282</fpage>-<lpage>1293</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mod.2005.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16275038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babaoglan</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Connor-Giles</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mistry</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schickedanz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Skeath</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Sanpodo: a context-dependent activator and inhibitor of Notch signaling during asymmetric divisions</article-title>. <source><italic>Development</italic></source>
<volume>136</volume>, <fpage>4089</fpage>-<lpage>4098</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.040386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babao&#x0011f;lan</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Housden</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furriols</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Deadpan contributes to the robustness of the notch response</article-title>. <source><italic>PLoS ONE</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e75632</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24086596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Badenhorst</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Tramtrack controls glial number and identity in the Drosophila embryonic CNS</article-title>. <source><italic>Development</italic></source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>4093</fpage>-<lpage>4101</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11641231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bayraktar</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Doe</surname><given-names>C. Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Combinatorial temporal patterning in progenitors expands neural diversity</article-title>. <source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>498</volume>, <fpage>449</fpage>-<lpage>455</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23783519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Izergina</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caussinus</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Reichert</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Amplification of neural stem cell proliferation by intermediate progenitor cells in Drosophila brain development</article-title>. <source><italic>Neural Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1749-8104-3-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18284664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing on JSTOR</article-title>. <source><italic>J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B</italic></source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>-<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harzer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burkard</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van der Horst</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laurenson</surname><given-names>A.-S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Novatchkova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reichert</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Knoblich</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>FACS purification and transcriptome analysis of drosophila neural stem cells reveals a role for Klumpfuss in self-renewal</article-title>. <source><italic>Cell Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>407</fpage>-<lpage>418</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2012.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22884370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bieda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Farnham</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Unbiased location analysis of E2F1-binding sites suggests a widespread role for E2F1 in the human genome</article-title>. <source><italic>Genome Res.</italic></source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>595</fpage>-<lpage>605</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.4887606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16606705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>J. Q.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Doe</surname><given-names>C. Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Identification of Drosophila type II neuroblast lineages containing transit amplifying ganglion mother cells</article-title>. <source><italic>Dev. Neurobiol.</italic></source>
<volume>68</volume>, <fpage>1185</fpage>-<lpage>1195</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dneu.20648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18548484</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boukhatmi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frendo</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Enriquez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crozatier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Tup/Islet1 integrates time and position to specify muscle identity in Drosophila</article-title>. <source><italic>Development</italic></source>
<volume>139</volume>, <fpage>3572</fpage>-<lpage>3582</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.083410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22949613</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rolland</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Betschinger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kinsey</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Knoblich</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The tumor suppressors Brat and Numb regulate transit-amplifying neuroblast lineages in Drosophila</article-title>. <source><italic>Dev. Cell</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>535</fpage>-<lpage>546</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2008.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18342578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Notch signalling: a simple pathway becomes complex</article-title>. <source><italic>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>678</fpage>-<lpage>689</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16921404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yavatkar</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuzin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tyson</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T.-Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.-H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Awasaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Use of a Drosophila genome-wide conserved sequence database to identify functionally related cis-regulatory enhancers</article-title>. <source><italic>Dev. Dyn.</italic></source>
<volume>241</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>-<lpage>189</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.22728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22174086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capaccione</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Pine</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The Notch signaling pathway as a mediator of tumor survival</article-title>. <source><italic>Carcinogenesis</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1420</fpage>-<lpage>1430</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/carcin/bgt127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23585460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cenci</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Drosophila Grainyhead specifies late programmes of neural proliferation by regulating the mitotic activity and Hox-dependent apoptosis of neuroblasts</article-title>. <source><italic>Development</italic></source>
<volume>132</volume>, <fpage>3835</fpage>-<lpage>3845</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16049114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Hedgehog signaling acts with the temporal cascade to promote neuroblast cell cycle exit</article-title>. <source><italic>PLoS Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e1001494</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23468593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connor-giles</surname><given-names>K. M. O.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skeath</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Numb inhibits membrane localization of sanpodo, a four-pass transmembrane protein, to promote asymmetric divisions in Drosophila</article-title>. <source><italic>Dev. Cell</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>243</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12919675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Djiane</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krejci</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fexova</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Dissecting the mechanisms of Notch induced hyperplasia</article-title>. <source><italic>EMBO J.</italic></source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>60</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2012.326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23232763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>L. Y.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>Y. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Control of daughter cell fates during asymmetric division: interaction of Numb and Notch</article-title>. <source><italic>Neuron</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(00)80278-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8755476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hertz</surname><given-names>G. Z.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Stormo</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Identifying DNA and protein patterns with statistically significant alignments of multiple sequences</article-title>. <source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>563</fpage>-<lpage>577</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/15.7.563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10487864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Homem</surname><given-names>C. C. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinmann</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burkard</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jais</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Esterbauer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Knoblich</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Ecdysone and mediator change energy metabolism to terminate proliferation in Drosophila neural stem cells</article-title>. <source><italic>Cell</italic></source>
<volume>158</volume>, <fpage>874</fpage>-<lpage>888</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.06.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25126791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Housden</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Drosophila reporter vectors compatible with &#x003a6;C31 integrase transgenesis techniques and their use to generate new notch reporter fly lines</article-title>. <source><italic>G3</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.111.001321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22384384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>B. T.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Lempicki</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources</article-title>. <source><italic>Nat. Protoc.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>44</fpage>-<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2008.211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19131956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inbal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halachmi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dibner</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Genetic evidence for the transcriptional-activating function of Homothorax during adult fly development</article-title>. <source><italic>Development</italic></source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>3405</fpage>-<lpage>3413</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11566847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izergina</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balmer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Reichert</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Postembryonic development of transit amplifying neuroblast lineages in the Drosophila brain</article-title>. <source><italic>Neural Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>44</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1749-8104-4-44</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Reichert</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Control of neural stem cell self-renewal and differentiation in Drosophila</article-title>. <source><italic>Cell Tissue Res.</italic></source>
<volume>359</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00441-014-1914-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24902665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerber</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fellert</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Hoch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Seven-up, the Drosophila homolog of the COUP-TF orphan receptors, controls cell proliferation in the insect kidney</article-title>. <source><italic>Genes Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1781</fpage>-<lpage>1786</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.12.12.1781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9637680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klinakis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Szabolcs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Politi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiaris</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Artavanis-Tsakonas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Efstratiadis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Myc is a Notch1 transcriptional target and a requisite for Notch1-induced mammary tumorigenesis in mice</article-title>. <source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</italic></source>
<volume>103</volume>, <fpage>9262</fpage>-<lpage>9267</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0603371103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16751266</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knoblich</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Mechanisms of asymmetric stem cell division</article-title>. <source><italic>Cell</italic></source>
<volume>132</volume>, <fpage>583</fpage>-<lpage>597</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.02.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18295577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Ilagan</surname><given-names>M. X. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The canonical Notch signaling pathway: unfolding the activation mechanism</article-title>. <source><italic>Cell</italic></source>
<volume>137</volume>, <fpage>216</fpage>-<lpage>233</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2009.03.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19379690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krejc&#x000ed;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Housden</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Direct response to Notch activation: signaling crosstalk and incoherent logic</article-title>. <source><italic>Sci. Signal.</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>ra1</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scisignal.2000140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19176515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koizumi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Odenwald</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The cis-regulatory dynamics of the Drosophila CNS determinant castor are controlled by multiple sub-pattern enhancers</article-title>. <source><italic>Gene Expr. Patterns</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>261</fpage>-<lpage>272</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gep.2012.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22691242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>S.-L.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Doe</surname><given-names>C. Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Transient nuclear Prospero induces neural progenitor quiescence</article-title>. <source><italic>Elife</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>e03363</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/elife.03363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Borgne</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bardin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Schweisguth</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The roles of receptor and ligand endocytosis in regulating Notch signaling</article-title>. <source><italic>Development</italic></source>
<volume>132</volume>, <fpage>1751</fpage>-<lpage>1762</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15790962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Erclik</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bertet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Voutev</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morante</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Celik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Desplan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Temporal patterning of Drosophila medulla neuroblasts controls neural fates</article-title>. <source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>498</volume>, <fpage>456</fpage>-<lpage>462</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23783517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ligoxygakis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delidakis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>A subset of notch functions during Drosophila eye development require Su(H) and the E(spl) gene complex</article-title>. <source><italic>Development</italic></source>
<volume>125</volume>, <fpage>2893</fpage>-<lpage>2900</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9655811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maurange</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Temporal transcription factors and their targets schedule the end of neural proliferation in Drosophila</article-title>. <source><italic>Cell</italic></source>
<volume>133</volume>, <fpage>891</fpage>-<lpage>902</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.03.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18510932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazzone</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Selfors</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albeck</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Overholtzer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sale</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pandya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aster</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Dose-dependent induction of distinct phenotypic responses to Notch pathway activation in mammary epithelial cells</article-title>. <source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</italic></source>
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>5012</fpage>-<lpage>5017</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1000896107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20194747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mootha</surname><given-names>V. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>K.-F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sihag</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lehar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Puigserver</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carlsson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ridderstr&#x000e5;le</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laurila</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>PGC-1alpha-responsive genes involved in oxidative phosphorylation are coordinately downregulated in human diabetes</article-title>. <source><italic>Nat. Genet.</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>-<lpage>273</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12808457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ntziachristos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Aifantis</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>From fly wings to targeted cancer therapies: a centennial for notch signaling</article-title>. <source><italic>Cancer Cell</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>318</fpage>-<lpage>334</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2014.02.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24651013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prokop</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Technau</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Homeotic regulation of segment-specific differences in neuroblast numbers and proliferation in the Drosophila central nervous system</article-title>. <source><italic>Mech. Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>74</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0925-4773(98)00068-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9651493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Posakony</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Genetic programs activated by proneural proteins in the developing Drosophila PNS</article-title>. <source><italic>Dev. Cell</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>413</fpage>-<lpage>425</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2005.01.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15737936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhyu</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>L. Y.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>Y. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Asymmetric distribution of numb protein during division of the sensory organ precursor cell confers distinct fates to daughter cells</article-title>. <source><italic>Cell</italic></source>
<volume>76</volume>, <fpage>477</fpage>-<lpage>491</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(94)90112-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8313469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>San-Ju&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Baonza</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The bHLH factor deadpan is a direct target of Notch signaling and regulates neuroblast self-renewal in Drosophila</article-title>. <source><italic>Dev. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>352</volume>, <fpage>70</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2011.01.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21262215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skalska</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stojnic</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cerda-Moya</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tajbakhsh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adryan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Chromatin signatures at Notch-regulated enhancers reveal large-scale changes in H3K56ac upon activation</article-title>. <source><italic>EMBO J.</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1889</fpage>-<lpage>1904</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201489923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26069324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Linear models and empirical bayes methods for assessing differential expression in microarray experiments</article-title>. <source><italic>Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2202/1544-6115.1027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Regulation of cell growth by Notch signaling and its differential requirement in normal vs. tumor-forming stem cells in Drosophila</article-title>. <source><italic>Genes Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>2644</fpage>-<lpage>2658</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.171959.111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22190460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sousa-Nunes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>W. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Mechanisms of asymmetric progenitor divisions in the Drosophila central nervous system</article-title>. <source><italic>Adv. Exp. Med. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>786</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>102</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-007-6621-1_6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23696353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Southall</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Neural stem cell transcriptional networks highlight genes essential for nervous system development</article-title>. <source><italic>EMBO J.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>3799</fpage>-<lpage>3807</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2009.309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19851284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Southall</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caygill</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>O. J.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Cell-type-specific profiling of gene expression and chromatin binding without cell isolation: assaying RNA Pol II occupancy in neural stem cells</article-title>. <source><italic>Dev. Cell</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>112</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2013.05.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23792147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spana</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Doe</surname><given-names>C. Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Numb antagonizes Notch signaling to specify sibling neuron cell fates</article-title>. <source><italic>Neuron</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(00)80277-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8755475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C56"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stojnic</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Diez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <comment>PWMEnrich: PWM enrichment analysis. R package version 4.2.0. <uri xlink:href="http://bioconductor.jp/packages/3.0/bioc/html/PWMEnrich.html">http://bioconductor.jp/packages/3.0/bioc/html/PWMEnrich.html</uri>.</comment>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mootha</surname><given-names>V. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gillette</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paulovich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pomeroy</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Golub</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</article-title>. <source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</italic></source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>15545</fpage>-<lpage>15550</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0506580102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bashirullah</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heberlein</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Aurora-A acts as a tumor suppressor and regulates self-renewal of Drosophila neuroblasts</article-title>. <source><italic>Genes Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>3453</fpage>-<lpage>3463</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1487506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17182870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millholland</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yashiro-Ohtani</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arcangeli</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wai</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>del Bianco</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tobias</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>c-Myc is an important direct target of Notch1 in T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia/lymphoma</article-title>. <source><italic>Genes Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>2096</fpage>-<lpage>2109</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1450406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16847353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.-Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>dFezf/Earmuff maintains the restricted developmental potential of intermediate neural progenitors in Drosophila</article-title>. <source><italic>Dev. Cell</italic></source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>126</fpage>-<lpage>135</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2009.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20152183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wernet</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Desplan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Homothorax and Extradenticle alter the transcription factor network in Drosophila ommatidia at the dorsal rim of the retina</article-title>. <source><italic>Development</italic></source>
<volume>141</volume>, <fpage>918</fpage>-<lpage>928</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.103127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24496628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Komori</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.-Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Klumpfuss distinguishes stem cells from progenitor cells during asymmetric neuroblast division</article-title>. <source><italic>Development</italic></source>
<volume>139</volume>, <fpage>2670</fpage>-<lpage>2680</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.081687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22745313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zacharioudaki</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Magadi</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Delidakis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>bHLH-O proteins are crucial for Drosophila neuroblast self-renewal and mediate Notch-induced overproliferation</article-title>. <source><italic>Development</italic></source>
<volume>139</volume>, <fpage>1258</fpage>-<lpage>1269</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.071779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22357926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="DEV126326C64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wildonger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barshow</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Younger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The bHLH repressor Deadpan regulates the self-renewal and specification of Drosophila larval neural stem cells independently of Notch</article-title>. <source><italic>PLoS ONE</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e46724</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0046724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23056424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>