<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3832538</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-23282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079777</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Metatranscriptomic Approach to the Identification of Microbiota Associated with the Ant <italic>Formica exsecta</italic></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Microbiota Associated with the Ant <italic>Formica exsecta</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>Helena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Dhaygude</surname><given-names>Kishor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lindstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>Stafva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Helanter&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>Heikki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sundstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>Liselotte</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Trontti</surname><given-names>Kalevi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Centre of Excellence in Biological Interactions, Department of Biosciences, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Stephen J.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Sheffield University, United States of America</addr-line></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>helena.z.johansson@helsinki.fi</email></corresp><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: HJ KD. Analyzed the data: HJ KD. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: KT HH LS. Wrote the paper: HJ KD SL HH LS KT.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e79777</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Johansson et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Social insects live in cooperative colonies, often in high densities and with closely related individuals, and interact using social contact behaviours. Compared to solitary insects, social insects have evolved multi-level immunity that includes immune responses common to holometabolous insects, and social immunity, which is exclusive to social taxa. This suggests that social insects may be subject to high pathogen pressure, yet relatively little is known about the range of symbiotic and pathogenic microbial communities that associate with social insects. In this study we examined transcriptome data generated from the ant <italic>Formica exsecta</italic> for sequences identifying as microbes (or other organisms potentially of non-ant origin). Sequences showing homology to two viruses and several other potentially or obligate intracellular organisms, such as <italic>Wolbachia, Arsenophonus, Entomoplasmatales</italic> and <italic>Microsporidia,</italic> were present in the transcriptome data. These homologous sequence matches correspond to genera/species that have previously been associated with a variety of insects, including social insects. There were also sequences with identity to several other microbes such as common moulds and soil bacteria. We conclude that this sequence data provides a starting point for a deeper understanding of the biological interactions between a species of ant and the micro- and macrobiotic communities that it potentially encounters.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work received funding from Academy of Finland (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aka.fi/eng">http://www.aka.fi/eng</ext-link>) grant numbers 140990 and 135970 to Heikki Helanter&#x000e4;, 134561 to Kalevi Trontti, and Centre of Excellence in Biological Interactions grant number 251337 to Liselotte Sundstr&#x000f6;m. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Identifying and classifying pathogens for a species of interest has great significance for fundamental research in ecology and evolution. The recent advent of genomic and transcriptomic methods have opened up the field to rapid, sensitive and comprehensive assessment of microbiota occurring in different natural environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Damon1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Scott1">[2]</xref>, including the gut of various species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Moran1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Gosalbes1">[4]</xref>, diseased individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-CoxFoster1">[5]</xref>, and apparently healthy tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Wittekindt1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Moore1">[7]</xref>.</p><p>Social insects (ants, bees, wasps and termites) live in cooperative colonies, often in high densities and with closely related individuals. They engage in contact behaviors such as trophallaxis (transfer of food or other fluids through mouth-to-mouth or anus-to-mouth feeding) and allogrooming. Crowded living conditions and contact behaviours allow disease to spread rapidly through colonies, and since nest mates are often related they tend to be genetically susceptible to the same pathogen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Schluns1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Cremer1">[9]</xref>. Compared to solitary insects, social insects are hence believed to be under increased pathogen pressure. In response, social insect have an expanded multilevel immune repertoire. These include highly conserved molecular defense pathways such as Toll, imd, Jak/STAT, JNK and RNAi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Brennan1">[10]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Simola1">[14]</xref>, and mechanical and humoral cellular responses such as phagocytosis, nodule formation, encapsulation and antimicrobial peptides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Schluns1">[8]</xref> that are shared with other holometabolous insects. Furthermore, and in contrast to solitary insects, social insects also have social immunity, i.e. individuals mount immune responses for the benefit of others <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Cremer1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Cotter1">[15]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Cremer2">[17]</xref>. Social immunity in ants and other social insects include the use of specialized glands <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Schluns1">[8]</xref>, and a variety of behaviours such as allogrooming to remove parasites from one another <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Oi1">[18]</xref>, task specialization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-SchmidHempel1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Bourke1">[20]</xref> and nest maintenance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Cremer1">[9]</xref>. In spite of their importance for the evolution of immunity, natural pathogen communities have been assessed in detail only for honey bees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-CoxFoster1">[5]</xref> and one species of ant, the red invasive fire ant <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Yang1">[21]</xref> (and references therein).</p><p>Another aspect of social contact behaviours such as trophallaxis is that they provide opportunities for frequent transmission of gut bacteria, which is relatively rare in non-social insects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Engel1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Zientz1">[23]</xref>. Consequently, social insects have some of the most distinctive and consistent gut microbial communities known among the insects. These communities have evolved to provide specialized beneficial functions in nutrition and protection for their host <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Engel1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Zientz1">[23]</xref>. Gut microbiota has been well characterized in the honey bee, and broadly characterized in some 60 species of ant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Stoll1">[24]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Ishak1">[27]</xref>. These studies show taxonomic as well as dietary influence on the composition of gut bacterial communities in ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Engel1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Anderson1">[26]</xref>.</p><p><italic>Formica exsecta</italic> is a common ant species with a distribution range spanning most of Northern Eurasia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Douwes1">[28]</xref>. It builds nests reaching diameters and depths up to 1&#x02013;1.5 m, which consist of a soil core overlaid by needles, grass, and small sticks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Seifert1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Czechowski1">[30]</xref>. Nests that reach maturity are relatively long lived (upto 20 years), however many fail to reach maturity, hence the average life span is six to seven years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-HaagLiautard1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Pamilo1">[32]</xref>. It is an omnivore, feeding mainly on small insects and honey dew collected from aphids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Werner1">[33]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Pisarski2">[35]</xref>. Eggs developing into sexuals are laid in May and mature to adults in June/July. Eggs destined to develop into new workers are laid intermixed with sexual-destined eggs and directly after them. Workers overwinter as adults and live for about one year, whereas male lifespan is restricted to a few weeks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Seifert1">[29]</xref>. With regards to potential infectious agents or symbionts, previous studies have shown a high population/nest prevalence of the intracellular parasite <italic>Wolbachia pipientis</italic> in several populations of <italic>F. exsecta</italic>, although the rate of individual infection is unknown <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Wenseleers1">[36]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Viljakainen2">[38]</xref>. Several species of mites have been associated with this and other <italic>Formica</italic> ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-SchmidHempel1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-LehtinenTapiola1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Eickwort1">[40]</xref>. The bacterial gut communities of this ant species have not been investigated.</p><p>This study joins several other recent publications where transcriptomic or genomic approaches have been used to identify sequences with homology to pathogenic and natural communities on and within species. Following the generation and assembly of an <italic>F. exsecta</italic> transcriptome, we utilized only those contigs that were found to not be of ant origin with the aim of identifying sequences with homology to potential intracellular pathogens and symbionts, including viruses, bacteria, and fungi; and biota closely associated with the ants and their environment. There were sequences with homology to two viruses, to several potential intracellular parasites (including <italic>Wolbachia,</italic> and candidates such as <italic>Arsenophonus</italic>), to potential beneficial symbionts (such as <italic>Entomoplasma, Burkholderia</italic> and yeasts), to six species of mite and to a range of common environmental fungi and bacteria.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Sampling and Sample Preparation</title><p><italic>Formica exsecta</italic> queens, workers, males and cocoons developing to these castes were collected from six localities (three island localities: Rovholmarna, Josk&#x000e4;r, Furusk&#x000e4;r, and three mainland populations: Harparskog, Pr&#x000e4;stkulla, Ing&#x000e5;) spanning an area of approximately 50 km<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s001">Table S1</xref>). These islands are relatively pristine and uninhabited, and form part of a nature conservancy area in which agricultural activities, including apiculture, are strictly forbidden. The mainland localities were sampled in recently (&#x0003c;10&#x02013;30 yrs.) clear-cut economical forest or meadowland close to small villages. No specific permission was required for sampling these ants. This species is not endangered or protected by Finnish or international laws. Finnish land legislation permits everyone the right to access all land without permission of the owner (Everyman&#x02019;s right).</p><p>Established colony queens and overwintered workers (hereafter old queens and workers) were sampled straight from the field colonies in late April and early May 2011. They were immediately transported to the laboratory and frozen alive at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C. Cocoons were maintained in the laboratory until sex and caste could be reliably assessed from external morphology and size, and then divided into three developmental classes: young (white cuticle and eyes), intermediate (white cuticle but pigmented eyes), and old (pigmented cuticle and eyes). A proportion of the cocoons eclosed to new queens, males and workers. Samples were frozen as above at the appropriate developmental stage. For the purposes of this study we used the three castes: queens, workers and males. For the workers and queens we used three age classes: old, new and cocoon. New males and male cocoons were analyzed together due to the low sample numbers. Note that the cocoons were not analyzed by developmental stage. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t001">Table 1</xref> lists detailed numbers of colonies, individuals, castes, ages and developmental classes.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0079777-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079777.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Number of individuals pooled in each of the total of 28 libraries sequenced by FIMM or BGI.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0079777-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0079777.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caste/sex</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FIMM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BGI</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Queen</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Old overwintered</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Old cocoon</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate cocoon</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young cocoon</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Worker</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Old overwintered</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Old cocoon</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate cocoon</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young cocoon</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Male</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Old cocoon</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate cocoon</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young cocoon</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Castes and developmental classes of <italic>F. exsecta</italic> are given together with number of source colonies in parentheses.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The nests were not directly assessed for disease symptoms, however all nests were sampled by experienced researchers who noted no obvious signs of disease with regards to nest appearance, individual ant appearance and general worker behaviour. It was noted that many individuals collected in the field or housed in the laboratory carried mites that likely originated from the field colonies.</p><p>Prior to RNA extraction, samples were rinsed in 96% ethanol and any unspecific material, including mites, was removed under a microscope. Total RNA for RNA-seq library construction was extracted from whole queens, workers, males, and cocoons using TriSure reagent (Bioline), following the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Each sample was extracted individually, high quality RNA was determined by the presence of an 18S rRNA peak using the Agilent 2100 bioanalyzer, and RNA was pooled after extraction into the respective libraries (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t001">Table 1</xref>) based on caste and stage so that each RNA sample had equal representation in the pool. The exception to this was the library of old workers sequenced in BGI, which was normalized according to populations (not individuals) due to difficulties in obtaining high quality RNA. The final number of ants that were used was 209 individuals from 59 colonies.</p><p>The mRNA was selected from the total RNA (50&#x02013;80 ug) pools using two rounds of Poly-A-Purist MAG kit (Ambion) and/or custom assays of library providers (see below). The first set of libraries was constructed by the Finnish Institute for Molecular Medicine (FIMM; University of Helsinki, Finland). In short, after the second round of poly-A selection and DNAse treatment cDNA was fragmented and sizes 200&#x02013;500 bases were selected to construct Pair-End sequencing Illumina libraries. The second library set was constructed in the same manner by the Beijing Genomic Institute (BGI, China) except selecting only approximately 200 base fragments. Sequencing of the first set of libraries was conducted by FIMM (PE-99) and the second by BGI (PE-91), in both cases using two lanes of Illumina HighSeq 2000. The raw reads of the meta-transcriptome will be available from 2014-08-29 on GenBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/</ext-link>) under bioproject ID PRJNA213662, sample accession numbers: SAMN02297446, SAMN02297447, SAMN02297448, SAMN02297449, SAMN02297450, SAMN02297451 and SAMN02297452.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Basic Bioinformatic Analyses and NCBI BLAST Searches</title><p>An initial quality check of the raw fastq data was done by assessing the phred score (or Q-value, ranging from 0&#x02013;40, where 40 denotes the highest quality) and trimming the low quality bases using Fastx toolkit v. 0.0.13 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Pearson1">[41]</xref>. Transcriptome assembly from the trimmed reads was performed with the software Trinity (Release 2012-05-18, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Grabherr1">[42]</xref>). An initial transcriptome (IT) assembly was performed, followed by realignment of the original transcripts to the IT. This was a quality control step for all transcripts which ensured that at least five (forward and reverse) paired-end reads were used and removed transcripts which had very low reads per kilobase per million reads (RPKM, see below). Only transcripts with a confirmed minimum of five paired-end reads were used for BLAST searches and mapping against protein sequences from <italic>Harpegnathos saltator, Camponotus floridanus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Bonasio1">[43]</xref>, <italic>Atta cephalotes</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Suen1">[44]</xref>, <italic>Linepithema humile</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Smith1">[45]</xref>, <italic>Pogonomyrmex barbatus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Smith2">[46]</xref>, <italic>S. invicta</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Wurm1">[47]</xref> and <italic>Acromyrmex echinatior</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Nygaard1">[48]</xref>. Full details of the final ant transcriptome assembly will be published elsewhere (Trontti et al. unpublished data). The reads that did not match to any ant genomes were BLAST searched against the virus, fungal, protozoan and bacterial genome databases at NCBI (BLAST version 2.2.26+). As cut off criteria in the BLAST searches we used a minimum alignment length of 100nt, E-value 0.001 a word size of 11, and a minimum of 70% sequence identity. Identified microbiota were then BLAST searched back against the <italic>F. exsecta</italic> transcriptome. By doing this we ensured that more than one gene in the identified microbiota was active so that sequence matches did not just represent single highly conserved genes/domains.</p><p>Expression values for the GenBank matches were calculated by aligning and counting all reads of each library, utilizing both FIMM and BGI data. From these, RPKM values (expression value in RNASeq) were calculated as follows: RPK/(total number of reads/1000000), where RPK&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;number of mapped reads/length of transcript in kb (transcript length/1000). This method quantifies gene expression from RNA sequencing data by normalizing for total read length and the number of sequencing reads. We give a total expression value, calculated over all ages and castes in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t002">Tables 2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t004">4</xref>, and a breakdown of expression values by caste, age class and sequencing provider in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s002">Table S2</xref>. Note that the number of individuals from each age class and caste varied, from 3 to 30. The samples were pooled by sex and age-class (see above) prior to transcriptome expression in order to obtain sufficient amounts of RNA, hence the libraries were not analyzed by locality. Aware that only a fraction of microbiological diversity is described and/or present on GenBank, we chose to conservatively identify microbiota to genus level.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0079777-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079777.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Sequences matching microbes, and a mite, associated with <italic>F. exsecta</italic>, identified from GenBank BLAST searches.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0079777-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0079777.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Function</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kingdom</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phyla</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Genus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expressionvalue</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Intracellular</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Virus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Discistovirus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dicistrovirus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4945.261</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Similar to IAPV, ABPV and KBV in honey bees (<italic>Apis mellifera</italic>).</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Iflavirus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Iflavirus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2984.429</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Similar to DWV in honey bees.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Proteobacteria</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Wolbachia_978</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321.331</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obligate endoparasite, widespread in arthropods, including <italic>F. exsecta.</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Proteobacteria</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Wolbachia_416</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3510.295</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A second strain of <italic>Wolbachia</italic>, known from previous studies on <italic>Formica</italic> ants.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungi<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Microsporidia</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Encephalitozoon</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.902</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unicellular parasites, related microsporidians (<italic>Nosema</italic> spp.) cause infection in bees.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Basidimycota</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cryptococcus</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">&#x02227;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.771</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some members of this genus are parasitic &#x02013; their effect on insects (if any) is unknown</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>(Likely)</bold><bold>Extracellular</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Proteobacteria</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acidiphilium</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8147.115</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acidophile, widespread in soils.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rhodococcus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7949.379</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generalist soil genus.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ascomycota</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">&#x02227;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.899</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pervasive in the environment, including indoor air, some opportunistic pathogens</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Penicillium</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.729</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Neurospora</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2888.620</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gibberella</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.147</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Environmental, inlcuding plant pathogens</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Podospora</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.751</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant pathogen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Eremothecium</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.331</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Yarrowia</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.028</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Basidiomycota</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ustilago</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.080</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animalia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arthropoda</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Varroa</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.196</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Varroa destructor, mite well known from honey bees</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Unknown</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ascomycota (yeast)</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Candida</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.144</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often found as symbionts in insects, including ants. Common and diverse in soils.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Saccharomyces</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.606</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Scizosaccharomyces</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.035</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Zygosaccaromyces</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.582</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Kluyveromyces</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">**</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">&#x02227;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.651</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Naumovozyma</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.658</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tetrapisispora</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2781.217</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Torulaspora</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.677</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Total expression value represents the combined expression value for all ages and castes, from both FIMM and BGI data.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>Intracellular microbes are known parasites or have at least one stage of their lifecycle inside the host. Extracellular microbes do not usually have lifecycles within hosts, but can in some cases be opportunistic pathogens. Unknown is used for yeast, these are pervasive in environments that contain moisture and carbohydrate sources, and may form symbiotic relationships with ants in their guts, or they can grow in the nest material, or be carried in via aphid dew that ants feed on. IAPV&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;Israel Acute Paralysis Virus, Acute Bee Paralysis Virus, KBV&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;Kashmir Bee Virus, DVW&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;deformed wing virus.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>*</label><p>current classification.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>**</label><p>Some <italic>Kluyveromyces</italic> are teleomorphs of <italic>Candida.</italic></p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>&#x02227;</label><p>Fungi that gave hits on both common and species specific genes in GenBank.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0079777-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079777.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Sequences matching eukaryotes of non-fungal origin identified from the 18s rRNA gene.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0079777-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0079777.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phylum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superorder</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Order</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0201c;cohort&#x0201d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">genus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expressionvalue</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genbank match</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arthropoda</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acariformes</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sarcoptiformes</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Astigmata</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acarus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.427</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU152495.1.1543</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Astigmata</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ewingia</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.687</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU152502.1.1702</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Astigmata</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Histiostoma</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.472</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GQ864328.1.1656</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Astigmata</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tyroborus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.140</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF203768.1.1516</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Parasitiformes</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mesostigmata</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dermanyssina</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Holostaspis</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.156</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ911851.1.1592</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gaeolaelaps</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.265</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ911852.1.1593</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Veigaiidae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Veigaia</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.186</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GQ864298.1.1627</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><label/><p>GenBank match denotes the GenBank accession number of the closest GenBank BLAST match. Total expression value represents the combined expression value for all ages and castes, from both FIMM and BGI data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0079777-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079777.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>16s rRNA sequence analysis.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0079777-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0079777.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phylum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subphylum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expressionvalue</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBankmatch</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comment</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinobacteria</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Actinomycetales</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Micrococcineae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ659818</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This phylum and genus are very common soil bacteria</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY189308</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ659818</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacteroidetes</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sphingobacteriaceae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pedobacter</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP001681</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Firmicutes</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Streptococcaceae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Streptococcus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB682354</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lactobacillaceae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lactobacillus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FN667112</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Common in soils. Symbiotic with e.g. honey bees</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Proteobacteria</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acetobacteraceae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Saccharibacter</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JN846886</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Camponotus fragilis</italic> gut bacteria.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JN846886</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Kozakia</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JN846887</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Anaplasmataceae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Anaplasma</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3793.28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP001391</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Wolbachia</italic> was closest GenBank match</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Burkholderiaceae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Burkholderia</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF763863</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Common soil bacteria. Often symbiotic with arthropods</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP000571</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arsenophonus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JN990929</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insect specialized intracellular clade</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Moraxellaceae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Enhydrobacter</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU706098</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soils/symbionts</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acinetobacter</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ435689</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonadaceae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Azomonas</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JQ659356</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Common in soils, also symbiotic or pathogenic in several taxa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Azomonas</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU072020</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HE586388</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tenericutes</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Entomoplasmataceae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Entomoplasma</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U67946</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obligate intracellular microbes. Often in association with insects</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF547212</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mesoplasma</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HM996851</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt108"><label/><p>Phylum, subphylum and genus from the RDP Classifier. The closest GenBank match is given with the total expression value from both FIMM and BGI data, together with a short description of the most likely habitat, derived from GenBank accessions and literature (further details in the discussion).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Ribosomal RNA</title><p>To cast the net wider we also isolated ribosomal GenBank matches from the transcriptome, namely the 16S, 18S and 28S ribosomal subunit genes for analysis. Sequences matching 18S rRNA eukaryotes were identified using NCBI BLAST searches. The Ribosomal Database Project (RDP) Classifier tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/">http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/</ext-link>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Wang1">[49]</xref>) was used to to classify sequences corresponding to the 16S rRNA gene in bacteria and the 28S gene (Large Subunit (LSU)) in fungi. The RDP Classifier tool implements a na&#x000ef;ve Bayesian Classifier to taxonomic classification based on these genes, using a minimum of 80% confidence of assignment. For bacteria, we also obtained the best match cultivated type strains from the Ribosomal Database <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Cole1">[50]</xref>, and aligned these sequences with those found from the transcriptome using Muscle as implemented in SeaView v. 4.4.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Gouy1">[51]</xref>. A phylogenetic tree was constructed by PhyML, again as implemented in SeaView v. 4.4.1 (model choice GTR, 100 bootstraps). A complimentary analysis of the fungal large subunit (LSU) genes was not possible owing to lack of suitable type strains and data quality.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Additional Analyses</title><sec id="s2d1"><title>Viruses</title><p>GenBank database searches revealed that ant-derived transcripts showed sequence similarity to viruses from the <italic>Dicistroviridae</italic> and <italic>Iflaviridae</italic> families (both virus families are insect-specific <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-VanOers1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Christian1">[53]</xref>). The available genomes of all Dicistroviruses and Iflaviruses were obtained from GenBank, and aligned with the ant-derived virus transcripts using ClustalW <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Larkin1">[54]</xref>. A phylogenetic tree was constructed from the alignment using the Maximum Likelihood method as implemented in PHYLIP 3.68 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Felsenstein1">[55]</xref>, with 100 bootstraps.</p><p>Some insect viruses are spread by vectors, or have low host-specificity such as many of the honey bee viruses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Levitt1">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Singh1">[57]</xref>. Since there were many phoretic mites on the ants, and since there were sequences with identity to the honey bee mite <italic>Varroa destructor</italic> in our transcriptome data (see below) we ruled out <italic>V. destructor</italic> as a vector or ant food source by BLAST searching of another <italic>F. exsecta</italic> transcriptome, generated by Badouin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Badouin1">[58]</xref> and publicly available on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.antgenomes.org">www.antgenomes.org</ext-link>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Wurm2">[59]</xref>. The samples for the Badouin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Badouin1">[58]</xref> transcriptome came exclusively from the <italic>Varroa</italic>-free island localities Furusk&#x000e4;r and Josk&#x000e4;r, which were also sampled for our study (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">methods</xref>). We further BLAST searched this transcriptome for sequences with homology to the viruses genomes derived from our transcriptome data.</p></sec><sec id="s2d2"><title>Wolbachia</title><p>Six different strains of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> have been associated with several <italic>Formica</italic> species in Finland and Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Reuter1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Viljakainen2">[38]</xref>. These strains do not appear to be specific to individual ant species, and concomitant infections of two or several strains commonly occur <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Reuter1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Viljakainen2">[38]</xref>. We confirmed that the sequences in our contigs matched two of these previously identified strains, by performing an alignment of <italic>wsp</italic> genes (outer surface protein precursors) from the ant-derived transcripts to <italic>Wolbachia wsp</italic> sequences already reported in GenBank (GenBank accession numbers: AY101196-AY1011200 from <italic>Formica exsecta</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Reuter1">[37]</xref> and EF554317 from <italic>Formica rufa</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Viljakainen2">[38]</xref>). Alignment was performed using MUMMER 3.23. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Kurtz1">[60]</xref>.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>All reads were found to be of high quality (Q&#x0003e;20), but trimming reduced the average read length from 99 bp to 90 for FIMM data, and 91 to 85 for BGI data. The IT assembly and realignment led to the removal of 48.6% of the total transcripts, leaving 81407 transcripts. A total of 53504 of these contigs did not align with the seven ant genomes (<italic>H. saltator, C. floridanus</italic>, <italic>A. cephalotes</italic>, <italic>L. humile</italic>, <italic>P. barbatus, S. invicta</italic> and <italic>A. echinatior</italic>), annotated using protein sequences. Of those contigs, 5746 returned sequence matches for organisms entered on the individual GenBank databases.</p><sec id="s3a"><title>GenBank BLAST Searches</title><p>Sequences with identity to <italic>Wolbachia</italic> were expressed in many contigs and with high expression values (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s002">Table S2</xref>). Combined expression values for the two strains were lowest in the old queens and workers, and highest in cocoons. Ant-derived transcripts showed homology with over 300 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> genes. Sequences with similarity to <italic>Wolbachia</italic> were also confirmed in the 16S rRNA data (see below). The ant-derived sequences matched strains wFex4 (alignment lenght: 357 bp, identity: 100, coverage: 59.2%) and wFex2 (alignment lenght: 599 bp, identity: 99.5, coverage: 99.83%). Sequences with homology to two soil/environmental prokaryotes, <italic>Rhodococcus (Actinobacteria)</italic> and <italic>Acidiphilum (Proteobacteria)</italic> were also expressed in all ages and castes from the ant-derived transcripts; the former is common in soils, the latter is an acidophile (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s002">Table S2</xref>).</p><p>Sequences with homology to one Dicistrovirus and one Iflavirus were present in the transcriptome data, and had very high expression values (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s002">Table S2</xref>). Both <italic>Iflaviridae</italic> and <italic>Dicistroviridae</italic> belong in the (+) ssRNA viruses (+) sense RNA, with similarity to <italic>Picornavirales</italic>. Our phylogenetic analyses showed that the genome with homology to <italic>Dicistroviridae</italic> grouped with Dicistroviruses found in a species of ant and several species of bee, whereas the genome with homology to <italic>Iflaviridae</italic> grouped with Iflaviruses infecting several different insect species, including bees (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079777-g001">Figure 1</xref>). The ant-derived Dicistrovirus had 75% nucleotide sequence similarity to the Kashmir Bee Virus, and the ant-derived Iflavirus had 70% nucleotide sequence similarity to the Deformed Wing Virus. The sizes of both virus genomes from the initial assembly (Dicistrovirus: 9554 bp, Iflavirus: 9160 bp) were consistent with genome sizes found in the other viruses in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079777-g001">Figure 1</xref> (range: ca 8000&#x02013;10500 bp). Sequences matching the Discistrovirus were expressed in all ages and castes, with the highest expression value found in new workers, and the lowest expression in old queens. Sequences matching the Iflavirus were expressed in all castes and ages, with the highest expression value in new queens and the lowest in new workers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s002">Table S2</xref>). Annotated virus draft genome assemblies are available under accession numbers KF500001 (Dicistrovirus) and KF500002 (Iflavirus) on GenBank. We identified the contig &#x02018;isotig09016&#x02019; in the published <italic>F. exsecta</italic> transcriptome generated by Badouin et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Badouin1">[58]</xref> which showed 99% identity with sequences yielding identity to the Iflavirus in our transcriptome.</p><fig id="pone-0079777-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079777.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Phylogeny of the available genomes of the insect-specific <italic>Discistroviridae</italic> and <italic>Iridoviridae</italic> from GenBank.</title><p>Social insect viruses are highlighted in blue and ant-derived assembled virus genomes from this study are highlighted in red.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0079777.g001"/></fig><p>Sequences with homology to seventeen species of fungi were present in the transcriptome data, seven of which were yeasts, two were common moulds (<italic>Aspergillus, Penicillium</italic>), six were plant pathogens, one a facultative endoparasite (<italic>Cryptococcus</italic>) and one an intracellular microsporidian from the genus <italic>Encephalitozoon</italic>. Since many of these fungi may share conserved genes we collapsed this list by removing sequences with homology only to genes shared with all other fungi (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t002">Table 2</xref>). This collapsed list included sequences with high similarity to only four species: <italic>Aspergillus oryzae, A. niger, Kluyveromyces</italic> and <italic>Cryptococcus,</italic> which were expressed in all castes and ages.</p><p>In spite of careful removal of mites from the ants, there were sequences with identity to <italic>V. destructor</italic> genes present in the transcriptome data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s002">Table S2</xref>) Notably, sequences matching <italic>V. destructor</italic> were not present among the 18S rRNA sequence data generated from our transcriptome data (see below), nor from Badouin et al.&#x02019;s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Badouin1">[58]</xref> transcriptome. <italic>Varroa destructor</italic> is the sole mite species that has had its genome sequenced, so similar genes and sequences from other species of mites will most likely also show homology with <italic>V. destructor</italic> sequences submitted to GenBank. The expression value was highest in new queens, and lowest in old workers, and the expression values were overall similar to expression patterns for total mite 18s rRNA sequences.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Ribosomal RNA BLAST Searches and RDP Classifier Results</title><p>The 18S rRNA sequences yielded matches to genes of seven mite species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t003">Table 3</xref>). Both mite super-orders, <italic>Acariformes</italic> and <italic>Parasitiformes</italic>, were represented, sorting into suborders <italic>Sarcoptiformes; Astigmata</italic> (four members) for the former and <italic>Mesostigmata; Dermanyssina</italic> and <italic>Mesostigmata: Veigaiidae</italic> for the latter (three members). Sequences yielding identity to <italic>Histiostoma</italic> showed the highest expression level overall (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t003">Table 3</xref>) and were expressed in all castes and age classes with the exception of old queens (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s002">Table S2</xref>), with the highest expression value in new queens. Sequences yielding identity to <italic>Veigaia</italic> had relatively low expression values, however they were expressed in all ages and castes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s002">Table S2</xref>). Total expression values for sequences matching mite 18S rRNA was highest in new workers and queens, and lowest in old queens and worker cocoons. No sequences with similarity to 18S rRNA mite genes were detected in the <italic>F. exsecta</italic> transcriptome generated by Badouin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Badouin1">[58]</xref>.</p><p>A total of 249 sequences that exhibited identity to bacterial 16S rRNA were retrieved from the transcriptome data and entered into RDP Classifier. Of these, 21 were retained for further analyses. The excluded matches failed to meet RDP criteria by having sizes less than 200 bp or failing alignment (188 sequences), 37 sequences were classified as bacteria but no further classification was possible, three were classified as chloroplasts, and three had confidence intervals below 80% at more than one stage of classification. NCBI BLAST matches and RDP classification mostly agreed, in case of disagreement NCBI BLAST results were chosen as the default (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t004">Table 4</xref>). Among the retained 21 sequences were matches to <italic>Firmicutes, Tenericutes, Actinobacteria</italic> and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t004">Table 4</xref>). A phylogenetic tree of these sequences and their closest cultivated type strains obtained from RDP is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079777-g002">Figure 2</xref>. Overall, the bootstrap values showed that the tree was not very robust in some of its deeper branches (which was expected considering that the tree spans deep phylogenetic divisions within bacteria). However, some of the sequences isolated from the ant transcriptome resolved well at the tips of the tree with particularly close matches to the type strains for <italic>Lactobacillus, Micrococcus, Arsenophonus,</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>. Furthermore, type strains for <italic>Entomoplasma, Burkholderia, and Wolbachia</italic> were also good matches to our sequence data.</p><fig id="pone-0079777-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079777.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic tree of bacterial 16S rRNA sequences, with closest type strains obtained from the Ribosomal Database project in black font.</title><p>Ant-derived contig IDs are given in red font. Red clade&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>Firmicutes</italic>, blue clade&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>Bacteroidetes</italic>, black clade&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>Proteobacteria</italic>, yellow clade&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>Tenericutes</italic>, green clade&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>Actinobacteria.</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0079777.g002"/></fig><p>Among the 21 16S rRNA sequences retained from the RDP classifier there were sequences with homology to bacteria whose life cycles are either completely within a host cell or require some stage of their life cycle within a host cell (hereafter intracellular). These were: <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> (<italic>Wolbachia</italic>), <italic>Enterobacteriacae</italic> (<italic>Arsenophonus),</italic> and <italic>Tenericutes</italic> (<italic>Entomoplasma</italic>). Sequences with identity to <italic>Acetobacteracaeae</italic> matched most closely to gut bacteria isolated from the ant <italic>Camponotus fragilis</italic>, and may also be intracellular. Total expression values when combined by genus showed that sequences with identity to <italic>Wolbachia</italic> had the highest value, followed by sequences yielding identity to <italic>Acetobacteraceae</italic> and sequences with homology to <italic>Entomplasmataceae.</italic> Sequences matching <italic>Arsenophonus</italic> did not have high expression values and were less encountered than the above genera (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t003">Table 3</xref>.) Sequences matching <italic>Wolbachia</italic> and <italic>Acetobacteraceae</italic> were expressed in all castes and ages (<italic>Wolbachia</italic> expression patterns as above), whereas sequences matching <italic>Arsenophonus</italic> were not expressed in new queens and new workers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s002">Table S2</xref>). The remaining sequences matched bacteria from subphyla commonly found in soils (subphyla <italic>Actinomycetales</italic>, <italic>Sphingobacteriaceae, Streptococcacae, Lactobaciallaceae, Burkholderiacae, Moraxellaceae</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonadaceae).</italic> Several members of these subphyla are capable of a beneficial or pathogenic symbiotic lifestyle with insect hosts, in particular <italic>Lactobaciallaceae</italic>, <italic>Burkholderiaceae</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonadaceae.</italic> Sequences matching these latter three genera were expressed in all castes and ages (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s002">Table S2</xref>).</p><p>Fifty-four LSU sequences were retrieved from the transcriptome data. Of these, eight failed to be classified as fungi using the RDP classifier, another 35 were classified as fungi, but no further taxonomic classification was possible, leaving only eight sequences that could be classified with some confidence (&#x0003e;80%) to species level. Of these, four sequences were classified as <italic>Basidiomycota</italic>, species <italic>Hohenbuehelia</italic> (wood decaying fungi), and the remaining sequences were classified as Ascomycota, two classifying as <italic>Plectosphaerella</italic> (plant pathogen) and two as <italic>Parmotrema</italic> (lichen) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0079777.s003">Table S3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Sequences with identity to a wide range of microbes, and some species of mite, were retrieved from within and on the ant <italic>Formica exsecta</italic>, by analysing data of non-ant origin from transcriptome assemblies. These included sequences yielding identity to two viruses, two <italic>Wolbachia</italic> strains, several potential intracellular symbionts (<italic>Arsenophonus</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic>Microsporidium</italic>) and potentially opportunistic pathogens (<italic>Aspergillus</italic> spp. and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp.). Since transcriptome data is generated from RNA, the sequence matches most likely represent some of the most active microbes associated with the ant <italic>F. exsecta</italic>.</p><p>The successful and expected retrieval of sequences matching <italic>Wolbachia</italic> from many contigs and among the 16S rRNA sequence data attests to the feasibility of this approach. Sequences matching <italic>Wolbachia</italic> showed high levels of identity with two strains that commonly infect Eurasian and Finnish populations of several closely related <italic>Formica</italic> wood ants, including <italic>Formica exsecta</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Wenseleers1">[36]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Viljakainen2">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Keller1">[61]</xref>. <italic>Wolbachia</italic> is a very common and widespread intracellular symbionts of insects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Duron1">[62]</xref>, including ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Wenseleers1">[36]</xref>. It usually shows no noticeable adverse effect but occasionally affects its host negatively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Stevens1">[63]</xref>. It is readily horizontally and vertically transmitted within and between <italic>Formica</italic> species, and has not been associated with any detrimental effects in <italic>F. exsecta</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Viljakainen2">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Keller1">[61]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Russell2">[64]</xref>. Expression of sequences matching <italic>Wolbachia</italic> appeared to decrease with age, in line with previous results on <italic>F. exsecta</italic> by Keller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Keller1">[61]</xref>. The mechanism and significance of this pattern remains unknown.</p><p>In addition to sequences yielding identity to <italic>Wolbachia,</italic> there were sequences with homology to other intracellular microbes. These were to the fungi <italic>Microsporidia,</italic> and to bacteria belonging to the <italic>Enterobacteriacae</italic> (<italic>Arsenophonus),</italic> the <italic>Entomoplasmatales</italic>, and the <italic>Aceterobacteraceae</italic> (<italic>Saccharibacter). Microsporidia</italic> are unicellular, fungal intracellular parasites. Present as spores in the soil, they are ingested and replicate in a wide range of hosts, including insects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Troemel1">[65]</xref>. Well-studied microsporidians in social insects include <italic>Kneallhazia solenopsae</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Fuxa1">[66]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Allen1">[68]</xref> and <italic>Vairimorpha invictae</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Jouvenaz1">[69]</xref> that both infect the fire ant <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic>. <italic>Kneallhazia solenopsae</italic> cause substantial brood reductions, queen debilitation and premature death of infected queens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Williams1">[70]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Oi2">[71]</xref>, and <italic>V. invictae</italic> cause significant reduction in nest growth and higher sensitivity to starvation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Briano1">[72]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Oi3">[73]</xref>. Both of these microsporidia are present in larvae and adults. Bacteria belonging to the <italic>Enterobacteriacae</italic> (<italic>Arsenophonus),</italic> and the <italic>Entomoplasmatales</italic> (particularly <italic>Spiroplasmas</italic>) are known reproductive parasites among various insect species, including social Hymenoptera <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Ishak1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Duron1">[62]</xref>. Screening across taxa and species has revealed that these bacteria are usually found in lower prevalence than <italic>Wolbachia</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Duron1">[62]</xref>, which expression values suggested was also the case for our data. <italic>Arsenophonus</italic> is best known from its association with the parasitic wasp <italic>Nasonia vitripennis</italic>, where it causes elevated death rates among male pupae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Darby1">[74]</xref>, however recent research suggest that it is one of the richest and most widespread genera of insect associates, with effects ranging from male-killing to symbiosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Novkov1">[75]</xref>. <italic>Entomoplasmatales</italic> are also primarily insect associated bacteria, found in a diversity of roles, again ranging from male-killing to beneficial symbiosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Funaro1">[76]</xref>. <italic>Entomoplasmatales</italic> have been found in ant guts, forming a host-specific clade among the army ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Funaro1">[76]</xref>, and <italic>Spiroplasmas</italic> were recently suggested to be prime candidates as a beneficial symbionts in two <italic>Solenopsis</italic> species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Ishak1">[27]</xref>. Several 16S rRNA sequences had their nearest GenBank match to bacteria found in the gut of another ant, <italic>Camponotus fragilis</italic> (GenBank IDs: JN846886 and JN846887). These were classified as <italic>Aceterobacteraceae</italic> by the RDP classifier. <italic>Aceterobacteraceae</italic> have been found in honey bee guts, and one such bacteria, <italic>Saccharibacter,</italic> has also been isolated from pollen, and may hence represent bacteria taken up through foraging <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Martinson1">[77]</xref>. The expression patterns in our data for sequences matching potential intracellular microbes varied and included: present in all ages and castes (e.g. <italic>Acetobacteraceae),</italic> absent only in the old age classes <italic>(Entmoplasmatales),</italic> present in only in new queens and workers <italic>(Microsporidia),</italic> and no discernable pattern (<italic>Arsenophonus).</italic> Both beneficial and pathogenic intracellular microbes may predominantly occur in certain age classes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Engel1">[22]</xref>, hence it is impossible to derive any definitive indication of role from this data.</p><p>Two apparent entire RNA virus genomes were assembled from the <italic>Formica exsecta</italic> transcriptome. Both were positive-sense single-stranded RNA viruses, one belonging to the class Iflaviridae and the other to the Dicistroviridae. These viruses grouped phylogenetically with the KBV, ABV and IAPV viruses that plague apiculture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Maori1">[78]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-De1">[79]</xref>, and with the Solenopsis invicta virus-1 that infects <italic>S. invicta</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Valles1">[80]</xref>. These viruses are rapidly evolving due to their lack of repair mechanisms and often the same virus can infect several different insect hosts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Levitt1">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Singh1">[57]</xref>. The virus genomes assembled from the <italic>F. execta</italic> transcriptome appear rather dissimilar to honey bee viruses, with no more than 75% nucleotide sequence identity to the phylogenetically closest honey bee viruses. Hence, these viruses possibly warrant classification as new viruses, however such verification and analysis (e.g. electron microscopy, negative strand qPCR and epidemiology) is beyond the scope of this study. None of the ants sampled here showed any obvious symptoms similar to those reported for bees with high levels of infection of Dicistroviruses (trembling, paralysis) or Iridoviruses (discolouring), and the pathology and extent of infection in natural ant populations are unknown. Several viruses infecting ants have been described: Solenopsis invicta virus-1, 2 and 3 characterised for <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Valles1">[80]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Valles3">[82]</xref>, and a <italic>Rhabdovirus</italic>, a picorna-like virus and a virus of uncertain classification recently identified from transcriptome data in the Caribbean Crazy ant, <italic>Nylanderia pubens</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Valles4">[83]</xref>. Viruses from several different classes hence appear common among ants.</p><p>One route for RNA viruses to enter insects is through ingestion, e.g two ant species, <italic>Formica rufa</italic> and <italic>Camponotus vagus</italic> were found to have ingested honey bee viruses by feeding on dead <italic>Varroa</italic> in honey bee hives <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Celle1">[84]</xref>, and Valles et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Valles5">[85]</xref>, reported sequences matching a cricket virus gene in ant-derived expressed sequence tag data, thought to originate from laboratory antfeed. In our transcriptome there were sequence matches to <italic>V. destructor,</italic> a mite that attacks the honey bee (<italic>Apis mellifera</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-CoxFoster1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Van1">[86]</xref>, However, there were no sequences matching <italic>Varroa</italic> 18S rRNA, a gene which is used for mite species identification <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Cruickshank1">[87]</xref>. Instead there were 18S rRNA sequence matches to six species of mite from genera with known ant associations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Bonasio1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Nilsson1">[93]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Vnninen1">[94]</xref>. Moreover, expression patterns of sequences matching total mite 18S rRNA and expression values for those sequences matching <italic>V. destructor</italic> were very similar. Hence, sequences matching <italic>Varroa</italic> were likely an artefact as genes from other species of mites are likely to match <italic>V. destructor,</italic> currently the only mite genome available in GenBank. No sequences matching Varroa 18S rRNA were present in the second transcriptome generated from <italic>F. exsecta</italic> ants living in habitat where apiculture is forbidden, yet sequences matching the Iflavirus was present. Sequences matching the Dicistrovirus were not present in this second transcriptome, however this is not surprising since the lowest expression values for sequences matching this virus in our data was in old workers (the age and caste sampled for the Badouin et al. transcriptome).</p><p>Nevertheless, mites (Acari) are ubiquitous and diverse in <italic>Formica</italic> wood ant nests <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-LehtinenTapiola1">[39]</xref>. They associate with ants mainly for dispersal (phoresy), or for feeding on bacteria and detritus in the nest or on the ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Eickwort1">[40]</xref>. Since it is the task of adult workers to forage we would expect the the highest expression values for sequences matching both mites and viruses in this caste and age class if either were indeed ingested. If the viruses were transmitted by mites, we would expect some similarity in expression patterns of the sequences with homology to mite genes and those with homology to viruses. To the contrary, old workers had relatively low expression values for 18S rRNA sequences matching any mites, high expression levels for sequences matching the Iflavirus and low expression values for sequences matching the Dicistrovirus. The highest expression value for 18S rRNA sequences matching mites was found in new queens, which had low expression values for sequences matching the Iflavirus, and relatively high expression values for sequences matching the Dicistrovirus. In short, there appears to be no association in this data between sequences matching mites and expression of sequences matching either of the viruses.</p><p>Some of the microbes for which there were sequence matches quite possible have roles both as beneficial ant symbionts and in the soil or nest environments. Yeasts, for example, are common in the environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Slvikov1">[88]</xref> and are unlikely insect pathogens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Martini1">[89]</xref>. Many insects are dependent on yeasts as sources of sterols and vitamins. A study in <italic>S. invicta</italic> found several yeasts present in the nest and guts of both larvae and workers. These provided nutrients during overwintering, thereby increasing nest survival and productivity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Ba1">[90]</xref>. Among bacteria, <italic>Burkholderiales</italic> and <italic>Pseudomodales</italic> are commonly found in ant guts and are thought to be beneficial symbionts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Anderson1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Ishak1">[27]</xref>, however they are also widespread in soils and may simply have been ingested by <italic>F. exsecta</italic>. <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> are commonly found in acidic environments such as composts, yet some species are also well characterised beneficial gut symbionts in e.g. honey bees and bumble bees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Martinson1">[77]</xref> and have also been recovered from ant guts, although any functional role in ants is unknown <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Anderson1">[26]</xref>. Sequences matching <italic>Burkholderiales, Pseudomodales</italic>, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and yeasts were expressed in all age classes, hence intra- or extracellular origin cannot be determined in this study.</p><p>Common soil bacteria or fungi may also act as opportunistic pathogens. There are several known generalist pathogens in the genus Aspergilli, but none of the species are exclusively entomopathogenic. <italic>Aspergillus ochraceaus</italic> is an example of a common environmental Aspergillus with entomopathogenic properties. This fungi infects the ant <italic>Atta bisphaerica</italic> resulting in about 50% mortality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Ribeiro1">[91]</xref>. Another potentially pathogenic fungi for which there were sequence matches in our data is <italic>Cryptococcus</italic>, which is widely distributed in soils and best known for causing infection in immuno-compromised humans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Kidd1">[92]</xref>. However, strains of <italic>Cryptococcus</italic> have been isolated from dead insects or insect chaff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Kidd1">[92]</xref>, although their role in insects is unknown.</p><p>The remaining sequences matched mainly fungal plant pathogens and common soil bacteria. These may be derived from ant feed or nest material. There were very few sequences matching saprotrophic wood or plant decaying fungi considering that <italic>F. exsecta</italic> mounds are made of plant material (including needles and other material from coniferous trees). The analysis of fungal LSU genes showed the difficulty of molecular identification of fungal species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Nilsson1">[93]</xref> compared to the bacterial classification scheme based on 16S rRNA. Unexpectedly, the entomopathogenic fungi <italic>Metarhizium anisopliae</italic> and <italic>Beauveria bassiana,</italic> common in soil samples in Finland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Vnninen1">[94]</xref>, and known to infect ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Reber1">[95]</xref>, did not match sequences in the transcriptome data. Ants almost certainly carry fungal spores into the nest, however if these fail to germinate in the dry and warm environment of the nests, or on the ants themselves, they will not be detectable in transcriptomic data.</p><p>Two factors are likely to have affected our results. Firstly, a poly-A treatment of the RNA was performed to reduce the non-eukaryotic content in the samples, and secondly, we applied strict criteria for the bioinformatic analysis. As a result, we fully expect that there are even more microbes and other taxa associated with these ants. Certain trends were apparent and we are confident that the biota presented here is truly associated with, and of importance, in <italic>F. exsecta</italic>. Similar to <italic>S. invicta</italic> (in its native range) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Yang1">[21]</xref>, <italic>F. exsecta</italic> is infected by <italic>Wolbachia</italic> and may be infected by several viruses and possibly also microsporidia. Transcriptome data derived from <italic>F. exsecta</italic> showed sequence matches to <italic>Burkholderiales, Lactobacillus Acetobacteraceae</italic> and <italic>Pseudomodales</italic> which are bacterial genera that often form part of the highly distinct bacterial gut communities in social insects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Anderson1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079777-Martinson1">[77]</xref>. There were also sequence matches to common reproductive parasites, of social as well as solitary insects, such as <italic>Entomoplasmatales</italic> and <italic>Arsenophonus.</italic> Our study provides a starting point for further research to establish which of these potential associates are neutral elements, random benefactors, pathogens, or have decisive positive effects on the fitness of <italic>F. exsecta</italic> ants and their nests.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0079777.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><bold>Geographic localities, numbers of </bold><bold><italic>F. exsecta</italic></bold><bold> nests sampled and number of individuals from those nests.</bold></p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0079777.s001.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0079777.s002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><bold>Expression values by sex and caste for all sequence matches in </bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t002"><bold>Tables 2</bold></xref><bold>&#x02013;</bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079777-t004"><bold>4</bold></xref><bold>, from both sequencing providers (Beijing Institute of Genomics, China, (BGI) and Finnish Institute of Molecular Medicine, Finland (FIMM).</bold></p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0079777.s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0079777.s003"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><bold>RDP classifier classification of the fungal large subunit (LSU) gene sequences.</bold></p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0079777.s003.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Jenni Paviala and Claire Morandin for assistance with sampling and RNA extractions, and Owen Rowe for comments on the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0079777-Damon1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Damon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lehembre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oger-Desfeux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ranger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Metatranscriptomics reveals the diversity of genes expressed by eukaryotes in forest soils</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e28967</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22238585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Scott1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Budsberg</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wixon</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balser</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Microbial community structure of leaf-cutter ant fungus gardens and refuse dumps</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e9922</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20360970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Moran1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sabree</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Distinctive gut microbiota of honey bees assessed using deep sampling from individual worker bees</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e36393</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22558460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Gosalbes1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gosalbes</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durb&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pignatelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abellan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez-Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Metatranscriptomic approach to analyze the functional human gut microbiota</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e17447</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21408168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-CoxFoster1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cox-Foster</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Conlan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A metagenomic survey of microbes in honey bee colony collapse disorder</article-title>. <source>Science (New York, NY)</source><volume>318</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>287</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Wittekindt1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wittekindt</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Padhi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Nodeomics: pathogen detection in vertebrate lymph nodes using meta-transcriptomics</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e13432</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20976145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Moore1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gustavsen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ch&#x000e9;nard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The sensitivity of massively parallel sequencing for detecting candidate infectious agents associated with human tissue</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e19838</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21603639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Schluns1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schluns</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crozier</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Molecular and chemical immune defenses in ants (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)</article-title>. <source>Myrmecol News</source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>249</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Cremer1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>SAO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmid-Hempel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Social immunity. Curr. Biol</article-title>. <source>CB</source><volume>17</volume>: <fpage>R693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17714663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Brennan1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title><italic>Drosophila</italic>: the genetics of innate immune system recognition and response. Annu. Rev. Immunol</article-title>. <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>483</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Viljakainen1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Viljakainen L (2008) Evolutionary genetics of immunity and infection in social insects University of Oulu, Finland.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-SivaJothy1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Siva-Jothy</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moret</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rolff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Insect immunity - an evolutionary ecology perspective</article-title>. <source>Adv In Insect Phys</source><volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Schluns2"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schluns H, Crozier YC, Crozier RH (2008) Sequence evolution in bulldog ants (Myrmeciinae). Proceedings of the 4th European meeting of the International Union for the Study of Social Insects. La-Roche-en-Ardenne, Belgium. p. 65.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Simola1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Simola</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wissler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donahue</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Helmkampf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Social insect genomes exhibit dramatic evolution in gene composition and regulation while preserving regulatory features linked to sociality</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source><volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23636946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Cotter1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kilner</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Personal immunity versus social immunity. Behav. Ecol</article-title>. <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>668</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Cotter2"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Topham</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>AJP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kilner</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Fitness costs associated with mounting a social immune response. Ecol. Lett</article-title>. <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1123</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Cremer2"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sixt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Analogies in the evolution of individual and social immunity. Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond., B, Biol. Sci</article-title>. <volume>364</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Oi1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oi</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Ant behavior and microbial pathogens (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)</article-title>. <source>The Florida Entomologist</source><volume>76</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-SchmidHempel1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schmid-Hempel P (1998) Parasites in social insects. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Bourke1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bourke AFG, Franks NR (1995) Social evolution in ants. Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Yang1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valles</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oi</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y-C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Loss of microbial (pathogen) infections associated with recent invasions of the red imported fire ant <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic>. Biol</article-title>. <source>Invasions</source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>3307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3318</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Engel1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The gut microbiota of insects - diversity in structure and function. FEMS Microbiol. Rev</article-title>. <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>735</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Zientz1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zientz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feldhaar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stoll</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Insights into the microbial world associated with ants. Arch. Microbiol</article-title>. <volume>184</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>206</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Stoll1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stoll</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gadau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feldhar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Bacterial microbiota associated with ants of the genus <italic>Tetraponera</italic>. Biol. J. Linn. Soc. Lond</article-title>. <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>399</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>412</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Russell1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldman-Huertas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lohman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Bacterial gut symbionts are tightly linked with the evolution of herbivory in ants. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</article-title>. <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>21236</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21241</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Anderson1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kautz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sullam</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Highly similar microbial communities are shared among related and trophically similar ant species. Mol. Ecol</article-title>. <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>2282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2296</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Ishak1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ishak</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plowes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kellner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Bacterial diversity in <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic> and <italic>Solenopsis geminata</italic> ant colonies characterized by 16S amplicon 454 pyrosequencing. Microb. Ecol</article-title>. <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>831</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Douwes1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Douwes P, Abenius J, Cederberg, Bj&#x000f6;rn Wahlstedt U (2012) Nationalnyckeln till Sveriges flora och fauna - Steklar: Myror - getingar. <italic>Hymenoptera: Formicidae - Vespidae</italic> Artdatabanken/SLU, Uppsala.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Seifert1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A taxonomic revision of the ant subgenus <italic>Coptoformica</italic> Mueller, 1923 <italic>(Hymenoptera, Formicidae)</italic></article-title>. <source>Zoosystema</source><volume>22</volume>: <fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>568</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Czechowski1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Czechowski W, Radchenko A, Czechowska W (2002) The ants (<italic>Hymenoptera, Formicidae)</italic> of Poland. Museum and Institute of Zoology. Poland.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-HaagLiautard1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Haag-Liautard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vitikainen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sundstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Fitness and the level of homozygosity in a social insect. J. Evol. Biol</article-title>. <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>134</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Pamilo1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pamilo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Life span of queens in the ant <italic>Formica exsecta</italic></article-title>. <source>Insectes Soc</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>119</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Werner1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Werner P, Catzeflis F, Cherix D (1979) A propos du polycalisme chez <italic>Formica (Croptoformica) exsecta</italic> Nyl. In: Cherix D, editor. Ecologie des Insectes Socieaux. Lausanne, Switzerland: UIEIS Section Francaise. 115&#x02013;126.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Pisarski1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pisarski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Characteristique de <italic>Formica (Croptoformica) exsecta</italic> Nylander 1946</article-title>. <source>Memorabilia Zoologica</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>38</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Pisarski2"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pisarski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Territoires et territorialisme de <italic>Formica (Croptoformica) exsecta</italic> Nyl</article-title>. <source>Memorabilia Zoologica</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Wenseleers1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wenseleers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Borm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huybrechts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Volckaert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Widespread occurrence of the micro-organism <italic>Wolbachia</italic> in ants. Proc. Biol. Sci</article-title>. <volume>265</volume>: <fpage>1447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1452</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Reuter1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>High levels of multiple <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infection and recombination in the ant <italic>Formica exsecta</italic>. Mol. Biol. Evol</article-title>. <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>748</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>753</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Viljakainen2"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Viljakainen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pamilo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title><italic>Wolbachia</italic> transmission dynamics in <italic>Formica</italic> wood ants. BMC Evol. Biol</article-title>. <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-LehtinenTapiola1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lehtinen, Tapiola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Associations of uropodid, prodinychid, polyaspidid, antennophorid, sejid, microgynid and zerconid mites with ants</article-title>. <source>Entomologisk Tidskrift</source><volume>108</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Eickwort1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eickwort</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Associations of mites with social insects. Annu. Rev. Entomol</article-title>. <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>488</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Pearson1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Improved tools for biological sequence comparison. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</article-title>. <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>2444</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2448</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Grabherr1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome. Nat. Biotechnol</article-title>. <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>644</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>652</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Bonasio1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonasio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mutti</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genomic comparison of the ants <italic>Camponotus floridanus</italic> and <italic>Harpegnathos saltator</italic>. Science</article-title>. <volume>329</volume>: <fpage>1068</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1071</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Suen1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Suen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teiling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abouheif</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The genome sequence of the leaf-cutter ant <italic>Atta cephalotes</italic> reveals insights into its obligate symbiotic lifestyle. PLoS Genet</article-title>. <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002007</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Smith1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zimin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abouheif</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Draft genome of the globally widespread and invasive Argentine ant (<italic>Linepithema humile</italic>). Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</article-title>. <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>5673</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5678</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Smith2"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Helmkampf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zimin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Draft genome of the red harvester ant <italic>Pogonomyrmex barbatus</italic>. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</article-title>. <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>5667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5672</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Wurm1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wurm</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riba-Grognuz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Corona</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nygaard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The genome of the fire ant <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic>. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</article-title>. <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>5679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5684</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Nygaard1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nygaard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schi&#x000f8;tt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wurm</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The genome of the leaf-cutting ant <italic>Acromyrmex echinatior</italic> suggests key adaptations to advanced social life and fungus farming</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source><volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21719571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Wang1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garrity</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tiedje</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Naive Bayesian classifier for rapid assignment of rRNA sequences into the new bacterial taxonomy. Appl. Environ. Microbiol</article-title>. <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>5261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5267</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Cole1"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cardenas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Ribosomal Database Project: improved alignments and new tools for rRNA analysis. Nucleic Acids Res</article-title>. <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>D141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Gouy1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gouy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>SeaView version 4: A multiplatform graphical user interface for sequence alignment and phylogenetic tree building. Mol. Biol. Evol</article-title>. <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>224</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-VanOers1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Van Oers MM (2010) Genomics and biology of Iflaviruses. In: Asgari S, Johnson K, editors. Insect Virology. Caister Academic Press, Norfolk. 231&#x02013;250.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Christian1"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Christian P, Carstens E, Domier L, Johnson J, Johnson K, <etal>et al</etal>. (2005) Dicistroviridae. In: Fauquet CM, Mayo MA, Maniloff J, Desselberger U, Ball LA, editors. Virus Taxonomy VIII. Elsevier Academic Press, San Diego. 783&#x02013;788.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Larkin1"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blackshields</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chenna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McGettigan</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0. Bioinformatics</article-title>. <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2947</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2948</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Felsenstein1"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny Inference Package (Version 3.2)</article-title>. <source>Cladistics</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>165</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Levitt1"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Levitt</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cox-Foster</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rajotte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Cross-species transmission of honey bee viruses in associated arthropods. Virus Res</article-title>. <volume>176</volume>: <fpage>232</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Singh1"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levitt</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rajotte</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ostiguy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>RNA viruses in hymenopteran pollinators: evidence of inter-taxa virus transmission via pollen and potential impact on non-Apis hymenopteran species</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e14357</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21203504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Badouin1"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Badouin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Belkhir</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gregson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galindo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sundstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Transcriptome Characterisation of the ant <italic>Formica exsecta</italic> with new insights into the evolution of desaturase genes in social Hymenoptera</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e68200</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23874539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Wurm2"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wurm</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Uva</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jemielity</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Fourmidable: a database for ant genomics</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19126223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Kurtz1"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phillippy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delcher</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smoot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shumway</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Versatile and open software for comparing large genomes. Genome Biol</article-title>. <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>R12</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Keller1"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liautard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sundstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Sex ratio and <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infection in the ant <italic>Formica exsecta</italic></article-title>. <source>Heredity</source><volume>87</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11703514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Duron1"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duron</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bouchon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boutin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bellamy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The diversity of reproductive parasites among arthropods: <italic>Wolbachia</italic> do not walk alone. BMC Biol</article-title>. <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Stevens1"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fialho</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Male-killing, nematode infections, bacteriophage infection, and virulence of cytoplasmic bacteria in the genus <italic>Wolbachia</italic></article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Ecol Syst</source><volume>32</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>545</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Russell2"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>JAR</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The ants (<italic>Hymenoptera: Formicidae</italic>) are unique and enigmatic hosts of prevalent <italic>Wolbachia</italic> (Alphaproteobacteria) symbionts, Myrmecol News</article-title>. <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Troemel1"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Troemel</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>New models of microsporidiosis: infections in Zebrafish, <italic>C. elegans</italic>, and honey bee. PLoS Pathog</article-title>. <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1001243</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Fuxa1"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fuxa</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milks</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sokolova</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Interaction of an entomopathogen with an insect social form: an epizootic of <italic>Thelohania solenopsae</italic> (Microsporidia) in a population of the red imported fire ant, <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic>. J. Invertebr. Pathol</article-title>. <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Knell1"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Knell</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hazard</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Light and electron microscope study of <italic>Thelohania solenopsae</italic> (Microsporida: Protozoa) in the red imported fire ant, <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic>. J. Invertebr. Pathol</article-title>. <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>192</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Allen1"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buren</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Microsporidan and fungal diseases of <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic> Buren in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Journal of New York Entomological Society</source><volume>82</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>130</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Jouvenaz1"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jouvenaz</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title><italic>Vairimorpha invictae</italic> N. Sp. (Microspora: Microsporida), a parasite of the red imported fire ant, <italic>Solenopsis invict</italic>a Buren (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) 2. J. Eukaryot. Microbiol</article-title>. <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>461</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Williams1"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oi</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knue</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Infection of red imported fire ant (<italic>Hymenoptera: Formicidae</italic>) colonies with the entomopathogen <italic>Thelohania solenopsae</italic> (Microsporidia: Thelohaniidae). J. Econ. Entomol</article-title>. <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Oi2"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oi</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Impact of <italic>Thelohania solenopsae</italic> (Microsporidia: Thelohaniidae) on polygyne colonies of red imported fire ants (Hymenoptera: Formicidae). J. Econ. Entomol</article-title>. <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>558</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>562</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Briano1"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Briano</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Natural occurrence and laboratory studies of the fire ant pathogen <italic>Vairimorpha invictae</italic> (Microsporida: Burenellidae) in Argentina. Environ. Entomol</article-title>. <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>894</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Oi3"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oi</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Briano</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valles</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Transmission of <italic>Vairimorpha invictae</italic> (Microsporidia: Burenellidae) infections between red imported fire ant (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) colonies. J. Invertebr. Pathol</article-title>. <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>115</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Darby1"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Darby</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilkes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Werren</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Characteristics of the genome of <italic>Arsenophonus nasoniae</italic>, son-killer bacterium of the wasp <italic>Nasonia</italic>. Insect Mol. Biol</article-title>. <volume>19</volume> Suppl 1<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Novkov1"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nov&#x000e1;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hypsa</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title><italic>Arsenophonus</italic>, an emerging clade of intracellular symbionts with a broad host distribution. BMC Microbiol</article-title>. <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Funaro1"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Funaro</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kronauer</surname><given-names>DJC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldman-Huertas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Army ants harbor a host-specific clade of <italic>Entomoplasmatales</italic> bacteria. Appl. Environ. Microbiol</article-title>. <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>346</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>350</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Martinson1"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martinson</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Danforth</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Minckley</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rueppell</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tingek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A simple and distinctive microbiota associated with honey bees and bumble bees. Mol. Ecol</article-title>. <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>628</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Maori1"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maori</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lavi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mozes-Koch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gantman</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peretz</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Isolation and characterization of Israeli acute paralysis virus, a dicistrovirus affecting honeybees in Israel: evidence for diversity due to intra- and inter-species recombination. J. Gen. Virol</article-title>. <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>3428</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3438</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-De1"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De</surname><given-names>MirandaJR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drebot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Complete nucleotide sequence of Kashmir bee virus and comparison with acute bee paralysis virus. J. Gen. Virol</article-title>. <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>2263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2270</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Valles1"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Valles</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A picorna-like virus from the red imported fire ant, <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic>: initial discovery, genome sequence, and characterization</article-title>. <source>Virology</source><volume>328</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15380366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Valles2"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Valles</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Isolation and characterization of Solenopsis invicta virus 3, a new positive-strand RNA virus infecting the red imported fire ant, <italic>Solenopsis invicta.</italic></article-title>. <source>Virology</source><volume>388</volume>: <fpage>354</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19403154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Valles3"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Valles</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A new positive-strand RNA virus with unique genome characteristics from the red imported fire ant, <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic></article-title>. <source>Virology</source><volume>365</volume>: <fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17477949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Valles4"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Valles</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oi</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X-X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buss</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Metatranscriptomics and pyrosequencing facilitate discovery of potential viral natural enemies of the invasive Caribbean crazy ant, <italic>Nylanderia pubens</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e31828</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22384082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Celle1"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Celle</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schurr</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cougoule</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Detection of Chronic bee paralysis virus (CBPV) genome and its replicative RNA form in various hosts and possible ways of spread. Virus Res</article-title>. <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>284</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Valles5"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Valles</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Expressed sequence tags from the red imported fire ant, <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic>: Annotation and utilization for discovery of viruses. J. Invertebr. Pathol</article-title>. <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Van1"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Van Der Geest LPS, Elliot SL, Breeuwer JAJ, Beerling AAM (n.d.) Diseases of Mites. Exp. Appl. Acarol</article-title>. <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>560</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Cruickshank1"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cruickshank</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular markers for the phylogenetics of mites and ticks</article-title>. <source>Syst Appl Acarol</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Slvikov1"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sl&#x000e1;vikov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vadkertiov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The diversity of yeasts in the agricultural soil. J. Basic Microbiol</article-title>. <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>430</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>436</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Martini1"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Applicata</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Biodiversity and conservation of yeasts. Biodivers. Conserv</article-title>. <source>1</source><volume>333</volume>: <fpage>324</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>333</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Ba1"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ba</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Yeast biota of the red imported fire ant. Mycol. Res</article-title>. <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>740</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>746</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Ribeiro1"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>MMR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seide</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>BMR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Della Lucia</surname><given-names>TMC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Diversity of fungi associated with <italic>Atta bisphaerica</italic> (Hymenoptera: Formicidae): The activity of <italic>Aspergillus ochraceus</italic> and <italic>Beauveria bassiana</italic></article-title>. <source>Psyche (Camb Mass)</source><volume>2012</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Kidd1"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sorrell</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Isolation of two molecular types of <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> var. <italic>gattii</italic> from insect frass. Med. Mycol</article-title>. <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Nilsson1"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ryberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kristiansson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abarenkov</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Taxonomic reliability of DNA sequences in public sequence databases: a fungal perspective</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>1</volume>: <fpage>e59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183689</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Vnninen1"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>V&#x000e4;nninen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Distribution and occurrence of four entomopathogenic fungi in Finland: effect of geographical location, habitat type and soil type. Mycol. Res</article-title>. <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0079777-Reber1"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chapuisat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Diversity, prevalence and virulence of fungal entomopathogens in colonies of the ant <italic>Formica selysi</italic></article-title>. <source>Insectes Soc</source><volume>59</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>239</lpage></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>