<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jexbot</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3638818</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23487304</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert049</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification of microRNA targets in tomato fruit development using high-throughput sequencing and degradome analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karlova</surname><given-names>Rumyana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"><sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Haarst</surname><given-names>Jan C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maliepaard</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van de Geest</surname><given-names>Henri</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bovy</surname><given-names>Arnaud G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lammers</surname><given-names>Michiel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Angenent</surname><given-names>Gerco C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Maagd</surname><given-names>Ruud A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><sup>1</sup><institution>Laboratory of Molecular Biology, Wageningen University</institution>, <addr-line>6700 ET Wageningen</addr-line>, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="AF0002"><sup>2</sup><institution>Business Unit Bioscience, Plant Research International</institution>, <addr-line>6700 AP Wageningen</addr-line>, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="AF0003"><sup>3</sup><institution>Business Unit Biodiversity and Breeding, Plant Research International</institution>, <addr-line>6700 AP Wageningen</addr-line>, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="AF0004"><sup>4</sup><institution>Centre for BioSystems Genomics (CBSG)</institution>, <addr-line>6700 AB Wageningen</addr-line>, <country>The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">*Present address: Department of Molecular Plant Physiology, University of Utrecht, 3584 CH Utrecht, The Netherlands</corresp><corresp id="c2">&#x02020;To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>Ruud.deMaagd@wur.nl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>64</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1863</fpage><lpage>1878</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(2) [2013].</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) play important roles in plant development through regulation of gene expression by mRNA degradation or translational inhibition. Despite the fact that tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) is the model system for studying fleshy fruit development and ripening, only a few experimentally proven miRNA targets are known, and the role of miRNA action in these processes remains largely unknown. Here, by using parallel analysis of RNA ends (PARE) for global identification of miRNA targets and comparing four different stages of tomato fruit development, a total of 119 target genes of miRNAs were identified. Of these, 106 appeared to be new targets. A large part of the identified targets (56) coded for transcription factors. Auxin response factors, as well as two known ripening regulators, <italic>COLORLESS NON-RIPENING</italic> (<italic>CNR</italic>) and <italic>APETALA2a</italic> (<italic>SlAP2a</italic>), with developmentally regulated degradation patterns were identified. The levels of the intact messenger of both <italic>CNR</italic> and <italic>AP2a</italic> are actively modulated during ripening, by miR156/157 and miR172, respectively. Additionally, two TAS3-mRNA loci were identified as targets of miR390. Other targets such as <italic>ARGONAUTE 1</italic> (<italic>AGO1</italic>), shown to be involved in miRNA biogenesis in other plant species, were identified, which suggests a feedback loop regulation of this process. In this study, it is shown that miRNA-guided cleavage of mRNAs is likely to play an important role in tomato fruit development and ripening.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key words:</title><kwd>Degradome</kwd><kwd>fruit development</kwd><kwd>microRNA</kwd><kwd>post-transcriptional regulation</kwd><kwd>tomato</kwd><kwd>transcription factors.</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are small, 21&#x02013;22 nucleotide RNA molecules encoded in the genomes of plants, animals, and even viruses. They are derived from single-stranded RNA precursors that can form stem&#x02013;loop structures (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Bartel, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Chen, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Song <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). MiRNAs regulate the expression of genes by binding to complementary sequences in specific mRNAs. This binding leads either to cleavage-induced degradation of the mRNA or suppression of its translation. Both processes eventually result in down-regulation of the product of the target gene (<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Meyers <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). In plants, the complementarity between miRNA and its targets is very high. The cleavage of the target mRNA occurs in the middle of the mRNA&#x02013;miRNA duplex (between the 10th and 11th nucleotide from the 5&#x02019; end of the miRNA) (<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Rhoades <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">German <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). A miRNA may regulate the expression of multiple genes, while it is also possible that multiple miRNAs control a single gene. Therefore, the identification of their target mRNAs is essential for the functional analysis of miRNAs.</p><p content-type="indent">Many plant miRNAs are conserved among species and have been implicated in processes such as development, abiotic stress tolerance, signal transduction, and resistance to pathogens (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Jones-Rhoades <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Ori <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Sun, 2011</xref>). Recently, using next-generation sequencing technology, many new, non-conserved miRNAs with low abundance could be identified. For example, high-throughput sequencing was first used to identify tomato small RNAs, including miRNAs from young green fruits and, more recently, from several fruit developmental stages (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Mohorianu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Zuo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). In these studies, 103 conserved miRNAs belonging to 24 families and 10 non-conserved miRNAs comprising nine families were identified. The targets of many of these miRNAs were predicted to be transcription factors (TFs). These include, for example, <italic>COLORLESS NON-RIPENING</italic> (<italic>CNR</italic>), a gene encoding a SQUAMOSA promoter-binding protein (SBP) (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Manning <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), a positive regulator of tomato fruit ripening, and a tomato <italic>APETALA2</italic> (<italic>SlAP2a</italic>) gene that was shown to be a negative regulator of ripening (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Chung <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karlova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). These two examples are members of TF families, of which some members may be targets of miR156/157 or miR172, respectively. Indeed, <italic>CNR</italic> was shown to be an <italic>in vivo</italic> target of miR156 in tomato (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), but the importance, or even the occurrence during ripening, of miRNA-directed cleavage for both genes is unknown. Thus, identifying miRNAs that regulate the expression of TFs controlling tomato fruit development and ripening, or of genes otherwise involved in these processes, will contribute to a better understanding of the regulation of fleshy fruit development. Moreover, the recent annotation of the complete tomato genome sequence (<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Tomato Genome Consortium, 2012</xref>) allows for miRNA&#x02013;mRNA pair identification on a genome-wide scale.</p><p content-type="indent">High-throughput degradome library sequencing, or parallel analysis of RNA ends (PARE), has been developed for genome-wide-scale identification of miRNA target genes. This method was successfully used to discover many new miRNA&#x02013;mRNA target pairs in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, rice, soybean, a moss, and grapevine (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Addo-Quaye <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">German <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Pantaleo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Song <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Here the high-throughput degradome library sequencing for global identification of targets of miRNAs from four different stages of tomato fruit development is described. New target genes of miRNAs were detected, many of which encoded TFs, which hints at the importance of miRNAs in regulating tomato fruit development. Known ripening regulators such as the <italic>CNR</italic> and <italic>AP2a</italic> TFs were also identified as targets of miR156 and miR172, respectively, with developmentally regulated degradation patterns in tomato fruit. The findings suggest the important role of miRNAs in tomato fruit development starting from the initiation of the fruit until the final ripe stage.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s3"><title>Plant material</title><p>Tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) variety &#x02018;Ailsa Craig&#x02019; plants were grown under standard greenhouse conditions. At anthesis, flowers were labelled, and developing fruits were harvested at 5 DPA (days post-anthesis), mature green (MG), breaker (Br), and red ripe (RR) stage (7 d post-breaker).</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Library preparation and sequencing</title><p>Fruits were frozen in liquid nitrogen, ground, and RNA was extracted using an InviTrap Spin Plant RNA mini kit (Stratec, Berlin, Germany). Purified poly(A) RNA was used to produce PARE libraries by Vertis Biotechologie AG (Freising, Germany) essentially following the protocol of <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">German <italic>et al.</italic> (2008</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) with slight modifications for high-throughput sequencing. Following <italic>Mme</italic>I digestion, the resulting 42bp fragments were gel purified and ligated to Illumina 3&#x02019; TruSeq adaptors (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA). Subsequently, the ligation products were PCR-amplified with a common 5&#x02019; primer and library-specific index primers for multiplex sequencing. Pooled libraries were sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq 2000 by ServiceXS BV (Leiden, The Netherlands) and upon deconvolution yielded ~26&#x02013;36 million raw reads per library. The sequence data from this study were submitted to the Gene Expression Omnibus repository under accession number GSE42661.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Sequence analysis</title><p>Raw reads were processed for removal of 5&#x02019; and 3&#x02019; adaptor sequences and filtered for quality, oligo(A) reads up to 15As, for tomato chloroplast DNA, and for small non-coding RNAs as present in the Rfam 10.1 database (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Gardner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). This was performed using parts of the FASTX Toolkit, version 0.0.13 (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit/">http://hannonlab.cshl.edu/fastx_toolkit/</uri>), and Vmatch version 2.0 (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vmatch.de/">http://www.vmatch.de/</uri>), wrapped in Perl and Bash scripts. After filtering, the remaining reads were mapped on the sense strand of the ITAG Release 2.3 cDNA models (SL2.40 genome build) using SHRiMP v2.0 (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">David <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) allowing one mismatch and retaining only the best scoring hit or hits in the event of equally scoring hits. Mapped reads were matched to potential miRNA target sites in tomato cDNAs, identified using the TargetFinder v1.6 script (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Allen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Fahlgren <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), using an updated version of the CleaveLand pipeline (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Addo-Quaye <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009<italic>a</italic>
</xref>), CleaveLand v3.0.1 (kindly provided by Dr M. Axtell), according to the instructions of the author. In order to allow for inaccurate target cleavage or variations in miRNA 5&#x02019; ends, the pipeline was modified to recognize targets cleaved at the 9th or 11th position of the miRNA, as well as at the 10th position. In CleaveLand 3, per single miRNA the likelihood for one or more random matches, at a given position, to the degradome data is calculated, using the binomial distribution. Here, the binomial probability is the fraction of eligible bases occupied by the degradome data, and the number of &#x02018;trials&#x02019; for the binomial distribution is the cumulative number of alignments at a given score. Because of the large number of likelihoods that are calculated, a false discovery rate (FDR) correction was applied, for each category, using the FDR procedure of <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Benjamini and Hochberg (1995</xref>), to give <italic>q</italic>-values that are adjusted for multiple testing and that can be interpreted in terms of the expected FDR at a chosen threshold. Tag numbers for any position were normalized for library size by using the formula TP10M (tags per 10 million)= (raw abundance/total filtered tags&#x02013;cDNA matches)&#x000d7;10 000 000.</p><p content-type="indent">Overlap between tags and coordinates of gene models, untranslated regions (UTRs), coding sequences (CDSs), exons, and introns (kindly provided by Stephane Rombauts), extracted with BedTools (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Quinlan and Hall, 2010</xref>), was determined using SAMtools (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Gene expression analysis</title><p>For comparison of degradome tag frequency and gene expression analysed by microarray hybridization, PARE-derived sequences from each library were treated as RNAseq data in the CLC Genomics Workbench (CLC bio, Aarhus, Denmark), giving a normalized expression value [reads per kilobase transcript per million reads (RKPM)] for all four libraries. Expression data were independently derived from MG, Br/turning, and RR stage cv. Ailsa Craig fruit RNA hybridization to the Affymetrix EU-SOL TOM3 microarray. Hybridizations were performed in triplicate with independent biological samples, background-corrected, and normalized. The methods and gene expression data from this study were submitted to the Gene Expression Omnibus repository under accession number GSE42783.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Gene expression analysis by quantitative PCR</title><p>RNA extraction, cDNA synthesis, and real-time quantitative PCR (qPCR) were performed as described before (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karlova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). The following primer pairs were used: <italic>AP2a</italic> spanning the miRNA target site (AGACTCCGAGCAGCAACAATGTAGG and TCCTTATTATCTGCTGGGGGAATCC), AP2a 3&#x02019; UTR (CC CCAGCAGATAATAAGGACTCAA and GAAATTAATGAAT GGTCAAGGTCTC), <italic>CNR</italic> spanning the miRNA target site (GCA TCAATGGCAGCCAAATAACC and CGGCTTATTCTTTTTGT CCTTCCC) and CNR 3&#x02019; UTR (TTCCCGGATTTCTAAGCAA ATTGT and GTTGGAATGTCAACATGGATATGCA).</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>RLM-5&#x02019;RACE</title><p>Total RNA (15 &#x000b5;g) from MG stage fruits was purified using TriPure isolation reagent (Roche, The Netherlands). mRNA was purified using the Dynabeads mRNA purification kit (Life Technologies, CA, USA). RNA ligase-mediated rapid amplification of 5&#x02019; cDNA ends (RLM-5&#x02019;RACE) was performed with the FirstChoice RLM-RACE kit according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (Ambion), with gene-specific primers for the <italic>SlDRM5</italic> gene: 5&#x02019;-AGACCGTCCCTGCTCACCCT-3&#x02019; and 5&#x02019;-GTTGTTCTAAGCGGTCTCCA-3&#x02019;. The final PCR product was extracted and purified from a 2% agarose gel, cloned into pGEMT-easy (Promega, Madison, WI, USA), and plasmid DNA from 10 different colonies was sequenced.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Results</title><sec id="s10"><title>Degradome library generation, sequencing, and sequence analysis</title><p>In order to identify targets of known and putative miRNAs from tomato, PARE libraries (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Addo-Quaye <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">German <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) of tomato cv. Ailsa Craig fruits of four developmental stages [5 days after pollination (5 DAP), MG, Br, and RR] were prepared. Between 26 and 36 million short sequence reads were obtained from each library, representing the 5&#x02019; ends of uncapped, polyadenylated RNAs. The reads were subsequently trimmed and filtered for contaminating small ribosomal and nuclear RNAs from the Rfam database as well as for organellar RNAs. The filtered tag reads were mapped on the ITAG v2.3 tomato predicted cDNA set, as well as on exons, introns, CDSs, and 5&#x02019;- or 3&#x02019;-UTRs separately (results shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> available at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Approximately 80&#x02013;85% of all filtered tags could be mapped to the (predicted) <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> transcriptome, suggesting that part of the tags map to as yet unannotated genes. A relatively large fraction (10%) mapped on regions annotated as introns, suggesting either erroneous annotation or the frequent retention of introns by alternative splicing. Similar findings have been reported previously for the degradome analysis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and rice (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">German <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). In the present analysis, at least one specific tag could be detected for an average of 25 000 out of the ~35 000 predicted cDNAs in each of the four libraries, and, after RNAseq analysis of the data, 20 976 cDNAs showing at least 1 RKPM and 12 239 genes showing &#x02265;10 RKPM, demonstrating the great depth of coverage of the tomato transcriptome in these experiments.</p><p content-type="indent">Previous studies revealed that the miRNA-guided cleavage is quite precisely between the 10th and 11th nucleotide from the 5&#x02019; end of the miRNA in the complementary region of the target transcript. Therefore, the 5&#x02019; position of tags that were mapped to tomato cDNAs were matched to predicted miRNA target sites (position 10 of the miRNA) using the CleaveLand pipeline version 3.0.1, a modified version of the original pipeline (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Addo-Quaye <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009<italic>a</italic>
</xref>). In this pipeline, tags are first mapped on cDNAs and the number of tags with the 5&#x02019; nucleotide corresponding to each position in the mRNA is counted, which can be depicted in a t (target)-plot. t-plot peaks corresponding to position 10 of an aligned miRNA are reported (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Additionally, to be able to capture products of less accurate cleavage, as well as to account for naturally occurring variation in miRNA length at its 5&#x02019;-processing site, the procedure was repeated for cleavage positions 9 and 11. As noted before (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Addo-Quaye <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), processes other than miRNA-directed cleavage (e.g. decapping followed by 5&#x02019;&#x02013;3&#x02019; breakdown of mRNA) may give rise to uncapped mRNA fragments that were also detected by the procedure, and indeed many tags and t-plot peaks not corresponding to a known miRNA target site were observed. For these reasons, the total number of tags detected per transcript is generally also representative of its expression level in a certain fruit developmental stage. This is demonstrated by the correlation between normalized tag numbers per kilobase transcript per million reads (presented as RKPM) from the libraries in this study and independently derived microarray expression data for comparable samples (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Target plots of validated target mRNAs. The abundance of each sequenced read is plotted as a function of the position of its 5&#x02019; end in the transcript. In red are the peaks of signatures at the predicted cleavage site of the corresponding miRNAs (arrows). (A) Cleavage features in <italic>SlAP2a</italic> mRNA by miR172a from the breaker (Br) fruit stage degradome library. (B) Cleavage features in <italic>CNR</italic> mRNA by miR156a at the Br fruit stage. (C) Cleavage features in <italic>SlDRM5</italic> mRNA by miR396 at the Br fruit stage. (D) RLM-RACE confirmation of the SlDRM5 cleavage site by miR396. The numbers above the vertical arrow indicate the number of sequences found at the exact miR396 cleavage site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert049_f0001"/></fig><p content-type="indent">CleaveLand classifies t-plot peaks in four categories (0&#x02013;4), with peaks of categories 0&#x02013;3 having &#x0003e;1 read per peak. Category 0 are peaks that represent a single maximum in a particular transcript, category 1 are peaks that are equal to the maximum, with more than one maximum per transcript, category 2 are peaks lower than the maximum but higher than the median of a transcript, and category 3 are peaks with an equal or less than median number of reads (for examples, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Category 4 peaks have only 1 read. The statistical significance of an observed peak&#x02013;miRNA match is represented by the <italic>P</italic>-value, the likelihood of a peak in a particular position occurring by chance, which is determined by both the total number of nucleotides/positions for each category and the miRNA&#x02013;target alignment score. This score was determined by the Targetfinder script (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Allen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Fahlgren <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), where all alignments with a penalty score up to 7 were included (listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>). For this procedure, all miRNAs reported to be present or expressed in tomato, collected from miRbase (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="www.mirbase.org">www.mirbase.org</uri>) and from the literature, were used. The entire output can be viewed in the Gene Expression Omnibus repository under accession number GSE42661. The protocol was repeated with the tomato Unigene collection from the Solanaceae Genomics Network (SGN) database, in order to find targets in transcripts that have not been mapped on the tomato genome sequence and hence have no corresponding cDNA sequence. This resulted in identification of nine additional targets with category 0 or 1 peaks (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>miRNA&#x02013;target mRNA pairs with a category 0 or 1 peak identified in at least two libraries or in one library with q-value &#x02264;0.05 and cleavage peak height &#x0003e;1 TP10M.A comprehensive list of all category 0 and 1 peaks, with <italic>P</italic>- and q-values and normalized read numbers can be found in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S3</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online. </p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target mRNA</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITAG2.3 annotation</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Common name</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cleavage position</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak categories</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR156/157</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g077920.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Squamosa promoter binding-like protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g045560.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Squamosa promoter binding-like protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlySBP2/SlSPL2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g012040.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Squamosa promoter binding-like protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlySBP6b/SlSPL6b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g015510.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Squamosa promoter binding-like protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlySBP10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g015840.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Squamosa promoter binding-like protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlySBP13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g062980.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Squamosa promoter binding-like protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc10g078700.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Squamosa promoter binding-like protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlySBP15/SlSPL15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR158</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No category 0 or 1 peaks with P &#x02264;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR159</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g009070.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAMyb-like1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g090530.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g073640.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAMYB-like2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g098770.1.1<sup>a</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xylanase inhibitor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR160</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g075150.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auxin response factor 16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARF16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc11g013470.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auxin response factor 17 (Fragment)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARF17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc11g069500.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auxin response factor 16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARF10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hendelman <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR161</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No category 0 or 1 peaks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR162</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc10g008310.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown Protein (AHRD V1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR164</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc03g115850.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAC domain protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g069710.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAC domain protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g062840.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAC domain protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g066330.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAC domain protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR165/166</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g066500.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">class III homeodomain-leucine zipper</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc12g044410.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">class III homeodomain-leucine zipper</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR167</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No category 0 or 1 peaks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR168</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g072300.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARGONAUTE 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGN-U563432</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGO1-1 (Nicotiana tabacum)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR169</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g068500.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thioredoxin o</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g068930.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jasmonate ZIM-domain protein 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g006930.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear transcription factor Y subunit A-3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g087240.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear transcription factor Y subunit A-3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc03g121940.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear transcription factor Y subunit A-3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g062210.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear transcription factor Y subunit A-3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR170/171</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g090950.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GRAS family transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g078800.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GRAS family transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc11g013150.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GRAS family transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR172</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g064960.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2-like ethylene-responsive transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlAP2b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g093150.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2-like ethylene-responsive transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlAP2c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Itaya <italic>et al.</italic> (2008); Moxon <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc03g044300.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2-like ethylene-responsive transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlAP2a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g049800.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2-like ethylene-responsive transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g075510.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2-like ethylene-responsive transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlAP2e</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc09g007260.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2-like ethylene-responsive transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc10g084340.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2-like ethylene-responsive transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc11g072600.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AP2-like ethylene-responsive transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlAP2d</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGN-U584830</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutamate permease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR173</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc10g005490.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein strawberry notch homolog 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR319</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g062680.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcription factor CYCLOIDEA (TCP transcription factor)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lanceolate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ori <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc12g014140.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcription factor CYCLOIDEA (TCP transcription factor)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g077250.2.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Transcription factor CYCLOIDEA (TCP transcription factor)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g012840.1.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Transcription factor CYCLOIDEA (TCP transcription factor)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g053410.2.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Transcription factor CYCLOIDEA (TCP transcription factor)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g048370.2.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Transcription factor CYCLOIDEA (TCP transcription factor)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g048390.1.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Transcription factor CYCLOIDEA (TCP transcription factor)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR390</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g058100.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown Protein (AHRD V1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sly-TASI3a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGN-U587265 (2&#x000d7;)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sly-TASI3b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc12g098430.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actin-related protein 2/3 complex subunit 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR393</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g079190.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auxin F-box protein 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g008780.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auxin F-box protein 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIR1-like protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc09g074520.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auxin F-box protein 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIR1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR394</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g015520.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-box family protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR395</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g054730.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High affinity sulphate transporter 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR396</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc12g096070.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth-regulating factor 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g005430.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth-regulating factor 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc03g082430.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth-regulating factor 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g075950.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth-regulating factor 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g083230.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth-regulating factor 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc10g083510.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth-regulating factor 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g041640.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth-regulating factor 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g077510.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth regulating factor 1 (Fragment)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g066730.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MADS-box protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g062740.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA (Cytosine-5-)-methyltransferase 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SlDRM5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc12g088670.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cathepsin B-like cysteine proteinase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDI-65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g032870.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02019;-Tyrosyl-DNA phosphodiesterase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g054050.2.1<sup>a</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutamate decarboxylase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR397</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No category 0 or 1 peaks with P &#x0003c; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR398</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g082890.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S-like RNase (Fragment)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc11g066390.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superoxide dismutase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR399</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc03g096770.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown Protein (AHRD V1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc12g015630.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genomic DNA chromosome 5 P1 clone MDF20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR403</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g069260.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARGONAUTE 1<sup>c</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR408</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g104400.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blue copper protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g074740.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blue copper-like protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR414</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No category 0 or 1 peaks with P &#x0003c; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR482/miR-Y</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No category 0 or 1 peaks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR828</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No category 0 or 1 peaks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR858</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g053330.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g065910.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myb-related transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc12g049300.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g034000.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myb-related transcription factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc03g083260.1.1<sup>a</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown Protein (AHRD V1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR894</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g095920.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">O-Methyltransferase family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR1916</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g014150.2.1<sup>a</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photosystem II stability/assembly factor Ycf48-like protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR1917</bold>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g059920.1.1<sup>a</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sesquiterpene synthase 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR1918</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g005330.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR1919</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No category 0 or 1 peaks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR5301*/472/482</bold>
<sup><bold>b</bold></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc11g065780.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs, resistance protein fragment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGN-U571260</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGN-U598669</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g036270.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g005770.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g009180.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g076000.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g009070.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nbs, resistance protein fragment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGN-U585460</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutamate permease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mohorianu <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g025160.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arsenite ATPase transporter (Eurofung)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mohorianu <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR4376</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No category 0 or 1 peaks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR5301</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc09g020000.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYB-like TF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR5302</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g078760.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5g47580/MNJ7_17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR5303</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g079800.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth-regulating factor 12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGN-U564554</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S-locus F-box-like protein b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>mir6022</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g005720.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LRR receptor-like serine/threonine- protein kinase, RLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g005760.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LRR receptor-like serine/threonine- protein kinase, RLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g005870.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LRR receptor-like serine/threonine- protein kinase, RLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g006550.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LRR receptor-like serine/threonine- protein kinase, RLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g052920.2.1<sup>a</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown Protein (AHRD V1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR6023</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc08g075710.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amino acid permease-like protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc09g055760.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-snare (AHRD V1***- Q2HS23_ MEDTR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR6024</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g005330.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein with an R1-specific domain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g008070.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc10g008230.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc11g070000.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nbs, resistance protein fragment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGN-U569340</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGN-U583156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR6026</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No category 0 or 1 peaks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>miR6027</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g009120.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g009150.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g009660.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g012890.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein with an R1-specific domain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc05g012910.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein with an R1-specific domain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc09g098130.1.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc10g047320.1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cc-nbs-lrr, resistance protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic>a</italic></sup> Targets with a <italic>P</italic>-value &#x02265;0.05</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic>b</italic></sup> miR5301*, miR472, and miR482 have overlapping target sites and similar predicted targets. Sly-miR482 (miR-Y in Moxon <italic>et al</italic>.) is different from the canonical miR482.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic>c</italic></sup> Although the iTAG annotation lists this gene as an <italic>AGO1</italic> homologue, it is in fact more homologous to the <italic>Arabidopsis AGO2</italic> gene (AT1G31280).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p content-type="indent">Based on the signature abundance at the putative miRNA target sites and as reported before (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Addo-Quaye <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2009<italic>b</italic>
</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Song <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), the cleavage products have been categorized into three classes. class I miRNA-guided cleavage products are the most significant (t-plots with category 0 and 1 peak and <italic>P</italic>-value &#x02264;0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The targets belonging to this class are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and discussed below. A comprehensive list of category 0 or 1 targets, their position within the transcript, peak height, and <italic>P</italic>-value for each library can be found in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S3</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online. Additionally, a Benjamini&#x02013;Hochberg correction was performed for multiple testing of the <italic>P</italic>-values, and the resulting <italic>q</italic>-values (FDRs) for categories 0 and 1 are reported. In the class II targets category (t-plots with category 2 peaks), the signature abundance was higher than the median on the transcript, but below the maximum. In total, for all four libraries 3956 putative cDNA targets belonging to class II were found. The rest of the cleavage signatures with low abundance were grouped in class III (category 3 and 4 peaks); 4444 targets for the four libraries together were found.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Identification of conserved and non-conserved targets of conserved miRNAs</title><p>Two categories of miRNAs, conserved and non-conserved, are present in land plants (for a review, see <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Sun, 2011</xref>). Conserved miRNAs are present in different plant lineages, often have high expression, and are encoded by multiple loci in the genomes. Non-conserved miRNAs are usually species specific and expressed at low levels, encoded by a single gene. From the 24 conserved miRNA families in tomato (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Mohorianu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Zhai <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Zuo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), targets classified as category I were identified for 21 of them (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). For miR167, miR397, and miR827, no targets grouped in class I were found. In most cases in plants, targets of an miRNA family belong mainly to the same gene family (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). However, some miRNAs can additionally cleave targets not belonging to the conserved target gene families (<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Sun, 2011</xref>). For most of the conserved miRNAs in the present study, members of the conserved target gene families were found as targets in tomato as well. Many appear also to target one or more non-conserved target genes. Of the latter, a large fraction had low tag counts at the peak position and a <italic>P</italic>-value &#x0003e;0.05, and therefore are considered not significant in this study. However, some are significant and warrant further study of their relevance in tomato. The miRNA that was found to target the highest number of different genes from unrelated families and all belonging to class I targets, is miR396, which was shown previously to be equally expressed in the tomato fruit from the MG stage onwards (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Mohorianu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). For instance, miR396 has been found to target a 50S ribosomal protein only in rice, and growth-related factor (GRF) TF genes in diverse species (<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Sun, 2011</xref>). From the 10 predicted tomato GRF TF targets of miR396, strong evidence (category 0 peaks) was found for eight of them (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Besides the GRFs, it was found that in tomato fruits miR396 also targets homologues of a MADS box gene, a DNA (cytosine-5-)-methyltransferase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>) gene, a cathepsin B-like cysteine proteinase gene, and a tyrosyl-DNA phosphodiesterase gene (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), in addition to several genes with lower significance (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). The miR396-directed processing of the DNA (cytosine-5-)-methyltransferase cDNA was independently confirmed by RLM-RACE analysis of the mRNA degradation products (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>). This gene was identified as one of four tomato domains rearranged methyltransferases (DRMs), <italic>SlDRM5</italic>, putatively involved in DNA methylation (<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Teyssier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">For some conserved miRNAs, such as miR162, only a few targets have been validated in any other species, but it is generally accepted that this miRNA regulates small RNA (including miRNA) production by targeting <italic>Dicer-like</italic> (<italic>DCL</italic>) RNase genes (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Xie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Of the two RNase-encoding mRNAs predicted to be targets of miR162 in tomato, evidence for targeting of one (Solyc10g005130.2.1) was found but above the <italic>P</italic>-value cut-off (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S3</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). For miR403, a member of the ARGONAUTE family different from that targeted by miR168 in tomato (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) was identified as a target (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Interestingly, the degradation pattern of the AGO2-like target of miR403 was increased at the MG stage and decreasing at the Br stage, while the AGO1-like target of miR168 degradation is lower and already decreases at the MG stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). This degradation pattern correlates with miR403 expression. MiR403 was shown to be highly expressed at the MG stage and decreases at the Br stage (<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Zuo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>miRNA-directed cleavage product abundance at different fruit stages. Normalized sequenced read abundance [peak height=tags per 10 million (TP10M)] on the <italic>y</italic>-axis. (A) Cleavage product abundances of <italic>AGO1</italic>-like (Solyc02g069260.2.1) by miR403 and of <italic>AGO1</italic>-like (Solyc06g072300.2.1) by miR168. (B) Cleavage product abundances of <italic>GAMYB-like 1</italic> and of <italic>GAMYB-like 2</italic> by miR159. (C) Cleavage product abundances of SlTIR1, and of two other <italic>TIR1</italic>-like mRNAs by miR393. (D) Cleavage product abundance of <italic>AP2a</italic> by miR172. (E) Cleavage product abundance of <italic>CNR</italic> by miR156.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert049_f0002"/></fig><p content-type="indent">For the rest of the conserved miRNAs, the predicted conserved targets were confirmed. For example, out of 13 MYB TF genes predicted to be a target of miR159, three with degradome tags at any developmental stage were found, and all these had at least one category 0 peak. All three are also predicted miR319 targets, with slightly higher TargetFinder penalty values (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Two of the identified MYB TF genes are <italic>GAMYB-like 1</italic> and <italic>GAMYB-like 2</italic> genes (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Gong and Bewley, 2008</xref>), which were shown to play a role in seed development in rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Kaneko <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Reyes and Chua, 2007</xref>). The present data show that while <italic>GAMYB-like 2</italic> degradation is higher at the 5 DAP fruit stage, the cleavage of <italic>GAMYB-like 1</italic> is higher at the MG stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). In conclusion, from the above-described target genes of miR159, different degradation patterns were observed, which is probably due to the difference in the transcript levels of these targets and not due to the level of miR159, which was shown to be equally expressed in different stages of tomato fruit development (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Buxdorf <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">MiR156 is generally known to target TF genes of the SBP family, which are involved in phase changes during plant development (<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Wu and Poethig, 2006</xref>). Out of 10 tomato SBP genes predicted to be targets of miR156, seven with a category 0 peak in at least one stage were detected. Among these are the two previously validated targets, one of which is <italic>CNR</italic> (Solyc02g077920.2.1), a regulator of tomato fruit ripening (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Thompson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Manning <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Members of another TF gene family, <italic>AP2</italic> homologues, were shown to be targeted by miR172, both through mRNA degradation and through translational inhibition (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Chen, 2004</xref>), and as such it affects flowering time and phase transition as well as floral organ identity (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Aukerman and Sakai, 2003</xref>). All eight tomato <italic>AP2</italic> genes predicted to be targets of miR172 were found to have category 0 tag peaks in almost all developmental stages tested. Among these are <italic>SlAP2a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>d</italic>, and <italic>e</italic>, which were all predicted to be targets of miR172 (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karlova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), but of which only <italic>AP2c</italic> is a previously validated target (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Itaya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). <italic>SlAP2b</italic> and <italic>SlAP2c</italic> cannot be distinguished based on the peak tag sequence as their homology extends 20 nucleotides 3&#x02019; of the miR172 processing site. As they are both expressed in the green fruit stages (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karlova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), they are probably both targets. The three other, newly identified miR172 targets are members of an <italic>AP2</italic> subclade, containing <italic>SlAP2d</italic> and <italic>SlAP2e</italic>, as well as <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowering time regulators <italic>SCHNARCHZAPFEN</italic> (<italic>SNZ</italic>) and <italic>SCHLAFM&#x000dc;TZE</italic> (<italic>SMZ</italic>), which is distinct from the subclade that contains <italic>SlAP2a</italic>, <italic>SlAP2b</italic>, <italic>SlAP2c</italic>, and <italic>Arabidopsis AP2</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karlova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). For the conserved miR319, the <italic>TCP</italic> family TF genes were identified as targets. From seven predicted tomato <italic>TCP</italic> TF targets of miR319, evidence was found for cleavage of all mRNAs, but interestingly the cleavage in all cases was found to be at position 11 relative to the 5&#x02019; end of Sly-miR319 as submitted to miRbase. As the submitted sequence is one nucleotide longer at the 5&#x02019; end than any of the published miR319 sequences from other species, it is assumed that the predominant miR319 species in tomato is similar to that of other species, which would bring the cleavage position to position 10. For miR164, four tomato <italic>No Apical Meristem/Cup-shaped Cotyledon</italic> (<italic>NAC</italic>) TF genes were identified as targets. Previously, miR164, through its NAC targets, were shown to be involved in regulation of organ boundaries and lateral root formation (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Laufs <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Mallory <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Guo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). As was shown before, miR166 in other species (<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Sun, 2011</xref>) targets TF genes of the class III Homeodomain Leucine Zipper (HD-ZIP) family. Evidence of targeting for two tomato HD-ZIP targets was found, including one that had been validated as a target before (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). As expected for miR169 and miR170/171, the A-subunit genes of the Nuclear Factor Y (NF-Y) or HAP transcription factors (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Combier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) and the GRAS/SCR (Scarecrow-related) TF family (<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Llave <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), respectively, were identified as targets. The results show that during tomato fruit development some conserved miRNAs are regulating non-conserved targets in addition to the conserved targets. In total, 16 non-conserved tomato-specific targets were identified for nine conserved miRNAs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Identification of targets of non-conserved miRNAs</title><p>The non-conserved miRNAs are found only in specific species. These miRNAs are often expressed at lower levels than the conserved miRNAs and therefore are more difficult to discover (<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Sun, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Zuo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Of the 22 non-conserved tomato miRNAs identified previously (<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Sun, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Zuo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), targets in class I could be identified for 15 in tomato fruits (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Only for miR158, miR161 (<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Zuo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), miR828, miR1919 (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), miR5300, miR5304 (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Mohorianu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), and miR6026 (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) significant target cleavage could not be detected. This may be explained by the low expression of these miRNAs in the tomato fruit, or by the absence of targets. A total of 36 target genes for the non-conserved tomato miRNAs were found in this study. This includes new targets not shown before in tomato. These new targets all belonged to class I (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). As shown previously for soybean (<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Song <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), the targets of non-conserved miRNAs were not enriched in TFs. The present data confirmed these results. In tomato fruits, targets of the non-conserved miRNAs miR158, miR894, and miR1917 encode enzymes. Other targets of miR393, miR1918, miR5301*, miR6022, miR6023, miR6024, and miR6027 are likely to be involved in signal transduction and/or disease resistance (see below, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Exceptions were miR858 and miR5301, for which targets belonging to the MYB class TF family were identified, as well as for miR5303 with a GRF TF as target. The status of miR5301 as a non-conserved mature miRNA unique in tomato is somewhat in doubt as it derives from the complementary strand of miR5301*, which in turn is the tomato homologue of miR482, a conserved miRNA (see below). Members of the MYB TF families were shown before to be targets of miR858 in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Fahlgren <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) and tomato (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). As for miR319, the conserved targets for miR858 were found to be cleaved at a site corresponding to position 11 of the published miR858 sequence, as was also reported by <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic> (2008</xref>) for another target (Solyc08g082890). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, MYB12 was shown to function as an activator of flavonoid biosynthesis. Flavonoids in the tomato fruit are found particularly in the peel, where their synthesis is regulated by a <italic>MYB12</italic> homologue, which is a predicted target of miR858 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online) (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Ballester <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). The targets identified here are other tomato homologues of <italic>MYB12</italic>, which suggests that also in tomato miR858 together with its targets could be involved in regulation of the biosynthesis of flavonoids or other metabolites (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Ballester <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Tomato immune receptor mRNAs targeted by microRNAs</title><p>Among the miRNAs that are conserved in different plant species, 22 nucleotide miR472 and miR482, which have similar sequences, target R (Resistance)-like genes, resulting in the formation of secondary, <italic>trans</italic>-acting small interfering RNAs (tasi-RNAs) (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Cuperus <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). In tomato fruits, both miRNAs have been shown to be expressed (<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Pilcher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Itaya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Sly-miR482 is shifted two nucleotides relative to miR472 and (non-tomato) miR482. MiR5301* (miR-W* in <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Mohorianu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), derived from the complementary strand of the miR5301 precursor, has a sequence intermediary between miR472 and (non-tomato) miR482 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S3</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Not surprisingly, miR472, miR482, and miR5301* are predicted to have largely similar targets among the <italic>CC-NBS-LRR</italic> (coiled coil&#x02013;nucleotide binding&#x02013;leucine-rich repeat domain) genes. The present degradome analysis only identified category 0 peaks in these targets for miR472 and miR5301* (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Additionally, a previously identified <italic>in vivo</italic> target of mir5301* (Solyc04g025160.2.1, encoding an Arsenite ATPase transporter homologue) was found (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Thus miR472 or miR5301* activity in developing tomato fruits has been shown, but no clear evidence of miR482 activity was found.</p><p content-type="indent">Recently a set of nine new microRNAs in Solanaceae (tobacco, potato, tomato), which target R genes, were described (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Of these, five (miR6022&#x02013;miR6024, miR6026, and miR6027) were shown to occur in tomato. The present data shows that during tomato fruit development miRNAs involved in the regulation of immune response-related genes are active.</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Signatures associated with the TAS3 precursors in tomato</title><p>In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, miR390 targets a single TAS3-precursor mRNA, and induces the phased production of tasiRNAs from that precursor, starting from the cleaved 3&#x02019; miR390 target site. Two dominant siRNA products from this process were shown to target two auxin response factor genes, ARF3 and ARF4, in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Allen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). In tomato, the miR390-derived product of a <italic>TASI3</italic> homologue, cDNA Solyc01g058100.2.1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), was detected, as well as an as yet unannotated <italic>TASI3</italic> homologue, SGN-U587265, which has two detected miR390 cleavage sites. Additionally, evidence was found for miR390-directed processing of one other tomato transcript (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, Solyc12g098430.1.1), which shows 97% identity with the putative arp2/3 complex 20kDa subunit from castor bean (GenBank accession no. EEF44192.1).</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Cleavage of miRNA targets involved in tomato fruit development and ripening</title><p>Previous studies in tomato have shown that a large part of the predicted miRNA targets are TFs (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Mohorianu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Zuo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). The present results prove those predictions; that is, a large fraction of the miRNA targets that were identified as class I targets at four different fruit developmental stages code for TFs. Several TF genes and genes that control fruit development and ripening have been found. Among those identified targets are <italic>ARF</italic> genes, a putative auxin receptor, <italic>SlTIR1</italic>, as well as fruit ripening regulators such as <italic>CNR</italic> and <italic>AP2a</italic>. The plant hormone auxin was shown to be a key regulator for fruit development. Recently, <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Ren <italic>et al.</italic> (2011</xref>) demonstrated that the tomato <italic>SlTIR1</italic> gene plays an important role at the flower-to-fruit transition. <italic>SlTIR1</italic> was found to be expressed in floral buds and flowers at the anthesis stage. From anthesis to post-anthesis when fruit set is expected to occur, the expression of <italic>SlTIR1</italic> declines in the ovary and sepal. Here it was found that <italic>SlTIR1</italic> as well as two other <italic>TIR1</italic> homologues are targets of miR393, with a peak of degradation in 5 DAP fruits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). These data suggest that miR393 is involved in controlling the expression of TIRs during tomato fruit set, which may be essential for the process. Overexpression of <italic>SLTIR1</italic> in tomato resulted in parthenocarpy and also in altered gene expression of <italic>ARF</italic> genes, such as <italic>SLARF6</italic> and ARF7 (<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Ren <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Another <italic>ARF</italic> gene, <italic>SlARF8</italic> was shown to be involved in tomato fruit set (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Goetz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Several members of the ARF family predicted to be targets of miR160 (<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Mallory <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) were found in the degradome libraries, including the two previously validated as targets (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Hendelman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Taken together, the data suggest that miRNAs in tomato are involved in the initiation of fruit growth by controlling the expression of <italic>ARF</italic> genes.</p><p content-type="indent">Fruit formation and fruit yield were affected in tomato by overexpression of miR156 (<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). MiR156 is known to target mRNA of the TF gene <italic>CNR</italic> (Solyc02g077920.2.1), a regulator of tomato fruit ripening (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Thompson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Manning <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Another ripening regulator, <italic>AP2a</italic>, was identified in the libraries as a target of miR172. <italic>AP2a</italic> was shown to regulate fruit ripening through negative regulation of ethylene biosynthesis and signalling (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Chung <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karlova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). For both ripening regulators <italic>CNR</italic> and <italic>AP2a</italic>, an increased amount of cleavage product was observed at the Br stage as compared with the other three fruit stages, which coincides with the highest expression level of the genes as shown by qPCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>, B). Both miR156 and miR172 are expressed at different fruit stages and their expression decreases at the RR (Br+7) stage (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Mohorianu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). To determine exactly how much of the <italic>CNR</italic> and <italic>AP2a</italic> transcripts are present as cleavage products, expression analysis by qPCR was used. For this purpose, two sets of primers were designed for each mRNA. One primer pair fits the 3&#x02019; UTR of the transcript (and thus detects both intact messenger and the 3&#x02019; product of cleavage). The other primer pair spans the miRNA target site and thus detects only the non-cleaved mRNA. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> and in agreement with the degradome data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">E</xref>), increased cleavage of the <italic>AP2a</italic> (48%) and <italic>CNR</italic> (30%) transcripts was observed at the Br stage as compared with the other fruit stages tested. Since <italic>AP2</italic> and <italic>CNR</italic> are important regulators of fruit ripening, their expression increases at the Br stage, which is concurrent with an increase in ethylene production. Here it is shown that not only the expression, but also the miRNA-dependent cleavage of <italic>AP2a</italic> and <italic>CNR</italic> increases at the same Br stage. Apparently both miR156 and miR172 significantly modulate the intact mRNA levels of their targets during ripening, without completely abolishing them.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Relative level of degradation of <italic>AP2a</italic> and of <italic>CNR</italic> mRNA by miR172 and miR156, respectively. Relative expression profiles of <italic>AP2a</italic> and <italic>CNR</italic> obtained by quantitative reverse transcription PCR with two different primers sets: in grey, primers spanning the miRNA cleavage site (detecting the level of the non-cleaved mRNA); in black, primers for the 3&#x02019; UTR, downstream of the cleavage sites (detecting both the intact and the cleaved mRNA) in tomato wild-type fruits at the 5 DAP, MG, Br, and RR stage. Error bars represent the SE. The expression levels are normalized relative to 5 DAP, which was set at 1, for each gene separately. (A) Relative expression profile of <italic>AP2a</italic>. (B) Relative expression profile of <italic>CNR.</italic> (C) Model of tomato fruit ripening control by <italic>CNR</italic>, <italic>AP2a</italic>, miR156, and miR172. The transcription factor genes <italic>AP2a</italic> and <italic>CNR</italic> are required for the normal ripening process. AP2a has a negative regulatory function in ethylene synthesis besides its positive ripening regulatory functions. <italic>CNR</italic> and <italic>AP2a</italic> regulate each other&#x02019;s expression in opposite ways and their expression is also negatively regulated by miR156 and miR172, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_ert049_f0003"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s17"><title>Conserved and non-conserved targets of the conserved miRNAs in tomato</title><p>Control of gene expression involves a variety of transcriptional and post-transcriptional processes. The abundance of a given mRNA depends on the equilibrium of its expression and degradation rates. In the last decade, a new class of small RNAs, miRNAs were shown to be involved in the regulation of gene expression by mRNA degradation, and many of their targets encoded members of TF families. To identify the function of tomato miRNAs, the relatively new method PARE was used for global analysis of mRNA cleavage products of miRNA action, comparing the mRNA degradomes from different stages of tomato fruit development. The data confirm, as was shown for other species, that miRNAs and their targeted mRNAs are clearly conserved in flowering plants (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Pantaleo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Song <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). For the 24 conserved and 22 non-conserved miRNAs identified previously for tomato, targets from class I could be detected for 19 and 15 miRNAs, respectively. Homologues of the targets of the conserved miRNAs were also detected in the degradome studies of other species. For example, miRNAs 156, 172, 160, 164, and 319 were shown to target mRNAs of primarily one family of (different) TFs each in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, rice, grapevine, and soybean (for a review, see <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Sun, 2011</xref>). Because some of these miRNAs and their targets were found to exist in mosses (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Addo-Quaye <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009<italic>b</italic>
</xref>), it is assumed that regulation of gene expression by miRNAs arose early in plant evolution, showing again the importance of the miRNA-dependent RNA degradation process. In this study new targets of conserved as well as of non-conserved miRNAs in tomato could be identified. For example, for the conserved miR396, apart from members of the expected GRF TF family, five different targets not shown in other plant species before were identified. One of these, SlDRM5, is a homologue of DNA (cytosine-5-)-methyltransferase 3, and is probably involved in DNA methylation in tomato. The function of these newly identified targets, and their regulation by miRNA in tomato fruit development remains to be determined.</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Targets of non-conserved miRNAs</title><p>For the non-conserved tomato miRNAs, 36 targets were identified, of which 35 were new targets not shown before in tomato. As shown previously in degradome studies in soybean (<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Song <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), the targets of the non-conserved miRNAs were not enriched in TFs. Interestingly, among the non-conserved miRNA targets were miRNAs that regulate innate immune responses. The data show that although some of the non-conserved miRNAs and their targets are hard to detect, because of their low expression, using degradome libraries from different fruit developmental stages is a successful strategy.</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>The role of miRNAs in tomato fruit development</title><p>Most fruit crops require pollination and fertilization to ensure fruit set. The phytohormone auxin is a key regulator of tomato fruit set and development (<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">Woodward and Bartel, 2005</xref>). Recently, it was shown that the tomato SlTIR1 (a putative auxin receptor) plays an important role in fruit set (<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Ren <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Using the PARE method, it could be shown that miRNAs may regulate initiation of fruit development through miR393 and miR167 targeting of SlTIR1 and ARFs, respectively.</p><p content-type="indent">Ripening affects several fruit quality traits, such as colour, flavour, and soluble solid content. In the cultivated tomato, it comprises a series of biochemical and physiological events, including softening, pigment change, development of flavour components, autocatalytic ethylene production, and climacteric respiratory behaviour (for a review, see <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Klee and Giovannoni, 2011</xref>). Two TFs that play a major role in regulation of tomato fruit ripening, <italic>CNR</italic> and <italic>AP2a</italic>, were known to be a target, or a putative target, of miR156/157 and miR172, respectively (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karlova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Moxon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). In this study, it was confirmed that <italic>SlAP2a</italic> is indeed a target of miR172 in tomato and, moreover, it was shown that both TF mRNAs are actively targeted during fruit development and ripening. The appearance of the t-plots of both mRNAs would suggest that most mRNA is present only in a cleaved state as there is one dominant peak at the cleavage position. In fact, qPCR experiments that distinguish uncleaved mRNA from total transcript show that for both genes intact and cleaved mRNAs are present simultaneously. The miRNA-directed cleavage of both <italic>CNR</italic> and <italic>AP2a</italic> mRNAs increases at the Br stage of the fruit, to at least 30% and 48%, respectively, which coincides with the peak of ethylene production. These numbers may be higher if the respective 3&#x02019; cleavage products have a faster turnover. In the RR stage, the contribution of 3&#x02019; cleavage products declines for both mRNAs, although more so for <italic>SlAP2a</italic>, while its intact mRNA level remains almost equal. This fits the earlier observed expression profile of miR172 during fruit development determined by northern blotting, which showed miR172 levels peaking at Br to Br+5 d and declining at Br+7 d (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Mohorianu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). For <italic>CNR</italic>, the level of its intact mRNA as well as of its 3&#x02019; cleavage product decreases during that stage. miR156/157 was shown to be expressed more equally from immature green stages onward, but also declined at Br+7 d (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Mohorianu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Although for both miRNAs fruit is not the organ with the highest expression in tomato, these levels are apparently well suited for achieving an attenuating effect on the intact mRNA levels of two important ripening regulators. <italic>AP2a</italic> expression was shown to be induced by ethylene, while AP2a is a negative regulator of ethylene biosynthesis (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Karlova <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Interestingly, AP2a was shown to be a repressor of <italic>CNR</italic> expression, while CNR positively regulates the expression of <italic>AP2a</italic>. The results presented here identify miR156/157 and miR172 as additional components of a regulatory network in tomato fruit ripening (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). The results suggest that miR156 and miR172 function in fruit ripening by modulating the activity of <italic>AP2a</italic> (which inhibits ethylene biosynthesis) and of <italic>CNR</italic>, particularly at and around the Br stage. As AP2a and CNR are considered as an inhibitor and an activator of ripening, respectively, this adds another layer of complexity to the regulatory network model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). In this model, the function of miR156/157 and miR172 in fruit ripening is to fine-tune the expression of <italic>CNR</italic> and <italic>AP2a</italic> to appropriate levels in the different stages of tomato fruit ripening. All these events are contributing in a balanced manner to the process of normal tomato fruit development and ripening. This also implies that natural or induced variation in miRNA expression could be used in breeding programmes aimed at modifying ripening parameters in tomato.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s20"><title>Supplementary data</title><p>Supplementary data are available at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Figure S1</ext-link>. Relationship between independent microarray hybridization-derived transcript abundance and transcript abundance derived from treatment of degradome data as RNAseq.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Figure S2</ext-link>. Examples of t-plots depicting categories.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Figure S3</ext-link>. Alignment of mir472/482-related sequences.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Table S1</ext-link>. Summary of the degradome tag mapping to the tomato genome.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Table S2</ext-link>. miRNA target prediction results for tomato cDNAs (ITAG2.3) and SGN-Unigenes.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert049/-/DC1">Table S3</ext-link>. Normalized CleaveLand v3 output matching degradome tags to predicted miRNA cleavage sites for targets with at least one category 0 or 1 peak in the four libraries.</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Data</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_64_7_1863__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_ert049_jexbot092965_file001.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_ert049_jexbot092965_file002.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_ert049_jexbot092965_file003.xlsx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Dr Michael Axtell (Pennsylvania State University) for providing us with the CleaveLand v3 scripts ahead of publication and for his advice on using the scripts, and Dr Stephane Rombauts (Flanders Institute of Biotechnology, Ghent University) for providing us with the tomato gene model details. This work was supported by the Netherlands Genomics Initiative (NGI) &#x02018;Horizon Breakthrough&#x02019; ZonMw grant no. 40-41009-98-9054 to RK, and by the Centre for BioSystems Genomics to RdeM.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addo-Quaye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshoo</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Axtell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Endogenous siRNA and miRNA targets identified by sequencing of the Arabidopsis degradome</article-title>.
<source>Current Biology</source>
<volume>18</volume>,
<fpage>758</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>762</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18472421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addo-Quaye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Axtell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009a</year>
<article-title>CleaveLand: a pipeline for using degradome data to find cleaved small RNA targets</article-title>.
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>25</volume>,
<fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19017659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addo-Quaye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunkar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Axtell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009b</year>
<article-title>Sliced microRNA targets and precise loop-first processing of MIR319 hairpins revealed by analysis of the <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> degradome</article-title>.
<source>RNA</source>
<volume>15</volume>,
<fpage>2112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2121</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19850910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>microRNA-directed phasing during trans-acting siRNA biogenesis in plants</article-title>.
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>121</volume>,
<fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15851028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aukerman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Regulation of flowering time and floral organ identity by a microRNA and its <italic>APETALA2</italic>-like target genes</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>15</volume>,
<fpage>2730</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2741</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballester</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Molthoff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Biochemical and molecular analysis of pink tomatoes: deregulated expression of the gene encoding transcription factor SLMYB12 leads to pink tomato fruit color</article-title>.
<source>Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>152</volume>,
<fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and function</article-title>.
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>116</volume>,
<fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14744438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>.
<source>Journal of the Royal Statististical Society. Series B (Methodological)</source>
<volume>57</volume>,
<fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>300</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buxdorf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stav</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapidot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ori</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Arazi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Identification and characterization of a novel miR159 target not related to MYB in tomato</article-title>.
<source>Planta</source>
<volume>232</volume>,
<fpage>1009</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1022</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20661587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>A microRNA as a translational repressor of <italic>APETALA2</italic> in Arabidopsis flower development</article-title>.
<source>Science</source>
<volume>303</volume>,
<fpage>2022</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2025</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12893888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Small RNAs and their roles in plant development</article-title>.
<source>Annual Review of Cell and Developmental Biology</source>
<volume>25</volume>,
<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrebalov</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McQuinn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>A tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) <italic>APETALA2/ERF</italic> gene, <italic>SlAP2a</italic>, is a negative regulator of fruit ripening</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>64</volume>,
<fpage>936</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>947</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21143675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Combier</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Frugier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>De Billy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>MtHAP2-1 is a key transcriptional regulator of symbiotic nodule development regulated by microRNA169 in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>Genes and Development</source>
<volume>20</volume>,
<fpage>3084</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3088</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17114582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuperus</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahlgren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Ruiz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Unique functionality of 22-nt miRNAs in triggering RDR6-dependent siRNA biogenesis from target transcripts in Arabidopsis</article-title>.
<source>Nature Structural and Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>17</volume>,
<fpage>997</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1003</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzamba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Brudno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>SHRiMP2: sensitive yet practical short read mapping</article-title>.
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>27</volume>,
<fpage>1011</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1012</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21278192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fahlgren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasschau</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>High-throughput sequencing of Arabidopsis microRNAs: evidence for frequent birth and death of <italic>MIRNA</italic> genes</article-title>.
<source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>2</volume>,
<fpage>e219</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17299599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Daub</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Rfam: Wikipedia, clans and the &#x02018;decimal&#x02019; release</article-title>.
<source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>39</volume>,
<fpage>D141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D145</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21062808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>German</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Construction of Parallel Analysis of RNA Ends (PARE) libraries for the study of cleaved miRNA targets and the RNA degradome</article-title>.
<source>Nature Protocols</source>
<volume>4</volume>,
<fpage>356</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>362</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>German</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Global identification of microRNA&#x02013;target RNA pairs by parallel analysis of RNA ends</article-title>.
<source>Nature Biotechnology</source>
<volume>26</volume>,
<fpage>941</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>946</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivian-Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koltunow</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Expression of aberrant forms of AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR8 stimulates parthenocarpy in Arabidopsis and tomato</article-title>.
<source>Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>145</volume>,
<fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>366</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17766399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Bewley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>A <italic>GAMYB</italic>-like gene in tomato and its expression during seed germination</article-title>.
<source>Planta</source>
<volume>228</volume>,
<fpage>563</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>572</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18542997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>MicroRNA directs mRNA cleavage of the transcription factor NAC1 to downregulate auxin signals for Arabidopsis lateral root development</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>17</volume>,
<fpage>1376</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1386</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15829603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hendelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Buxdorf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stav</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kravchik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arazi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Inhibition of lamina outgrowth following <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR 10 (SlARF10) derepression</article-title>.
<source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>78</volume>,
<fpage>561</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>576</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22287097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itaya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bundschuh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Archual</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Joung</surname><given-names>J-G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>PX</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Small RNAs in tomato fruit and leaf development</article-title>.
<source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>
<volume>1779</volume>,
<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18078843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones-Rhoades</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>MicroRNAs and their regulatory roles in plants</article-title>.
<source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source>
<volume>57</volume>,
<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Inukai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Loss-of-function mutations of the rice <italic>GAMYB</italic> gene impair alpha-amylase expression in aleurone and flower development</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>16</volume>,
<fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14688295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karlova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosin</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Busscher-Lange</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parapunova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Angenent</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>de Maagd</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Transcriptome and metabolite profiling show that <italic>APETALA2a</italic> is a major regulator of tomato fruit ripening</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>23</volume>,
<fpage>923</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>941</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21398570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Genetics and control of tomato fruit ripening and quality attributes</article-title>.
<source>Annual Review of Genetics</source>
<volume>45</volume>,
<fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laufs</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Peaucelle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Traas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>MicroRNA regulation of the <italic>CUC</italic> genes is required for boundary size control in Arabidopsis meristems</article-title>.
<source>Development</source>
<volume>131</volume>,
<fpage>4311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4322</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15294871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pignatta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bendix</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunkard</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>MicroRNA regulation of plant innate immune receptors</article-title>.
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
<volume>109</volume>,
<fpage>1790</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1795</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wysoker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Homer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Abecasis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</article-title>.
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>25</volume>,
<fpage>2078</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2079</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Addo-Quaye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagadeeswaran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Axtell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunkar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Transcriptome-wide identification of microRNA targets in rice</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>62</volume>,
<fpage>742</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>759</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20202174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Llave</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasschau</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Cleavage of Scarecrow-like mRNA targets directed by a class of Arabidopsis miRNA</article-title>.
<source>Science</source>
<volume>297</volume>,
<fpage>2053</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2056</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallory</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>MicroRNA-directed regulation of Arabidopsis <italic>AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR17</italic> is essential for proper development and modulates expression of early auxin response genes</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>17</volume>,
<fpage>1360</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1375</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15829600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallory</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>MicroRNA regulation of NAC-domain targets is required for proper formation and separation of adjacent embryonic, vegetative, and floral organs</article-title>.
<source>Current Biology</source>
<volume>14</volume>,
<fpage>1035</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1046</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15202996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>A naturally occurring epigenetic mutation in a gene encoding an SBP-box transcription factor inhibits tomato fruit ripening</article-title>.
<source>Nature Genetics</source>
<volume>38</volume>,
<fpage>948</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>952</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16832354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Souret</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Sweating the small stuff: microRNA discovery in plants</article-title>.
<source>Current Opinion in Biotechnology</source>
<volume>17</volume>,
<fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>146</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16460926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohorianu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwach</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Gomollon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moxon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Szittya</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorefan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalmay</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Profiling of short RNAs during fleshy fruit development reveals stage-specific sRNAome expression patterns</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>67</volume>,
<fpage>232</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>246</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moxon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Szittya</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwach</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusholme</surname></name><name><surname>Pilcher</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalmay</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Deep sequencing of tomato short RNAs identifies microRNAs targeting genes involved in fruit ripening</article-title>.
<source>Genome Research</source>
<volume>18</volume>,
<fpage>1602</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1609</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18653800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ori</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Etzioni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Regulation of <italic>LANCEOLATE</italic> by <italic>miR319</italic> is required for compound-leaf development in tomato</article-title>.
<source>Nature Genetics</source>
<volume>39</volume>,
<fpage>787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>791</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17486095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pantaleo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Szittya</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Moxon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Miozzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalmay</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgyan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Identification of grapevine microRNAs and their targets using high-throughput sequencing and degradome analysis</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>62</volume>,
<fpage>960</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>976</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20230504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilcher</surname><given-names>RLR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moxon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pakseresht</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalmay</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Identification of novel small RNAs in tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>)</article-title>.
<source>Planta</source>
<volume>226</volume>,
<fpage>709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>717</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17415587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title>.
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>26</volume>,
<fpage>841</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>842</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>The auxin receptor homologue in <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> stimulates tomato fruit set and leaf morphogenesis</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>62</volume>,
<fpage>2815</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2826</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21266497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>ABA induction of miR159 controls transcript levels of two MYB factors during Arabidopsis seed germination</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>49</volume>,
<fpage>592</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>606</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17217461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhoades</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Prediction of plant microRNA targets</article-title>.
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>110</volume>,
<fpage>513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>520</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12202040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>QX</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Identification of miRNAs and their target genes in developing soybean seeds by deep sequencing</article-title>.
<source>BMC Plant Biology</source>
<volume>11</volume>,
<fpage>5</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21219599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>MicroRNAs and their diverse functions in plants</article-title>.
<source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>18</volume>,
<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21874378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teyssier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernacchia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Maury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>How</surname></name><name><surname>Kit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stammitti-Bert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallusci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Tissue dependent variations of DNA methylation and endoreduplication levels during tomato fruit development and ripening</article-title>.
<source>Planta</source>
<volume>228</volume>,
<fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>399</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18488247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrebalov</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Orfila</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grierson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Molecular and genetic characterization of a novel pleiotropic tomato-ripening mutant</article-title>.
<source>Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>120</volume>,
<fpage>383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10364389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Tomato Genome Consortium</collab>.
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>The tomato genome sequence provides insights into fleshy fruit evolution</article-title>.
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>485</volume>,
<fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>641</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22660326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Auxin: regulation, action, and interaction</article-title>.
<source>Annals of Botany</source>
<volume>95</volume>,
<fpage>707</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>735</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15749753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Temporal regulation of shoot development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> by miR156 and its target <italic>SPL3</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>Development</source>
<volume>133</volume>,
<fpage>3539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3547</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16914499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasschau</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Negative feedback regulation of Dicer-Like1 in Arabidopsis by microRNA-guided mRNA degradation</article-title>.
<source>Current Biology</source>
<volume>13</volume>,
<fpage>784</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>789</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12725739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>de Paoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>MicroRNAs as master regulators of the plant NB-LRR defense gene family via the production of phased, trans-acting siRNAs</article-title>.
<source>Genes and Development</source>
<volume>25</volume>,
<fpage>2540</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2553</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22156213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Over-expression of sly-miR156a in tomato results in multiple vegetative and reproductive trait alterations and partial phenocopy of the sft mutant</article-title>.
<source>FEBS Letters</source>
<volume>585</volume>,
<fpage>435</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>439</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21187095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Sculpting the maturation, softening and ethylene pathway: the influences of microRNAs on tomato fruits</article-title>.
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>13</volume>,
<fpage>7</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22230737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>