<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">G3 (Bethesda)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>G3: Genes|Genomes|Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2160-1836</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Genetics Society of America</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5015929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27402359</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">GGG_029983</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.116.029983</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genetics of Immunity</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Microsporidia Intracellular Development Relies on Myc Interaction Network Transcription Factors in the Host</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Botts</surname><given-names>Michael R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn2"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>Lianne B.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Probert</surname><given-names>Christopher S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Fengting</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Troemel</surname><given-names>Emily R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Division of Biological Sciences, Section of Cell and Developmental Biology, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, California 92093</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="afn2" fn-type="present-address"><label>1</label><p>Present address: Department of Biomolecular Chemistry, University of Wisconsin-Madison School of Medicine and Public Health, Madison, WI 53706</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>2</label>Corresponding author: Division of Biological Sciences, Section of Cell and Developmental Biology, University of California, San Diego, 9500 Gilman Drive, #0349, 4202 Bonner Hall, La Jolla, CA 92093-0349. E-mail: <email>etroemel@ucsd.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2707</fpage><lpage>2716</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Botts <italic>et al.</italic></copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="2707.pdf"/><abstract><p>Microsporidia are ubiquitous parasites that infect a wide range of animal hosts, and these fungal-related microbes undergo their entire replicative lifecycle inside of host cells. Despite being widespread in the environment and causing medical and agricultural harm, virtually nothing is known about the host factors important to facilitate their growth and development inside of host cells. Here, we perform a genetic screen to identify host transcription factors important for development of the microsporidian pathogen <italic>Nematocida parisii</italic> inside intestinal cells of its natural host, the nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. Through this screen, we identified the <italic>C. elegans</italic> Myc family of transcription factors as key host regulators of microsporidia growth and development. The Mad-like transcription factor <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link>, and the Max-like transcription factors <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">MXL-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> promote pathogen levels, while the Myc-Mondo-like transcription factor <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link> inhibits pathogen levels. We used epistasis analysis to show that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">MXL-1</ext-link>, which are thought to function as a heterodimer, appear to be acting canonically. In contrast, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link>, which are also thought to function as a heterodimer, appear to be acting in separate pathways (noncanonically) in the context of pathogen infection. We also found that both MDL-1::GFP and MML-1::GFP are expressed in intestinal cells during infection. These findings provide novel insight into the host transcription factors that regulate microsporidia development.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>C. elegans</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>N. parisii</italic></kwd><kwd>intestine</kwd><kwd>microsporidia</kwd><kwd>pathogenesis</kwd><kwd>Genetics of Immunity</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="40"/><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Microsporidia comprise a phylum of fungal-like obligate intracellular parasites that infect all phyla of animals, including humans and agriculturally important animals (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Vavra and Lukes 2013</xref>). Disease caused by microsporidia infection poses a threat in an agricultural setting, particularly in commercial apiculture and aquaculture (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Stentiford <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Stentiford <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Higes <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Troemel 2011</xref>). In addition, there are 14 species of microsporidia that are known to cause disease in humans, including life-threatening wasting diarrhea in immunocompromised people (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Didier and Weiss 2011</xref>). Furthermore, recent estimates have found that microsporidia may infect up to 56% of immunocompetent people, and the true impact of microsporidia infection on human health is poorly understood (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Sak <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Despite the prevalence of disease associated with microsporidia infection, there is a dearth of effective treatments for treating microsporidiosis.</p><p>Microsporidia have a very specialized obligate intracellular lifestyle, which begins with the transmissible spore form (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>) (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Keeling and Fast 2002</xref>). This spore contains a coiled polar tube that can rapidly fire and pierce host cells, and through which a parasite cell called a sporoplasm can be injected directly into a host cell. The sporoplasm develops into an intracellular multinucleate replicative form called a meront, which then differentiates back into spores that are shed by the host. Thus, microsporidia undergo all of their replication inside of the host cell. Microsporidia complete this infectious lifecycle with some of the smallest known eukaryotic genomes [as small as 2.3&#x000a0;Mb in one human-infecting species (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Corradi <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>)], having lost genes conserved among other eukaryotes (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Katinka <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Texier <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Williams 2009</xref>). For example, microsporidia have lost mitochondrial pathways like oxidative phosphorylation, in keeping with their lack of true mitochondria. Genome compaction in obligate intracellular pathogens such as microsporidia results in dependence on host resources to facilitate intracellular growth, and pathogen hijacking of host cell processes to redirect these resources. One such mechanism by which microsporidia may acquire host resources is through microsporidia-encoded nucleotide and nucleoside transport proteins that import nucleotides and nucleosides from the host-cell cytoplasm into the parasite cell (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Tsaousis <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Cuomo <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). However, almost nothing is known about which host cell machinery is important for providing a hospitable host cell environment for microsporidian growth.</p><fig id="fig1" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>RNAi clones identified in transcription factor library screen cause decreased spore levels in infected animals. (A) After <italic>N. parisii</italic> invades <italic>C. elegans</italic> intestinal cells, it replicates in a meront form, and then differentiates into spores. (B) Spore levels (spores/animal) of infected N2 animals after treatment with RNAi, using clones that were hits from the screen (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1/TableS1.xlsx">Table S1</ext-link>). Spore levels were measured with DY96 staining of spores and quantification by hemocytometer. All RNAi treatments were normalized with a L4440 empty vector control, which was set to a baseline of 100% spore levels. Spore levels shown as the mean of three independent experiments. Error bars are SEM. All RNAi conditions were significantly different than empty vector treated animals (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="2707f1"/></fig><p>Several studies have identified changes in gene expression that occur during microsporidia infection, and have identified conserved pathways that are regulated by infection (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Szumowski and Troemel 2015</xref>). These pathways include the ubiquitin proteasome system (UPS) in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> infected with <italic>Nematocida parisii</italic> (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Bakowski <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), and the type-I interferon response pathways in human foreskin fibroblasts infected with <italic>Anncallia algerae</italic> (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Panek <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). However, the functional consequences of these gene expression changes are not well understood, and no transcription factors have been identified that are responsible for controlling these changes. Indeed, virtually nothing is known about host factors that aid in growth of microsporidian pathogens in any system.</p><p>Here, we describe the use of <italic>N. parisii</italic>, a natural microsporidian pathogen of <italic>C. elegans</italic> nematodes (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Troemel <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), for high throughput RNAi screening to identify host transcription factors that are important for pathogen development in a whole animal. We identified several conserved transcription factors required for normal pathogen development, including components of the <italic>C. elegans</italic> Myc interaction network, which is reduced in number compared to other animals (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Pickett <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). In mammals, the Myc transcription factor was originally identified for its role in cancer, and it has several interaction partners that, together with Myc, have been shown to regulate gene expression, cell growth, differentiation, apoptosis, and energy metabolism (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Tu <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). Orthologs for the mammalian Myc interaction network of transcription factors have been identified in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, and there are four major players in this network (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link></italic>, and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic>) that have been shown to regulate tissue differentiation, metabolism, and animal lifespan (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Riesen <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">McFerrin and Atchley 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Pickett <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura <italic>et al.</italic> 2016</xref>). We found that all of these transcription factors regulate <italic>N. parisii</italic> pathogen levels, acting later during the microsporidia life cycle to affect spore levels. Three of these factors (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link></italic>, and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>)</italic> promote pathogen development, while one of them (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic>) represses pathogen development. Our epistasis analysis indicates there is both canonical and noncanonical activity of these transcription factors during infection. We also analyze ModENCODE data for transcription factors binding sites in the promoter regions of infection-regulated genes. In addition, we show that MDL-1::GFP and MML-1::GFP proteins are expressed in intestinal nuclei during infection, and we characterize other transcription factors that regulate pathogen development for their interaction with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link>, identifying new genetic interactions for this factor. Altogether, these findings describe results of the first genetic screen for host factors important for establishing a replicative niche for microsporidia, and identify novel targets that could be used to combat microsporidia-associated disease.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2"><title>C. elegans strains</title><p><italic>C. elegans</italic> was maintained on nematode growth media (NGM) seeded with <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50-1;class=Strain">OP50-1</ext-link> as described (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Brenner 1974</xref>). Previously generated strains used in this study include:<list list-type="bullet" id="L1"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain">N2</ext-link></p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP106;class=Strain">OP106</ext-link>
<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006843;class=Gene">unc-119</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00145093;class=Variation">ed3</ext-link>) III</italic>; <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBTransgene00007980;class=Transgene">wgIs106</ext-link> [mdl-1</italic>::<italic>TY1</italic>::<italic>EGFP</italic>::<italic>3xFLAG + <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006843;class=Gene">unc-119</ext-link>(+)]</italic></p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP527;class=Strain">OP527</ext-link>
<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006843;class=Gene">unc-119</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00252617;class=Variation">tm4063</ext-link>) III</italic>; <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBTransgene00022350;class=Transgene">wgIs527</ext-link>[mml-1</italic>::<italic>TY1</italic>::<italic>EGFP</italic>::<italic>3xFLAG + <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006843;class=Gene">unc-119</ext-link>(+)]</italic></p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CB4037;class=Strain">CB4037</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene">glp-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00144590;class=Variation">e2141</ext-link>) III</p></list-item></list><italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>)</italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250520;class=Variation">tm1530</ext-link>)</italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250507;class=Variation">tm1516</ext-link>)</italic>, and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00092124;class=Variation">ok849</ext-link>)</italic> mutants were each backcrossed to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain">N2</ext-link> wild type to generate these strains. The <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>) and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250507;class=Variation">tm1516</ext-link>)</italic> mutants were obtained from the National Bioresource Project of Japan and the <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic> Genetics Center, and backcrossed in our lab to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain">N2</ext-link> three times. The <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250520;class=Variation">tm1530</ext-link>)</italic> and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00092124;class=Variation">ok849</ext-link>)</italic> mutants were a kind gift from Dr. Andrew Samuelson, and were backcrossed to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain">N2</ext-link> three times in their lab, and then backcrossed a further three times into <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain">N2</ext-link> in our lab, because preliminary results indicated there were differences in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain">N2</ext-link> backgrounds contributing to pathogen growth. These backcrossings led to these four strains:<list list-type="bullet" id="L2"><list-item><p>ERT414 <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link></italic>) X</p></list-item><list-item><p>ERT480 <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250520;class=Variation">tm1530</ext-link>)</italic> V</p></list-item><list-item><p>ERT353 <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250507;class=Variation">tm1516</ext-link>)</italic> III</p></list-item><list-item><p>ERT355 <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00092124;class=Variation">ok849</ext-link>)</italic> III</p></list-item></list>Double mutants were constructed by backcrossing <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250520;class=Variation">tm1530</ext-link>)</italic> or <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250507;class=Variation">tm1516</ext-link>)</italic> males with <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>)</italic> hermaphrodites:<list list-type="bullet" id="L3"><list-item><p>ERT418 <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250520;class=Variation">tm1530</ext-link>) V</italic>;<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>) X</italic></p></list-item><list-item><p>ERT419 <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250507;class=Variation">tm1516</ext-link>) III;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>) X</italic></p></list-item></list>GFP transgene complementation lines were made by crossing ERT414 <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>) X</italic> with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP106;class=Strain">OP106</ext-link>
<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBTransgene00007980;class=Transgene">wgIs106</ext-link> [MDL-1</italic>::<italic>EGFP</italic>::<italic>TY1</italic>::<italic>3xFLAG]</italic> to generate ERT447 <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>) X</italic>; <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBTransgene00007980;class=Transgene">wgIs106</ext-link></italic>, and by crossing <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00092124;class=Variation">ok849</ext-link>)</italic> with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP527;class=Strain">OP527</ext-link>
<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBTransgene00022350;class=Transgene">wgIs527</ext-link> [MML-1</italic>::<italic>EGFP</italic>::<italic>TY1</italic>::<italic>3XFLAG]</italic> to generate ERT420 <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00092124;class=Variation">ok849</ext-link>) III</italic>; <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBTransgene00022350;class=Transgene">wgIs527</ext-link></italic>. Oligonucleotides used to PCR genotype cross progeny are as follows: <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>)</italic> forward TCG GTG CTT TCC TAG TTC GT, reverse ATT GGA CCC CTT GGG ATA AG; <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250520;class=Variation">tm1530</ext-link>)</italic> forward GGG GAC AAG TTT GTA CAA AAA AGC AGG CTG GAT GTC TGA CAT GAG TGA CCT CG, reverse GGG GAC CAC TTT GTA CAA GAA AGC TGG GTG TTG AAT TAT CGA CTG CGA TG; <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250507;class=Variation">tm1516</ext-link>)</italic> forward GCC AGC TCC TCT CAA AAG CCG, reverse CTG TCG ACT TGA ATG GCT CCG C; and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00092124;class=Variation">ok849</ext-link>)</italic> forward CGA GTC CAC CTG TGA ACT GG, reverse GAG AAC TCC GAC GAA TGA TCA GCC.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Spore levels RNAi screen</title><p>To identify RNAi clones that cause a decrease in spore levels, we developed a screen to quantify spore levels in animals grown in 96-well plates. RNAi bacteria were grown in 1&#x000a0;ml of Luria Broth (LB) containing 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml carbenicillin in deep-well 96-well plates overnight with shaking. The bacteria were then subjected to centrifugation at 5000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic> for 15&#x000a0;min and the supernatant discarded. The bacteria were then resuspended in 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L of S-medium containing 1&#x000a0;mM <underline>isopropyl &#x003b2;-<sc>d</sc>-1-thiogalactopyranoside</underline> (IPTG). Synchronized <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene">glp-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00144590;class=Variation">e2141</ext-link>)</italic> L1 animals were suspended in S-medium containing IPTG, and then dispensed in 96-well plates in a 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l volume with 200 animals per well. Fifteen microliters of RNAi bacteria were then added to each well, and the plates were incubated at 25&#x000b0; with shaking at 200&#x000a0;rpm in the dark. After 24&#x000a0;hr, 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>6</sup> spores were added to each well in 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of S-Medium with 1&#x000a0;mM IPTG along with an additional 15&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of RNAi bacteria. At 24&#x000a0;hr post-inoculation (hpi), an additional 25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of RNAi bacteria was added to each well to prevent starvation. At 44&#x000a0;hpi 15&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of 16% paraformaldehyde was added to each well, and plates were placed at 4&#x000b0;.</p><p>Infected animals were then transferred to deep-well 96-well plates, and washed three times with phosphate buffered saline (PBS) containing 1% sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS). A staining solution of 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL Direct Yellow 96 (DY96) in PBS with 1% SDS was added to each well, and the plates were incubated at room temperature overnight. The staining solution was washed with five washes with PBS plus 1% SDS (5&#x000a0;min room temperature incubation between each wash), followed by two washes with PBS with 0.1% Tween-20. Stained animals were then transferred to clear-bottom 96-well plates, and fluorescence was quantified using a BMG Labtech Novostar plate reader.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Spore levels assay</title><p>Spore levels were quantified as described (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Szumowski <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Briefly, 500 synchronized <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain">N2</ext-link> L1s were grown on RNAi plates for 24&#x000a0;hr at 25&#x000b0;. These animals were then washed off plates using M9, and transferred to a fresh 6-cm RNAi plate seeded with RNAi bacteria and 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>6</sup>
<italic>N. parisii</italic> spores, then grown at 25&#x000b0;. At 40&#x000a0;hpi, infected adult animals were washed off of the plates using M9, and then fixed in acetone. Fixed animals were washed three times with PBS containing 0.1% Tween-20 (PBS-T), before transferring to a 96-well plate for sorting with the Union Biometrica COPAS Biosort machine to dispense 50 animals per well into a new 96-well plate. Wells containing 50 infected animals in 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of water were then mixed with 150&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of lysis buffer containing PBS with 2% SDS, 0.01% 2-mercaptoethanol, and 4&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml DY96; lysis was monitored microscopically, and complete lysis was typically achieved after 2&#x000a0;hr incubation at room temperature. Spores were then counted by visualizing DY96 stained spores on a hemocytometer.</p><p>Spore levels were quantified in mutant worms identically as described above, except that RNAi bacteria with an empty RNAi vector was used (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HT115;class=Strain">HT115</ext-link>
<italic>E. coli</italic> with L4440 plasmid) as the food source. All experiments were performed in independent triplicates and analyzed for statistical significance using ANOVA and GraphPad software (Prism).</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Sporoplasm counting assay</title><p><italic>N. parisii</italic> sporoplasms were quantified as described (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Balla <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). Briefly, synchronized L1s were added to RNAi plates seeded with a mixture of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HT115;class=Strain">HT115</ext-link>
<italic>E. coli</italic> and 4&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>6</sup>
<italic>N. parisii</italic> spores. Animals were allowed to feed on the bacteria and spore mixture for 4&#x000a0;hr at 25&#x000b0; before fixing with 4% paraformaldehyde on ice for 30&#x000a0;min. Fixed animals were then washed with PBS-T prior to staining with MicroB fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH) probe against <italic>N. parisii</italic> rRNA. Sporoplasms within intestinal tissue were counted microscopically using a Zeiss AxioImager microscope and a 40&#x000a0;&#x000d7; objective. At least 100 animals were counted for each replicate, with three independent experiments performed. Mean number of sporoplasms per worm was compared using ANOVA and GraphPad software (PRISM).</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Pathogen load analysis by FISH</title><p>Pathogen load was analyzed as described (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Balla <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). Briefly, animals were washed off infection plates, fixed with acetone and then stained with a mix of five oligonucleotide probes, named Micro A&#x02013;E conjugated to the red Cal Fluor 610 dye (Biosearch Technologies) that are specific to <italic>N. parisii</italic> ribosomal RNA. Pathogen load was measured with the COPAS Biosort (Union Biometrica) by quantifying red fluorescence, and normalizing to time of flight to measure size. Events were gated to remove events that were not of worm size.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Identification of transcription factor binding sites near N. parisii infection-regulated genes</title><p>To identify transcription factor binding sites, we downloaded modENCODE high confidence peak transcription factor binding sites (TFBS) data, using the &#x0201c;TF binding site&#x0201d; file for 22 transcription factors reported in <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Gerstein <italic>et al.</italic> (2010</xref>), using modENCODE release #33 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://intermine.modencode.org/release-33/begin.do">http://intermine.modencode.org/release-33/begin.do</ext-link>). We then used bedTools version 2.22.1 to derive the [&#x02013;2000&#x000a0;bp, +150&#x000a0;bp] regions of genes in the WB190 <italic>C. elegans</italic> genome to perform an analysis of the intersection between these regions and the high confidence modENCODE TFBS regions. We then took a previously described RNA-seq dataset from a time-course of <italic>C. elegans</italic> infected with <italic>N. parisii</italic> (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Bakowski <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), found the number of binding sites for each transcription factor within infection-regulated (IR) genes, and used Fisher&#x02019;s exact test to determine the association of binding sites for each transcription factor with the promoters of IR genes, to determine the odds ratio that a particular transcription factor is enriched for having binding sites in IR genes. We used a two-sided alternative hypothesis, and counted only unique transcription factor-gene upstream sequence intersections (upstream sequences with multiple TFBS were only counted once). We then performed FDR correction for multiple comparisons using the Benjamini-Hochberg procedure with an FDR threshold of 0.01.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>qRT-PCR analysis</title><p>RNA was isolated from animals with Tri-Reagent and bromochloropropane (Molecular Research Center). mRNA was reverse transcribed into cDNA using oligo dT and the RETROscript kit (Ambion). cDNA for each sample was quantified with iQ SYBR Green Supermix (Bio-Rad) on a CFx Connect Real-time PCR Detection System (Bio-Rad). <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004897;class=Gene">snb-1</ext-link></italic> was used as a control gene. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007659;class=Gene">C17H1.6</ext-link> was used as a positive control for a gene that is differentially expressed after infection. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> forward primer: GGG AGC ACT TAC CTC CAC AT. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic> forward primer: CATTGGAAGCAGAGGGTACG. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic> reverse primer: GTTGTGTCATCGTCGGGTAC. GFP forward primer: TGGCAGACAAACAAAAGAATG. GFP reverse primer: GTTGAACGCTTCCATCTTCA. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004897;class=Gene">snb-1</ext-link></italic> forward primer: CCG GAT AAG ACC ATC TTG ACG. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004897;class=Gene">snb-1</ext-link></italic> reverse primer: GAC GAC TTC ATC AAC CTG AGC. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016052;class=Gene">dod-3</ext-link></italic> forward primer: AAGCCATGTGCATATTGTGG. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016052;class=Gene">dod-3</ext-link></italic> reverse primer: ATACTGGATCGTCTCAAGTTCG. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001244;class=Gene">elo-6</ext-link></italic> forward primer: CACCCACTTAAAACCCCACT. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001244;class=Gene">elo-6</ext-link></italic> reverse primer: AAATAGCAAGACCCGCATTC. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007331;class=Gene">pho-11</ext-link></italic> forward primer: TCCACAGAAACACGTCAACA. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007331;class=Gene">pho-11</ext-link></italic> reverse primer: TGTTCGAATTTTCTGGTTTCTC. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020191;class=Gene">clec-53</ext-link></italic> forward primer: ACTGGAATGATGATGTTCGTTT. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020191;class=Gene">clec-53</ext-link></italic> reverse primer: GCCATTTTGAGTTTTGATAGACC. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021768;class=Gene">Y51F10.7</ext-link> forward primer: GCGATTATTGACTTGATTGCTG. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021768;class=Gene">Y51F10.7</ext-link> reverse primer: TACTTGACAAACGCCGAACT. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00013637;class=Gene">Y105C5A.13</ext-link> forward primer: GGAAATGCGAATCCCAAC. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00013637;class=Gene">Y105C5A.13</ext-link> reverse primer: TCTGCACTTGGTTGATCTGAA. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012757;class=Gene">Y41C4A.11</ext-link> forward primer: GATTGCTCAATTTGTGTTTGG. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012757;class=Gene">Y41C4A.11</ext-link> reverse primer: AAAGTTAAGCGTGGTGTTTCC. Fold change was calculated using the Pfaffl method (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Pfaffl 2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Western blots</title><p>Animals were washed off NGM plates with M9 buffer, and then washed once with M9 to remove bacteria. Samples were then resuspended in sample buffer with 1% SDS and 50&#x000a0;mM dithiothreitol (DTT) and boiled at 95&#x000b0; for 10&#x000a0;min. Lysates were then run on a 4&#x02013;20% gradient SDS-PAGE gel (Bio-Rad) and transferred to Polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membrane (Bio-Rad). The blots were stained with M2 anti-FLAG antibody (Sigma-Aldrich) diluted at 1:1000 and JLA20 anti-actin antibody (Millipore) diluted at 1:1000. The blots were treated with ECL reagent (Amersham GE Healthcare Life Sciences), and imaged either on a Bio-Rad ChemiDoc or on film.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Fluorescence imaging of C. elegans</title><p>MDL-1::GFP::3xFLAG and MML-1::GFP::3xFLAG-expressing animals were imaged with a Zeiss LSM700 confocal microscope, as previously described (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Dunbar <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). All other fluorescence images were captured with a Zeiss AxioImager M1 fluorescence microscope.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad version 6.0 (Prism) software. For comparing multiple means (sporoplasm counting assay, spore levels assay, and FISH pathogen load), one-way ANOVA was performed comparing all means to a wild type control. For all plots, statistical significance is denoted using asterisks (*&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, **&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01, ***&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001, ****&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001).</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Data availability</title><p>The authors state that all data necessary for confirming the conclusions presented in the article are represented fully within the article.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s13"><title>Results</title><sec id="s14"><title>Identification of C. elegans transcription factors that regulate N. parisii spore levels</title><p>To identify host genes that are important for the development of microsporidia, we developed a fluorescence plate-reader-based assay to measure the levels of <italic>N. parisii</italic> spores inside of the <italic>C. elegans</italic> host. We used a chitin-binding dye called Direct Yellow 96 (DY96) to label the chitin-containing spore coat of <italic>N. parisii</italic> spores. DY96 fluoresces very brightly in the green channel, which is compatible with most fluorescence plate-readers (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Hoch <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). (The most commonly used chitin-binding dye, Calcofluor White, emits in the blue channel, which is less useful for plate reader assays). We stained animals at 44&#x000a0;hpi, when animals are typically filled with &#x0003e;&#x000a0;20,000 spores, thus providing robust DY96 signal (Supplemental Material, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1/FigureS1.ai">Figure S1</ext-link>). However, because DY96 can also stain <italic>C. elegans</italic> eggs (which contain chitin), we used conditionally sterile <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene">glp-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00144590;class=Variation">e2141</ext-link>)</italic> animals and carried out the assay at the nonpermissive temperature of 25&#x000b0; where these mutants do not produce eggs (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Priess <italic>et al.</italic> 1987</xref>).</p><p>With the DY96 plate-based assay, we screened a feeding RNAi library composed of &#x0223c;345 <italic>C. elegans</italic> predicted transcription factors to identify factors that regulate pathogen growth. This library represents roughly one-third of the total number of transcription factors in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> genome, and was selected because it has been previously used to identify regulators of pathogen response genes (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Estes <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). To screen the library, synchronized <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene">glp-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00144590;class=Variation">e2141</ext-link>)</italic> L1 larvae were grown in liquid culture 96-well plates, and fed bacteria expressing dsRNA against <italic>C. elegans</italic> genes for 24&#x000a0;hr. These animals were then infected with <italic>N. parisii</italic> spores, and 44 hpi they were fixed and stained with DY96 to label newly made spores. Fluorescence intensity was then quantified for each well using a fluorescent plate reader and normalized to the RNAi empty vector control (L4440) well. We used an arbitrary cut-off of &#x0003c;&#x000a0;65% of normalized DY96 fluorescence signal to define RNAi hits that decrease spore levels (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1/TableS1.xlsx">Table S1</ext-link>), which identified 32 RNAi clones. Ten clones were discarded because they caused larval arrest or lethal phenotypes, and the remaining 22 clones were tested with a secondary screening assay. To verify the phenotypes, we used a previously described spore levels assay in which infected animals are lysed to release spores, which are then counted using a hemocytometer (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Szumowski <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Nine RNAi clones caused a significant decrease in spore levels at 40 hpi, including two components of the &#x0201c;Myc interaction network&#x0201d;, <underline>M</underline>a<underline>d</underline>-<underline>L</underline>ike 1 (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>)</italic>, <underline>M</underline>a<underline>x</underline>-<underline>L</underline>ike 2, (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>)</italic>, and also a FoxA transcription factor, (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004013;class=Gene">pha-4</ext-link>)</italic>, which has been shown to have largely overlapping target genes with <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>) (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). The identification of three genes related to the Myc interaction network of transcription factors in <italic>C. elegans</italic> suggested that this pathway may be important for regulating <italic>N. parisii</italic> growth, which we further examined as described below.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>C. elegans Myc interaction network controls pathogen levels later in the pathogen life cycle</title><p>Canonical signaling of the factors in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> Myc interaction network, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">MXL-1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>. To confirm the role of <italic>C. elegans</italic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> during <italic>N. parisii</italic> infection, we investigated whether a deletion in <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> would recapitulate the <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> RNAi phenotype. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>)</italic> mutants have a 500&#x000a0;bp deletion in the <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> coding region that should lead to a truncated protein of only 64 amino acids (aa) lacking any functional domains, and is thus a presumed null mutation. Indeed, we found that <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>)</italic> mutants have a dramatic reduction in spore levels at 40&#x000a0;hpi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>), confirming this hit from our screen. <italic>C. elegans</italic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> protein has been shown to physically interact with the transcription factor <underline>M</underline>a<underline>x</underline>-<underline>l</underline>ike <underline>1</underline>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">MXL-1</ext-link> protein in two-hybrid studies (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Pickett <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Grove <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), and studies of aging and proteostasis in <italic>C. elegans</italic> support the model that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">MXL-1</ext-link> act together as a heterodimeric transcription factor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>) (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Furthermore, in mammalian systems, the homologs of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">MXL-1</ext-link> (Mad and Max) act as a heterodimeric transcription factor. It was not possible to identify <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link></italic> in our screen because the <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link></italic> RNAi clone was not present in the transcription factor RNAi library we used. Therefore, we investigated its role in spore levels with an <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250520;class=Variation">tm1530</ext-link>)</italic> mutant, which contains a 423 bp deletion. Here we found significantly reduced spore levels in <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250520;class=Variation">tm1530</ext-link>)</italic> animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>), suggesting that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">MXL-1</ext-link> could act together with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> in a canonical heterodimer to promote <italic>N. parisii</italic> spore levels.</p><fig id="fig2" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>C.<italic>elegans</italic> Myc interaction network transcription factors regulate <italic>N. parisii</italic> pathogen development. (A) Canonical wiring of Myc interaction network transcription factors. The mammalian homologs are listed above the <italic>C. elegans</italic> genes. MML-1 and MXL-2 are thought to act as a heterodimeric pair that promotes transcription and lifespan, and their activity is opposed by MDL-1 and MXL-1 acting as heterodimeric pair. (B and C) Spore levels at 40&#x000a0;hpi shown as the mean of three independent experiments, normalized to wild type animals. (D and E) Pathogen load of <italic>N. parisii</italic> meronts at 24&#x000a0;hpi, measured using an <italic>N. parisii</italic>-specific rRNA FISH probe. Three technical replicates were performed in each of three independent experiments. Fluorescence was measured with a COPAS Biosort and normalized to time-of-flight as a measure of body size, and then normalized to wild-type animals, with at least 325 animals per technical replicate. ns, not significant. *&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, **&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01, ***&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001, ****&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="2707f2"/></fig><p>Next, we examined how spore levels are regulated by two other components of the Myc transcription factor network, the <underline>M</underline>yc-<underline>M</underline>ondo-<underline>l</underline>ike <underline>1</underline> transcription factor (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link>)</italic> and the <underline>M</underline>a<underline>x</underline>-<underline>l</underline>ike transcription factor <underline>2</underline> (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>)</italic>. Based on mammalian Myc data and results in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, it is thought that the MDL-1/MXL-1 heterodimer represses expression of genes activated by a heterodimeric transcription factor composed of MML-1/MXL-2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>) (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Pickett <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Grove <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Thus, animals defective in <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic> and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link></italic> would be predicted to have increased spore levels. In support of this model, we found that <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00092124;class=Variation">ok849</ext-link></italic>)&#x02014;a mutant containing a 1390 bp deletion in the <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic> coding sequence&#x02014;had higher spore levels compared to wild type animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). Somewhat surprisingly, however, we found, in a secondary assay from our RNAi screen, that RNAi against <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link></italic> had a phenotype of reduced spore levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). To further examine this phenotype, we analyzed <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250507;class=Variation">tm1516</ext-link>)</italic> mutants, which have a 645 bp deletion that removes the putative DNA-binding domain, resulting in a 64&#x000a0;aa truncated protein with no functional domains, and has been previously characterized to be a null mutant (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Pickett <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Indeed, we found that <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250507;class=Variation">tm1516</ext-link>)</italic> mutants had reduced spore levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>), confirming our RNAi results. Thus, there appears to be noncanonical activity of the <italic>C. elegans</italic> Myc interaction transcription factor network during <italic>N. parisii</italic> infection (see epistasis results described in next section for further analysis).</p><p>To determine the pathogen growth stage at which the Myc interaction network regulates <italic>N. parisii</italic> development inside of <italic>C. elegans</italic> intestinal cells, we examined pathogen levels at an earlier stage of infection, prior to spore formation. Like all microsporidia, <italic>N. parisii</italic> first replicates in the meront stage before differentiating into spores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). <italic>N. parisii</italic> meronts are actively replicating and spreading throughout the <italic>C. elegans</italic> intestine at the 24&#x000a0;hpi timepoint, and so we quantified pathogen load at this stage using a FISH probe specific to <italic>N. parisii</italic> rRNA to label meronts in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain">N2</ext-link> wild type, and in <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>)</italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250520;class=Variation">tm1530</ext-link>)</italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250507;class=Variation">tm1516</ext-link>)</italic>, and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00092124;class=Variation">ok849</ext-link>)</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2, D and E</xref>). With this assay, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>)</italic> animals had a &#x0223c;25% decrease in meront levels, while the other mutants did not have a significant change. Thus, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> may have an effect on pathogen growth at this earlier time point of infection independent of the rest of the Myc interaction network. Overall, these data suggest that the Myc interaction network is more important for pathogen development during the later part of the life cycle when spores are being produced.</p><p>Because <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> mutants have a small but significant effect on pathogen growth at a stage before spore levels, we examined whether this phenotype may be due to a feeding defect that causes these animals to ingest fewer <italic>N. parisii</italic> spores. To determine whether <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain">N2</ext-link> and mutant animals were feeding at a similar rate, and thus receiving similar inoculums of <italic>N. parisii</italic> spores, we counted sporoplasms in wild type and mutant L1 animals after being fed spores for 4&#x000a0;hr. As a positive control to confirm that we can see a feeding difference in this assay, we used <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001133;class=Gene">eat-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00000014;class=Variation">ad465</ext-link>)</italic> mutants, which have a known feeding defect. Consistent with <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001133;class=Gene">eat-2</ext-link></italic> mutants having an &#x0223c;twofold reduction in feeding, we found that they also have a twofold decrease in the number of sporoplasms/animal. All of the loss of function mutants in the Myc transcription factor family had similar numbers of sporoplasms compared to wild-type animals, and thus do not affect the initial pathogen invasion events into intestinal cells (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1/FigureS2.tif">Figure S2</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Epistasis analysis of Myc interaction network shows noncanonical roles during infection</title><p>To more directly investigate the interactions among components of the Myc interaction network during infection with <italic>N. parisii</italic>, we performed genetic epistasis analysis. First, we investigated interactions between <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> and other components in the pathway that cause a decrease in spore levels. Canonically, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> interacts with <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link></italic> to regulate downstream outputs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>) and indeed we found that <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>);<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250520;class=Variation">tm1530</ext-link>)</italic> double mutants had the same level of spore reduction as <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>)</italic> or <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250520;class=Variation">tm1530</ext-link>)</italic> single mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). This result is consistent with these factors acting together as a heterodimeric complex to regulate gene expression. In contrast, we found that <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250507;class=Variation">tm1516</ext-link>);<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>)</italic> double mutants had reduced spore levels compared to either single mutant, indicating that these two factors likely act in parallel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig3" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Epistasis analysis of MDL-1, MXL-1, MML-1, and MXL-2 shows noncanonical activity of this pathway during infection. (A) Spore levels at 40&#x000a0;hpi were quantified in N2, <italic>mdl-1(tm311)</italic>, <italic>mxl-1(tm1530)</italic>, <italic>mxl-2(tm1516)</italic>, <italic>mxl-1(tm1530)</italic>;<italic>mdl-1(tm311)</italic>, and <italic>mxl-2(tm1516);mdl-1(tm311) C. elegans</italic>. Spore levels are the mean of three independent experiments, normalized to N2. Error bars are SEM. (B) Spore level values for N2, <italic>mdl-1(tm311)</italic> and <italic>mxl-2(tm1516)</italic> mutants treated with RNAi to knockdown <italic>mdl-1</italic>, <italic>mxl-2</italic>, or <italic>mml-1</italic>. Animal genotypes are denoted by brackets, and each column shows either empty vector control (L4440) or RNAi treatment. (C) Spore levels for N2 and <italic>mdl-1(tm311)</italic> animals treated with RNAi against all other transcription factor library hits (all comparisons with empty RNAi vector control found to be significant except for the three marked &#x0201c;ns&#x0201d;). Error bars represent the SEM for three independent experiments consisting of three replicates per experiment. ns, not significant. *&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, **&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01, ***&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="2707f3"/></fig><p>Next, we examined the epistatic interactions among these factors with RNAi knock-down in different mutant backgrounds. Consistent with the mutant analysis above, we found that RNAi against <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link></italic> in an <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> mutant background caused a further decrease in spore levels. We found that RNAi against <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> in an <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link></italic> mutant background caused a further decrease in spore levels. Thus, based on double mutant analysis, as well as RNAi in both single mutant backgrounds, we find that wild-type <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> acts in parallel to wild-type <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link></italic> to increase spore levels. We also found that RNAi against <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic> still caused an increase in spore levels in an <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>), indicating that <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic> acts in parallel to <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic>. Similarly, RNAi against <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic> still caused an increase in spore levels in an <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00250507;class=Variation">tm1516</ext-link>)</italic> mutant background (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). In summary, we have found that all four major components in the Myc interaction network regulate spore levels, with three components promoting spore levels (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link></italic>, and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link></italic>), and one component inhibiting spore levels (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic>). <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link></italic> appear to act together, while <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link></italic> and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic> act independently of them, and each other.</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Interaction between MDL-1 and other transcription factors that regulate spore levels</title><p>One of the other hits from our screen was the FoxA transcription factor <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004013;class=Gene">PHA-4</ext-link>. Although <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004013;class=Gene">PHA-4</ext-link> is not a primary member of the Myc interaction network, previous studies have indicated that there is a significant overlap in genes that contain both a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004013;class=Gene">PHA-4</ext-link> binding site (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Lifespan studies have shown that the effect of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> increase in lifespan is dependent on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004013;class=Gene">PHA-4</ext-link>. Because of this link, we probed RNAi against <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004013;class=Gene">PHA-4</ext-link> and the other transcription factor library hits in an <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>)</italic> mutant background, which would allow us to detect other transcription factors that may be working in the same pathway as <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic>. When RNAi against the nine screen hits was combined with a loss of <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> function, there was an additive decrease in spore levels for some genes (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004077;class=Gene">pop-1</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006796;class=Gene">unc-62</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001186;class=Gene">egl-18</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020399;class=Gene">ztf-4</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007776;class=Gene">dmd-4</ext-link></italic>, and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link></italic>), but not for <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004013;class=Gene">pha-4</ext-link></italic>, consistent with the link between <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004013;class=Gene">pha-4</ext-link></italic> and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> previously reported (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). In addition, there was no further decrease with RNAi against <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012101;class=Gene">zip-10</ext-link></italic>, which suggests that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012101;class=Gene">ZIP-10</ext-link> may act together&#x02014;a previously unknown interaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). Altogether, these data suggest that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004013;class=Gene">PHA-4</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012101;class=Gene">ZIP-10</ext-link> act in the same pathway as the Mad-like transcription factor <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> to regulate <italic>N. parisii</italic> spore levels.</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Analysis of transcription factor regulation of infection response gene expression</title><p>One potential role for host transcription factors that regulate spore levels is that they could be mediating a transcriptional response to <italic>N. parisii</italic> infection. Alternatively, these factors could be regulating gene expression independent of infection, and this basal regulation is important for pathogen development. To identify transcription factors that might directly regulate expression of infection response genes, either through induced or basal expression, we compared a modENCODE ChIP-seq dataset (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Gerstein <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) with an RNAseq dataset of the <italic>C. elegans</italic> response to <italic>N. parisii</italic> infection that we previously generated (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Bakowski <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). We searched for high-confidence transcription factor binding sites found within the promoter regions (&#x02013;2000&#x000a0;bp and +150&#x000a0;bp from predicted transcription start sites) of infection-regulated genes (genes that are &#x0003e;twofold up or down regulated). We then analyzed these data for: 1) the transcription factor that had binding sites in upstream regions of the greatest number of infection-regulated genes, and 2) enrichment of binding sites for a particular transcription factor in the upstream regions of infection-regulated genes compared to upstream regions of all genes in the genome. We found that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> had the third highest number of predicted binding sites among the 22 transcription factors from modENCODE that we analyzed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1/TableS2.xlsx">Table S2</ext-link>). However, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> did not show enrichment for binding sites upstream of infection-regulated genes compared to the rest of the genome (enrichment is defined as an odds ratio &#x0003e;&#x000a0;1, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1/TableS2.xlsx">Table S2</ext-link>). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> binding sites were only found in 13% of genes (78 of 620 genes) differentially expressed upon infection at any timepoint, while <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> binding sites can be found in 22% of upstream regions of all genes in the genome. We also did not find <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> enriched in the upstream regions of genes upregulated or downregulated by infection when we analyzed these gene sets separately (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1/TableS2.xlsx">Table S2</ext-link>). Due to the limited number of transcription factors analyzed in the ModENCODE project, it is difficult to say which transcription factor is the predominant transcription factor that regulates infection response genes in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, but these data suggest that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> is not the predominant transcription factor that regulates expression of infection-regulated genes.</p><p>Because <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> had such a strong phenotype in controlling pathogen development, however, we further investigated whether it might be directly controlling gene expression of at least some of the infection response genes. Therefore, we next used qRT-PCR to analyze a subset of genes whose transcripts change in response to <italic>N. parisii</italic>, and whose promoters contains a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> binding site to determine whether <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> was required for their change in expression upon <italic>N. parisii</italic> infection, or for controlling their expression basally. In choosing infection-regulated genes with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> binding sites we used a more stringent promoter region cut-off of &#x02013;700 to +100&#x000a0;bp from the transcriptional start site, and analyzed five genes that are repressed during infection (<italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016052;class=Gene">dod-3</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001244;class=Gene">elo-6</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007331;class=Gene">pho-11</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020191;class=Gene">clec-53</ext-link></italic>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021768;class=Gene">Y51F10.7</ext-link>) and two genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00013637;class=Gene">Y105C5A.13</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012757;class=Gene">Y41C4A.11</ext-link>) that are induced during infection (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1/TableS3.xlsx">Table S3</ext-link>). Relative transcript abundance was determined at 40&#x000a0;hpi, because this is a time point when we see large differences in spore levels. Here we found that <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> was not required for regulating gene expression upon infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). In particular, we found that the infection-repressed genes we tested are still repressed upon infection in <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> mutants, like in wild-type animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). Similarly, infection-induced genes are still induced in <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00249359;class=Variation">tm311</ext-link>)</italic> animals, like in wild-type animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). A gene known to be highly induced during infection, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007659;class=Gene">C17H1.6</ext-link>, was used a positive control for gene induction upon infection (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Bakowski <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), and the increase in transcript was at least 1000-fold in infected animals (data not shown). We also analyzed whether <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> regulates expression of these genes in the absence of infection, and found that <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> appears to play a minor role in regulating basal expression of some of these genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). In summary, through querying a subset of infection response genes that had predicted <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> binding sites, we did not find a role for <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> in mediating the transcriptional response to infection.</p><fig id="fig4" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>qRT-PCR analysis of the role of MDL-1 in expression of infection-regulated genes. qRT-PCR analysis was performed on infection-regulated genes that have MDL-1 binding sites in their promoter regions, including genes downregulated by infection (<italic>dod-3</italic>, <italic>elo-6</italic>, Y51F10.7, <italic>clec-53</italic>, and <italic>pho-11</italic>), and genes upregulated by infection (Y105C5A.13 and Y41C4A.11). (See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1/TableS3.xlsx">Table S3</ext-link> for RNAseq data.) mRNA fold change is the mean of three independent experiments each consisting of technical duplicates. Error bars are SEM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="2707f4"/></fig></sec><sec id="s19"><title>MDL-1::GFP and MML-1::GFP are expressed in the intestine during infection</title><p>To investigate the expression of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link> proteins&#x02014;two transcription factors with opposing and strong effects on spore levels&#x02014;we analyzed animals that contain integrated versions of either MDL-1::GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG or MML-1::GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG transgenes. Both of these transgenes were generated by the TransgeneOme project, and consist of genomic DNA with a GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG tag integrated at the C-terminus of each gene, flanked by several kilobases of regulatory region upstream and downstream of the gene of interest (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Sarov <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). First we investigated whether these tagged versions of the transcription factors could complement the mutant phenotypes, which would indicate that they are functional, and give confidence that they reflect endogenous protein expression. Here, we found that there was partial complementation for the reduced spore levels phenotype of <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> mutants with the MDL-1::GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG transgene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>), and full complementation for the increased spore level phenotype of <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00092124;class=Variation">ok849</ext-link>)</italic> mutants with MML-1::GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). Next, we examined their expression by Western blots and with fluorescence imaging. Here we found that both the MDL-1::GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG transgene, and the MML-1::GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG transgenes produced proteins of the expected sizes on a Western blot (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1/FigureS3.tif">Figure S3</ext-link>). When we analyzed tissue distribution of these transgenic proteins, we found that both GFP-tagged proteins were expressed in intestinal nuclei during infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5, C and D</xref>). Altogether, these data suggest that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> are likely expressed during infection within intestinal cells, the site of infection by <italic>N. parisii</italic>.</p><fig id="fig5" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>MDL-1::GFP-3&#x000d7;FLAG and MML-1::GFP-3&#x000d7;FLAG transgenes complement the mutant phenotypes and are expressed in the intestine during infection. (A) Spore levels of N2, <italic>mdl-1(tm311)</italic>, MDL-1::GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG, and <italic>mdl-1(tm311)</italic>; MDL-1::GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG <italic>C. elegans</italic>. (B) Spore level values of N2, <italic>mml-1(ok849)</italic>, MML-1:: GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG, and <italic>mml-1(ok849)</italic>; MML-1::GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG animals. For (A) and (B), spore levels are the average of three independent experiments; error bars represent SEM. ns, not significant. *&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, ****&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001. (C) Expression of MDL-1:: GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG in animals 24&#x000a0;hpi with <italic>N. parisii</italic>. (D) Expression of MML-1::GFP::3&#x000d7;FLAG in animals 24&#x000a0;hpi with <italic>N. parisii</italic>. For (C) and (D), arrows indicate intestinal nuclei expressing GFP, GFP is in green, autofluorescence in yellow, and scale bars are 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m. Left image for each shows GFP+ autofluorescence and right images show GFP+ autofluorescence + DIC brightfield. (E) Model for noncanonical wiring of Myc interaction network during <italic>N. parisii</italic> infection of <italic>C. elegans</italic>, based on epistasis analysis. MDL-1 acts with PHA-4 and ZIP-10 to promote pathogen development. It also acts together with MXL-1, likely as a heterodimeric binding partner to promote pathogen development. In parallel MML-1 inhibits pathogen development, while MXL-2 promotes pathogen development.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="2707f5"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s20"><title>Discussion</title><p>We have described an RNAi-based genetic screen to identify host transcription factors that are important for growth and development of the microsporidian pathogen <italic>N. parisii</italic> in its natural host, <italic>C. elegans</italic>. Despite the Microsporidia phylum containing over 1400 species, prior to this study almost nothing was known about the host factors important for the intracellular development of any species of microsporidia. Using our <italic>N. parisii</italic>/<italic>C. elegans</italic> screening strategy, we identified nine host genes whose knockdown decreases spore levels, and through investigating the Myc pathway further, identified a gene whose knockdown increases spore levels. These genes represent the first description of host transcription factors that regulate microsporidia growth and development. Because we screened a library of transcription factors, it is likely that these host genes are regulators of various processes (metabolism, stress response, etc.) that may be important for different aspects of pathogen growth, including production of essential metabolites, or helping the host cells cope with the incredibly rapid replication of the pathogen within the host cell. Further analysis of these transcription factors, including identifying potential downstream pathways and effectors that contribute to the observed spore-levels phenotypes will be critical for understanding microsporidian success as an intracellular pathogen.</p><p>Some of the major hits from our screen for host factors that regulate pathogen development are players in the Myc interaction network of transcription factors. In mammals, this network contains 11 transcription factors: three Myc, four Mad/Mxi, two Mnt/Mga, and two Mondo proteins, and these transcription factors are important regulators of cell growth, proliferation, and energy metabolism. Interestingly, two intracellular apicomplexan parasites, <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> and <italic>Theleria</italic>, have been shown to upregulate mammalian c-Myc upon infection (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Franco <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Dessauge <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>), so mammals and nematodes may share a role for Myc interaction network factors in the response to intracellular parasites. However, the connection between these findings is not clear, given that <italic>C. elegans</italic> lacks a clear Myc ortholog. Further analysis of mammalian Myc interaction network players that have clear <italic>C. elegans</italic> orthologs could shed light on this question. The <italic>C. elegans</italic> Myc interaction network is highly reduced, being comprised of only four major players, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">mxl-1</ext-link></italic>, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link></italic>, and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic>, with MDL-1:MXL-1 (Mad-Max) heterodimers and MML-1:MXL-2 (Myc-Mondo-Max) heterodimers. Of note, a previous study that indicated these two heterodimers have opposing functions in lifespan also indicated that they regulate expression of genes that are associated with pathogen response and immunity, but the significance of this regulation is unknown (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).</p><p>In this work we have shown that <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic> have strong and opposing effects on the growth and development of microsporidia within <italic>C. elegans</italic> intestinal cells. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> appears to be acting canonically with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">MXL-1</ext-link> to promote pathogen growth. In contrast, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link> appears to inhibit pathogen growth, and be acting independently of its standard binding partner, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link>, which promotes pathogen growth. Thus, it may be that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link> acts with a different heterodimeric binding partner to inhibit pathogen development, and similarly <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> acts with a different heterodimeric binding partner to promote pathogen development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>). <italic>C. elegans</italic> has a paralog of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">MXL-1</ext-link>, called <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003511;class=Gene">MXL-3</ext-link>, which regulates lipolysis and autophagy in response to nutrient availability (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">O&#x02019;Rourke and Ruvkun 2013</xref>), and can also interact with the transcription factor <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004804;class=Gene">SKN-1</ext-link> to mediate a starvation response (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Paek <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), but this protein is not thought to interact with other members of the Myc interaction network of transcription factors (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Grove <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Future work could investigate the role of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003511;class=Gene">MXL-3</ext-link> in regulating spore levels.</p><p>Recent findings by <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura <italic>et al.</italic> (2016</xref>) have shown that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> are responsive to signals from the germline to promote increased lifespan. Transcriptional profiling of <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">mml-1</ext-link></italic> and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">mxl-2</ext-link></italic> mutants revealed that these transcription factors regulate an overlapping cohort of target genes, although <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> appears to regulate a large number of genes independently of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link>. Thus <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> is likely interacting with other binding partners to regulate gene expression. Given that our study indicates that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> have distinct functions in regulating pathogen development, interaction between <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> and other transcription factors may be a common mechanism to achieve distinct outputs by this factor. Another important finding from <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura <italic>et al.</italic> (2016</xref>) is that <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> signaling leads to an upregulation of autophagy gene expression. Interestingly, ubiquitin-mediated responses and autophagy have previously been shown to provide defense against <italic>N. parisii</italic> in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, although <italic>N. parisii</italic> infection does not upregulate transcription of autophagy genes directly, but rather upregulates expression of ubiquitin ligase components that could act upstream of autophagy (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Bakowski <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura <italic>et al.</italic> (2016</xref>) showed that the MML-1/MXL-2 regulation of autophagy is found only in animals lacking a germline, such as the <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene">glp-1</ext-link>(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00144590;class=Variation">e2141</ext-link>)</italic> mutants that we used in our RNAi screen. However, in our study, the effect of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> on spore levels was the same whether animals have a germline or not. Thus, it is unlikely that the effect of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link> on pathogen development is due solely to their regulation of autophagy via germline removal as described by <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura <italic>et al.</italic> (2016</xref>).</p><p>We also identified other transcription factors from our screen for regulators of microsporidia growth, and found that two of them appear to act together with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> based on epistasis analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5E</xref>). One of them, <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004013;class=Gene">pha-4</ext-link></italic>, is a transcription factor whose putative target genes largely overlap with those of <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), and we found that it has no additive effect on spore levels when it is mutated together with <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic>. Analysis of these two factors for their effects on lifespan showed similar interactions (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). We also identified a novel genetic interaction between the bZIP transcription factor <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012101;class=Gene">zip-10</ext-link></italic> and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic>. <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012101;class=Gene">zip-10</ext-link></italic> has previously been described to regulate <italic>C. elegans</italic> body size and male tail morphogenesis downstream of the TGF-&#x003b2; signaling ligand <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000936;class=Gene">dbl-1</ext-link></italic>, and the smad transcription factor <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004862;class=Gene">sma-9</ext-link></italic> (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Liang <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). However, little is known about the effectors downstream of <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012101;class=Gene">zip-10</ext-link></italic>, particularly within intestinal cells, which is the site of <italic>N. parisii</italic> infection. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> does not appear to regulate the transcriptional response to infection, but there are likely to be multiple effectors downstream of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">MDL-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012101;class=Gene">ZIP-10</ext-link>, as well as downstream of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003509;class=Gene">MXL-1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003510;class=Gene">MXL-2</ext-link>, that are promoting intracellular pathogen development, while effectors downstream of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003378;class=Gene">MML-1</ext-link> likely inhibit intracellular pathogen development. Further analysis of the interaction of <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012101;class=Gene">zip-10</ext-link></italic> and <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003163;class=Gene">mdl-1</ext-link></italic> both genetically and biochemically, including understanding the upstream signaling that regulate these transcription factors, and downstream effectors of these transcription factors will enhance our understanding of how an intracellular pathogen hijacks host resources, and also provide new understanding into the plasticity of the Myc interaction network in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplemental Material</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_6_9_2707__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="ps"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.029983_FigureS1.ps"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.029983_FigureS2.tif"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.029983_FigureS3.tif"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.029983_TableS1.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.029983_TableS2.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.029983_TableS3.xlsx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Andy Samuelson for <italic>C. elegans</italic> strains and for the <italic>mml-1</italic> RNAi clone, Michael David&#x02019;s lab for use of their fluorescence plate reader, and Keir Balla, Robert Luallen, and Kirthi Reddy for critical reading of the manuscript. Some strains were provided by the <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic> Genetics Center (CGC), which is funded by National Institutes of Health (NIH) Office of Research Infrastructure Programs (P40 OD010440). This work was supported by NIH F32AI114190 to M.R.B., NIH predoctoral training grant T32 GM008666 to L.B.C., NIH grant R01GM114139, the David and Lucile Packard Foundation, and Burroughs Wellcome Fund fellowship to E.R.T.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p>Supplemental material is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1">www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.029983/-/DC1</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn2"><p>Communicating editor: S. Lee</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakowski</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desjardins</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smelkinson</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunbar</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Moyado</surname><given-names>I. F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Ubiquitin-mediated response to microsporidia and virus infection in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e1004200</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24945527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruglyak</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Troemel</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A wild <italic>C. elegans</italic> strain has enhanced epithelial immunity to a natural microsporidian parasite.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>e1004583</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25680197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1974</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The genetics of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>77</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4366476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corradi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pombert</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farinelli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Didier</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The complete sequence of the smallest known nuclear genome from the microsporidian <italic>Encephalitozoon intestinalis</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20865802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuomo</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desjardins</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakowski</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Microsporidian genome analysis reveals evolutionary strategies for obligate intracellular growth.</article-title>
<source>Genome Res.</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2478</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2488</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22813931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dessauge</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilaly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Werling</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2005</year>&#x02003;<article-title>c-Myc activation by <italic>Theileria</italic> parasites promotes survival of infected B-lymphocytes.</article-title>
<source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1075</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1083</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15580287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Didier</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Microsporidiosis: not just in AIDS patients.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Opin. Infect. Dis.</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>490</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>495</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21844802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunbar</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smelkinson</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Troemel</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>C. elegans</italic> detects pathogen-induced translational inhibition to activate immune signaling.</article-title>
<source>Cell Host Microbe</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22520465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Estes</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunbar</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Troemel</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>bZIP transcription factor zip-2 mediates an early response to <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> infection in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>107</volume>: <fpage>2153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2158</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20133860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shastri</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boothroyd</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Infection by <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> specifically induces host c-Myc and the genes this pivotal transcription factor regulates.</article-title>
<source>Eukaryot. Cell</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>493</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24532536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z. J</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Nostrand</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arshinoff</surname><given-names>B. I.</given-names></name></person-group>, <italic>et al</italic>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Integrative analysis of the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> genome by the modENCODE project.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>330</volume>: <fpage>1775</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1787</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21177976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grove</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Masi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrasa</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newburger</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alkema</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A multiparameter network reveals extensive divergence between <italic>C. elegans</italic> bHLH transcription factors.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>138</volume>: <fpage>314</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>327</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19632181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartolome</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Botias</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin-Hernandez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>Nosema ceranae</italic> (Microsporidia), a controversial 21st century honey bee pathogen.</article-title>
<source>Environ. Microbiol. Rep.</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23757127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoch</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galvani</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szarowski</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2005</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Two new fluorescent dyes applicable for visualization of fungal cell walls.</article-title>
<source>Mycologia</source>
<volume>97</volume>: <fpage>580</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>588</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16392246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Llop</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolzenburg</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> Myc-Mondo/Mad complexes integrate diverse longevity signals.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Genet.</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e1004278</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24699255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katinka</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duprat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornillot</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Metenier</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomarat</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2001</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genome sequence and gene compaction of the eukaryote parasite <italic>Encephalitozoon cuniculi</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>414</volume>: <fpage>450</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>453</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fast</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Microsporidia: biology and evolution of highly reduced intracellular parasites.</article-title>
<source>Annu. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12142484</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savage-Dunn</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcriptional repressor and activator activities of SMA-9 contribute differentially to BMP-related signaling outputs.</article-title>
<source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>305</volume>: <fpage>714</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>725</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17397820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McFerrin</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atchley</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Evolution of the Max and Mlx networks in animals.</article-title>
<source>Genome Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>915</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>937</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21859806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karalay</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horikawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2016</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Mondo complexes regulate TFEB via TOR inhibition to promote longevity in response to gonadal signals.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>10944</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27001890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Rourke</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvkun</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>MXL-3 and HLH-30 transcriptionally link lipolysis and autophagy to nutrient availability.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>668</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>676</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23604316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glover-Cutter</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Mitochondrial SKN-1/Nrf mediates a conserved starvation response.</article-title>
<source>Cell Metab.</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>526</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>537</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23040073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>El Alaoui</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbach</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Demettre</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Hijacking of host cellular functions by an intracellular parasite, the microsporidian <italic>Anncaliia algerae</italic>.</article-title>
<source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e100791</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24967735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfaffl</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2001</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A new mathematical model for relative quantification in real-time RT-PCR.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>e45</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11328886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Breen</surname><given-names>K. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayer</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A <italic>C. elegans</italic> Myc-like network cooperates with semaphorin and Wnt signaling pathways to control cell migration.</article-title>
<source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>310</volume>: <fpage>226</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>239</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17826759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Priess</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnabel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnabel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1987</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The <italic>glp-1</italic> locus and cellular interactions in early C. elegans embryos.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>601</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>611</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3677169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riesen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feyst</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattanavirotkul</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezcurra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tullet</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>MDL-1, a growth- and tumor-suppressor, slows aging and prevents germline hyperplasia and hypertrophy in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Aging (Albany, N.Y.)</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>98</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sak</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelikanova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kvetonova</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Unapparent microsporidial infection among immunocompetent humans in the Czech Republic.</article-title>
<source>J. Clin. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1064</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1070</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21191056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schanze</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozniakovski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A genome-scale resource for in vivo tag-based protein function exploration in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>150</volume>: <fpage>855</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>866</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22901814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stentiford</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feist</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Microsporidia: diverse, dynamic, and emergent pathogens in aquatic systems.</article-title>
<source>Trends Parasitol.</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>578</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24091244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stentiford</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Becnel</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Didier</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2016</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Microsporidia&#x02014;emergent pathogens in the global food chain.</article-title>
<source>Trends Parasitol.</source>
<volume>32</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>336</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>348</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26796229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szumowski</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Troemel</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Microsporidia-host interactions.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25847674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szumowski</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Botts</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Popovich</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smelkinson</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Troemel</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The small GTPase RAB-11 directs polarized exocytosis of the intracellular pathogen <italic>N. parisii</italic> for fecal-oral transmission from <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>111</volume>: <fpage>8215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8220</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24843160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Texier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidau</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigues</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>El Alaoui</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delbac</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Microsporidia: a model for minimal parasite-host interactions.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Opin. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>449</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20542726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Troemel</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>New models of microsporidiosis: infections in zebrafish, <italic>C. elegans</italic>, and honey bee.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1001243</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21379567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Troemel</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiteman</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barriere</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Microsporidia are natural intracellular parasites of the nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Biol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>2736</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2752</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19071962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsaousis</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunji</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucocq</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirt</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A novel route for ATP acquisition by the remnant mitochondria of <italic>Encephalitozoon cuniculi</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>453</volume>: <fpage>553</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>556</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18449191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Helander</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilstal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lourenco</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Myc and its interactors take shape.</article-title>
<source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
<volume>1849</volume>: <fpage>469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>483</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24933113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vavra</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Microsporidia and &#x02018;the art of living together.&#x02019;</article-title>
<source>Adv. Parasitol.</source>
<volume>82</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>319</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23548087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Unique physiology of host-parasite interactions in microsporidia infections.</article-title>
<source>Cell. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1551</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1560</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19673893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>