<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microbiology</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Microbiology (Reading, Engl.)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Micro</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">mic</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1350-0872</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1465-2080</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Society for General Microbiology</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3353397</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816880</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">050278</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.050278-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Standard</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genes and Genomes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Quantitative RNA-seq analysis of the <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> transcriptome</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="recto-page-foot"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mic.sgmjournals.org">http://mic.sgmjournals.org</ext-link></alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="verso-running-head">R. R. Chaudhuri and others</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="recto-running-head">Transcriptome of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names>Roy R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Lu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kanji</surname><given-names>Alpa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>Timothy T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>Paul P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>Jyoti</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maskell</surname><given-names>Duncan J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>Andrew J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Veterinary Medicine, University of Cambridge, Madingley Road, Cambridge CB3 0ES, UK</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, Wellcome Trust Genome Campus, Hinxton, Cambridge CB10 1SA, UK</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Ussery</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence</bold> Andrew J. Grant <email xlink:href="ajg60@cam.ac.uk">ajg60@cam.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn id="fn1" fn-type="other"><p>The complete dataset for quantifying transcript levels in this study has been deposited in the ArrayExpress database with the accession no. E-MTAB-706. The complete protein sequencing dataset from this study has been deposited in the PRIDE database with the accession nos 17661 and 17684.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. --><volume>157</volume><issue>Pt 10</issue><fpage>2922</fpage><lpage>2932</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2011 SGM</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="2922_mic050278.pdf"/><abstract><p><italic>C</italic><italic>ampylobacter jejuni</italic> is the most common bacterial cause of foodborne disease in the developed world. Its general physiology and biochemistry, as well as the mechanisms enabling it to colonize and cause disease in various hosts, are not well understood, and new approaches are required to understand its basic biology. High-throughput sequencing technologies provide unprecedented opportunities for functional genomic research. Recent studies have shown that direct Illumina sequencing of cDNA (RNA-seq) is a useful technique for the quantitative and qualitative examination of transcriptomes. In this study we report RNA-seq analyses of the transcriptomes of <italic>C. jejuni</italic> (NCTC11168) and its <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant. This has allowed the identification of hitherto unknown transcriptional units, and further defines the regulon that is dependent on <italic>rpoN</italic> for expression. The analysis of the NCTC11168 transcriptome was supplemented by additional proteomic analysis using liquid chromatography-MS. The transcriptomic and proteomic datasets represent an important resource for the <italic>Campylobacter</italic> research community.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp1">Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra)</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp2">Defra/Higher Education Funding Council of England</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp3">Veterinary Training and Research Initiative</funding-source><award-id rid="sp3">VT0105</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp4">Medical Research Council</funding-source><award-id rid="sp4">G0801161</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp5">Wellcome Trust</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp6">Wellcome Trust</funding-source><award-id rid="sp6">079643/Z/06/Z</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Disc-work</meta-name><meta-value>Sarah Ferris</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>openaccess</meta-name><meta-value>free</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OpenAccessEmbargo</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><def-list list-type="simple" list-content="abbreviations"><title>Abbreviations: </title><def-item><term>CDS</term><def><p>coding sequence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LC</term><def><p>liquid chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ncRNA</term><def><p>non-coding RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNA-seq</term><def><p>transcriptome sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPKM</term><def><p>reads per kb of transcript per million mapped reads</p></def></def-item></def-list></notes></front><body><sec id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> is the most common bacterial cause of foodborne disease in the developed world, with an estimated one in every 100 individuals in the UK developing a <italic>Campylobacter</italic>-related illness each year, resulting in an economic burden of up to &#x000a3;500 million per annum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r19">Humphrey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Although most cases are self-limiting, <italic>C. jejuni</italic> has been associated with severe post-infection complications, including polyneuropathies such as Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r14">Goodyear <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). The bacterium is a common gut commensal of animals destined for human consumption, and faecal contamination of meat during processing is a recognized route of transmission to humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r9">Corry &#x00026; Atabay, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r18">Herman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). <italic>C. jejuni</italic> (NCTC11168) was the first food-borne pathogen to be sequenced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r26">Parkhill <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>) due to its importance as a pathogen and the fact that it has a relatively small genome (1.6 Mb). Many other <italic>Campylobacter</italic> species have been sequenced, and these genome sequences have facilitated many functional genomics-based approaches to study the roles of individual genes and proteins in colonization, environmental survival and virulence.</p><p>An important step in the control of bacterial gene expression is the initiation of transcription, which is dependent on the DNA-dependent RNA polymerase core enzyme binding a sigma factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r30">Polyakov <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>). Unlike <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, which has seven sigma factors, the genome sequence of <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 revealed the presence of only three (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r26">Parkhill <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>): RpoD (&#x003c3;<sup>70</sup>), responsible for the transcription of most genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r28">Petersen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>), and RpoN (&#x003c3;<sup>54</sup>) and RpoF/FliA (&#x003c3;<sup>28</sup>), which control the expression of genes required for flagellum biosynthesis and chemotaxis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r17">Hendrixson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r20">Jagannathan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r45">Wassenaar <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>). The lack of sigma factors in <italic>C. jejuni</italic> suggests that alternative regulatory mechanisms must exist and/or that the two alternative sigma factors play wider regulatory roles than those characterized in other species. Although &#x003c3;<sup>54</sup> is known to be involved in the transcription of flagellar genes including those encoding the hook, basal body and minor flagellin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r5">Carrillo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r16">Hendrixson &#x00026; DiRita, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r47">W&#x000f6;sten <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), the complete RpoN regulon in <italic>C. jejuni</italic> has not been fully defined.</p><p><italic>C. jejuni</italic> remains a poorly understood pathogen and many of the paradigms that have been established with &#x02018;model&#x02019; bacterial species such as <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> do not apply to it. Consequently, new approaches are required to understand this pathogen. Recently, several eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r8">Cloonan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">Mortazavi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r46">Wilhelm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) and prokaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r27">Perkins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r48">Yoder-Himes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) have been profiled at the transcriptome level using direct high-throughput Illumina sequencing of cDNA. This technique offers the ability to survey the entire transcriptome of an organism in a high-throughput and quantitative manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r23">Marioni <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r42">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Since a large number of sequencing reads can be readily obtained, the method is sensitive and offers a large dynamic range. Thus RNA-seq can be used to detect and quantify RNA expressed at very low levels, in contrast with what can be found using DNA microarrays (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r25">Nagalakshmi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>).</p><p>In this study we have used Illumina high-throughput DNA sequencing to study mRNA expression levels (i.e. the transcriptome) of <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168, and have compared the transcriptome data with protein expression data. In addition we have used RNA-seq to map and quantify the transcriptome of an <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant. We have compared RNA-seq with existing microarray technologies for their abilities to identify differentially expressed genes, and we have identified putative small non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs) that would not have been apparent using microarray technology.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title/><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Bacteria.</title><p><italic>E. coli</italic> strain DH5&#x003b1; was grown at 37 &#x000b0;C on Luria&#x02013;Bertani (LB) agar or in LB broth. Preparation of electrocompetent <italic>E. coli</italic> cells and transformations were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">Dower <italic>et al.</italic>, 1988</xref>). <italic>C. jejuni</italic> was routinely cultured on Mueller&#x02013;Hinton (MH) agar (Oxoid) supplemented with 5&#x0200a;% defibrinated horse blood (hereafter referred to as MH blood agar plates) at 42 &#x000b0;C under microaerobic conditions (5&#x0200a;% O<sub>2</sub>, 5&#x0200a;% CO<sub>2</sub>, 5&#x0200a;% H<sub>2</sub>, 85&#x0200a;% N<sub>2</sub>) in a MACS VA500 variable atmosphere workstation (Don Whitley Scientific). Liquid cultures of <italic>C. jejuni</italic> were grown in brain heart infusion (BHI) broth (Oxoid) at 42 &#x000b0;C under microaerobic conditions with agitation at 150 r.p.m. Where necessary for selection, media were supplemented with chloramphenicol (10 &#x000b5;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), ampicillin (100 &#x000b5;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) or trimethoprim (10 &#x000b5;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Generation of <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 <italic>rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> mutant.</title><p>The <italic>C. jejuni rpoN</italic> mutant was generated by insertional inactivation of the gene using a chloramphenicol acetyltransferase (<italic>cat</italic>) cassette. Standard methods were used for molecular cloning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r32">Sambrook &#x00026; Russell, 2001</xref>). Chromosomal and plasmid DNA purifications were performed using commercial kits following the manufacturers&#x02019; instructions (Qiagen). Routine DNA modifications including restriction endonuclease digestion of DNA, modifications of DNA and ligations were carried out according to the manufacturers, instructions (Promega, Invitrogen, Roche, New England Bioloabs). PCR primers were designed using Primer3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://frodo.wi.mit.edu/">http://frodo.wi.mit.edu/</ext-link>primer3/) and purchased from Sigma. All PCRs were performed in 50 &#x000b5;l reaction volumes in 0.2 ml Eppendorf tubes in an Applied Biosystems GeneAmp PCR Systems 9700 (Applied Biosystems). Reactions contained 200 &#x000b5;M dNTPs, 2 mM Mg<sup>2+</sup>, 0.01 vols Proof Start DNA polymerase (Qiagen; 2.5 U &#x000b5;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), 0.1 vols polymerase buffer (10&#x000d7;), 1 &#x000b5;M forward and reverse primers, and template DNA (~50 ng plasmid DNA or ~100 ng chromosomal DNA). Typical thermal cycler conditions were 94 &#x000b0;C for 4 min, 30 cycles of 94 &#x000b0;C for 1 min, 55 &#x000b0;C for 1 min and 72 &#x000b0;C for 1 min, followed by a final extension of 72 &#x000b0;C for 7 min. DNA and RNA concentration and purity were measured using a Nanodrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer. The <italic>rpoN</italic> gene was amplified by PCR from <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 chromosomal DNA using primers ajg285 (5&#x02032;-GGGGGGATCCATGTTAAAGCAAAAAATCACC-3&#x02032;) and ajg286 (5&#x02032;-GGGGGGATCCTTATCCTTCAAGTTCATATAA-3&#x02032;); the resulting fragment was cloned as a <italic>Bam</italic>HI fragment into <italic>Bam</italic>HI-digested pUC19 to generate the plasmid pAK1. To facilitate subsequent selections a chloramphenicol resistance gene with its promoter was amplified by PCR from pEnterprise2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r17">Hendrixson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>) using primers ajg289 (5&#x02032;-GGATCCCTTAAGCTCGGCGGTGTTCCTTTCCAA-3&#x02032;) and ajg290 (5&#x02032;-GGATCCCTTAAGCGCTTTAGTTCCTAAAGGG-3&#x02032;) and inserted as an <italic>Afl</italic>II fragment into <italic>Afl</italic>II-digested pAK1 (<italic>rpoN</italic> contained a unique <italic>Afl</italic>II restriction site), generating pAK2. pAK2, with a <italic>cat</italic> cassette in the forward orientation relative to <italic>rpoN</italic>, was introduced into <italic>C. jejuni</italic> by natural transformation using a plate biphasic method adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r41">Van Vliet <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref>. The structure of a representative isolate, with a chromosomally located <italic>rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> insertion, was confirmed by PCR and Southern hybridization (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Motility assays.</title><p>Motility assays were performed essentially as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r34">Silverman &#x00026; Simon (1973)</xref>. Briefly, a platinum wire was dipped into a single colony and used to stab MH motility medium containing 0.4&#x0200a;% agar. Motility was assessed by measuring colony diameter after incubation at 42 &#x000b0;C for 16 h.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>RNA preparation for RNA-seq.</title><p><italic>C. jejuni</italic> strains were cultured for 48 h on MH blood agar plates with antibiotics added as appropriate. Bacterial lawns were harvested in 1 ml BHI broth, 50 &#x000b5;l of which was inoculated into 10 ml BHI broth in a 50 ml Falcon centrifuge tube with a loosened cap, and grown for 16 h at 42 &#x000b0;C under microaerobic conditions with agitation at 150 r.p.m. to generate a starter culture. The OD<sub>600</sub> of starter cultures was measured by using a 6305 UV/Visible Spectrophotometer (Jenway). Starter cultures were diluted appropriately in BHI broth and used to inoculate 10 ml BHI broth containing 10 &#x000b5;g trimethoprim ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in a 50 ml falcon tube (previously equilibrated at 42 &#x000b0;C in microaerobic conditions for 16 h) to a calculated OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.00002. Cultures were grown at 42 &#x000b0;C under microaerobic conditions with shaking at 150 r.p.m. for 24 h. Growth was monitored by recording OD<sub>600</sub> and by determining viable c.f.u. ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> by serial 10-fold dilution of cultures in BHI broth and plating onto MH agar. Plates were incubated microaerobically at 42 &#x000b0;C for 48 h before colonies were counted. <italic>C. jejuni</italic> cultures were fixed with 2 vols RNA protect bacteria (Qiagen) and harvested. RNA was isolated from the pellet using the SV RNA isolation kit (Promega) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. 23S and 16S rRNA was depleted using a MicrobExpress kit (Ambion). Genomic DNA was removed with two digestions, using amplification-grade DNase I (Invitrogen), to below levels detectable by PCR. RNA was reverse-transcribed using random primers (Invitrogen) and Superscript III (Invitrogen) at 45 &#x000b0;C for 3 h and denatured at 70 &#x000b0;C for 15 min. <italic>leuB</italic> (using primers QJAW084 5&#x02032;-GCAAGTATAGATGCTTATGGAGTG-3&#x02032; and QJAW085 5&#x02032;-CTCTTTCAGGTCTTTGATCTATGG-3&#x02032;), <italic>aroA</italic> (QJAW092 5&#x02032;-GCTTTGGCTAAGGGTAAATCTAGT-3&#x02032; and QJAW093 5&#x02032;-ATCAAGTTCTCTAGCTTCAACACC-3&#x02032;), <italic>lpxD</italic> (QJAW104 5&#x02032;-GGAGCTTATATAGGCGATAATGTC-3&#x02032; and QJAW105 5&#x02032;-CAAAACCGTCACTTCCTATTACAC-3&#x02032;) and <italic>guaB</italic> (QJAW108 5&#x02032;-GGGTGTTGATGTTGTTGTGC-3&#x02032; and QJAW109 5&#x02032;-GGCGATATTTCCTGCGATAA-3&#x02032;) were used as targets for a PCR as a positive control for reverse transcription.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>Library construction and sequencing.</title><p>Library construction and sequencing were carried out as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r27">Perkins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-6"><title>Read mapping and visualization.</title><p>Reads were mapped to the <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 genome sequence (GenBank accession no. AL111168) using Novoalign version 2.05 (Novocraft Technologies; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.novocraft.com">http://www.novocraft.com</ext-link>) with default settings. Reads that mapped to more than one position in the genome were randomly distributed amongst the matching regions. Mapped reads were visualized using the version of BamView (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r6">Carver <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>) integrated into Artemis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r31">Rutherford <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). All subsequent analyses were performed using R version 2.8.0.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-7"><title>Quantification of transcript levels.</title><p>To estimate the level of transcription for each gene, the number of reads that mapped within each annotated coding sequence (CDS) was determined. To account for the possibility of unannotated ncRNA genes, the number of reads that mapped within each intergenic region of &#x0003e;150 bp was also determined. Reads that mapped within 50 bp of the adjacent genes were discarded to prevent the presence of 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; untranslated regions of adjacent transcripts from influencing the read count for the intergenic region. To enable comparison of expression levels, between both different RNA-seq experiments and different genes within the same experiment, it is necessary to normalize the read counts. The number of reads per kb of transcript per million mapped reads (RPKM) has been proposed as a useful metric that normalizes for variation in transcript length and sequence yield (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">Mortazavi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). RPKM values for each gene and intergenic region were calculated for the data from each Illumina lane, and mean RPKM values were determined for the wild-type and <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant samples. As RPKM values are log-normally distributed, it is convenient to express them as log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1). The complete dataset from this study has been deposited in the ArrayExpress database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress</ext-link>) with the accession no. E-MTAB-706.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-8"><title>Analysis of differential expression.</title><p>Differential expression was assessed using DESeq (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r2">Anders &#x00026; Huber, 2010</xref>). The total read count was determined for each gene and intergenic region by combining data from the two technical replicate sequencing runs. Read counts for the wild-type and the <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant were compared to determine the log<sub>2</sub>-fold change in abundance of each transcript. DESeq allows a <italic>P</italic>-value to be determined in the absence of any available biological replicates, by treating the two conditions as replicates, under the assumption that only a small proportion of transcripts is differentially expressed. <italic>P</italic>-values were calculated under this assumption, and adjusted for multiple testing using the false discovery rate controlling procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r3">Benjamini &#x00026; Hochberg, 1995</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-9"><title>Microarray analysis.</title><p>Raw data from an earlier <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant microarray study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">Kamal <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) were retrieved from B&#x000b5;G@Sbase and reanalysed by using Limma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r36">Smyth, 2005</xref>). Background signals were subtracted from the foreground, and any resulting negative signals were assigned an arbitrary value of 0.5, to prevent problems arising from taking the log of a negative number. Within-array Loess normalization was performed for each array, and signals were scaled between arrays to have the same median-absolute-deviation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r37">Smyth &#x00026; Speed, 2003</xref>). Within-array replicate spot signals were averaged, and correlation of the signals for technical replicate arrays was assessed using the duplicate Correlation function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r38">Smyth <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Differential expression was assessed by using a linear modelling approach with empirical Bayes statistics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r35">Smyth, 2004</xref>), and the resultant <italic>P</italic>-values were adjusted for multiple testing using the false discovery rate controlling procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r3">Benjamini &#x00026; Hochberg, 1995</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-10"><title>Cellular fractionation and protein sequencing.</title><p>Bacteria were harvested from 5 ml culture (bacteria were grown as described above for RNA preparation for RNA-seq) by centrifugation in a micro-centrifuge (Hettich Mikro 22R) at 13&#x0200a;000 r.p.m. and 4 &#x000b0;C for 2 min. The supernatant was removed by aspiration, and the protein samples were resuspended in 2&#x000d7; final sample buffer (FSB) [0.125 M Tris/HCl (pH 6.8), 4&#x0200a;% SDS, 20&#x0200a;% glycerol, 10&#x0200a;% 2-mercaptoethanol, 0.05&#x0200a;% Bromophenol Blue], reduced with DTT and alkylated with iodoacetamide prior to separation in a 4&#x02013;12&#x0200a;% NuPAGE Bistris gel (Invitrogen). Gels were stained with colloidal Coomassie Blue (Sigma) and bands were excised and in-gel digested with trypsin (sequencing grade; Roche). The extracted peptides were analysed with online nano liquid chromatography (LC)-MS/MS on an Ultimate 3000 Nano/Capillary LC System (Dionex) coupled to a Q-Tof Premier (Waters) or LTQ FT Ultra (ThermoElectron) mass spectrometer equipped with a nanoelectrospray source. Samples were first loaded and desalted on a PepMap C18 trap (0.3 or 0.5 mm id &#x000d7; 5 mm, Dionex) then separated on a C18 analytical column [Atlantis 100 &#x000b5;m id &#x000d7; 22 cm (Waters), PepMap 75 &#x000b5;m id &#x000d7; 25 cm (Dionex) or BEH 75 &#x000b5;m id x 10 cm (Waters)] over a 45, 60 or 90 min linear gradient of 4&#x02013;32&#x0200a;% CH<sub>3</sub>CN/0.1&#x0200a;% FA. The Q-Tof Premier mass spectrometer was operated in the standard data-dependent acquisition (DDA) mode at a resolution of 10&#x0200a;000 (V mode) controlled by Masslynx 4.1. The survey scans were acquired over <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 400&#x02013;1500, and the four most abundant multiply charged ions (2<sup>+</sup>, 3<sup>+</sup> and 4<sup>+</sup>) with a minimal intensity at 20 or 30 counts s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> were subject to MS/MS for 3 s with dynamic exclusion for 120 s. The instrument was externally calibrated. The Raw files were processed by Proteinlynx Global Server (PLGS) 2.2.5 with and without deconvolution of MS/MS spectra by MaxEnt3. The LTQ FT Ultra mass spectrometer was operated in a similar DDA mode to the Q-Tof premier with a resolution at 100&#x0200a;000 at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 400, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r29">Pickard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). The raw files were processed with BioWorks 3.3 (ThermoElectron). The data were subjected to a database search with Mascot Server 2.2 (Matrix Science) against an in-house-built <italic>Campylobacter</italic> genomic six-frame translated database using the following parameters: trypsin/P with maximum three missed cleavage sites; peptide mass tolerance at &#x000b1;20 p.p.m. (FT) or 50 p.p.m. (Q-Tof Premier); MS/MS fragment mass tolerance at &#x000b1;0.49 Da (FT) or 0.2 Da (Q-Tof Premier); and variable modifications, Acetyl (Protein N-term), Carbamidomethyl (C), Deamidated (NQ), Dioxidation (M), Formyl (N-term), Gln&#x02192;pyro-Glu (N-term Q), Methyl (E), Oxidation (M). The Mascot result was processed with the in-house Percolator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r4">Brosch <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), and then filtered with the following rules: peptides with less than 7 amino acids or a posterior error probability &#x0003e;0.05 were removed. Proteins with two or more non-redundant peptides were kept. For those proteins with only one peptide identified, the peptide must be found in both datasets (Q-Tof Premier and FT) and with a PEP &#x0003c;0.01 and &#x02265;10 amino acids. If the peptide was found in only one of the datasets, then the peptide must also have a Mascot score above the identification threshold. This resulted in an overall false discovery rate &#x0003c;0.1&#x0200a;%. The complete dataset from this study has been deposited in the PRIDE database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/pride/q.do">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/pride/q.do</ext-link>) with the accession nos 17661 and 17684.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-11"><title>Secondary structure and conservation analysis for <italic>C. jejuni</italic> non-coding candidates.</title><p>To identify potential unannotated ncRNA genes, large intergenic regions (&#x0003e;150 bp) from the complete genome sequence of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 were searched against RFAMSEQ (a subset of the EMBL nucleotide database) using a combination of wu-<sc>blast</sc> filters and covariance models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r1">Altschul <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r11">Eddy &#x00026; Durbin, 1994</xref>). Reliable matches were subsequently aligned to the reference sequence, and a consensus secondary structure was predicted using the WAR package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r40">Torarinsson &#x00026; Lindgreen, 2008</xref>); this formed a &#x02018;seed&#x02019; alignment. Covariance models were built from the resulting alignment and secondary structure; these were searched against RFAMSEQ10 using the Rfam pipeline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r11">Eddy &#x00026; Durbin, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">Gardner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). New and reliable hits were added to the seed, and a new CM was built and researched. This procedure was iterated until there were no new reliable hits. The subsequent alignments were analysed using the structured RNA gene prediction methods RNAz (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r44">Washietl <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) and Alifoldz (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r43">Washietl &#x00026; Hofacker, 2004</xref>). These were computed using a sliding window across alignments generated from the seed sequences using <sc>clustal</sc>
<sc>w</sc> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r39">Thompson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>). The window size used was 100 columns and a step-size of 10 columns for both methods. Each prediction method was run on both the forward and reverse complement strands.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec1-3"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Mapping DNA sequence reads generated by Illumina-based RNA-seq to the annotated <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 genome &#x02013; global interpretations</title><p>In order to characterize the <italic>C. jejuni</italic> transcriptome using RNA-seq, RNA was prepared from a pool of five independent cultures of <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 grown for 24 h to an OD<sub>600</sub> 1.0 (log<sub>10</sub> 10 c.f.u. ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) in BHI broth. The 16S and 23S rRNA species were depleted prior to sequencing using selective capture and magnetic separation. The resulting RNA was reverse-transcribed into cDNA which was then processed into a library of molecules that could be sequenced on the Illumina Genome Analyser. The procedure was repeated for RNA derived from a <italic>C. jejuni rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> mutant. To assess technical variance, we sequenced each biological sample on two Illumina lanes. The sequence reads were mapped to the genome sequence of NCTC11168 and were displayed using the genome browser Artemis and Bamview (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>). The total number of reads obtained and mapped for each sample is detailed in Supplementary Table S1 (available with the online version of this paper). As previously reported for RNA-seq analysis of eukaryotic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r46">Wilhelm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) and prokaryotic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r27">Perkins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) RNA, the sequence coverage was not uniform across each CDS; however, our technical replicates were in close agreement (Supplementary Fig. S1), with the log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) values for each gene and intergenic region giving Pearson correlation coefficients of 0.984 and 0.982 between replicates for the wild-type and <italic>rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> samples, respectively (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;2.2&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;16</sup> in both cases). Full details of the number of reads mapping to each gene and intergenic region together with log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) values are available in Supplementary Table S2.</p><fig id="f1" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Fig. 1. </label><caption><p>RNA-seq sequence data mapped to the <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 genome and visualized using Artemis and Bamview. The top section shows the position of reads derived from the wild-type (red) and reads from the <italic>rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> mutant (green). The middle section shows a plot of sequence coverage, using the same colour scheme. The lower section shows a representation of the DNA strands and the six possible reading frames, and indicates the positions of annotated features. The highlighted gene, <italic>Cj1242</italic>, is downregulated in the <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant. This gene encodes the invasion antigen CiaC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r7">Christensen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="050278-f1"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Protein-coding genes</title><p>The distribution of log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) values for the 1624 protein-coding genes annotated in the <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">Gundogdu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>. The distribution is approximately normal, with a mean&#x000b1;<sc>sd</sc> of 7.44&#x000b1;2.14. Only three protein-coding genes did not have any reads that mapped within their coding regions from either the wild-type or <italic>rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> RNA-seq: <italic>Cj0344</italic>, <italic>Cj0877c</italic> and <italic>Cj0973</italic>. These genes are all annotated as encoding hypothetical proteins; Cj0877c is described as &#x02018;very hypothetical&#x02019;. Two more genes, annotated as encoding the hypothetical protein Cj0971 and the RepA homologue Cj1667c, had no mapped reads in the wild-type sample but did have mapped reads derived from the <italic>rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> sample.</p><fig id="f2" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Fig. 2. </label><caption><p>Density plot showing the distribution of log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) values obtained for the protein-coding genes in wild-type <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="050278-f2"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Pseudogenes</title><p>The original annotation of <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 identified 20 pseudogenes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r26">Parkhill <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>), and reanalysis of the genome revised this total to 19 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">Gundogdu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). We were able to detect reads for all of the pseudogenes (Supplementary Table S3, available with the online version of this paper) although only four exhibited a log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) value above the first quartile of the distribution obtained from the protein-coding genes (<italic>Cj0501</italic>, <italic>Cj0565</italic>, <italic>Cj1064</italic> and <italic>Cj1528</italic>). Closer inspection of the data indicates that most of the pseudogenes had a strong transcriptional profile at the start of the CDS with just a few isolated reads mapping to the remainder of the CDS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>). Two of the pseudogenes (<italic>Cj1064</italic> and <italic>Cj0501</italic>) had strong transcriptional profiles throughout the entire CDS, suggesting that transcription may be maintained to express functional domains or peptides, or that the inactivation of these genes was evolutionarily recent. The sequences of our reads matched the published genome sequences for these two genes.</p><fig id="f3" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Fig. 3. </label><caption><p>Artemis plots showing RNA-seq data obtained for pseudogenes (as for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>). (a) <italic>Cj0654c</italic> showed an expression pattern typical of most pseudogenes in the genome, with a high level of expression at the 5&#x02032; end of the gene that diminishes towards the 3&#x02032; end. (b) <italic>Cj1064</italic> showed a high level of expression across the length of the pseudogene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="050278-f3"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>tRNA</title><p>There are 43 tRNA-encoding genes annotated in the <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">Gundogdu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), with 33 distinct anticodons. The log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) values of the tRNA genes show a similar mean to the protein-coding genes (7.67; Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.3188), but a reduced variance (Fisher&#x02019;s <italic>F</italic> test, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.0040). It is a common observation that the use of alternative synonymous codons is non-random (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r33">Sharp <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>); in <italic>C. jejuni</italic> this has been attributed to the low GC-content of the genome, with a preference for AT-rich synonyms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">Fuglsang, 2003</xref>). It might be expected that the expression levels of the tRNAs would reflect the codon usage bias, but this does not seem to be the case (Supplementary Tables S4 and S5, available with the online version of this paper). For example, the tRNA gene with the highest log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) value (12.12) encodes tRNA-Arg with an anticodon CCU. However, the codon recognized by this tRNA, AGG, is used only 1340 times in the genome, whereas the synonym AGA is used 8195 times, yet its cognate tRNA with the anticodon UCU has the lowest log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) value of all the arginine tRNAs (7.88). Leucine is the most frequently used amino acid in the <italic>C. jejuni</italic> proteome, yet the four tRNA-Leu genes all have average log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) values. The levels of tRNA transcription seem to be dependent on genomic context, for example, the CCU anticodon tRNA-Arg is encoded downstream of the highly expressed <italic>fusA</italic> gene, and the three tRNA-Ile genes are located within rRNA operons.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>ncRNA sequences</title><p>A limitation of expression microarrays is that they only provide information on specific genomic regions to which probe sequences have been designed. RNA-seq allows investigation of transcription across the whole genome, and hence enables the discovery of novel ncRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r48">Yoder-Himes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Four ncRNAs (excluding rRNA and tRNA) are currently annotated in the <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 genome: the signal recognition particle RNA, the TPP riboswitch, the RNA component of RNaseP and 10Sa RNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">Gundogdu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Transcripts were identified in the RNA-seq data for all of these. Additionally, we performed a screen of all large intergenic regions for potential unannotated ncRNA genes based on evolutionary conservation and structural prediction using the Rfam alignment pipeline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">Gardner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), RNAz (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r44">Washietl <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) and Alifoldz (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r43">Washietl &#x00026; Hofacker, 2004</xref>), and identified five candidate regions which may be worth investigating further (intergenic_671549&#x02013;671895, intergenic_722652&#x02013;722740, intergenic_906748&#x02013;907066, intergenic_1127982&#x02013;1128192 and intergenic_1575021&#x02013;1575288) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref>), although one of these (intergenic_906748&#x02013;907066) did not show a significant level of expression in our data.</p><table-wrap id="t1" position="float"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Secondary structure and conservation analysis for <italic>C. jejuni</italic> ncRNA candidates</title><p>ID, unique identifier containing genomic location; maxRnazP, the maximal RNAz probability on the forward or reverse strand &#x02013; values greater than 0.5 were classified as putative ncRNA genes; minAlifoldZ, the lowest (best) Z-score from the RNAalifoldZ predictions on the forward or reverse strand; numSeqs, no. of homologous sequences used in the Rfam seed alignment; aveLen, average length of the sequences in the Rfam seed alignment; GC content, average G+C content for all the sequences in the Rfam seed alignment; GC enrichment, enrichment of G+C nucleotides relative to the genomic background [computed as log<sub>2</sub>(GC-content/0.3055)]. One homologue was identified in the <italic>C. jejuni</italic> genome (EMBL ACC:AL111168.1) for each ncRNA candidate.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ID no.</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">MaxRnazP</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">MinAlifoldZ</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">numSeqs</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aveLen</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aveID</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">GC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrichment</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intergenic_671549&#x02013;671895</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.957647</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.796566</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">342.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.285</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.1001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intergenic_722652&#x02013;722740</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.995352</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.995194</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.295</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0504</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intergenic_906748&#x02013;907066</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.932765</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89473</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">311</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.232</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.397</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intergenic_1127982&#x02013;1128192</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.999921</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.559228</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.281</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.1205</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intergenic_1575021&#x02013;1575288</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.999869</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.999657</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.221</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.4671</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="f4" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Fig. 4. </label><caption><p>Consensus secondary structure predictions for the forward (left) and reverse (right) complement intergenic_671549&#x02013;671895 (a), intergenic_722652&#x02013;722740 (b), intergenic_906748&#x02013;907966 (c), intergenic_1127982&#x02013;1128192 (d) and intergenic_1575021&#x02013;1575288 (e). The colour markup indicates the sequence conservation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="050278-f4"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>RNA-seq and proteome analysis of <italic>C. jejuni</italic> hypothetical genes and pseudogenes</title><p>mRNA transcript levels do not necessarily correlate with protein levels, or indeed whether the transcript is translated. We carried out a comprehensive proteomic analysis using LC-MS of peptides from whole-cell lysates of <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168. We obtained good coverage with 11462 peptides mapping to 1041 predicted genes. We did not obtain any peptides that mapped to any of the pseudogenes. This might suggest that, even though we obtained transcripts for a number of the pseudogenes, they are not translated. Alternatively, any translated products may be below the level of detection or below our ~6 kDa molecular mass cut-off. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref> shows the number of peptides obtained for each protein-coding gene plotted against the log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) value. Fitting a log-linear model with quasi-Poisson errors indicates a significant relationship between mRNA expression level and the observed peptide count (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;2&#x000d7;10<sup>16</sup>). For the gene <italic>pnp</italic> (Cj1253), a peptide sequence was obtained that included one amino acid encoded upstream of the annotated start codon. This suggests that the annotated <italic>pnp</italic> start codon is incorrect; the most plausible alternative is the TTG codon at position 1183537.</p><fig id="f5" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Fig. 5. </label><caption><p>Plot of the observed number of peptides from wild-type <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 against log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) as a measure of the mRNA expression level. The blue line indicates the predicted protein level according to the fitted log-linear regression with quasi-Poisson errors. Red points indicate mRNAs predicted to encode peptides below the 6 kDa threshold of detection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="050278-f5"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>RNA-seq and microarray analysis of a <italic>C. jejuni rpoN</italic> mutant</title><p>We generated a <italic>C. jejuni rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> mutant and compared the growth of the mutant with the wild-type. Bacteria were cultured in MH broth with shaking in microaerobic conditions at 42 &#x000b0;C. The doubling time for each strain was determined for exponential phase growth: wild-type, 1.40&#x000b1;0.12 generations per hour; mutant 1.41&#x000b1;0.01 generations per hour. The difference between the growth rates was not statistically significant (Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003e;0.05) based on viable counts. Motility assays were performed on the wild-type and <italic>rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> mutant. Following 72 h incubation at 42 &#x000b0;C in microaerobic conditions, the mutant was completely non-motile (data not shown). Genes that were expressed in the <italic>rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> mutant were identified from the RNA-seq data using DEseq (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r2">Anders &#x00026; Huber, 2010</xref>). The log<sub>2</sub> (fold changes) and estimated <italic>P</italic>-values obtained from the data are available in Supplementary Table S2. Twenty-five genes and two intergenic regions showed significantly altered expression in the <italic>rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> mutant compared with the wild-type (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.1; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). Seventeen protein-coding genes showed significant downregulation in the <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant, including 12 that are annotated as encoding flagellar proteins and two others (<italic>Cj0040</italic> and <italic>Cj1465</italic>) that are co-located with flagellar gene clusters. The other three downregulated genes (<italic>Cj0243c</italic>, <italic>Cj1242</italic> and <italic>Cj1650</italic>) are all annotated as encoding hypothetical proteins, although Cj1242 has recently been identified as the invasion antigen CiaC, which is secreted by the <italic>C. jejuni</italic> flagellar type III secretion system and is potentially important in virulence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r7">Christensen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Cj1650 is an orthologue of the <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> protein HP1076, which has been identified as a flagellar export co-chaperone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r22">Lam <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Two intergenic regions, located between <italic>tpx</italic>&#x02013;<italic>napA</italic> (positions 731983&#x02013;732128) and <italic>luxS</italic>&#x02013;<italic>Cj1199</italic> (positions 1127982&#x02013;1128192), were also identified as significantly downregulated. The latter region was also identified in the screen for potential ncRNA genes, suggesting the possibility of a novel ncRNA involved in flagellar regulation. Genes identified as being upregulated in the <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant include two gene clusters: <italic>Cj0423&#x02013;Cj0425</italic>, which is annotated as encoding a putative integral membrane protein and two putative periplasmic proteins; and <italic>metAB</italic>, which encode enzymes involved in amino acid metabolism and are located close to <italic>flgE2</italic>. An additional membrane protein gene, <italic>cstA</italic>, and another amino acid metabolism gene, <italic>cysM</italic>, are also upregulated in the <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant, together with <italic>Cj0667</italic>, <italic>Cj0898</italic> and <italic>Cj1650</italic>, all of which are of unknown function. Interestingly, <italic>Cj0667</italic> is the first gene in the operon containing <italic>rpoN</italic>.</p><table-wrap id="t2" position="float"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>RNA-seq data for genes and intergenic regions identified as differentially expressed in the <italic>rpoN</italic>&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;:&#x0200a;<italic>cat</italic> mutant relative to the wild-type</title><p>The log<sub>2</sub>(fold change) (logFC) values for the RNA-seq and microarray, and the wild-type log<sub>2</sub>(RPKM+1) values are coloured by value (red &#x0003e;yellow &#x0003e;blue). RNaseq and microarray <italic>P</italic>-values of &#x0003c;0.05 are in bold type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="050278-t1"/></table-wrap><p>We compared differentially expressed genes identified in the RNA-seq data with those identified in a reanalysis of data derived from an earlier microarray-based study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">Kamal <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Both studies compare wild-type <italic>C. jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 with an <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant, although it should be noted that different growth conditions were employed. (Kamal <italic>et al.</italic> used bacteria from a 24 h plate culture, resuspended in MH broth to OD<sub>600</sub> ~0.1, and grown at 37 &#x000b0;C for 18 h with shaking at 75 r.p.m.) All but one of the genes identified as being significantly downregulated in the <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant by RNA-seq were also significantly downregulated in the microarray data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6</xref> and Supplementary Table S2). Conversely, for the upregulated genes, only one (<italic>metA</italic>) was significant in both datasets. The microarray data detected considerably more significantly downregulated genes than were identified using RNA-seq. This is in part due to the additional biological replicates available for the microarray data, which add statistical power. However, most of the genes in question show no evidence of downregulation in the RNA-seq data irrespective of <italic>P</italic>-value, which would be unexpected were they genuinely part of the <italic>rpoN</italic> regulon. It is possible that the assignment of these genes as differentially expressed is an artefact of the microarray hybridization or analysis procedure. Alternatively, the differences between the two datasets could reflect the different culture conditions employed in the two studies, although we consider this unlikely. As RNA-seq becomes increasingly commonplace, it will be possible to resolve this issue by characterizing the effect of growth conditions on the <italic>rpoN</italic> regulon.</p><fig id="f6" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Fig. 6. </label><caption><p>log<sub>2</sub>(fold change) values obtained using RNA-seq, plotted against the equivalent values from the microarray study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">Kamal <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Genes showing significant differential expression in the RNA-seq data (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05) are highlighted in red, genes showing significant differential expression in the microarray data (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05) are shown as triangles. (Red triangles, differential expression in the RNA-seq and microarray data; red circles, differential expression in the RNA-seq data; black triangles, differential expression in the microarray data; black circles, no differential expression in either data set.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="050278-f6"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Concluding remarks</title><p>In this study we have used direct high-throughput Illumina sequencing of cDNA (RNA-seq) to analyse the transcriptome of <italic>C. jejuni</italic> (NCTC11168). Our studies demonstrate the efficacy of high-throughput sequencing for defining mRNA expression levels and identifying differentially expressed genes and novel transcribed regions of the genome (for example, identification of potential unannotated ncRNA genes). We hope that the transcriptome and proteome datasets will be a useful resource to the <italic>Campylobacter</italic> research community.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the <funding-source rid="sp1">Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra)</funding-source> Senior Fellowship in Veterinary Microbiology to D.&#x0200a;J.&#x0200a;M. A.&#x0200a;J.&#x0200a;G. was supported by <funding-source rid="sp2">Defra/Higher Education Funding Council of England</funding-source> under the <funding-source rid="sp3">Veterinary Training and Research Initiative</funding-source> (grant no. <award-id rid="sp3">VT0105</award-id>), and by a <funding-source rid="sp4">Medical Research Council</funding-source> grant (<award-id rid="sp4">G0801161</award-id>) awarded to A.&#x0200a;J.&#x0200a;G. P.&#x0200a;P.&#x0200a;G. and T.&#x0200a;T.&#x0200a;P. were funded by the <funding-source rid="sp5">Wellcome Trust</funding-source>. L.&#x0200a;Y. and J.&#x0200a;C. were funded by the <funding-source rid="sp6">Wellcome Trust</funding-source> grant no. <award-id rid="sp6">079643/Z/06/Z</award-id>.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>Five supplementary tables and a supplementary figure are available with the online version of this paper.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>1990</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>215</volume>, <fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2010</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>R106</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>1995</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate &#x02013; a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>. <source>J R Stat Soc B</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>300</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brosch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2009</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Accurate and sensitive peptide identification with Mascot Percolator</article-title>. <source>J Proteome Res</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>3176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3181</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr800982s</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19338334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrillo</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taboada</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanthier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhulp</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mykytczuk</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<bold>&#x00026; other authors (</bold><year>2004</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Genome-wide expression analyses of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 reveals coordinate regulation of motility and virulence by flhA</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>279</volume>, <fpage>20327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20338</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M401134200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14985343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carver</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;hme</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berriman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2010</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>BamView: viewing mapped read alignment data in the context of the reference sequence</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>676</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>677</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20071372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Konkel</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2009</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Identification of a <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic>-secreted protein required for maximal invasion of host cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>650</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>662</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06797.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19627497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cloonan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolle</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steptoe</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<bold>&#x00026; other authors (</bold><year>2008</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Stem cell transcriptome profiling via massive-scale mRNA sequencing</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>619</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corry</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atabay</surname><given-names>H. I.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2001</year><bold>).</bold>
<source>Poultry as a source of Campylobacter and related organisms, Symposium series</source>, <fpage>96S</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>114S</lpage>
<publisher-name>Society for Applied Microbiology</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dower</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragsdale</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>1988</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>High efficiency transformation of <italic>E. coli</italic> by high voltage electroporation</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>6127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6145</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/16.13.6127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3041370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>1994</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>RNA sequence analysis using covariance models</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2079</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2088</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/22.11.2079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8029015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuglsang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2003</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>The genome of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic>: codon and amino acid usage</article-title>. <source>APMIS</source>
<volume>111</volume>, <fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>618</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0463.2003.1110603.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12969016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>P. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daub</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawrocki</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolbe</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindgreen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<bold>&#x00026; other authors (</bold><year>2009</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Rfam: updates to the RNA families database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>37</volume> (<issue>Database issue</issue>), <fpage>D136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D140</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18953034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodyear</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Hanlon</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plomp</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veitch</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochrane</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullens</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molenaar</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<bold>&#x00026; other authors (</bold><year>1999</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Monoclonal antibodies raised against Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome-associated <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> lipopolysaccharides react with neuronal gangliosides and paralyze muscle-nerve preparations</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<volume>104</volume>, <fpage>697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>708</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI6837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10491405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gundogdu</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorrell</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wren</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2007</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Re-annotation and re-analysis of the <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> NCTC11168 genome sequence</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>162</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-8-162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17565669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hendrixson</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>DiRita</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2003</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Transcription of sigma54-dependent but not &#x003c3;28-dependent flagellar genes in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> is associated with formation of the flagellar secretory apparatus</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>687</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>702</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03731.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14617189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hendrixson</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akerley</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>DiRita</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2001</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Transposon mutagenesis of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> identifies a bipartite energy taxis system required for motility</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>214</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>224</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02376.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11298288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyndrickx</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grijspeerdt</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandekerchove</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollier</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Zutter</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2003</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Routes for <italic>Campylobacter</italic> contamination of poultry meat: epidemiological study from hatchery to slaughterhouse</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>1169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1180</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268803001183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14959785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2007</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Campylobacters as zoonotic pathogens: a food production perspective</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Microbiol</source>
<volume>117</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>257</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2007.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17368847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jagannathan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Constantinidou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Penn</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2001</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Roles of <italic>rpoN</italic>, <italic>fliA</italic>, and <italic>flgR</italic> in expression of flagella in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>183</volume>, <fpage>2937</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2942</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.183.9.2937-2942.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11292815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorrell</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagannathan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Constantinidou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Studholme</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsden</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laing</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<bold>&#x00026; other authors (</bold><year>2007</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Deletion of a previously uncharacterized flagellar-hook-length control gene <italic>fliK</italic> modulates the &#x003c3;54-dependent regulon in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>153</volume>, <fpage>3099</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3111</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.2007/007401-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17768253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotaka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Au</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2010</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Molecular interaction of flagellar export chaperone FliS and cochaperone HP1076 in <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic></article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>4020</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4032</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.10-155242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20581225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marioni</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mane</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilad</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2008</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>RNA-seq: an assessment of technical reproducibility and comparison with gene expression arrays</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1517</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.079558.108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18550803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2008</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>628</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagalakshmi</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waern</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raha</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2008</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>The transcriptional landscape of the yeast genome defined by RNA sequencing</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>320</volume>, <fpage>1344</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1349</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1158441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18451266</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wren</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mungall</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ketley</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Basham</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chillingworth</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feltwell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<bold>&#x00026; other authors (</bold><year>2000</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>The genome sequence of the food-borne pathogen <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> reveals hypervariable sequences</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>403</volume>, <fpage>665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>668</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35001088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingsley</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fookes</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>P. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Assefa</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Croucher</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<bold>&#x00026; other authors (</bold><year>2009</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>A strand-specific RNA-Seq analysis of the transcriptome of the typhoid bacillus <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>e1000569</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19609351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ussery</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>On</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2003</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>RpoD promoters in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> exhibit a strong periodic signal instead of a -35 box</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>326</volume>, <fpage>1361</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1372</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-2836(03)00034-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12595250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pickard</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toribio</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petty</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Tonder</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulding</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rance</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<bold>&#x00026; other authors (</bold><year>2010</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>A conserved acetyl esterase domain targets diverse bacteriophages to the Vi capsular receptor of <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhi</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>192</volume>, <fpage>5746</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5754</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00659-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20817773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polyakov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Severinova</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Darst</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>1995</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Three-dimensional structure of <italic>E. coli</italic> core RNA polymerase: promoter binding and elongation conformations of the enzyme</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>373</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(95)90114-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8521466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horsnell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajandream</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2000</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Artemis: sequence visualization and annotation</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>944</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>945</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/16.10.944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11120685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r32"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2001</year><bold>).</bold>
<source>Molecular Cloning: a Laboratory Manual</source>, <edition>3rd edn</edition>
<publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2010</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Forces that influence the evolution of codon bias</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>
<volume>365</volume>, <fpage>1203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1212</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2009.0305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20308095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>1973</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Genetic analysis of flagellar mutants in Escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>113</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4567134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2004</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Linear models and empirical bayes methods for assessing differential expression in microarray experiments</article-title>. <source>Stat Appl Genet Mol Biol</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>Article 3</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r36"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2005</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Limma: linear models for microarray data</article-title>. In <source>Bioinformatics and Computational Biology Solutions using R and Bioconductor</source>, pp. <fpage>397</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>420</lpage> Edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudoit</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/0-387-29362-0_23</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Speed</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2003</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Normalization of cDNA microarray data</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>273</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1046-2023(03)00155-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14597310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaud</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2005</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Use of within-array replicate spots for assessing differential expression in microarray experiments</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>2067</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2075</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15657102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>1994</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>4673</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4680</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/22.22.4673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torarinsson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindgreen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2008</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>WAR: Webserver for aligning structural RNAs</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>36</volume> (<issue>Web Server issue</issue>), <fpage>W79&#x02013;84</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18492721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Vliet</surname><given-names>A. H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wooldridge</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ketley</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>1998</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Genetic manipulation of enteric <italic>Campylobacter</italic> species</article-title>. <source>Methods in Microbiology</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>407</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>419</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0580-9517(08)70301-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2009</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>RNA-Seq: a revolutionary tool for transcriptomics</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Washietl</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofacker</surname><given-names>I. L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2004</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Consensus folding of aligned sequences as a new measure for the detection of functional RNAs by comparative genomics</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>342</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2004.07.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15313604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Washietl</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofacker</surname><given-names>I. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2005</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Fast and reliable prediction of noncoding RNAs</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>2454</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2459</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0409169102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15665081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wassenaar</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleumink-Pluym</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuijten</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Zeijst</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>1994</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Differential flagellin expression in a <italic>flaA</italic>
<italic>flaB</italic><sup>+</sup> mutant of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>3901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8063406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>B. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marguerat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodhead</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Penkett</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;hler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2008</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Dynamic repertoire of a eukaryotic transcriptome surveyed at single-nucleotide resolution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>453</volume>, <fpage>1239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1243</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18488015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>W&#x000f6;sten</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagenaar</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Putten</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2004</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>The FlgS/FlgR two-component signal transduction system regulates the fla regulon in <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>279</volume>, <fpage>16214</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16222</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M400357200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14960570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoder-Himes</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chain</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wurtzel</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiedje</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorek</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<bold>(</bold><year>2009</year><bold>).</bold>
<article-title>Mapping the <italic>Burkholderia cenocepacia</italic> niche response via high-throughput sequencing</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>3976</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3981</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0813403106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19234113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>