<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">G3 (Bethesda)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>G3: Genes|Genomes|Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2160-1836</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Genetics Society of America</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5068931</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27473314</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">GGG_028639</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.116.028639</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Investigations</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Evolution of the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> Genes in Amaranthaceae and Their Expression Patterns in the Course of Vegetative Growth and Flowering in <italic>Chenopodium rubrum</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drabe&#x00161;ov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Jana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0010c;ern&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Lucie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma&#x00161;terov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Helena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kolou&#x00161;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Pavla</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>&#x02021;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Potock&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>&#x00160;torchov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Helena</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6701-179X</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>*</label>Institute of Experimental Botany, Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic, 165 02 Prague 6, Czech Republic</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02020;</label>Department of Experimental Plant Biology, Faculty of Natural Sciences, Charles University, 128 44 Prague 2, Czech Republic</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>&#x02021;</label>Department of Genetics and Microbiology, Faculty of Natural Sciences, Charles University, 128 44 Prague 2, Czech Republic</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>1</label>Corresponding author: Institute of Experimental Botany, Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic, v.v.i Rozvojov&#x000e1; 263, 165 02 Prague 6, Lysolaje, Czech Republic. E-mail: <email>storchova@ueb.cas.cz</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>10</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3065</fpage><lpage>3076</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Drabesova <italic>et al.</italic></copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="3065.pdf"/><abstract><p>The <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> gene family controls important aspects of plant development: <italic>MFT</italic>-like genes affect germination, <italic>TFL1</italic>-like genes act as floral inhibitors, and <italic>FT</italic>-like genes are floral activators. Gene duplications produced paralogs with modified functions required by the specific lifestyles of various angiosperm species. We constructed the transcriptome of the weedy annual plant <italic>Chenopodium rubrum</italic> and used it for the comprehensive search for the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> genes. We analyzed their phylogenetic relationships across Amaranthaceae and all angiosperms. We discovered a very ancient phylogenetic clade of <italic>FT</italic> genes represented by the <italic>CrFTL3</italic> gene of <italic>C. rubrum</italic>. Another paralog <italic>CrFTL2</italic> showed an unusual structural rearrangement which might have contributed to the functional shift. We examined the transcription patterns of the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> genes during the vegetative growth and floral transition in <italic>C. rubrum</italic> to get clues about their possible functions. All the genes except for the constitutively expressed <italic>CrFTL2</italic> gene, and the <italic>CrFTL3</italic> gene, which was transcribed only in seeds, exhibited organ-specific expression influenced by the specific light regime. The <italic>CrFTL1</italic> gene was confirmed as a single floral activator from the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> family in <italic>C. rubrum</italic>. Its floral promoting activity may be counteracted by <italic>CrTFL1</italic>. <italic>C. rubrum</italic> emerges as an easily manipulated model for the study of floral induction in weedy fast-cycling plants lacking a juvenile phase.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>transcriptome</kwd><kwd><italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T/TERMINAL FLOWER1</italic> gene family</kwd><kwd>evolution</kwd><kwd>flowering</kwd><kwd>gene rearrangement</kwd><kwd>Amaranthaceae</kwd><kwd><italic>Chenopodium rubrum</italic></kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="1"/><ref-count count="62"/><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Land plants evolved numerous adaptations to protect against drying, to ensure fertilization, and to cope with Earth&#x02019;s gravity. The effective control of plant architecture was made possible by an intricate network of regulatory proteins, phytohormones, and growth substances (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Va&#x00148;kov&#x000e1; <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Novel gene families encoding transcription factors and cofactors appeared when plants conquered the land. One of them, the <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T/TERMINAL FLOWER1</italic> (<italic>FT/TFL1</italic>) gene family, regulates the transition from the vegetative to the reproductive phase and controls plant growth (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Wickland and Hanzawa 2015</xref>). The family can be divided into three phylogenetic clusters: <italic>MOTHER OF FT AND TFL1</italic> (<italic>MFT</italic>)-like, <italic>TFL1</italic>-like, and <italic>FT</italic>-like. The most ancestral clade includes <italic>MFT</italic>-like genes, found in mosses, lycopods, and all seed plants (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Hedman <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Their original function is related to growth arrest and dormancy, satisfying the essential need of land plants to control their size and architecture. The <italic>TFL1</italic>-like clade originated in seed plants in order to independently regulate seed and bud dormancy (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Kalgren <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). The most recent <italic>FT</italic>-like clade arose with angiosperms. The FT-like proteins constitute the principal component of florigen, a long sought after substance promoting flowering (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Corbesier <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Jaeger and Wigge 2007</xref>). The evolution of the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> genes was driven by extensive gene duplications. They occurred in all lineages of flowering plants and were often associated with functional shifts (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Pin <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Navarro <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>).</p><p>Six members of the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> gene family exist in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, a model long-day plant (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Kardailsky <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Kobayashi <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). The <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>TWIN SISTER OF FT</italic> (<italic>TSF</italic>) genes are floral promoters. In contrast with <italic>FT</italic>, the <italic>TSF</italic> gene is activated by cytokinins under nonpermissive short days (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">D&#x02019;Aloia <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), demonstrating the functional diversification of both flowering activators. Members of the <italic>TFL1</italic> subfamily act as floral repressors. <italic>TFL1</italic> maintains inflorescence meristem in the shoot apex and delays its differentiation into floral organs (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Simon <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>). <italic>ARABIDOPSIS THALIANA CENTRORADIALIS HOMOLOG</italic> (<italic>ATC</italic>) functions as a graft transmissible floral repressor under short days (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). <italic>BROTHER OF FT AND TFL1</italic> (<italic>BFT</italic>) inhibits floral initiation under salt stress (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Ryu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Finally, <italic>MFT</italic> is highly expressed in seeds and affects germination by interacting with abscisic acid and gibberellin signaling pathways (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Xi <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).</p><p>Functional shifts of FT proteins have occurred in many plant species, <italic>e.g.</italic>, in sunflower (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Blackman <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), tobacco (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Harig <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), sugarcane (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Coelho <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), and soybean (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). Novel FT-derived floral repressors carry mutations in the positions proven to be critical for regulatory function by site-specific mutagenesis in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Hanzawa <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ahn <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Ho and Weigel 2014</xref>). For example, BvFT1 inhibits flowering in sugar beet, whereas its paralog BvFT2 is a floral promoter. This functional shift was associated with the exchange of Tyr-134 for Asn, and Trp-138 for Gln (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Pin <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).</p><p><italic>Chenopodium rubrum</italic> (red goosefoot) is the only representative of the family Amaranthaceae besides sugar beet, in which <italic>FT</italic>-like genes have been identified and their functions estimated in transgenic <italic>A. thaliana</italic>. The <italic>CrFTL1</italic> gene acted as a floral promoter similarly to its ortholog <italic>BvFT2</italic> in sugar beet (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Pin <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). In contrast, the <italic>CrFTL2</italic> gene orthologous to the sugar beet repressor <italic>BvFT1</italic> was not involved in flowering control (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Ch&#x000e1;b <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Drabe&#x00161;ov&#x000e1; <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). <italic>C. rubrum</italic> is a tetraploid species (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Loeve and Loeve 1982</xref>), most likely an allotetraploid (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Ch&#x000e1;b <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kolano <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), which has originated quite recently according to its position on the phylogenetic tree (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Fuentes-Bazan <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Red goosefoot is a short-day annual without a juvenile phase. It represents an opportunistic weedy species which prefers disturbed, ephemeral habitats. It may be induced to flowering by a single period of darkness at the seedling stage (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cumming 1967</xref>). <italic>C. rubrum</italic> has long been used in classical physiological studies of flowering (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Seidlov&#x000e1; and Krekule 1973</xref>), and more recently in genetic studies (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Veit <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Ch&#x000e1;b <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Drabe&#x00161;ov&#x000e1; <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).</p><p>In the current work, we performed a comprehensive study of the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> gene family in <italic>C. rubrum</italic>. We constructed a reference transcriptome, identified the members of this family, and generated the phylogenetic tree across angiosperms. The absence of the juvenile phase and the existence of only one floral activator from the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> gene family makes <italic>C. rubrum</italic> an attractive model to study floral induction and for comparison with other amaranths.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2"><title>Plant material and growth conditions</title><p>Seeds of <italic>C. rubrum</italic> ecotype 374 (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cumming 1967</xref>) were germinated in Petri dishes with wet filtration paper. Germinating seeds were planted in 96-well flat-bottom ELISA plates (one seedling per well). The wells were filled with perlite (particle size 0.4&#x02013;0.8 mm) and perforated at the bottom (1 mm-hole) to provide a nutrient solution. The plates were floated in half-strength Hoagland solution which was replaced each second day. After 3 or 5 d, only average sized seedlings with opened cotyledons (75%) were maintained; the remaining plants were discarded. Selected plantlets were exposed to various photoperiodic treatments &#x02013; permanent light, one or three periods of darkness followed by permanent light, and a diurnal regime with 12 hr light and 12 hr darkness (Supplemental Material, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf">File S1</ext-link>). The modified floral dip method used in attempts to transform <italic>C. rubrum</italic> is described in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>RNA isolation</title><p>Leaf, root, stem, or apical tissues from seedlings, young, or mature plants cultivated under various photoperiodic regimens were collected and flash frozen in liquid nitrogen. Sampling in dark was performed under a dim green light (about 520 nm, Green Hornet LED headlight). Total RNA was isolated using a Plant RNeasy Mini kit (Quiagen, Valencia, CA). DNA contamination was removed by DNase I treatment according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol (DNA-free, Ambion, TX). RNA quality and concentration were checked on a 0.9% agarose gel and by NanoDrop (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Finland).</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>RNAseq</title><p>We sequenced and assembled several <italic>C. rubrum</italic> transcriptomes, utilizing both 454 pyrosequencing and Illumina HiSeq to achieve a reliable reference transcriptome. The mixture of equal amounts of 44 RNA samples extracted from various tissues of seedlings or mature plants cultivated under various photoperiodic treatments in the growth chamber or in the greenhouse (200 &#x003bc;g in total) was dried in GenTegra tubes (GenTegra, Pleasanton, CA) and sent to Evrogen Joint Stock Company (Moscow, Russia) to prepare a normalized cDNA library (10 &#x003bc;g), which was afterward sequenced using Roche 454 GS-FLX platform with Titanium reagents in the DNA Core facility at Brigham Young University (Provo, UT). We obtained 2,285,349 raw reads from which 1,830,810 reads passed quality filtering. Median read length was 463 bp and the average was 412 bp. The total number of bases reached 754,859,592.</p><p>In addition, we selected RNAs isolated in two replicates from 9 organs and developmental stages and sent 12 samples to the University of Southern California Epigenome Center (CA) for library preparation and HiSeq Illumina sequencing, which generated paired end reads (50 bp, fragment size about 200 bp).</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Transcriptome assembly</title><p>Raw Illumina reads were processed to eliminate artifacts from library construction and low quality reads with the Trimmomatic v0.32 software (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bolger <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). We trimmed all edge bases below quality score 20 and discarded reads shorter than 48 bp. Orphan reads were assigned as single reads. Only paired end reads were used for the reference transcriptome assembly.</p><p>454 reads were assembled using Newbler (Gs <italic>De novo</italic> Assembler v2.8, Roche, Germany) with default settings. A file with the list of sequencing adaptors and primers was specified in order to remove sequencing and PCR artifacts.</p><p>For Illumina data we used the following four <italic>de novo</italic> assemblers: Trinity v2013-02-25, v2014-04-13, and v2.0.6 (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Grabherr <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) SOAPdenovo-Trans v1.03 (<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Xie <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), Velvet-Oases v0.2.09 (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Schulz <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), and Trans-Abyss v1.5.1 (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Robertson <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Trinity was used with the default k-mer size 25, SOAPdenovo-Trans was used with k-mer sizes 20&#x02212;45 and a step size of 5, Velvet-Oases was used with k-mer sizes 21&#x02212;29 and step size of 2, and Trans-Abyss was used with k-mer sizes 25&#x02212;45 and a step size of 2. The assemblies calculated with various k-mers by the same assembler were combined to produce a merged assembly. The utilities offered by individual software packages were applied. Raw data were deposited in SRA database under the accession number PRJNA305086.</p><p>Transcriptome assemblies were performed with a 12-core Linux workstation with 60 GB memory (Laboratory of Plant Reproduction, IEB) and with computing resources of virtual organization Metacentrum (Czech National Grid Organization). Contigs shorter than 200 bp were discarded from all assemblies. Redundant contigs were further discarded using CD-HIT v4.6 (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Li and Godzik 2006</xref>) with settings -c 1.0 -n 5. Contigs shorter than 200 bp were excluded from assemblies and the &#x0201c;best&#x0201d; set of assembled transcripts were than selected using the tr2aacds pipeline from the EvidentialGene package v2013.07.27 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arthropods.eugenes.org/about/about-EvidentialGene/EvidentialGene_trassembly_pipe.html">http://arthropods.eugenes.org/about/about-EvidentialGene/EvidentialGene_trassembly_pipe.html</ext-link>). Only the primary (main) output transcripts were used for follow-up analyses. The coverage of selected genes was quantified using RSEM (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Li and Dewey 2011</xref>) bundled with the Trinity software package. Reads were aligned to the reference transcriptome using the Bowtie aligner (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Langmead <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Coverage values were <italic>in silico</italic> normalized as FPKM (Fragments Per Kilobase of target transcript length per Million reads mapped) (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Trapnell <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Assembly quality metrics</title><p>Several tools were adopted to compare the quality of the assemblies. The first method estimated the proportion of completeness of each assembled transcript by the Ortholog Hit Ratio (OHR) (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">O&#x02019;Neil <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), where an OHR close to 1.0 indicates that the particular transcript was assembled to its full length. The transcripts were aligned against two reference databases: 357 ultraconserved ortholog coding sequences from <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Kozik <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), and a list of 959 single copy nuclear genes shared among <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>Oryza</italic>, <italic>Populus</italic>, and <italic>Vitis</italic> (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Whereas OHR refers to the completeness of the newly assembled transcripts, the following two metrics&#x02014;contiguity and completeness (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Martin and Wang 2011</xref>)&#x02014;consider the coverages of selected reference transcripts. Completeness is defined as the percentage of expressed reference transcripts covered by all the assembled transcripts, contiguity is the percentage of expressed reference transcripts covered by a single, longest-assembled transcript. The threshold value is the proportion of a particular reference transcript that is covered by an assembled transcript. Both metrics were calculated according to <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>. Open reading frames in assembled transcripts were identified and translated using the protein databases of five species: <italic>Citrus clementina</italic>, <italic>C. sinensis</italic>, <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> (downloaded from the Phytozome, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Goodstein <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), <italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> (downloaded from the <italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> Resource: bvseq.molgen.mpg.de, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Dohm <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (downloaded from the TAIR10, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org">www.arabidopsis.org</ext-link>). Protein sequences were then aligned against databases used also for the calculations of OHR as described above (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Kozik <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).</p><p>RSEM-EVAL package, part of DETONATE (<italic>De novo</italic> TranscriptOme rNa-seq Assembly with or without the Truth Evaluation) toolkit was used to calculate each assembly score (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Due to a big number of contigs in the Oases assembly we were not able to calculate the score for this assembly. Chimeric transcripts were identified and cut using the approach described by <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Yang and Smith (2013)</xref>. Chimera identification was based on <italic>blastx</italic> analyses against protein databases derived from five different species as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>RT qPCR</title><p>One microgram of RNA and oligo dT primers (500 ng) were heated for 5 min at 65&#x000b0;, chilled on ice, and mixed with Transcriptor buffer (Roche, Mannheim, Germany), 0.5 &#x003bc;l of Protector RNase Inhibitor (Roche, Germany), 2 &#x003bc;l of 10 mM dNTPs, and 10 units of Transcriptor Reverse Transcriptase (Roche, Germany). The first strand of cDNA was synthesized at 55&#x000b0; for 30 min. RNA samples were reverse transcribed in two independent RT reactions and each cDNA specimen was measured twice.</p><p>The first strand of cDNA was diluted 10&#x02212;20 times and qPCR was performed using the LightCycler 480 SYBR Green I Master (Roche, Germany) in a final volume of 10 &#x003bc;l with 300&#x02212;500 nM of each of the high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) purified primers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/TableS1.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>), supplied by Metabion (Germany). The LightCycler LC 480 (Roche, Germany) was programmed as follows: 10 min of initial denaturation at 95&#x000b0;, then 40 cycles for 10 s at 95&#x000b0;, 10 s at 60&#x000b0; (<italic>CrTFL1</italic>, <italic>CrBFT</italic>, <italic>CrMFT1</italic>, <italic>CrMFT2</italic>, <italic>CrCAB</italic>) or 8 s at 58&#x000b0; (<italic>actin</italic>, <italic>CrFTL1</italic>, <italic>CrFTL2</italic>), followed by 15 s at 72&#x000b0;. PCR efficiencies were estimated from calibration curves generated from serial dilution of cDNAs. A calibrator was used to correct for run-to-run variation. The relative ratio of the target and reference gene was calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="eq"><mml:math id="me1"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>E</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>E</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where E<sub>T</sub> /E<sub>R</sub> represents the efficiency of target/reference amplification and C<sub>p</sub>T/C<sub>p</sub>R represents the cycle number at target/reference detection threshold (crossing point). Expression values were normalized with <italic>actin</italic> (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Drabe&#x00161;ov&#x000e1; <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). This reference gene could not be applied to RNA extracted from seeds, because of its low expression. Normalization by cDNA (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Libus and &#x00160;torchov&#x000e1; 2006</xref>), followed by the recalculation with regard to <italic>actin</italic>-normalized samples, was therefore adopted for RNA extracted from dry or imbibed seeds. The specificity of qPCR was confirmed by amplicon resequencing.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Identification of the FT/TFL1 genes</title><p>A local database was made from the reference transcriptome of <italic>C. rubrum</italic>. It was searched using the <italic>tblastn</italic> algorithm with <italic>A. thaliana FT/TFL1</italic> protein sequences as queries. The first hits were blasted against an <italic>A. thaliana</italic> protein database using <italic>blastx</italic> to confirm mutual homology. The coding sequences of the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> genes in <italic>C. rubrum</italic> were amplified by PCR with primers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/TableS1.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>) designed according to sequences from the reference transcriptome and with cDNA as a template. Another set of primers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/FigureS1.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/TableS1.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>) was developed to amplify the <italic>CrFTL</italic> genes from genomic DNA. Cleaned PCR products (GeneJET PCR purification kit, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Finland) were sent to Macrogen Europe Laboratory (Netherlands) for Sanger sequencing. All GenBank accession numbers including newly obtained sequences and the list of species are given in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/TableS2.pdf">Table S2</ext-link>.</p><p>Spinach <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> genes were identified in the Spinach 1.0.1 genomic draft published on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bvseq.molgen.mpg.de/blast/">http://bvseq.molgen.mpg.de/blast/</ext-link> using the <italic>tblastn</italic> tool with <italic>C. rubrum</italic> queries and named according to their respective <italic>A. thaliana</italic> or <italic>C. rubrum</italic> homologs. The exons recognized in genomic sequences according to their similarity with <italic>C. rubrum</italic> genes were joined together to provide virtual sequences of the particular transcripts. Two copies of the <italic>SoFTL1-2</italic> gene found in close mutual vicinity in the scaffold 8759 were designated <italic>SoFTL1-2a</italic> and <italic>SoFTL1-2b</italic>. The <italic>SoTFL1</italic> gene was assembled from the sequences found in two scaffolds, 68,707 and 48,765, most likely due to a misassembly of the spinach genomic draft. Sugar beet genes were retrieved from GenBank by <italic>blastp</italic> with <italic>C. rubrum</italic> protein queries, except for <italic>BvFTL3</italic>, which was identified in RefBeet-1.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bvseq.molgen.mpg.de/blast/">http://bvseq.molgen.mpg.de/blast/</ext-link>). Owing to an inherent incompleteness of transcriptomes, Amaranthaceae transcriptomes published by One Thousand Plants (1KP) Consortium were not used for data mining.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Phylogenetic analyses</title><p>Multiple nucleotide sequence alignment of coding regions guided by the protein sequence alignment was conducted using MUSCLE (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Edgar 2004</xref>) with default parameters, as implemented in Geneious 7.1.5, and extensive manual editing. The alignment was analyzed by the maximum-likelihood (ML) method using RAxML (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Stamatakis 2014</xref>). A &#x003b3; model of rate heterogeneity was applied on three distinct data partitions corresponding to three codon positions. Bootstrap support of the majority rule consensus tree was calculated from 1000 pseudoreplicates. Gaps were treated as missing characters. The proportion of synonymous (Ks) and nonsynonymous (Ka) substitutions between two sequences was calculated using DnaSP v.5 (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Librado and Rozas 2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>3D structure model</title><p>Amino acid CrFTL2 sequence in FASTA format was uploaded through the I-TASSER web interface (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zhanglab.ccmb.med.umich.edu/I-TASSER/">http://zhanglab.ccmb.med.umich.edu/I-TASSER/</ext-link>) together with the template FT (<italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic>, MMDB ID: 33642) in Program Database (PDB) format. In addition, a 3D model of CrFTL2 was independently computed with Modeler sofware (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Webb and Sali 2014</xref>) using multiple templates (pdb codes 1wkp, 3axy, 1qou, 2iqy, 2jyz) in order to avoid biases introduced by single template and prediction algorithm.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Data availability</title><p>The authors state that all data necessary for confirming the conclusions presented in the article are represented fully within the article.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s12"><title>Results</title><sec id="s13"><title>Transcriptome assembly</title><p>454 pyrosequencing produced 2,285,349 raw reads from which 1,830,810 reads passed quality filtering. We also obtained &#x0223c;25 million raw reads from each of 12 RNA samples sequenced by Illumina (altogether 293,391,190 raw read pairs). 253,682,808 read pairs (86.5%) passed quality check and were used for assembly. A single assembly was generated from the 454 data set by Newbler and 22 assemblies were created from all Illumina reads by four distinct assemblers. A combined superassembly was produced by the EvidentialGene pipeline. The assembly characteristics are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="t1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>The characteristics of <italic>C. rubrum</italic> transcriptome assemblies produced by various assemblers</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="15.7%" span="1"/><col width="0.99%" span="1"/><col width="6.58%" span="1"/><col width="8.08%" span="1"/><col width="9.14%" span="1"/><col width="4.99%" span="1"/><col width="8.08%" span="1"/><col width="4.04%" span="1"/><col width="11.1%" span="1"/><col width="7.07%" span="1"/><col width="8.41%" span="1"/><col width="6.73%" span="1"/><col width="9.09%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" valign="top" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Contigs</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Chimeras</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DETONATE</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Contiguity 80%</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Completeness 80%</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assembler</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Number</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average Length</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonredundant</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N50</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcripts</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Score</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Beta vulgaris</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabidopsis</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Beta vulgaris</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabidopsis</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trinity v2013-02-25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176,176</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1165</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176,176</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2240</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4364</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;13300254357</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.839</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.897</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.804</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.855</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trinity v2014-04-13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109,230</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1224</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109,230</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2130</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1661</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11942708245</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.888</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.849</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.914</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.873</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trinity v2.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103,364</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">839</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103,272</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1388</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">606</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;13489216000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.857</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.815</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,915</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.875</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trans-Abyss (MK)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">478,002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">687</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">477,947</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1041</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2028</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10478540027</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.917</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.882</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.937</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.897</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Velvet-Oases (MK)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,025,841</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1022</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">681,326</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1788</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,337</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/<sup><italic>a</italic></sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.869</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.823</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.938</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.904</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOAPdenovo-Trans (MK)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">698,830</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">692,919</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;20560646452</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.306</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.251</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.926</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.825</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Newbler</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,587</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1227</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,580</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1354</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16700290718</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.657</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.615</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.687</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.643</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EvidentialGene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40,487</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">912</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40,487</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1383</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15661125094</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.885</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.846</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.894</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1n1"><label>a</label><p>Not calculated.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Newbler assembled reads derived from the normalized cDNA library. It produced 22,587 contigs (N50 = 1354) with nearly zero redundancy. Trans-Abyss generated fewer transcripts (478,002) than Oases or SOAPdenovo-Trans, N50 = 1041. The newest version of Trinity (2015) was the best in terms of a low proportion of chimeric transcripts and zero redundancy. Finally, a combined superassembly was compiled by the EvidentialGene pipeline from all the assemblies except of those produced by SOAPdenovo-Trans. The main output comprised 40,487 transcripts with no redundancy, defined as 100% nucleotide sequence identity. Basic assembly characteristics (for example N50) did not allow to decide which assembly should be chosen as a reference transcriptome. We have therefore employed additional quality metrics to evaluate the assemblies.</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Assembly quality metrics</title><p>The highest completeness (93.7%) and contiguity (91.7%) values, estimated using <italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> reference, were achieved by Trans-Abyss (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). Using <italic>A. thaliana</italic> as a reference brought consistent results with slightly lower values owing to a large phylogenetic distance between <italic>Chenopodium</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Trans-Abyss was immediately followed by Trinity and Oases. The assembly of the normalized cDNA library performed by Newbler exhibited only moderate completeness (68.7%) and contiguity (65.7%). Newbler used a 454 data set, which contained &#x0003c;1% of reads compared to the Illumina data set, though the reads were much longer. The worst performing program was SOAPdenovo-Trans with the lowest contiguity: 30.6%. This ranking was confirmed by DETONATE metrics.</p><p>The EvidentialGene superassembly (main output) showed the second highest contiguity (88.5%), a slightly lower completeness (89.4%) and a much lower number of transcripts (40,487). The reduction in transcript number was achieved owing to decreased redundancy and chimerism (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>), which represent a challenge for the assembly of the transcriptomes in polyploid plants (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Nakasugi <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) Thus, we selected this superassembly as a suitable reference transcriptome of. <italic>C. rubrum</italic> for further studies. At the same time, we retained the Newbler, Trans-Abyss, and Trinity assemblies, and the alternative set of contigs from EvidentialGene superassembly as useful resources to search for rare or alternative transcripts.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Evolution of the FT/TFL1 genes in Amaranthaceae</title><p>We identified eight members of the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> gene family in the reference <italic>C. rubrum</italic> transcriptome, including the previously described <italic>CrFTL1</italic> and <italic>CrFTL2</italic> genes (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Ch&#x000e1;b <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Most transcripts occurred in two slightly different variants (nucleotide sequence similarity of coding regions &#x0003e;98%) most likely derived from two homeologous copies existing in tetraploid <italic>C. rubrum</italic>. Owing to a very low divergence of the homeologous pairs, only one representative sequence (confirmed by Sanger sequencing) was included in phylogenetic analyses. Only three short reads transcribed from the <italic>CrFTL3</italic> gene were found in all data sets. Thus, the entire C<italic>rFTL3</italic> genomic sequence was obtained by Sanger sequencing genomic DNA (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/FigureS1.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link>) and the <italic>CrFTL3</italic> coding region was predicted from it.</p><p>We aligned the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> homologs from <italic>C. rubrum</italic>, spinach, and sugar beet together with <italic>Amborella trichopoda</italic>, <italic>Zea mays</italic>, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, and <italic>Jatropha curcas</italic> genes and constructed a ML phylogenetic tree depicting the evolutionary history of the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> family in angiosperms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). The phylogram shows two well-supported clades corresponding to the <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>TFL1</italic> subfamilies. Furthermore, it contains unresolved basal branches representing the members of the <italic>MFT</italic> subfamily&#x02013;the single <italic>AtriMFT</italic> gene from <italic>A. trichopoda</italic>, the cluster of <italic>Z. mays</italic> genes, and two clades with <italic>C. rubrum MFT</italic> paralogs. The <italic>CrMFT1</italic> gene clustered together with spinach <italic>SoMFT1</italic> and two <italic>Bv</italic><italic>MFT</italic> paralogs. The <italic>CrMFT2</italic> gene and its spinach homolog belonged to the same clade as <italic>A. thaliana MFT</italic>.</p><fig id="fig1" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The ML phylogenetic tree of the <italic>FT</italic>/<italic>TFL1</italic> genes in angiosperms constructed by RAxML. Bootstrap support of the majority rule consensus tree was calculated from 1000 pseudoreplicates. GenBank accession numbers are given in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/TableS2.pdf">Table S2</ext-link>. Species abbreviations: Cr, <italic>Chenopodium rubrum</italic> (red); Bv, <italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> (blue); So, <italic>Spinacia oleracea</italic> (green); At, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>; Atri, <italic>Amborella trichopoda</italic>; Jc, <italic>Jatropha curcas</italic>; Smo, <italic>Selaginella moellendorffii</italic>; Zm, <italic>Zea mays</italic>. ATC, <italic>CENTRORADIALIS</italic> (<italic>A. thaliana</italic>). </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3065f1"/></fig><p>The gene duplication in <italic>C. rubrum</italic> and sugar beet, which generated <italic>CrFTL1</italic> and <italic>CrFTL2</italic> (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Ch&#x000e1;b <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), and <italic>BvFT2</italic> and <italic>BvFT1</italic> (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Pin <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), was well documented in the <italic>FT</italic> clade. Moreover, another cluster composed of <italic>FTL3</italic> genes diverged before this duplication, but after the separation of Amaranthaceae genes from monocots and <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>. We found no other <italic>FTL3</italic> homologs in any public database except for spinach and sugar beet. One homeolog pair of each of the <italic>BFT</italic>, <italic>CEN</italic>, and <italic>TFL1</italic> genes was identified in <italic>C. rubrum</italic>. The <italic>BFT</italic> genes formed the clade at the base of the <italic>TFL1</italic> subfamily.</p><p>The evolution of the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> genes was accompanied by gene duplications and gene losses. The deepest gene duplication occurred in the <italic>MFT</italic> lineage in early angiosperm evolution. <italic>C. rubrum</italic> and spinach, as well as <italic>J. curcas</italic> retained both paralogs, but <italic>MFT2</italic> was lost in sugar beet. Instead, two <italic>MFT1</italic> copies evolved in sugar beet. The <italic>FT</italic> clade exhibited the duplication leading to <italic>FTL2</italic> genes, but also a more ancient event creating the <italic>FTL3</italic> cluster. Recent duplications of <italic>SoCEN</italic> and <italic>SoFTL1</italic> genes occurred in spinach.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Genomic structure of the CrFTL2 gene and 3D structure of the CrFTL2 protein</title><p>To understand the structural evolution of the <italic>CrFTL</italic> genes, we determined their genomic sequences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/FigureS1.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link>). We revealed a large intron (3157 bp) inserted in the first exon of the <italic>CrFTL2</italic> gene. Unlike the other angiosperm <italic>FT</italic>/<italic>TFL1</italic> genes which contain three introns and four exons, <italic>CrFTL2</italic> harbors four introns and five exons. The novel exon 1a replaced part of the former first exon in a mature transcript and coded for a stretch of 17 amino acids with no significant sequence similarity to anything. A fragment of a novel intron (about 1100 bp) was highly similar (80%) to the first exon of the <italic>CHOLINE TRANSPORTER LIKE</italic> gene (<italic>CTL</italic>) from sugar beet (XM_010692082). However, this intron was spliced out leaving no <italic>CTL</italic> sequence in the mature <italic>CrFTL2</italic> transcript. The substantial rearrangement of the <italic>CrFTL2</italic> gene was most likely achieved by recombination which removed the start of the first exon and replaced it with an additional, long intron and a novel exon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(A) The genomic structures of the <italic>CrFTL</italic> genes in <italic>C. rubrum</italic>: <italic>CrFTL1</italic>, <italic>CrFTL2</italic> with the additional intron and the novel exon 1a, <italic>CrFTL2</italic> pseudogene, <italic>CrFTL3</italic>. (B) The 3D structure of the CrFTL2 protein as predicted by Modeler (left) or I-TASSER using an <italic>A. thaliana</italic> FT template (right). The CrFTL2 chain is depicted as a ribbon with a blue N-terminus and a red C-terminus. The FT chain is represented by a backbone of the same color. Arrows show Gly-18, the starting point of the sequence homology between FT and CrFTL2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3065f2"/></fig><p>We constructed 3D models of the CrFTL2 protein using both multitemplate modeling and <italic>A. thaliana</italic> FT only as a template (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). The two 3D predictions were very similar and showed an &#x003b1; helical structure at the N-terminus similar to FT protein and animal phosphatidylethanolamine-binding proteins (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ahn <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Thus, the novel exon encoded a very similar 3D structure as the original one despite a completely different primary sequence. The CrFTL2 protein lacked 11 amino acid residues at the C-end, which might have changed its ligand-binding capacity.</p><p>We also identified a homeolog <italic>CrFTL2</italic> copy carrying the mutation in the splice site (AG &#x0003e; TG) upstream of the fourth exon, which prevented the production of a functional transcript. This copy also lacked exon 1a. Thus, only one of the <italic>CrFTL2</italic> homeologs was functional, the other one was a pseudogene. The <italic>CrFTL1</italic> and <italic>CrFTL3</italic> genes harbored a typical gene structure with variable intron sizes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/TableS3.pdf">Table S3</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Amino acid divergence in the FT subfamily in Amaranthaceae</title><p>We aligned amino acid sequences of the FT subfamily from sugar beet, spinach, and <italic>C. rubrum</italic> with <italic>A. thaliana</italic> FT protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). The FTL1 proteins of the three amaranths showed identity in almost all conserved positions (marked dark green in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>) and high mutual sequence similarity (83&#x02013;93%). The FTL2 proteins carried mutations in the positions critical for a regulatory function (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Ho and Weigel 2014</xref>). Gln-140 was exchanged for Pro in SoFTL2, or for Ile in CrFTL2. Trp-138 was replaced by Gln in BvFT1, which turned the floral activator into a repressor in sugar beet (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Pin <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). The CrFTL2 protein diverged very much from its counterparts, exhibiting only 78% similarity with its closest homolog in spinach. In addition to the different N-terminus encoded by the novel exon 1a, it lacked the conserved GGRR motif at the C-terminus owing to a premature stop codon. The Ka/Ks ratio (0.41) calculated from the nt alignment of <italic>CrFTL2</italic> and <italic>SoFTL2</italic> suggested relaxed selection constraints. This finding together with the constitutive expression of the <italic>CrFTL2</italic> gene (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Ch&#x000e1;b <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), not compatible with a floral repressor function, indicates subfunctionalization.</p><fig id="fig3" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The alignment of the FTL proteins from <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, sugar beet, spinach, and <italic>C. rubrum</italic>. The squares above the alignment mark the residues conserved in &#x0003e;95% (darker) or &#x0003e;90% angiosperm FTL proteins according to <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Ho and Weigel (2014)</xref>. The exons and the A, B, C, D segments of the fourth exons are designated. The amino acids essential for the floral promoting function are shown above the alignment. The amino acid positions in CrFTL3 important for the comparison with other FTLs are given under the alignment. The sequence derived from the first exon unrelated to other FTL proteins was excluded in CrFTL2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3065f3"/></fig><p>The FTL3 lineage belonged to the FT subfamily based on the phylogenetic tree and also on the occurrence of critical amino acid residues. Tyr-85, Glu-109, Trp-138, Gln-140, and Asn-152 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>) were all conserved with Pro-140 in CrFTL3 a notable exception. In contrast, FTL3 proteins contained unique amino acid residues in the positions conserved in other FT/TFL1 proteins: Ser-7, Ala-39, Gly-78, Thr-163 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/TableS4.pdf">Table S4</ext-link>). Synapomorphic amino acid replacements in the FTL3 lineage indicated possible changes of function.</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Plant growth under various light regimes</title><p>We grew <italic>C. rubrum</italic> plants till the age of 32 d under three distinct light regimes: (1) constant light (LL), (2) 12 hr D&#x02013;12 hr L during an entire experiment (LD), and (3) three periods 12 hr D&#x02013;12 hr L applied to 5-d-old seedlings followed by permanent light (3LD LL) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf">File S1</ext-link>). The first regime did not induce flowering, whereas the second and third one resulted in flowering in all plants. Constant light used as a control regime suppressing flowering may be considered to be a nonphysiological treatment. However, the <italic>C. rubrum</italic> ecotype 374 was collected close to the Arctic Circle (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cumming 1967</xref>). Constant light represents natural conditions in its native sites in the weeks around the summer solstice. We collected the plants and prepared herbarium specimens to document their habitus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). Phenotypes of LL and 3LD LL plants were similar which documented a strong morphogenetic effect of constant light. Seedlings treated with at least three dark periods produced longer hypocotyls and roots that were twice as short as those in LL plants.</p><fig id="fig4" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Phenotypes of <italic>C. rubrum</italic> plantlets growing under three light regimes. LL: permanent light; 3 LD&#x02013;LL: three consecutive periods 12 hr light/12 hr dark followed by permanent light; LD: 12 hr light/12 hr dark. The actual size (in cm) is given on the left. The plants were pressed and scanned.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3065f4"/></fig><p>Mature (25 d) LD plants were branched with well visible inflorescences. In contrast, LL and 3LD LL plants were shorter and less branched and produced broader leaves. Their root systems were dense, with many adventitious roots, in contrast with the narrow root systems of LD plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Organ-specific expression of the FT/TFL1 genes</title><p>The expression of the <italic>TFL1</italic> subfamily in whole aerial parts of seedlings was very low. Only <italic>CrTFL1</italic> transcripts were measurable; they displayed a weak diurnal rhythmicity under both short-day and long-day conditions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/FigureS2.pdf">Figure S2</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/FileS3.pdf">File S3</ext-link>). However, when gene expression was estimated in separated organs, prominent transcript patterns were discovered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Relative expression of the <italic>CrFTL1</italic>, <italic>CrTFL1</italic>, <italic>CrCEN</italic>, and <italic>CrBFT</italic> genes in apical parts, hypocotyls, cotyledons, roots, stems, and leaves of <italic>C. rubrum</italic> plants under three light regimes. LL: permanent light (yellow); 3 LD&#x02013;LL: three consecutive periods 12 hr light/12 hr dark followed by permanent light (red); LD: 12 hr light/12 hr dark (black).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3065f5"/></fig><p>We followed transcripts of the <italic>FT</italic>/<italic>TFL1</italic> genes by RT qPCR in roots, hypocotyls, cotyledons, and apical parts of <italic>C. rubrum</italic> seedlings, as well as in stems, roots, leaves, and apical parts of mature plants cultivated under three light regimes as described above (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). The first RNA collection occurred in the middle of the third dark period applied on light-grown seedlings 5 d old. The second sample was taken in the middle of the following light period. Seedlings grown under permanent light were sampled at the same time. We continued RNA collection in 10 d-, 15 d-, 20 d-, and 25-d-old plants, always in the middle of a light period.</p><p>High activation of the floral promoter <italic>CrFTL1</italic> was observed in cotyledons treated by the inductive dark period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). Increased <italic>CrFTL1</italic> expression was recorded in leaves of mature LD plants, albeit at a lower level than in cotyledons, and also in LD apical parts. The <italic>CrTFL1</italic> transcription profile was complementary to <italic>CrFTL1</italic> in terms of organ specificity. High expression was observed in hypocotyl, stems, and roots, but was zero in leaves. The <italic>CrTFL1</italic> transcript levels in aerial parts were higher in constant light. It was inhibited at night and also during the day following the dark period. The <italic>CrTFL1</italic> transcription remained low in LD plants, but increased when 3LD LL plants were transferred to permanent light. Darkness activated <italic>CrTFL1</italic> expression in roots, opposite to the effect in hypocotyls. <italic>CrTFL1</italic> expression remained low when root samples were taken at light under any regime.</p><p>The <italic>CrCEN1</italic> gene was moderately expressed in apical parts with only small differences among the light regimes. Its expression increased in roots of mature plants grown at light. In contrast, the <italic>CrBFT</italic> gene was highly expressed in roots of seedlings grown under constant light and its transcript levels dropped in mature plants. <italic>CrBFT</italic> expression in light-grown hypocotyls might be an overflow of root expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). In general, the members of the <italic>TFL1</italic> subfamily substantially differed in expression patterns and also in their responses to light regimes.</p><p>The <italic>CrMFT1</italic> gene was transcribed in roots. It seemed to be activated by light in roots and also in stems of 25-d-old plants. <italic>CrMFT2</italic> expression was low in all organs except for a single outlier: the roots of 25-d-old plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/FigureS3.pdf">Figure S3</ext-link>).</p><p>In addition to vegetative tissues, we also examined gene expression in <italic>C. rubrum</italic> seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>). The two <italic>CrMFT</italic> paralogs exhibited very high expression in dry and imbibed seeds, with a sharp decrease following germination. Other <italic>FT</italic>/<italic>TFL1</italic> genes, including <italic>CrFTL2</italic>, showed zero or very low transcript levels in seeds. Interestingly, we measured a very low, but detectable level of <italic>CrFTL3</italic> transcripts in dry seeds, the only organ in which <italic>CrFTL3</italic> expression was recorded.</p><fig id="fig6" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Relative expression of the <italic>CrMFT1</italic>, <italic>CrMFT2</italic>, and <italic>CrFTL2</italic> genes in seeds and germinating seedlings of <italic>C. rubrum</italic>. Dry seeds (S), imbibed seeds (I), primary roots (R), and aerial parts of seedlings before cotyledon opening (A). The left y axis expression values refer to <italic>CrMFT</italic> genes, the right y axis refers to <italic>CrFTL2</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3065f6"/></fig><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref> shows a summary of distinct organ-specific expression of the <italic>FT</italic>/<italic>TFL1</italic> genes. The highest levels were achieved by the <italic>TFL1</italic> subfamily genes in roots and by <italic>MFT</italic> genes in seeds. The distinct organ-specific expression of the <italic>CrFTL1</italic>, <italic>CrTFL1</italic>, and <italic>CrCEN</italic> genes in above-ground parts of the plants is documented. The results obtained by RT qPCR were in good agreement with coverage values (FPKM) estimated from Illumina data (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/TableS5.pdf">Table S5</ext-link>).</p><table-wrap id="t2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Expression of the <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> genes in various <italic>C. rubrum</italic> organs</title></caption><table frame="above" rules="groups"><col width="11.12%" span="1"/><col width="11.11%" span="1"/><col width="11.11%" span="1"/><col width="11.11%" span="1"/><col width="11.11%" span="1"/><col width="11.11%" span="1"/><col width="11.11%" span="1"/><col width="11.11%" span="1"/><col width="11.11%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cotyledon</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypocotyl</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stem</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apical Part</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flower</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seed</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CrMFT1</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000&#x02013;5000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t2n1"><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;5000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CrMFT2</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150&#x02013;500</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;5000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CrBFT</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#x02013;150</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000&#x02013;5000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CrCEN</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500&#x02013;1000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000&#x02013;5000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CrTFL1</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000&#x02013;5000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000&#x02013;5000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150&#x02013;500</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#x02013;150</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000&#x02013;5000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CrFTL1</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t2n2"><italic><sup>b</sup></italic></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;5000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;5000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#x02013;150</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CrFTL2</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500&#x02013;1000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500&#x02013;1000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500&#x02013;1000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500&#x02013;1000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500&#x02013;1000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500&#x02013;1000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500&#x02013;1000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150&#x02013;500</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CrFTL3</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#x02013;150</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2n1"><label>a</label><p>Six classes of relative expression relative to actin were estimated by RT qPCR: &#x0003e;5000; 1000&#x02013;5000; 500&#x02013;1000; 150&#x02013;500; 50&#x02013;150; 0&#x02013;50. Seedlings were cultivated in a growth chamber, adult plants grew in a greenhouse or in a growth chamber. Each estimation is based on 10&#x02013;20 individuals.</p></fn><fn id="t2n2"><label>b</label><p>High expression only in plants induced to flowering.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Gene expression profiles provide valuable clues about possible function but more direct evidence is needed to elucidate gene functions with certainty. The functional proof may be achieved by a stable transformation of the plant with particular genes. Thus, we tried to transform <italic>C. rubrum</italic> by the floral dipping method described by <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Veit <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> using the same binary vector pFGC5941 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). However, we failed to confirm DNA transfer by PCR. Moreover, we noticed that some control plants were able to grow on the plate with 5 mg l<sup>-1</sup> of herbicide BASTA. Increased herbicide concentration killed all plants. Naturally resistant seedlings often germinated from large seeds produced by young plants. We concluded that the floral dipping method described by <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Veit <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> was not a reliable tool to achieve stable transformation of <italic>C. rubrum</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s20"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s21"><title>CrFTL1 is a single floral activator of the FT/TFL1 gene family in C. rubrum</title><p>Flowering may be induced by environmental clues only when the plants are ready to bloom. Trees start to flower at the age of several years, sometimes even decades, in contrast with annual plants. Short-day <italic>C. rubrum</italic> represents an extreme even among annuals owing to its capability to flower at the seedling stage. Very early flowering and fast generation cycling is widespread among weedy plants, but it has been only rarely investigated at molecular level. <italic>Ipomoea nil</italic> (Japanese morning glory) is another example in which flowering can be induced as a seedling in short days (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Hayama <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Wada <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).</p><p>We generated a reference transcriptome of <italic>C. rubrum</italic> based on a superassembly combined from several individual assemblies by EvidentialGene pipeline and used it for a comprehensive survey of the <italic>FT</italic>/<italic>TFL1</italic> genes. Unlike <italic>A. thaliana</italic> or Japanese morning glory with two floral activators, <italic>C. rubrum</italic> relies on the single inducer from the <italic>FT</italic>/<italic>TFL1</italic> gene family &#x02013; <italic>CrFTL1</italic>. The other two <italic>FTL</italic> paralogs &#x02013; <italic>CrFTL2</italic> (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Ch&#x000e1;b <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) and the newly identified gene <italic>CrFTL3</italic> &#x02013; were not involved in the control of flowering as documented by the constitutive or nearly zero transcription, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>), which was unchanged by floral induction.</p></sec><sec id="s22"><title>The structural evolution of the CrFTL2 gene indicates a functional shift</title><p>The <italic>CrFTL2</italic> gene has undergone a dramatic structural evolution and shown an accelerated substitution rate since its divergence from the sugar beet floral repressor <italic>BvFT1</italic> (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Pin <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). A new exon and a long intron replaced the first 50 bp of the coding sequence. The novel exon encoded an &#x003b1; helix similar to the original chain, preserving the protein 3D structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>), despite a distinct primary sequence. The new intronic sequence was partly derived from the <italic>CTL</italic> gene, which is interesting in light of the recent finding that <italic>A. thaliana</italic> FT protein binds phosphatidylcholine <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). The novel intron is spliced out and the <italic>CTL</italic> sequence does not appear in a mature transcript. However, the recombination event, which probably restructured the gene, might have been a part of broader rearrangements affecting the control of both choline metabolism and flowering.</p><p>The spinach <italic>SoFTL2</italic> gene possesses the standard first exon similar to sugar beet <italic>BvFT1</italic>. Thus, the rearrangement affecting the <italic>CrFTL2</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>) had to occur relatively recently, after the separation of spinach and <italic>C. rubrum</italic> ancestors. The second homeolog <italic>CrFTL2</italic> copy is not functional which raises the question of whether it was inactivated before or after the origin of tetraploid <italic>C. rubrum</italic> from its so far unknown diploid ancestors.</p><p>The function of the <italic>CrFTL2</italic> gene remains enigmatic, but it is certainly not related to flowering control. A reliable protocol for gene transfer in <italic>C. rubrum</italic> has not been developed yet. Our attempt to adopt floral dipping method (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Veit <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>) for the stable <italic>C. rubrum</italic> transformation failed, but other methods like VIGS (virus induced gene silencing) may be successful in the future to provide evidence about the <italic>CrFTL2</italic> function.</p><p>The loss of floral repressor may allow seedlings to flower immediately after germination, if days are shortening in the fall. It appears to be a useful adaptation to a weedy opportunistic life style of <italic>C. rubrum</italic>. The loss of function often results in pseudogenization. However, relatively high and stable expression and the preservation of the 3D structure of the CrFTL2 protein after a complex gene rearrangement indicate a functional shift.</p></sec><sec id="s23"><title>The CrFTL3 and CrMFT genes diverged early</title><p>We discovered a third <italic>FTL</italic> paralog in Amaranthaceae. It arose early in the dicot evolution, most likely on the base of Caryophyllales (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). We cannot decide whether this clade is restricted to Amaranthaceae. We may have found <italic>FTL3</italic> homologs only in spinach and sugar beet, because no other Caryophyllales genomic drafts were available. Transcriptomic records are more numerous, but they may miss <italic>FTL3</italic> sequences due to very low transcription. We detected <italic>CrFTL3</italic> expression in seeds by RT qPCR, albeit at a negligible level. The FTL3 proteins contained several synapomorphic amino acid substitutions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>) which suggested a substantial functional divergence. We speculate that this gene may be involved in embryo growth control, which is in line with its ancient origin.</p><p>The two <italic>CrMFT</italic> genes were highly expressed in seeds and downregulated after germination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>), which implicates their role in seed dormancy control, as in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Xi <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). However, unlike <italic>A. thaliana</italic> having only one <italic>MFT</italic> gene, <italic>C. rubrum</italic> retained two <italic>MFT</italic> paralogs. Their different expression in roots indicates their function in vegetative growth.</p></sec><sec id="s24"><title>The genes of the TFL1 subfamily in C. rubrum show diverse expression patterns</title><p>The <italic>CrTFL1</italic> gene displayed the most variable expression, highly responding to darkness when applied on 5-d-old seedlings. Whereas <italic>CrTFL1</italic> was strongly inhibited by dark in hypocotyls and retained a low activity the following day, it was highly upregulated in roots but only at night (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). The TFL1 and FT proteins are non-cell-autonomous in <italic>A. thaliana</italic>; they spread among tissues (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Conti and Bradley 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Corbesier <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). It is therefore possible that the CrTFL1 protein migrates at light from hypocotyl to the apex in <italic>C. rubrum</italic> seedlings. It may maintain apical meristematic activity, support vegetative growth, and counteract the FT protein in a similar way as in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Hanano and Goto 2011</xref>). A sudden decrease in <italic>CrTFL1</italic> transcripts caused by dark may contribute to floral induction in <italic>C. rubrum</italic>. The role of <italic>TFL1</italic> in roots was little investigated. The most recent evidence based on whole genome-association mapping (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Lachowiec <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>) suggests that <italic>TFL1</italic> acts as a repressor of root growth in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> seedlings. The coincidence of short roots in dark-treated seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>) and <italic>CrTFL1</italic> upregulation by dark in roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>) indicate a similar inhibitory function in <italic>C. rubrum</italic>.</p><p><italic>FT</italic> and <italic>TFL1</italic> regulate a shoot architecture in various plants. For example, the <italic>SFT</italic> and <italic>SP</italic> genes, orthologs of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>TFL1</italic> in tomato, control branching pattern and leaf shape in an antagonistic way. Their ratio, rather than individual transcript levels, shape tomato compound leaves (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Lifschitz <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). We observed <italic>CrFTL1</italic> expression in leaves, whereas <italic>CrTFL1</italic> was transcribed in stem and roots, not in leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). Thus, <italic>CrTFL1</italic> does not seem to affect leaf shape.</p><p><italic>CrBFT</italic> was transcribed mostly in seedling roots, less in mature plants. Its expression was downregulated by dark. The opposite effect of darkness on <italic>CrBFT</italic> and <italic>CrTFL1</italic> could reflect their antagonistic roles in root growth regulation. <italic>CrCEN</italic> expression was little influenced by light regime, being limited to shoot apical parts in seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). In general, the three members of the <italic>TFL1</italic> subfamily exhibited very distinct patterns of organ-specific expression (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>), suggesting their different roles in plant growth and reproduction.</p></sec><sec id="s25"><title>Future perspectives</title><p><italic>C. rubrum</italic> emerges as a very promising model for the studies of flowering owing to the absence of a juvenile phase and the presence of the single <italic>FT</italic>-like floral activator <italic>CrFTL1</italic>, which is upregulated 6 hr after lights-on, regardless of photoperiod (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Drabe&#x00161;ov&#x000e1; <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). A midnight break inhibits both flowering and <italic>CrFTL1</italic> transcription (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Ch&#x000e1;b <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). The determination of the time period critical for floral induction and the availability of the reference transcriptome make it possible to conduct experiments to identify the genes controlling the induction to flowering in <italic>C. rubrum</italic>. The comparison of floral regulatory pathways among <italic>C. rubrum</italic> and other amaranths will improve our understanding of the adaptation of crops and weedy species to the ever changing environment.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s26"><title/></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplemental Material</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_6_10_3065__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028639_FileS1.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028639_TableS4.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028639_TableS5.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028639_FileS2.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028639_FileS3.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028639_FigureS1.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028639_FigureS2.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028639_FigureS3.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028639_TableS1.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028639_TableS2.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028639_TableS3.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank J.D. Stone for critical reading and linguistic revision, P. Mr&#x000e1;z and V. Mr&#x000e1;zov&#x000e1; for scanning pressed plants of <italic>C. rubrum</italic>, Charles Meyer Nicolet for advice on Illumina sequencing and K. Ha&#x00161;kovcov&#x000e1; for excellent technical assistance. The access to computing and storage facilities owned by parties and projects contributing to the National Grid Infrastructure MetaCentrum, provided under the program &#x0201c;Projects of Large Infrastructure for Research, Development, and Innovations&#x0201d; (LM2010005), is greatly appreciated.&#x0200b; Financial support was provided through the grants of the Grant Agency of the Czech Republic P506/12/1359 and 13-02290S to H.&#x00160;.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p>Supplemental material is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1">www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028639/-/DC1</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn2"><p>Communicating editor: B. J. Andrews</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banfield</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A divergent external loop confers antagonistic activity on floral regulators <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>TFL1</italic>.</article-title>
<source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>614</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16424903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blackman</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strasburg</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raduski</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieseberg</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The role of recently derived <italic>FT</italic> paralogs in sunflower domestication.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>635</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20303265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>2114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ch&#x000e1;b</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kol&#x000e1;&#x00159;</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;torchov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Two <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>) homologs in <italic>Chenopodium rubrum</italic> differ in expression patterns.</article-title>
<source>Planta</source>
<volume>228</volume>: <fpage>929</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>940</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18654796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Minow</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalfun</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colasanti</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Putative sugarcane <italic>FT/TFL1</italic> genes delay flowering time and alter reproductive architecture <italic>in Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Front. Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24904616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>TERMINAL FLOWER</italic> is a mobile signal controlling <italic>Arabidpsis</italic> architecture.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>767</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>778</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbesier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Q. Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>FT protein movement contributes to long-distance signaling in floral induction of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>316</volume>: <fpage>1030</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1033</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17446353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cumming</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1967</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Early-flowering plants</article-title>, pp. <fpage>277</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>299</lpage> in <source><italic>Methods in Developmental Biology</italic></source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wilt</surname><given-names>F. H. </given-names></name><name><surname>Wessels</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<publisher-name>Crowell Co</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x02019;Aloia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonhomme</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouche</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamseddak</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ormenese</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Cytokinin promotes flowering of Arabidopsis via transcriptional activation of the <italic>FT</italic> paralogue <italic>TSF</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>972</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>979</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21205031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohm</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Minoche</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holtgr&#x000e4;we</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capella-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zakrzewski</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The genome of the recently domesticated crop plant sugar beet (<italic>Beta vulgaris</italic>).</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>505</volume>: <fpage>546</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>549</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24352233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drabe&#x00161;ov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ch&#x000e1;b</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kol&#x000e1;&#x00159;</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha&#x00161;kovcov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;torchov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A darklight transition triggers expression of the floral promoter <italic>CrFTL1</italic> and downregulates <italic>CONSTANS</italic>-like genes in a short-day plant <italic>Chenopodium rubrum</italic>.</article-title>
<source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>2137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2146</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24642846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edger</surname><given-names>P. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landherr</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Identification of shared single copy nuclear genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>Populus</italic>, Vitis and Oryza and their phylogenetic utility across various taxonomic levels.</article-title>
<source>BMC Evol. Biol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20181251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2004</year>&#x02003;<article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1792</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1797</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuentes-Bazan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansion</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borsch</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Towards a species level tree of the globally diverse genus Chenopodium (Chenopodiaceae).</article-title>
<source>Mol. Phylogenet. Evol.</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22051350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodstein</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neupane</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Phytozome: a comparative platform for green plant genomics.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>D1178</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D1186</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22110026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-seq data without a reference genome.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>644</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>652</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanano</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>Arabidopsis TERMINAL FLOWER1</italic> is involved in the regulation of flowering time and inflorescence development through transcriptional repression.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3172</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3184</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21890645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanzawa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Money</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2005</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A single amino acid converts a repressor to an activator of flowering.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>7748</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7753</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15894619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harig</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beinecke</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oltmanns</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muth</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Proteins from the <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T-like</italic> subclade of the PEBP family act antagonistically to regulate floral initiation in tobacco.</article-title>
<source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>908</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>921</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22889438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayama</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agashe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luley</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A circadian rhythm set by dusk determines the expression of <italic>FT</italic> homologs and the short-day photoperiodic flowering response in <italic>Pharbitis</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2988</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3000</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17965272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000e4;llman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagercrantz</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Early evolution of the <italic>MFT</italic>-like gene family in plants.</article-title>
<source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>70</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>369</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19288213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>W. W. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Structural features determining flower-promoting activity of <italic>Arabidopsis FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>552</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>564</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24532592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jane</surname><given-names>W. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana CENTRORADIALIS</italic> homologue (<italic>ATC</italic>) acts systemically to inhibit floral initiation in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>184</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22702636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigge</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>FT protein acts as a long-range signal in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1050</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1054</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17540569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalgren</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gyllestrand</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000e4;llman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Evolution of the PEBP gene family in plants: functional diversification in seed plant evolution.</article-title>
<source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>156</volume>: <fpage>1967</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1977</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21642442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kardailsky</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagenais</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>1999</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Activation tagging of the floral inducer <italic>FT</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>286</volume>: <fpage>1962</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1965</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10583961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwabuchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>1999</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A pair of related genes with antagonistic roles in mediating flowering signals.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>286</volume>: <fpage>1960</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1962</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10583960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolano</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomczak</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molewska</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jellen</surname><given-names>E. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maluszynska</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Distribution of 5S and 35S rRNA gene sites in 34 <italic>Chenopodium</italic> species (Amaranthaceae).</article-title>
<source>Bot. J. Linn. Soc.</source>
<volume>170</volume>: <fpage>220</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>231</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc">Kozik, A., I. Kozik, H. Van Leeuwen, A. Van Deynze, and R. Michelmore, 2008&#x02003;Eukaryotic ultra conserved orthologs and estimation of gene capture in EST libraries. Plant and Animal Genomes Conference XVI, San Diego.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lachowiec</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Queitsch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlgorg</surname><given-names>&#x000d6;.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A genome-wide association analysis reveals epistatic cancellation of additive genetic variance for root length in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Genet.</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>e1005541</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26397943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome.</article-title>
<source>Genome Biol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>R25</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19261174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>RSEM: accurate transcript quantification from RNA-Seq data with or without a reference genome.</article-title>
<source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fillmore</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Evaluation of <italic>de novo</italic> transcriptome assemblies from RNA-Seq data.</article-title>
<source>Genome Biol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>553</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25608678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Godzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Cd-hit: a fast program for clustering and comparing large sets of protein or nucleotide sequences.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1658</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1659</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Librado</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>DnaSP v5: a software for comprehensive analysis of DNA polymorphism data.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1452</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19346325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Libus</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;torchov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Quantification of cDNA generated by reverse transcription of total RNA provides a simple alternative tool for quantitative RT-PCR normalization.</article-title>
<source>Biotechniques</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>164</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16925017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lifschitz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayre</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Florigen and anti-florigen &#x02013; a systemic mechanism for coordinating growth and termination in flowering plants.</article-title>
<source>Front. Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>465</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25278944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loeve</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loeve</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1982</year>&#x02003;<article-title>IOPB chromosome number reports LXXIV.</article-title>
<source>Taxon</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>120</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>126</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Next-generation transcriptome assembly.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>682</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanehara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doermann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> florigen FT binds to diurnally oscillating phospholipids that accelerate flowering.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>4553</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25080933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakasugi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowhurst</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bally</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Combining transcriptome assemblies from multiple de novo assemblers in the allo-tetraploid plant <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>.</article-title>
<source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e91776</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24614631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>C. J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abelenda</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruz-Or&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cu&#x000e9;llar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamaki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Control of flowering and storage organ formation in potato by <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>478</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21947007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neil</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzurisin</surname><given-names>J. D. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>N. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emrich</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Population-level transcriptome sequencing of nonmodel organisms <italic>Erynnis propertius</italic> and <italic>Papilio zelicaon</italic>.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>310</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20478048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benlloch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnet</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wremerth-Weich</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraft</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>An antagonistic pair of <italic>FT</italic> homologs mediates the control of flowering time in sugar beet.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>330</volume>: <fpage>1397</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1400</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21127254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>De novo</italic> assembly and analysis of RNA-seq data.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Methods</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>909</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>912</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20935650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The floral repressor <italic>BROTHER OF FT AND TFL1</italic> (<italic>BFT</italic>) modulates flowering initiation under high salinity in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Cells</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21809215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerbino</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vingron</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Oases: robust <italic>de novo</italic> RNA-seq assembly across the dynamic range of expression levels.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1086</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1092</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22368243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seidlov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krekule</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1973</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The negative response of photoperiodic floral induction in <italic>Chenopodium rubrum</italic> L. to preceding growth.</article-title>
<source>Ann. Bot. (Lond.)</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>614</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Igeno</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1996</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Activation of floral meristem identity genes in Arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>384</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8900276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-analysis of large phylogenies.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1312</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1313</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24451623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcript assembly and abundance estimation from RNA-Seq reveals thousands of new transcripts and switching among isoforms.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>511</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Va&#x00148;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petr&#x000e1;&#x00161;ek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Za&#x0017e;&#x000ed;malov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kam&#x000ed;nek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Motyka</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Auxins and cytokinins in plant development ... and interactions with other phytohormones 2014.</article-title>
<source>J. Plant Growth Regul.</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>714</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veit</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrechtova</surname><given-names>J. T. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2004</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Isolation of a <italic>FLORICAULA/LEAFY</italic> putative orthologue from <italic>Chenopodium rubrum</italic> and its expression during photoperiodic flower induction.</article-title>
<source>Plant Physiol. Biochem.</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>578</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15331084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veit</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrechtova</surname><given-names>J. T. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Floral dip transformation of <italic>Chenopodium rubrum</italic></article-title>, pp. <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage> in <source><italic>Floriculture</italic>, <italic>Ornamental and Plant Biotechnology: Advances and Topical Issues</italic></source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Teixeira da Silva</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<publisher-name>Global Science Books</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Isleworth, UK</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiraya</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeno</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Salicylic acid and the flowering gene <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> homolog are involved in poor-nutrition stress-induced flowering of <italic>Pharbitis nil</italic>.</article-title>
<source>J. Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>167</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>452</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Functional evolution of phosphatidylethanolamine binding proteins in soybean and arabidopsis.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>336</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25663621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sali</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Protein structure modeling with MODELLER.</article-title>
<source>Methods Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>1137</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24573470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickland</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanzawa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T/TERMINAL FLOWER1</italic> gene family: Functional evolution and molecular mechanisms.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Plant</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>983</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>997</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25598141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>MOTHER OF FT AND TFL1</italic> regulates seed germination through a negative feedback loop modulating ABA signaling in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1748</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20551347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>SOAPdenovo-Trans, <italic>de novo</italic> transcriptome assembly with short RNA-seq reads.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1660</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1666</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24532719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Optimizing <italic>de novo</italic> assembly of short-read RNA-seq data for phylogenomics.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>328</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23672450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruhlman</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mower</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Comparative analyses of two Geraniaceae transcriptomes using next-generation sequencing.</article-title>
<source>BMC Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>228</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24373163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>