<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120229//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.2.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art520.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_MOLBIO10846 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEfx1 jpg ?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Biochem Parasitol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Biochem. Parasitol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular and Biochemical Parasitology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0166-6851</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1872-9428</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier/North-Holland Biomedical Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4222701</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0166-6851(14)00090-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molbiopara.2014.07.012</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Short Technical Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>SLaP mapper: A webserver for identifying and quantifying spliced-leader addition and polyadenylation site usage in kinetoplastid genomes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fiebig</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gluenz</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>Steven</given-names></name><email>steven.kelly@plants.ox.ac.uk</email><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Sir William Dunn School of Pathology, University of Oxford, South Parks Road, Oxford OX1 3RE, UK</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Department of Biochemistry, University of Cambridge, Tennis Court Road, Cambridge CB2 1QW, UK</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>Department of Plant Sciences, University of Oxford, South Parks Road, Oxford OX1 3RB, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. Tel.: +44 01865 275123. <email>steven.kelly@plants.ox.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date						pub-type="ppub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>196</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>30</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2014 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p> This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><title>Graphical abstract</title><fig id="fig0010" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="fx1"/></fig></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple"><list-item id="lsti0060"><label>&#x02022;</label><p>A web-server for identification of spliced-leader and polyadenylation addition sites.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0050"><label>&#x02022;</label><p>Fully automated site quantification and gene assignment.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0055"><label>&#x02022;</label><p>Multiple species within the Kinetoplastida.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract><p>The Kinetoplastida are a diverse and globally distributed class of free-living and parasitic single-celled eukaryotes that collectively cause a significant burden on human health and welfare. In kinetoplastids individual genes do not have promoters, but rather all genes are arranged downstream of a small number of RNA polymerase II transcription initiation sites and are thus transcribed in polycistronic gene clusters. Production of individual mRNAs from this continuous transcript occurs co-transcriptionally by trans-splicing of a &#x0223c;39 nucleotide capped RNA and subsequent polyadenylation of the upstream mRNA. SLaP mapper (<bold>S</bold>pliced-<bold>L</bold>eader <bold>a</bold>nd <bold>P</bold>olyadenylation mapper) is a fully automated web-service for identification, quantitation and gene-assignment of both spliced-leader and polyadenylation addition sites in Kinetoplastid genomes. SLaP mapper only requires raw read data from paired-end Illumina RNAseq and performs all read processing, mapping, quality control, quantification, and analysis in a fully automated pipeline. To provide usage examples and estimates of the quantity of sequence data required we use RNAseq obtained from two different library preparations from both <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> and <italic>Leishmania mexicana</italic> to show the number of expected reads that are obtained from each preparation type. SLaP mapper is an easy to use, platform independent webserver that is freely available for use at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.stevekellylab.com/software/slap" id="intr0005">http://www.stevekellylab.com/software/slap</ext-link>. Example files are provided on the website.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>RNA splicing</kwd><kwd>Trypanosoma</kwd><kwd>Leishmania</kwd><kwd>Polyadenylation</kwd><kwd>RNA-Seq</kwd><kwd>Kinetoplastida</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>The Kinetoplastida are a diverse and globally distributed group of free-living and parasitic single-celled eukaryotes. In kinetoplastids messenger RNAs are produced by co-transcriptional processing of continuously transcribed polycistronic gene clusters <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Co-transcriptional processing occurs via trans-splicing of a &#x0223c;39 nucleotide 5&#x02032;-capped spliced-leader sequence and 3&#x02032; polyadenylation of the upstream gene <xref rid="bib0010 bib0015 bib0020 bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[2&#x02013;5]</xref>. Trans-splicing occurs predominantly at AG dinucleotides, however no canonical nucleotide motif has been identified for polyadenylation sites. Moreover, the AAUAAA motif found at polyadenylation sites in most other eukaryotes <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> is not present in kinetoplastids <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p><p>Several tools have been developed that predict trans-splice acceptor and polyadenylation sites <xref rid="bib0040 bib0045 bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[8&#x02013;10]</xref>, however, these tools do not predict relative site usage. Current sequencing technology now makes it possible to determine these sites empirically on a genome-wide scale and quantify the extent to which different trans-splice and polyadenylation sites are used. RNA-sequencing studies of <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> and <italic>Leishmania major</italic> have already begun to reveal the large extent to which individual genes can harbour multiple trans-splice and polyadenylation sites <xref rid="bib0055 bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[11,12]</xref>. To capitalise on this technological advancement, and enable widespread analysis of trans-splice and polyadenylation sites within the community, we have developed a fully automated web-service called SLaP Mapper. This server only requires raw read data obtained by paired-end Illumina RNASeq, and uses this raw read data to identify and quantify trans-splice-acceptor and polyadenylation sites genome-wide.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec0010"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Differences in library construction</title><p>Typical libraries generated from random hexamer primed cDNA are suitable for identification of splice acceptor sites (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). However, the extent to which polyadenylation sites are discovered depends on the library preparation protocol that is used (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). To generate a library enriched for poly(A) containing reads it is recommended that the first strand cDNA synthesis reaction is primed with a 5&#x02032;-T15VN-3&#x02032; oligonucleotide (V&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;A, G or C; N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;T, A, G or C) <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, followed by second strand synthesis with random hexamer primers.</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Algorithm overview</title><p>SLaP mapper uses pre-built indices for the currently available kinetoplastid genomes. The user must supply raw sequence reads in gzipped fastq format (phred encoding offset is automatically detected). Due to FTP limitations SLaP mapper can only accept individual files less than 2&#x000a0;GB. Read files larger then 2&#x000a0;GB can be analysed using SLAP mapper by splitting these files into pieces each smaller than 2&#x000a0;GB then combining the results files. Once read files have been uploaded, reads containing a putative poly(A) tail or spliced-leader sequence are identified, the spliced-leader or poly(A) tail is removed from the read and the rest of the read is mapped to the user specified genome. Each putative identified splice-acceptor site is checked to confirm that it does not contain the spliced-leader sequence and <italic>bona fide</italic> splice-acceptor sites are assigned to their nearest directionally appropriate coding sequence (CDS). Similarly, putative poly(A) addition sites are checked that they do not encode runs of A residues and <italic>bona fide</italic> sites are assigned to their nearest directionally appropriate CDS. When the analysis is complete the results are emailed to the user in tab-delimited text, BED and GFF file formats so that the results are easily viewed in spreadsheet editors or viewed on commonly used genome browsers such as the Integrative genomics viewer <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A). The results files contain the position of the observed site, its dinucleotide (for trans-splice sites only), its strand, its occurrence (i.e. the number of mapped reads) and the nearest directionally appropriate CDS (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B). A summary of the mapping and filtration processes and the settings used to perform these steps is also provided in the results package that is emailed to the user.</p><p>SLaP mapper is an analysis pipeline and uses a number of freely available programs and custom written Perl scripts. The algorithm proceeds in five phases.<list list-type="simple"><list-item id="lsti0005"><label>(1)</label><p><bold>Read quality control</bold>. This step uses the Trimmomatic read processing tool <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> to remove known Illumina adaptor sequences and to trim reads based on quality scores. At this step read-pairs are also assessed for overlapping segments and those reads that overlap in the centre are joined using the fastq-join utility <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0010"><label>(2)</label><p><bold>Identification, preparation and mapping of spliced-leader and poly(A) containing reads</bold>. Here all reads are treated individually and scanned for the presence of poly(A) tails or the appropriate species-specific spliced-leader sequence. A spliced-leader containing read is defined as a read containing at least 12 nucleotides of the 3&#x02032; end of the spliced-leader sequence, this minimum length is changeable by the user. A poly(A) containing read is defined as a read which ends in 5 or more A residues (reads are treated as un-stranded and scanned on both strands). The minimum poly(A) length is also specifiable by the user. Spliced-leader reads are split at the splice junction and the non-spliced-leader part of the read is mapped to the selected reference genome. Similarly the poly(A) read is split at the run of A residues and the non-poly(A) tail part of the read is mapped to the selected reference genome. Read mapping is performed using bowtie2 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0015"><label>(3)</label><p><bold>Filtering of putative splice-acceptor and poly(A) reads</bold>. Mapped putative splice-junction reads are checked to ensure that the location in the genome does not encode the 12 bases of the splice acceptor. Similarly mapped putative poly(A) tail reads are checked to ensure that the location in the genome does not contain an analogous run of A residues as was present in the read. Only <italic>bona fide</italic> splice-junction and polyadenylation addition sites are retained for further analysis. The option to disable this poly(A) site filter is provided on the webserver.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0020"><label>(4)</label><p><bold>Assigning sites to genes</bold>. Once reads have been mapped the location of the sites is recorded and they are assigned to CDS according to the following rules. Trans-splice sites are assigned to a CDS if they occur on the same strand as the CDS and downstream of the stop codon of the preceding gene and upstream of the stop codon of the gene in question. Polyadenylation sites are assigned to a CDS if they lie on the same strand as the CDS, downstream of the start codon of the CDS and upstream of the start codon of the next downstream CDS. Splice leader addition sites and poly(A) sites that occur within CDS are assigned to the CDS in which they reside. It should be noted here that trypanosomatid genomes contain a number of stable transcripts lacking CDSs that occur between true mRNAs. Thus it is possible that some sites belonging to non-coding transcripts may be incorrectly annotated to CDSs by this method. For this reason a separate file is also provided that lists the identified sites without assigning them to CDS.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0025"><label>(5)</label><p><bold>Quantification</bold>. Sites are quantified as the number of reads which uniquely map to each site location.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec0025"><label>3</label><title>Discussion and conclusions</title><p>SLaP mapper is a simple to use resource that enables users to identify and quantify trans-splice and polyadenylation sites in kinetoplastid genomes. It is the only such software of its kind and it requires only a web-browser and no specialised knowledge of any programming environment. The user only need select the appropriate species and upload unprocessed read files. We describe the expected number of informative reads per-million reads that are obtained using two different library preparation protocols in two different species (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). This shows that relatively little sequence data (&#x0003c;10 million reads) is required to provide a comprehensive genome-wide analysis of site usage.</p><p>Recent RNA-sequencing studies of <italic>T. brucei</italic> and <italic>L. major</italic> have revealed that many genes can harbour multiple alternative processing sites <xref rid="bib0055 bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[11,12]</xref>. While the functional significance of these sites has yet to be determined on a genome wide scale, it is likely that some of these alternative sites are important to the regulation and/or function of the final transcript. For example, alternative use of two different spliced-leader addition sites in <italic>T. brucei</italic> facilitates the dual localisation of an isoleucyl-tRNA synthetase <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. In this case the alternative processing sites either include or exclude a mitochondrial localisation signal from the N-terminus of the final polypeptide. SLaP mapper can be readily used to detect such alternative processing sites for transcripts (for example see <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p>In addition to providing a resource that will facilitate the annotation of novel kinetoplastid genomes, this server can also be used to quantify differences in splice-acceptor and polyadenylation site usage across a range of species. This is useful for comparative gene expression studies and in the analysis of post-transcriptional processing of kinetoplastid mRNA. Future releases of SLaP mapper will include more kinetoplastid genomes as they become available.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivens</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Worthey</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berriman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genome of the kinetoplastid parasite, Leishmania major</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>309</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>436</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16020728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agabian</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trypanosome mRNAs share a common 5&#x02032; spliced leader sequence</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>38</volume><year>1984</year><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6088073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ullu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tschudi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temporal order of RNA-processing reactions in trypanosomes: rapid trans splicing precedes polyadenylation of newly synthesized tubulin transcripts</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>13</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8417363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boothroyd</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for trans splicing in trypanosomes</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>47</volume><year>1986</year><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3022935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>LeBowitz</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>H.Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusche</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beverley</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coupling of poly(A) site selection and trans-splicing in Leishmania</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>7</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>996</fpage><lpage>1007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8504937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How the messenger got its tail: addition of poly(A) in the nucleus</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><volume>15</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1974368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schurch</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hehl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vassella</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roditi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accurate polyadenylation of procyclin mRNAs in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> is determined by pyrimidine-rich elements in the intergenic regions</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>14</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>3668</fpage><lpage>3675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7910942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickstead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gull</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ab initio identification of novel regulatory elements in the genome of <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> by Bayesian inference on sequence segmentation</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>6</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>e25666</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21991330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>T.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic study of sequence motifs for RNA trans splicing in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>25</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>9586</fpage><lpage>9594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16227607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gopal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Awadalla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaasterland</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A computational investigation of kinetoplastid trans-splicing</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><volume>6</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>R95</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16277750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolev</surname><given-names>N.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaeli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tschudi</surname></name><name><surname>C</surname></name></person-group><article-title>The transcriptome of the human pathogen <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> at single-nucleotide resolution</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>6</volume><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rastrojo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrasco-Ramiro</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crespillo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reguera</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguado</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The transcriptome of Leishmania major in the axenic promastigote stage: transcript annotation and relative expression levels by RNA-seq</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>14</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>223</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23557257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorvaldsdottir</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesirov</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrative Genomics Viewer (IGV): high-performance genomics data visualization and exploration</article-title><source>Brief Bioinform</source><volume>14</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22517427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0070"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0075"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aronsky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Command-line tools for processing biological sequencing data</chapter-title><year>2011</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://codegooglecom/p/ea-utils" id="intr0010">http://codegooglecom/p/ea-utils</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0080"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><volume>9</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0085"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rettig</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochsenreiter</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dual targeting of isoleucyl-tRNA synthetase in <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> is mediated through alternative trans-splicing</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>40</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1299</fpage><lpage>1306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21976735</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>MF is supported by the Wellcome Trust. SK is a Leverhulme Trust Early Career Fellow. EG is a Royal Society University Research Fellow. MC is supported by the Wellcome trust 085256/Z/08/Z. The authors would like to thank the two anonymous Referees for their advice on the manuscript.</p></ack></back><floats-group><fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>(A) Screen shot of SLaP mapper results as visualised on the IGV genome browser. Four data tracks are shown. CDS are the gene models from V6 of the <italic>L. mexicana</italic> genome. Coverage is the from raw RNAseq reads mapped to the <italic>L. mexicana</italic> V6 genome (the coloured lines in the coverage plot indicate single nucleotide polymorphisms between the genome reference and the strain used for RNAseq). SAS are the splice acceptor addition sites identified by SLaP mapper. PAS are the polyadenylation addition sites identified by SLaP mapper. (B) The corresponding entries in the SLaP mapper results file for all SAS sites shown in A. The poly(A) results for the 55 sites shown in part A are not listed for space reasons. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl0005" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The number of reads observed using different library preparation methods in two different species. <italic>L. mexicana</italic> based on 3 independent biological replicates. <italic>T. brucei</italic> based on 2 independent biological replicates. Numbers in brackets indicate one standard deviation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Species</th><th align="left">Library type</th><th align="left">Poly(A) reads per million reads</th><th align="left">Trans-splice reads per million reads</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>L. mexicana</italic></td><td align="left">T15VN</td><td align="char">34&#x000a0;784 (2100)</td><td align="char">4343 (300)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>L. mexicana</italic></td><td align="left">Random primed</td><td align="char">5673 (730)</td><td align="char">79&#x000a0;773 (10&#x000a0;000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>T. brucei</italic></td><td align="left">T15VN</td><td align="char">167&#x000a0;864 (8000)</td><td align="char">4782 (250)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>T. brucei</italic></td><td align="left">Random primed</td><td align="char">701 (50)</td><td align="char">76&#x000a0;563 (4800)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>