<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">gbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4316629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25527045</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evu276</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evu276</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Secreted Proteins of <italic>Achlya hypogyna</italic> and <italic>Thraustotheca clavata</italic> Identify the Ancestral Oomycete Secretome and Reveal Gene Acquisitions by Horizontal Gene Transfer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Misner</surname><given-names>Ian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evu276-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evu276-AFF2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="evu276-COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Blouin</surname><given-names>Nic</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evu276-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>Guy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evu276-AFF3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>Thomas A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evu276-AFF3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evu276-AFF4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>Christopher E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evu276-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="evu276-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Biological Sciences, The University of Rhode Island</aff><aff id="evu276-AFF2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Biological Sciences, The University of Maryland, College Park</aff><aff id="evu276-AFF3"><sup>3</sup>Biosciences, University of Exeter, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="evu276-AFF4"><sup>4</sup>Integrated Microbial Biodiversity Program, Canadian Institute for Advanced Research, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="evu276-COR1">*Corresponding author: E-mail: <email>imisner@umd.edu</email>.</corresp><fn id="evu276-FN1"><p><bold>Associate editor:</bold> Yves Van De Peer</p></fn><fn id="evu276-FN2"><p><bold>Data deposition:</bold> The secretome sequences from Achlya and Thraustotheca have been submitted to GenBank under the accession numbers KM037916-KM039053.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" license-type="creative-commons"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Saprotrophic and parasitic microorganisms secrete proteins into the environment to breakdown macromolecules and obtain nutrients. The molecules secreted are collectively termed the &#x0201c;secretome&#x0201d; and the composition and function of this set of proteins varies depending on the ecology, life cycle, and environment of an organism. Beyond the function of nutrient acquisition, parasitic lineages must also secrete molecules to manipulate their host. Here, we use a combination of <italic>de novo</italic> genome and transcriptome sequencing and bioinformatic identification of signal peptides to identify the putative secreted proteome of two oomycetes, the facultative parasite <italic>Achlya hypogyna</italic> and free-living <italic>Thraustotheca clavata</italic>. By comparing the secretomes of these saprolegnialean oomycetes with that of eight other oomycetes, we were able to characterize the evolution of this protein set across the oomycete clade. These species span the last common ancestor of the two major oomycete families allowing us to identify the ancestral secretome. This putative ancestral secretome consists of at least 84 gene families. Only 11 of these gene families are conserved across all 10 secretomes analyzed and the two major branches in the oomycete radiation. Notably, we have identified expressed elicitin-like effector genes in the saprotrophic decomposer, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>. Phylogenetic analyses show six novel horizontal gene transfers to the oomycete secretome from bacterial and fungal donor lineages, four of which are specific to the Saprolegnialeans. Comparisons between free-living and pathogenic taxa highlight the functional changes of oomycete secretomes associated with shifts in lifestyle.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>oomycete</kwd><kwd>horizontal gene transfer</kwd><kwd>evolution</kwd><kwd>comparative genomics</kwd><kwd>osmotrophy</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The Oomycota are a diverse assemblage of fungal-like protists placed within the eukaryotic supergroup, Stramenoplia (<xref rid="evu276-B28" ref-type="bibr">Dick et al. 1999</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B27" ref-type="bibr">Dick 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B2" ref-type="bibr">Adl et al. 2012</xref>) Oomycetes are the most diverse lineage of heterotrophic stramenopiles currently described (<xref rid="evu276-B27" ref-type="bibr">Dick 2001</xref>) and are ubiquitous members of freshwater aquatic communities and damp terrestrial environments (with fewer species inhabiting estuarine or marine environments). In their vegetative state, oomycetes take the form of colorless, coenocytic (multinucleate) siphons. Although many oomycetes are saprobes, it is the numerous parasitic members of the phylum that garner the most attention. These parasitic oomycetes infect a diverse array of plants, invertebrates, and vertebrates (<xref rid="evu276-B77" ref-type="bibr">Seymour and Johnson 1973</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B61" ref-type="bibr">Noga and Dykstra 1986</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B58" ref-type="bibr">Mendoza et al. 1993</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B40" ref-type="bibr">Hussein et al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B49" ref-type="bibr">Latijnhouwers et al. 2003</xref>). Plant and animal infections range from those that are chronic but nonlethal to those that are highly virulent and destroy the host organism. Oomycete infections of plants can cause blights, wilts, cankers, rusts, lesions, and/or (root) rots, contributing to billions of US dollars worth of agricultural losses each year (<xref rid="evu276-B91" ref-type="bibr">Tyler 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B100" ref-type="bibr">Nowicki et al. 2012</xref>).</p><p>Like many species that survive via dependent interaction on other organisms (dead or alive), osmotrophic oomycetes secrete a suite of proteins with functions including basic metabolic processes, nutrient acquisition, cell wall manufacture/adhesion/digestion, and virulence (<xref rid="evu276-B45" ref-type="bibr">Kamoun 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B71" ref-type="bibr">Raffaele et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B12" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al. 2012</xref>).</p><p>Collectively termed the &#x0201c;secretome,&#x0201d; these proteins occur across a wide taxonomic range of osmotrophs, including fungi, oomycetes, and bacteria (<xref rid="evu276-B24" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al. 2010</xref>) often reflecting the niche these microbes reside in, rather than there phylogenetic affinities (<xref rid="evu276-B81" ref-type="bibr">Soanes et al. 2008</xref>). The plant pathogenic oomycetes in the genera <italic>Phytophthora</italic> and <italic>Hyaloperonospora</italic> have characteristic sequence motifs, RxLR and LFLAK-DEER (Crinklers), present across hundreds of secreted proteins. This specialized set of effector proteins is responsible for suppression of host defense and is capable of triggering (necrotrophs) or preventing (hemibiotrophs) localized cell death in their host, among other pathogenic effects (<xref rid="evu276-B10" ref-type="bibr">Bos 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B6" ref-type="bibr">Birch et al. 2008</xref>, <xref rid="evu276-B7" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B23" ref-type="bibr">Cheung et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B50" ref-type="bibr">Levesque et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B63" ref-type="bibr">Oh et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B86" ref-type="bibr">Stassen and Van den Ackerveken 2011</xref>).</p><p>Elicitins and elicitin-like proteins, which trigger the hypersensitive response in the host plants (<xref rid="evu276-B43" ref-type="bibr">Jiang, Tyler, Whisson, et al. 2006</xref>), are a class of effector proteins responsible for extracellular lipid transport that were believed to be exclusive to <italic>Phytophthora</italic> and <italic>Pythium</italic> (<xref rid="evu276-B67" ref-type="bibr">Panabieres et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B43" ref-type="bibr">Jiang, Tyler, Whisson, et al. 2006</xref>) but recently identified in the <italic>Saprolegnia parasitica</italic> genome (<xref rid="evu276-B41" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al. 2013</xref>). Elicitin-like genes are highly divergent, but appear to have functions related to true Elicitins. A characteristic feature of this gene family is the presence of three disulfide bonds, formed from six cysteine residues, necessary to stabilize the alpha-helix (<xref rid="evu276-B34" ref-type="bibr">Fefeu et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B9" ref-type="bibr">Boissy et al. 1999</xref>).</p><p>In the oomycetes secretome proteins are often encoded by genes located in &#x0201c;labile&#x0201d; and variable regions of the genome, usually flanked by transposable elements and chromosomal regions with high cross over rates (<xref rid="evu276-B71" ref-type="bibr">Raffaele et al. 2010</xref>). These regions are typified by lower levels of genome conservation and therefore demonstrate higher rates of gene duplication and accelerated rates of sequence evolution, leading to protein divergence and neofunctionalization (<xref rid="evu276-B42" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B82" ref-type="bibr">Soanes and Talbot 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B71" ref-type="bibr">Raffaele et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B70" ref-type="bibr">Raffaele and Kamoun 2012</xref>). The increased evolutionary rate identified in oomycete effector gene families has therefore been suggested to facilitate host jumps and adaptation to novel host defense systems, making oomycetes highly successful pathogens (<xref rid="evu276-B70" ref-type="bibr">Raffaele and Kamoun 2012</xref>). Understanding the evolution of the oomycete secretome is therefore important, because it encompasses the proteins that drive interactions between parasite and the host environment.</p><p>Comparative studies of plant parasitic fungi and oomycetes in the Peronosporaleans show similarities in secretome composition and function (<xref rid="evu276-B12" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al. 2012</xref>). These similarities are assumed to be the result of convergent evolution. However, <xref rid="evu276-B73" ref-type="bibr">Richards et al. (2011)</xref> examined the effect of fungal derived horizontal gene transfer (HGT) on the genomes of <italic>Phytophthora ramorum</italic>, <italic>Phytophthora sojae</italic>, <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic>, and <italic>Hyaloperonospora parasitica</italic> and were able to identify 34 candidate HGTs. Seventeen of these gene families encode proteins that function as part of the secretome, and many have undergone large-scale expansion by gene duplication post transfer, implicating HGT as an important evolutionary mechanism in the oomycetes. Similarly, <xref rid="evu276-B4" ref-type="bibr">Belbahri et al. (2008)</xref> have identified a bacterial-derived HGT of a candidate plant virulence factor, a cutinase gene family homolog, into the oomycete lineage.</p><p>Members of the Saprolegnialeans, which can infect fish (<xref rid="evu276-B14" ref-type="bibr">Burr and Beakes 1994</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B40" ref-type="bibr">Hussein et al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B94" ref-type="bibr">van West 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B84" ref-type="bibr">Sosa et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B65" ref-type="bibr">Oidtmann et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B46" ref-type="bibr">Ke et al. 2009</xref>), decapods (<xref rid="evu276-B92" ref-type="bibr">Unestam 1965</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B20" ref-type="bibr">Cerenius and S&#x000f6;derh&#x000e4;ll 1984</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B64" ref-type="bibr">Oidtmann et al. 2004</xref>), and even some plants (<xref rid="evu276-B53" ref-type="bibr">Madoui et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B90" ref-type="bibr">Trapphoff et al. 2009</xref>), have been understudied relative to the agriculturally relevant members of the Peronosporaleans. Moreover, comparisons between closely related nonpathogenic saprobes and the pathogenic oomycetes are lacking, due to the absence of genomic data from the nonpathogenic forms. The recent release of the <italic>S</italic><italic>. parasitica</italic> genome (<xref rid="evu276-B41" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al. 2013</xref>) has provided genomic data from the Saprolegnialeans from a facultative pathogen of fish. For comparative purposes, we identified two saprolegnian species for genome sequencing: the facultative decapod parasite <italic>Achlya hypogyna</italic> (PRJNA169234) and the nonpathogenic saprobe <italic>Thraustotheca clavata</italic> (PRJNA169235). These organisms provide an opportunity to understand the evolution of the secretome relative to lifestyle and across the deepest division in the oomycetes. We used a bioinformatic approach (<xref rid="evu276-B45" ref-type="bibr">Kamoun 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B24" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B71" ref-type="bibr">Raffaele et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B12" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al. 2012</xref>) to identify the proteins belonging to the secretomes of <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>. The secretome proteins were categorized into orthologous gene families and compared with the secretomes from the Peronosporalean and Saprolegnialeans oomycetes and the Hyphochytridiomycete, <italic>Hyphochytrium catenoides</italic> (<xref rid="evu276-B73" ref-type="bibr">Richards et al. 2011</xref>), the putative sister group of the oomycetes (<xref rid="evu276-B93" ref-type="bibr">Van der Auwera et al. 1995</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B50" ref-type="bibr">Levesque et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B71" ref-type="bibr">Raffaele et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B51" ref-type="bibr">Links et al. 2011</xref>).</p><p>Although the complete genomes of <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> have additional interesting features, here we focus on the secretome of these organisms and what the expansion of available Saprolegnean genomes can reveal about this critical gene set, across oomycetes. We were able to 1) identify and annotate the ancestral secretome of the two most diverse oomycete clades; 2) compare the Saprolegnialean-specific secretome with the secretome of the Peronosporaleans, highlighting the differences in metabolic and pathogenic genes; 3) characterize the evolution of secretome genes and functions across four distinct lifestyles; and 4) identify novel HGT events key to the evolution of the Saprolegnialean secretome.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Culturing and Nucleotide Extraction</title><p><italic>Achlya hypogyna</italic> (ATTC 48635) and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> (ATCC 34112) were obtained from American Type Culture Collection (Manassas, VA). Cultures were maintained on cornmeal agar plates and grown in 1.5 l of 50% Luria Broth (LB) at 25 &#x000b0;C for extraction. After 5 days 4.5 l of each species in 50% LB were flash frozen with liquid nitrogen before being ground with mortar and pestle into a powder. While frozen, 5 ml of ground material was placed into 30 ml of Carlson Lysis Buffer (<xref rid="evu276-B18" ref-type="bibr">Carlson et al. 1991</xref>) with 0.1 mg/ml of Proteinase K. Samples were incubated at 65 &#x000b0;C for 60 min followed by 20 min on ice. Samples were centrifuged at 7,130 &#x000d7;g for 10 min to remove cellular debris, supernatant was combined with 20 ml of phenol:chloroform:isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1) and gently mixed for 5 min. Extraction was centrifuged at 7,130 &#x000d7;g for 5 min. The phenol extraction was repeated twice. Nucleic acid was precipitated using 30 ml of 0 &#x000b0;C 95% EtOH and 1/10 volume of 3M sodium acetate, and samples were placed in a freezer overnight (&#x02212;20&#x000b0;C). The following day samples were centrifuged at 7,130 rpm for 30 min to pellet nucleic acids. Pellets were washed twice with 70% EtOH and resuspended in 2 ml of TE. Samples were treated with RNAse A (10 mg/ml), incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for 60 min, and precipitated as above. DNA quantity and quality was accessed using a NanoDrop 8000 (Thermo Scientific, Wilmington, DE). Samples were stored at &#x02212;20 &#x000b0;C.</p><p>For RNA extraction, cultures of <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> were acclimatized at 25 &#x000b0;C for 2 weeks at 12:12 Light:Dark before 16 LB 50% concentration and 16 diH<sub>2</sub>O 150 ml subcultures were created, each with three autoclaved hemp seeds. Cultures were then incubated at 4, 15, 25, and 35 &#x000b0;C and harvested at 0.5, 1, 3, and 6 h in both light and dark conditions to collect the widest spectrum of RNA possible. Fresh material was ground under liquid nitrogen immediately after harvest, and ground material was placed directly in extraction buffer. RNA was extracted from <italic>A</italic><italic>c. hypogyna</italic> using the Qiagen RNeasy kit (Qiagen, CA) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. RNA from all experiments was pooled and quality was assessed using a NanoDrop 8000 (Thermo Scientific, CA).</p></sec><sec><title>Sequencing and Assembly</title><sec><title>Genome</title><p><italic>Achlya hypogyna</italic> DNA was sequenced using one half plate of Roche 454 FLX (<xref rid="evu276-B55" ref-type="bibr">Margulies et al. 2005</xref>) and one lane of 72 cycle paired-end Illumina-Solexa (<xref rid="evu276-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bentley et al. 2008</xref>). Roche 454 reads were trimmed on the CLC Genomics Workbench v5.0 (CLC Bio Aarhus, Denmark) using the default settings. Illumina reads were trimmed using CLC with default setting while removing sequences shorter than 70 bp. The 454 trimmed reads were combined with the trimmed Illumina reads for de novo assembly on the CLC Genomics Workbench. Default settings were used for de novo assembly with the length fraction set to 0.7 and the similarity set to 0.9, the minimum distance for paired-end Illumina reads was 150 bp with the maximum distance set to 217 bp.</p><p><italic>Thraustotheca clavata</italic> DNA was sequenced using one half plate of 3 kb paired-end Roche 454 FLX and two lanes of 108 cycle paired-end Illumina. Roche 454 reads were trimmed on the CLC Genomics Workbench v5.0 using the default settings, we removed 12 bases from the 5&#x02032;-end and reads lengths that were under 150 bp and over 450 bp. Illumina reads were trimmed using CLC using default setting while removing sequences shorter than 40 and 9 bp from the 5&#x02032;-end. Length and 5&#x02032;-sequence removal thresholds were determined by analyzing nucleotide frequency plots generated using FastQC v0.10.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</ext-link>, last accessed December 18, 2014). The 454 trimmed reads were combined with the trimmed Illumina reads for de novo assembly on the CLC Genomics Workbench. Default settings were used for de novo assembly with the length fraction set to 0.3 and the similarity set to 0.95 for 454 reads and 0.99 for Illumina, the minimum distance for paired-end 454 reads was 300 bp with the maximum distance at 3,500 bp, for Illumina reads the minimum was 179 bp and the maximum at 716 bp.</p></sec><sec><title>Transcriptome</title><p>Library construction and sequencing via the Illumina GAII were performed by Genome Quebec using one lane of single 108 bp reads. The data were trimmed on CLC Genomics Workbench (v5.0) to remove reads shorter than 70 bp and those reads whose cumulative bases with quality scores below 0.05. Default parameters for transcriptome assembly were used to create assemblies in CLC.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Identification and Annotation of Secretome Proteins</title><p>The <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> proteins were identified using MAKER v2.31.4 program (<xref rid="evu276-B15" ref-type="bibr">Cantarel et al. 2008</xref>) MAKER was trained using the protein sequences from <italic>S</italic>. <italic>parasitica</italic> (Broad Institute) and transcripts from <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> or <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>, respectively (<xref rid="evu276-B59" ref-type="bibr">Misner et al. 2013</xref>). The MAKER pipeline was set to create <italic>ab initio</italic> gene predictions using repeat masked and unmasked genomic data using SNAP (<xref rid="evu276-B48" ref-type="bibr">Korf 2004</xref>) and GeneMark (<xref rid="evu276-B52" ref-type="bibr">Lomsadze et al. 2005</xref>) with the annotation edit distance = 0.85. SNAP was also used to make HMM-based gene predictions as outlined in the MAKER manual.</p><p>To identify proteins belonging to the secretomes of all ten oomycetes and the one hyphochytridiomycete analysed in this study, the predicted proteomes of each species were analyzed by four bioinformatic tools, SignalP v4.0 (<xref rid="evu276-B32" ref-type="bibr">Emanuelsson et al. 2007</xref>), TargetP v1.1 (<xref rid="evu276-B33" ref-type="bibr">Emanuelsson et al. 2000</xref>), WoLF PSORT (<xref rid="evu276-B39" ref-type="bibr">Horton et al. 2007</xref>), and TMHMM v2.0 (<xref rid="evu276-B83" ref-type="bibr">Sonnhammer et al. 1998</xref>). For a protein to be included in the putative secretome it must have a SignalP <italic>D</italic>-score &#x02265;0.5, a localization of &#x0201c;S&#x0201d; in TargetP, a WoLF PSORT annotation of extracellular, and no transmembrane regions after the signal peptide. These programs were run successively, in the order above, removing failed proteins at each step. TargetP was run using the &#x0201c;nonplant&#x0201d; setting and WoLF PSORT was run with the &#x0201c;fungi&#x0201d; setting as in (<xref rid="evu276-B71" ref-type="bibr">Raffaele et al. 2010</xref>).</p><p>Complete protein sets from all 11 taxa analysed were placed into gene families using OrthoMCL (<xref rid="evu276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2006</xref>, <xref rid="evu276-B22" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Functional annotations were made by running PFAM (<xref rid="evu276-B69" ref-type="bibr">Punta et al. 2012</xref>) on the CLC Genomics Workbench v5.1 (CLC Bio Aarhus, Denmark), BlAST2GO (<xref rid="evu276-B25" ref-type="bibr">Conesa et al. 2005</xref>) and Reversed Position Specific (RPS)-BLAST against the KOG-LE database (<ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/pub/mmdb/cdd/">ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/pub/mmdb/cdd/</ext-link>, last accessed December 18, 2014) with a cutoff of 1e<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>5</sup>. Each OrthoMCL group in this study was assigned a KOG category based upon the majority consensus for the group. For consistency, we predicted the secretome data sets for all 11 organisms using the same methodology and provide the sequences for these data sets (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary file S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Our secretome data were then combined with the secretome predictions from the other available crown oomycetes and <italic>Hy</italic><italic>p</italic>. <italic>catenoides</italic>, in order to identify shared, unique, and overrepresented gene families. Carbohydrate-active (CAZy) enzymes were annotated by submitting proteins from each secretome to the dbCAN webserver (<xref rid="evu276-B97" ref-type="bibr">Yin et al. 2012</xref>) available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://csbl.bmb.uga.edu/dbCAN/annotate.php">http://csbl.bmb.uga.edu/dbCAN/annotate.php</ext-link> (last accessed December 18, 2014). To validate gene gains and losses &#x0201c;missing&#x0201d; secretome genes were BLAST searched against the full genome from each organism using tBLASTn. Protein families that were &#x0201c;lost&#x0201d; from the secretome but identified in the cytosolic proteome were manually inspected for a proper start codon to minimize false negative N-terminal signal peptide predictions.</p><p>To verify protein expression <italic>Achlya hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> secretome proteins were reciprocal BLAST searched against their respective transcriptome assemblies using BLAST + (v2.2.28). Transcriptome nucleotide sequences were compared with secretome protein databases using BLASTx with an <italic>e</italic>-value of 1e<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>10</sup>. Secretome proteins were compared with transcriptome nucleotide databases using tBLASTn and an <italic>e</italic>-value of 1e<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>10</sup>. Reciprocal BLAST hits were determined using a custom python script.</p></sec><sec><title>Secretome Evolution Analysis</title><p>Secretome proteins were assigned to 886 OrthoMCL gene families and 3,348 were unassigned genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary file S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Individual gene families contained both secreted and nonsecreted protein members. These were aligned in MAFFT v7.017 (LINSI method), and gene trees were generated using RAxML using the PROTCATLG model with 500 bootstraps (100 bootstraps for families with more than 200 sequences). Individual gene family trees were reconciled to the species tree was scored for gains, duplications, and losses with NOTUNG v2.8.1.2 (<xref rid="evu276-B29" ref-type="bibr">Durand et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B95" ref-type="bibr">Vernot et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B87" ref-type="bibr">Stolzer et al. 2012</xref>). NOTUNG (1.5 duplication and 1 loss cost) was first run in batch mode and trees were rearranged using a &#x0201c;threshold&#x0201d; of 80%. Rearranged trees were reconciled against the species tree using the &#x0201c;phylogenomics&#x0201d; flag. Singletons and unassigned genes were scored as novel gains in each of the leaf nodes where they occurred. The species tree used to reconcile individual gene trees was generated via RAxML 8.0.22 (PROTOGAMMALG model, 1,000 bootstraps) from a concatenated MAFFT (LINSI method) alignment of 15 gene families with a single representative from each taxon. The 15 one to one gene families were identified through an all versus all BLASTp (1e<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>20</sup> cut-off).</p></sec><sec><title>Phylogenetic Analysis</title><p>Secretome proteins from <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> were clustered into 422 unique gene families using OrthoMCL representing 874 proteins. For each of the 422 OrthoMCL groups the longest protein sequence, from <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> or <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>, was identified and extracted using a custom Perl script. In the event of a tie, multiple sequences were extracted for that OrthoMCL group. The 478 longest sequences from each gene family (including ties) were run, individually, through a gene-by-gene phylogenetic pipeline to generate fast maximum-likelihood (ML) trees as in <xref rid="evu276-B73" ref-type="bibr">Richards et al. (2011)</xref>. Briefly, secretome proteins were compared with a database containing 895 (215 eukaryotic and 680 prokaryotic; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary file S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) genomes using BLASTp (cutoff of 1e<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>10</sup>). Similar sequences were aligned using MUSCLE (<xref rid="evu276-B30" ref-type="bibr">Edgar 2004a</xref>, <xref rid="evu276-B31" ref-type="bibr">2004b</xref>). TrimAl (<xref rid="evu276-B17" ref-type="bibr">Capella-Gutierrez et al. 2009</xref>) was then used to automatically mask and remove regions with ambiguous or &#x0201c;gappy&#x0201d; alignment. FastTree (<xref rid="evu276-B68" ref-type="bibr">Price et al. 2010</xref>) was used to compute the approximate likelihood ratio test trees from the masked alignments. The generated trees were manually curated to identify HGT, putative function, and gene family composition. For candidate HGTs we refined the alignment and mask manually using Seaview (<xref rid="evu276-B99" ref-type="bibr">Gouy et al. 2010</xref>), removing distant paralogs, gappy, and partial sequences and checking GenBank nr, GenBank expressed sequence tags (ESTs), and DOE JGI genome databases for additional relevant taxa and sequence diversity. For the final phylogenies we used PhyML (<xref rid="evu276-B36" ref-type="bibr">Guindon et al. 2005</xref>) with the model parameters estimated for each data set (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T2">table 2</xref>) using ProtTest 3 (<xref rid="evu276-B26" ref-type="bibr">Darriba et al. 2011</xref>) and with 500 bootstrap replicates.</p></sec><sec><title>Alternative Tree Topology Tests</title><p>For four trees where the phylogeny demonstrated direct support for HGT (i.e., an oomycete group branching with and within a donor group [fungi or bacteria] with strong bootstrap support), we conducted alternative topology tests. To further test, the topological support consistent with HGT we recalculated the best ML tree using RAxML (<xref rid="evu276-B85" ref-type="bibr">Stamatakis 2006</xref>) constraining monophyly of the donor group (illustrated in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary figs. S3</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">S7&#x02013;S9</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) using the PROTCATWAGF model, and the final ML optimization was done with the +&#x00393; model (not CAT&#x02014;i.e., PROTGAMMAWAGF). The trees, constrained and unconstrained, for each alignment were combined to a single file and used as input to Consel (<xref rid="evu276-B79" ref-type="bibr">Shimodaira and Hasegawa 2001</xref>) where they were compared using the approximately unbiased test (<xref rid="evu276-B78" ref-type="bibr">Shimodaira 2002</xref>; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T3">table 3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Genome Assembly</title><p>Using Illumina and Roche 454 sequencing technologies and the CLC Genomics Workbench (v 5.0), we were able to assemble high-quality draft genomes from <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic>. <italic>hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> using a combination of Roche 454 and Illumina paired-end sequencing. The <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic>. <italic>hypogyna</italic> de novo assembly consisted of 3,075 contigs with an average length of 14,124 bp and a N<sub>50</sub> of 52,035 bp totaling 43.43 Mb of assembled sequence data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T1">table 1</xref>). We were able to estimate the completeness, and size, of the genome by using the Conserved Eukaryotic Genes Mapping Approach (CEGMA) and BLAT. The <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic>. <italic>hypogyna</italic> genome was 98% complete, having 243 of the 248 CEGs. Mapping of transcriptome sequences (10,349 transcripts) to the <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic>. <italic>hypogyna</italic> genome assembly using BLAT showed that 89.9% of the expressed genes were present in the assembled genome (cutoff of 1e<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>10</sup>). Based upon the CEGMA and BLAT analyses, the estimated genome size for <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic>. <italic>hypogyna</italic> is between 44 and 48Mb. The <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic>. <italic>hypogyna</italic> assembly had a GC content of 56.80% with a 60.71% GC content in the coding regions. Repetitive genomic elements were identified using de novo RepeatScout libraries in RepeatMasker and it was determined that 8.37% of the assembled <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic>. <italic>hypogyna</italic> DNA was repetitive (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T1">table 1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="evu276-T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Genome Assembly Statistics for Organisms Included in This Study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genome Statistic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Achlya hypogyna</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Thraustotheca clavata</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Saprolegnia parasitica</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Albugo candida</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pythium ultimum</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phytophthora capsici</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phytophthora ramorum</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phytophthora sojae</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hyaloperonospora arabidopsis</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated genome size (Mb)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of contigs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,336</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,288</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,747</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">917</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,576</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">862</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,108</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N50 (kb)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">390</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total contig length (Mb)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">190</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G + C content (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Repeat (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of predicted proteins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,430</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,154</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,065</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,797</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,824</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,291</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,805</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,743</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,989</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,510</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>The same procedures were used to evaluate the <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> de novo assembly, which consisted of 5,338 contigs having an average length of 7,330 bp and a N<sub>50</sub> of 15,004 bp totaling 39.1 Mb of assembled DNA. CEGMA analysis found 188 complete CEGs and suggested a 75.81% complete assembly. Contrary to CEGMA, BLAT mapping indicated that 87.94% of the12,841 <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> RNAseq transcripts were present in the assembly. Based upon these analyses the estimated genome size of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> is between 48 and 51 Mb. The GC content of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> was 37.92% with 40.33% GC content in coding regions. The repetitive DNA content of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> was determined to be 4.10% using the same procedures for the <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic>. <italic>hypogyna</italic> repeat identification (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T1">table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Secretome Identification and Composition</title><p>To identify secretome proteins, we used an in silico redundant conservative approach (<xref rid="evu276-B89" ref-type="bibr">Torto et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B38" ref-type="bibr">Haldar et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B96" ref-type="bibr">Win et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B45" ref-type="bibr">Kamoun 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B12" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al. 2012</xref>). Signal peptides were predicted using SignalP v4.0, subcellular targeting was completed using TargetP and WoLF-PSORT, and only proteins predicted as secreted by all three methods were considered to be part of the secretome. Transmembrane domains were identified using TMHMM, and any secreted proteins containing transmembrane domains after the signal peptide were excluded from the secretome. Therefore, the secretome constituents reported here (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T1">table 1</xref>) are conservative predictions. Given the nature of this analysis incomplete gene prediction, particularly failure to accurately recover the 5&#x02032; of the gene model and therefore the N-terminus of the predicted protein, will directly affect the ability to positively identify secretome proteins. However, previous studies have shown that sampling and cross comparing multiple lineages can partially account for this source of error when putatively secreted proteins are compared across orthologue groups (<xref rid="evu276-B11" ref-type="bibr">Braaksma et al. 2010</xref>).</p><p>Each of the 11 secretomes (10 oomycetes + <italic>Hyp</italic><italic>. catenoides</italic>) in this study were identified using the above procedure and individually submitted to OrthoMCL (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.orthomcl.org">www.orthomcl.org</ext-link>, last accessed December 18, 2014) for gene family assignment to existing OrthoMCL groups (<xref rid="evu276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2006</xref>, <xref rid="evu276-B22" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Proteins were placed into OrthoMCL groups using BLASTp with an <italic>e</italic>-value of 1e<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>5</sup> and 50% match. The <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> predicted secretome consisted of 262 gene families, containing 739 individual proteins (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T2">table 2</xref>). Thirty-eight proteins matched other sequences in the online database but had &#x0201c;no group&#x0201d; (designation by OrthoMCL DB). An additional 218 proteins had no OrthoMCL database hits and are considered unique. The predicted secretome of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> contained 160 gene families encompassing 405 individual proteins, 25 of which had no group and 52 that had no hits to the OrthoMCL database (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T2">table 2</xref>). Therefore, although the <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> secretome is smaller, a higher proportion of the <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> secretome (353/405 proteins) had OrthoMCL group assignments than <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> (521/739 proteins).
<table-wrap id="evu276-T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>OrthoMCL Distributions of Secretome Proteins by Species</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAPpar</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACHhyp</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">THRcla</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHYcap</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHYinf</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHYram</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHYsoj</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HYAara</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PYTult</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALBcan</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HYPcat</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lifestyle</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saprotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemibiotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemibiotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemibiotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemibiotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obligate biotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Necrotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obligate biotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saprotroph</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total secretome</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">986</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">739</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">405</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">972</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,187</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,085</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">438</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">679</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">206</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">460</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of hits in OrthoMCL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">613</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">521</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">353</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">869</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">876</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,179</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,303</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">258</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">601</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">257</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">262</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">271</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">338</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">332</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">181</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of no Group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of no hits</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">373</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">255</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,782</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteins with transcript</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">309</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">281</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="evu276-TF3"><p>N<sc>ote.</sc>&#x02014;SAPpar, <italic>S. parasitica</italic>; ACHhyp, <italic>Ac</italic>. <italic>hypogyna</italic>; THRcla, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>; PHYcap, <italic>Ph</italic>. <italic>capsici</italic>; PHYinf, <italic>Ph</italic>. <italic>infestans</italic>; PHYram, <italic>Ph</italic>. <italic>ramorum</italic>; PHYsoj, <italic>Ph</italic>. <italic>soja</italic>e; HYAara, <italic>Hya</italic>. <italic>arabidopsi</italic>s; PYTult, <italic>Py</italic>. <italic>ultimum</italic>; ALBcan, <italic>Al</italic>. <italic>candida</italic>; HYPcat, <italic>Hyp</italic>. <italic>catenoides</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>The <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> secretomes were compared with the secretomes of eight oomycetes, and <italic>Hy</italic><italic>p</italic>. <italic>catenoides</italic> using gene family clustering (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T2">table 2</xref>). The unknown sequences from all 11 secretomes (those that had no hits in OrthoMCL or returned hits with no group) were compared by BLAST against one another to identify potential homology between these nonannotated secretome proteins. BLAST results identified no significant similarity in any of the comparisons (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Ancestral Oomycete Secretome</title><p>To identify the ancestral oomycete secretome (AOS) we analyzed the three saprolegnian taxa in comparison with seven sequenced members of the Peronosporaleans. Collectively, these species represent a wide range of oomycete lifestyles, from free-living saprobes to obligate parasites of plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T2">table 2</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B37" ref-type="bibr">Haas et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B50" ref-type="bibr">Levesque et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B71" ref-type="bibr">Raffaele et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B51" ref-type="bibr">Links et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B41" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al. 2013</xref>). Using the secretome of the putative sister group of the oomycetes, Hyphochytridiomycete, <italic>Hy</italic><italic>p</italic>. <italic>catenoides</italic>, for an outgroup we utilized NOTUNG (<xref rid="evu276-B29" ref-type="bibr">Durand et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B95" ref-type="bibr">Vernot et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B87" ref-type="bibr">Stolzer et al. 2012</xref>) to model gene gain, loss, and duplication. Based on this comparative analysis, the last common ancestor of the ten oomycetes investigated contained 84 gene families (OrthoMCL groups), which we infer were represented by at least 266 proteins in the AOS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F1">fig. 1</xref>). Thirty-eight of the 84 AOS gene families were present in the secretome of <italic>Hy</italic><italic>p</italic>. <italic>catenoides</italic> (460 individual proteins). Only 11 of the 84 gene families occur in all ten oomycete secretomes and two of those families are also present in <italic>Hy</italic><italic>p</italic>. <italic>catenoides</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary file S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Additionally, duplication of these proteins represents a considerable factor across the oomycete species tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">fig. 2</xref>), demonstrating considerable expansion and reconfiguration of the secretome across the oomycetes. <italic>Achlya hypogyna</italic> encodes 264 proteins derived from the AOS (121 with sequence data supporting mRNA expression), whereas <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> has only 202 AOS-derived proteins (136 with sequence data supporting mRNA expression).
<fig id="evu276-F1" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 1.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>Predicted evolutionary pattern of gene families gained and lost in representative oomycetes. Numbers in black represent gains, duplications, and losses of all gene families. Numbers in color indicate evolutionary events specific to the genes within each gene family predicted to be in the secretome. Stars signify the acquisition of genes via HGT, leading to the Saprolegnialean taxa. A minimum of 84 OrthoMCL gene families are inferred to represent the AOS.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evu276f1p"/></fig>
<fig id="evu276-F2" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 2.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>Evolutionary patterns of secretome genes and their inferred KOG function. Column (<italic>A</italic>) under both headings represents the proteins that are derived from the AOS. Column (<italic>B</italic>) includes numbers and functions of secretome proteins not inferred to have been derived from the AOS. AOS-derived proteins are mostly associated with metabolic functions. In contrast, non-AOS derived proteins include the host&#x02013;pathogen interaction genes and appear to be less conserved, owing to the large proportion that are poorly characterized.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evu276f2p"/></fig></p><p>Putative functional annotation of the AOS ranged from amino acid and carbohydrate metabolism, and cell wall degrading enzymes (CWDEs), covering 11 of the 25 KOG categories (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary file S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Twelve of the 84 AOS gene families had no hits to the KOG database or were of &#x0201c;general&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;unknown&#x0201d; function (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). &#x0201c;Carbohydrate transport and metabolism&#x0201d; (KOG: G) represented the largest portion of the AOS, with 31 gene families present, making up 37% of the entire AOS. Moreover, 7 of the 11 gene families that putatively encode secreted proteins found in all oomycetes (64%) were also in KOG category G. &#x0201c;Posttranslational modification, protein turnover, chaperones&#x0201d; (KOG: O) was the next most abundant group, containing 13 gene families, followed by &#x0201c;signal transduction mechanisms&#x0201d; (KOG: T) and &#x0201c;amino acid transport and metabolism&#x0201d; (KOG: E), with nine and six gene families, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). CAZy enzymes were present in 30 of the 84 AOS gene families, as described below.</p><p>Phylogenetic analysis of the AOS showed that 7 secretome gene families were exclusive to oomycetes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), whereas five families were too divergent to generate alignments (BLASTP cutoff of 1e<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>10</sup>) for phylogenetic analysis when sampling across our local genome database of 895 genomes, including 215 eukaryotes and 680 prokaryotes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary file S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). BLAST searches of these sequences to the NCBI <italic>nr</italic> database (March 2014) also did not return any low <italic>e</italic>-value (&#x0003c;1e<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>5</sup>) hits outside of the oomycetes sampled.</p></sec><sec><title>Elicitins</title><p>Eight highly divergent gene families in our analysis were predicted to encode elicitin-like proteins. Manual alignment of elicitin-like sequences in OG5_133826 (the only elicitin-like family found in all ten oomycete secretomes) showed that 101 out of the 119 sequences contained the six necessary cysteine residues for proper folding and function (<xref rid="evu276-B43" ref-type="bibr">Jiang, Tyler, Whisson, et al. 2006</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Of the 18 sequences that were missing cysteine residues, six of them belong to <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> and four to <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>. Two sequences from <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic>, one from <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>, and two from <italic>S</italic>. <italic>parasitica</italic> had the necessary sequence structure to be putative elicitin-like genes.</p><p>Further analysis of the <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> secretomes identified four other elicitin-like gene families, two from each species. These sequences contained all the necessary cysteine residues and were aligned with the other members of the gene family (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Additionally, several elicitin genes were present in transcriptome data (<xref rid="evu276-B59" ref-type="bibr">Misner et al. 2013</xref>), indicating this gene family is functional in a saprobic decomposer. This is the first report of elicitin-like genes occurring in a reportedly strictly saprotrophic oomycete. Although there are no confirmed reports of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> acting as a pathogen, the possibility cannot be ruled out given taxonomic and identification uncertainties in the group that this species may capable of living as a pathogen. However, these data may suggest a more fundamental role for elicitin-like genes in lipid transport function, that can be functional in diverse ecologies including saprotrophic function (<xref rid="evu276-B8" ref-type="bibr">Blein et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B43" ref-type="bibr">Jiang, Tyler, et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B43" ref-type="bibr">Jiang, Tyler, Whisson, et al. 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Secretome Gene Gain, Duplication, and Loss</title><p>Of the 886 OrthoMCL groups (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary file S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) that contain at least a single gene that putatively encodes a secreted protein, we were able to align and make phylogenetic trees for 695 groups. The NOTUNG analysis of 695 trees was used to identify gain, duplication, and loss events of all the putatively secreted orthologue families, throughout the oomycete phylogeny and therefore included both secreted (color values in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F1">fig. 1</xref>) and nonsecreted (black values in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F1">fig. 1</xref>) genes within each orthologue set. To identify evolutionary events within secretome genes only, all 695 trees analyzed by NOTUNG were manually analyzed to decipher evolutionary patterns. Secretome genes were classified into one of five categories and mapped on to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F1">figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">2</xref>. &#x0201c;Novel gain&#x0201d; was used for proteins that lack homologs in either the secretome or cytosolic proteome of taxa derived before the labeled node. &#x0201c;Gain from proteome&#x0201d; represents gene families that have cytosolic proteins in taxa derived prior to the labeled node, but are predicted by our pipeline as secreted, at the labeled node. &#x0201c;Duplications&#x0201d; are categorized by the duplication of secretome genes at the labeled node. &#x0201c;Loss to proteome&#x0201d; indicates proteins that are present in the genome, but no longer pass our secretome prediction pipeline. &#x0201c;Total loss&#x0201d; categorized proteins that could no longer be detected at, or after, a given node of the tree in either the secreted or cytosolic forms. This classification scheme was manually applied at each node of the tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F1">figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">2</xref>).</p><p>Gains and losses were functionally compared by species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">fig. 2</xref>), the largest changes occur in the KOG category of metabolism and those families involved in host&#x02013;pathogen interactions (crinklers [CRN], RxLR, Elicitins, and necrosis-inducing peptides [NPP]). Each species has specific alterations of gene families involved in carbohydrate transport and metabolism (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T3">table 3</xref>)&#x02014;a pattern consistent with a gain of carbohydrate transport and metabolism in the Peronosporalean clade, demonstrated by <xref rid="evu276-B73" ref-type="bibr">Richards et al. (2011)</xref>. Oomycetes appear to be flexible in reconfiguring carbohydrate metabolism, which has undoubtedly led to successful lifestyles as osmotrophic feeders enabling host switching between plants and animals. However, most of the genes gained in any specific species did not have KOG classification hits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">fig. 2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="evu276-T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Distribution of Key CAZy Families by Species</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAPpar</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACHhyp</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">THRcla</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHYcap</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHYinf</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHYram</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHYsoj</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HYAara</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PYTult</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALBcan</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HYPcat</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facultative</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saprotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemibiotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemibiotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemibiotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemibiotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obligate biotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Necrotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obligate biotroph</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saprotroph</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBM family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM1<sup>AOS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM63<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CBM9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CE family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CE1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CE10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CE12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CE13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CE14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CE16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CE3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CE4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CE5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CE7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;CE8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GH family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH114</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH18<sup>AOS</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH72<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH81<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GH89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GT family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GT1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GT24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GT25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GT31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GT32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GT4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GT41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GT60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GT62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GT71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;GT8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PL family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;PL1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>A</sup></xref><sup>OS</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="evu276-TF3"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;PL12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;PL14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;PL3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;PL4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;PL7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="evu276-TF1"><p>N<sc>ote</sc>.&#x02014;Numbers represent protein copy number per species or <italic>S. parasitica</italic> (SAPpar), <italic>Ac</italic>. <italic>hypogyna</italic> (ACHhyp), <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> (THRcla), <italic>Ph</italic>. <italic>capsici</italic> (PHYcap), <italic>Ph</italic>. <italic>infestans</italic> (PHYinf), <italic>Ph</italic>. <italic>ramorum</italic> (PHYram), <italic>Ph</italic>. <italic>sojae</italic> (PHYsoj), <italic>Hya</italic>. <italic>arabidopsis</italic> (HYAara), <italic>Py</italic>. <italic>ultimum</italic> (PYTult), <italic>Al</italic>. <italic>candida</italic> (ALBcan), and <italic>Hyp</italic>. <italic>catenoides</italic> (HYPcat). <sup>AOS</sup> predicted in AOS.</p></fn><fn id="evu276-TF2"><p><sup>a</sup>Predicted in HGT.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p><italic>Hyaloperonospora arabidopsis</italic> had the largest number of secretome gene losses with 257, followed by <italic>Ph. infestans</italic> with 235 losses. With only 20 secretome genes gained, <italic>Albugo candida</italic> has the fewest secretome additions of all species studied. Within the Saprolegniales <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> had only 66 secretome gene gains. Notably, 49.9% (202 proteins) of the <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> secretome proteins placed in OrthoMCL groups were present in the AOS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary file S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). This is the highest percentage of any of the 11 species, suggesting little innovation in the secretome of this nonpathogenic decomposer. Similar to <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>, 35.7% of the <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> proteins and 31.4% of the <italic>S</italic>. <italic>parasitica</italic> proteins were found in AOS gene families. The patterns of gains and functionality of proteins between the two facultatively parasitic species, <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>parasitica</italic> were comparable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">fig. 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>CAZy Enzymes</title><p>The breakdown of carbohydrates in the extracellular environment is a key activity among osmotrophic feeders such as oomycetes (<xref rid="evu276-B74" ref-type="bibr">Richards and Talbot 2013</xref>). The CAZy database is a comprehensive archive of all known carbohydrate functioning enzymes including enzymes known to function in the breakdown of many cell wall structures such as pectin, hemicellulose, and cellulose found in plant cell walls and chitin and cellulose found in fungal and animal biological structures (<xref rid="evu276-B62" ref-type="bibr">O'Connell et al. 2012</xref>). The oomycete secretomes had numerous and diverse CAZy database profiles (<xref rid="evu276-B16" ref-type="bibr">Cantarel et al. 2009</xref>), which covered all five CAZy classes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T3">table 3</xref>). CAZy enzymes are present in 30 AOS orthologue families covering all CAZy classes except glycosyltransferases with 33 unique CAZy families, 16 of which are glycoside hydrolases (GH; <xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T3">table 3</xref>). <italic>Albugo candida</italic> had the fewest CAZy enzymes (23), all present in AOS gene families. Two CAZy families GH18 and PL1 were shown to be derived from HGT events in our analysis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary figs. S3</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">S4</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p></sec><sec><title>Horizontal Gene Transfer</title><p>Phylogenetic analysis of the secretome gene families indicates multiple origins for both the AOS and putative secreted protein families acquired during the diversification of the oomycetes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F1">fig. 1</xref>). Using a phylogenomic approach, we identified seven putative HGT events (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S3</ext-link>&#x02013;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">S9</ext-link>, Supplementary Material online), six of which have not been previously reported. Three HGTs are from fungal lineages and four from bacterial lineages. Four of these transfers have been identified on the basis of robust phylogenetic relationships and three proposed based on restricted and discontinuous taxon distributions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). All of the putative HGT-derived gene families present in the AOS (three) are annotated as involved in pathogenicity and/or carbohydrate metabolism. <xref rid="evu276-B73" ref-type="bibr">Richards et al. (2011)</xref> previously suggested that pectate lyase (OG5_134795) was a putative transfer from fungi to the oomycetes. Our expanded genome sampling supports this conclusion (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S4</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online), indicating that pectate lyase was acquired deep within the radiation of the oomycetes at a similar position reported for a sugar transporter (<xref rid="evu276-B73" ref-type="bibr">Richards et al. 2011</xref>). The other two HGTs in the AOS were endoglucanase (OG5_137267) of bacterial origin, and carbohydrate-binding protein (OG5_136547), transferred from fungi (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary figs. S5</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">S6</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). The remaining four novel HGT events (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary figs. S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">S7</ext-link>&#x02013;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">S9</ext-link>) were specific to Saprolegnialeans, with three bacterial and one fungal derived transfer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F1">fig. 1</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Ancestral Oomycete Secretome</title><p>Secreted proteins play a crucial biological role in the success of saprobes and parasites, as both types of organisms require nutrients and macromolecules from the extracellular environment. By identifying the secretomes of <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>, we are able to make direct comparisons to the secretomes of Peronosporalean oomycetes, and <italic>Hy</italic><italic>p</italic>. <italic>catenoides</italic> to understand secretome evolution and determine the AOS. The variability of lifestyle, across two major lineages of oomycetes (Saprolegnialeans and the Peronosporaleans) and the putative sister group of the oomycetes (<italic>Hy</italic><italic>p</italic>. <italic>catenoides</italic>) (<xref rid="evu276-B19" ref-type="bibr">Cavalier-Smith and Chao 2006</xref>), provides the most comprehensive examination of these crucial proteins to date. Functionally, the gene families of the AOS play putative roles primarily in carbohydrate and amino acid metabolism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">fig. 2</xref>). This is consistent with the importance of the secretome of these microbes in acquiring extracellular nutrients (<xref rid="evu276-B74" ref-type="bibr">Richards and Talbot 2013</xref>). The carbohydrate metabolic functions are carried out by the numerous CAZy classified proteins, some of which are present in the AOS (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T3">table 3</xref>). Strikingly, a number of &#x0201c;effector&#x0201d; gene families that were previously believed to be derived features of the Peronosporaleans are also present in the AOS. These include CWDEs, protease inhibitors, Epi-like genes, oxidoreductases, and elicitin-like genes. Three of these gene families contain novel virulence genes identified by <xref rid="evu276-B71" ref-type="bibr">Raffaele et al. (2010)</xref>, specifically a serine protease, pectate lyase, and carbonic anhydrase, which are located in the &#x0201c;plastic-secretome&#x0201d; of <italic>Ph. infestans</italic>.</p><p>The presence of effectors in the AOS supports the hypothesis presented by <xref rid="evu276-B3" ref-type="bibr">Beakes et al. (2012)</xref>, that pathogenesis is the ancestral state and that the saprobic nature of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> is a derived state. As mentioned earlier, the possibility exists that <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> is an unrecognized facultative pathogen; however, its reduced secretome could be interpreted as a sign it has lost or reduced many of the genes that encode functions to engage with host as a parasite. We were also able to identify mRNA products for 69% of the predicted secretome in <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> maintained in supplemented culture medium, versus expression of 42% of <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> secretome proteins in the same culture conditions. This may be the direct result of the lifestyle of each organism and the greater complexity of the <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> secretome. Functional analyses of these effector genes in <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> is necessary to identify the biological activity and localization of these proteins, which would shed more light onto the evolution of these virulent gene families. Additional sequencing of earlier diverging oomycete lineages will also help clarify the evolutionary innovation in infection mechanisms among this diverse and important lineage.</p></sec><sec><title>Elicitin-Like Proteins in the Saprolegnialeans</title><p>After a thorough investigation of the <italic>Phytophthora</italic> EST database (<xref rid="evu276-B72" ref-type="bibr">Randall et al. 2005</xref>) and the genomes of <italic>Ph. ramorum</italic> and <italic>Ph. sojae</italic>, <xref rid="evu276-B43" ref-type="bibr">Jiang, Tyler, Whisson, (2006)</xref> determined that group-B and group-C elicitin and elicitin-like genes were not present outside of <italic>Phytophthora</italic> and <italic>Pythium</italic> species. However, in a recent study of the <italic>S</italic>. <italic>parasitica</italic> genome, 29 elicitin-like proteins were identified (<xref rid="evu276-B41" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al. 2013</xref>). We have further identified 26 novel group-B elicitin-like genes in the <italic>A</italic><italic>c</italic>. <italic>hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> across four OrthoMCL gene families. Not all 26 have maintained the necessary cysteine residues for proper folding of the domain; 11 genes have the structure and sequence homology to be putative elicitin-like proteins (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary figs. S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Elicitin-like sequences are likely to play a role in lipid binding (<xref rid="evu276-B43" ref-type="bibr">Jiang, Tyler, Whisson, et al. 2006</xref>) and could explain their conservation in the Saprolegniaceae. Although all elicitin-like sequences have signal peptides, some elicitins have been localized to the extracellular surface where they function in sterol binding (<xref rid="evu276-B53" ref-type="bibr">Madoui et al. 2009</xref>). This extracellular membrane bound function is unlikely in the saprolegnialean elicitin-like genes as they lack identifiable transmembrane motifs that would be necessary for anchoring into the extracellular membrane, unless the protein binds to a second membrane bound protein.</p></sec><sec><title>CAZy Secretome Evolution</title><p>It is clear that the AOS encompassed a large diversity of enzymes that functioned in degrading carbohydrates in the external environment a key requirement for osmotrophic function. CBM63, GH14, glycosyl transferase (GT) 24, and GT60 are exclusive to saprolegnialean taxa, whereas GH7, GH30 and the horizontally transferred GH10 (<xref rid="evu276-B73" ref-type="bibr">Richards et al. 2011</xref>) are specific to the Peronosporaleans. The AOS CAZy enzymes identified included proteins that are predicted to function in breaking down cellulose, hemicellulose, pectin, and chitin (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T3">table 3</xref>). Two GH families, GH18 and GH19, contain chitinases and are expanded with multiple copies in saprolegnialean taxa when compared with the Peronosporaleans. The process of chitin degradation is the primary reason that saprolegnialean taxa had more CAZy enzymes then members of the Peronosporaleans. Small amounts of chitin (&#x0003c;1% cell wall carbohydrates) have been reported in saprolegnian taxa (<xref rid="evu276-B35" ref-type="bibr">Guerriero et al. 2010</xref>). Additionally, many of the organisms fed upon by saprolegnian species contain chitin as an important, and sugar rich, biological structure.</p><p>The low number of CAZy enzymes in <italic>Al</italic>. <italic>candida</italic> is most likely related to its obligate biotrophic lifestyle. Reduction in the diversity of these enzyme families may be consistent with specialization and dependence on specific host-derived nutrient sources (<xref rid="evu276-B13" ref-type="bibr">Brunner et al. 2013</xref>). In comparison, the generalist <italic>Phytophthora</italic> spp. have been shown to encode an expanded CAZy repertoire (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T3">table 3</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B66" ref-type="bibr">Ospina-Giraldo et al. 2010</xref>). As one example, <italic>Ph. infestans</italic> and <italic>Pythium ultimum</italic> have expanded polysaccharide lyase (PL) gene families compared with the saprolegnialean species. The secretome of the obligate biotroph, <italic>Al</italic>. <italic>candida</italic>, lacks all PL genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T3">table 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Coupled Changes in Lifestyle and Secretomes</title><p>As evolutionary lineages undergo transitions between free-living and parasitic lifestyles the organisms face different challenges for nutrient acquisition and survival. Gene family expansion, via duplication, and contraction (gene loss) are two mechanisms by which an organism can adapt to these lifestyle changes and evolutionary pressures. Attempts have been made to track gene family evolution, broadly in the alveolates and stramenopiles (<xref rid="evu276-B57" ref-type="bibr">Martens et al. 2008</xref>), and more specifically in the oomycetes using stramenopile outgroups (<xref rid="evu276-B76" ref-type="bibr">Seidl et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B1" ref-type="bibr">Adhikari et al. 2013</xref>). These analyses have demonstrated that lifestyle has an enormous impact on the protein family complement of an organism. However, analysis of oomycete taxa has been limited by both distant outgroups (diatoms) and nearly exclusive focus on the Peronosporalean taxa. The different lifestyles among the Saprolegnialean and Peronosporalean species are reflected in their respective secretome compositions at a finer scale than has been possible previously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F1">figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">2</xref>). The Saprolegnialean secretomes are dominated by proteins in small gene families that are related to carbohydrate metabolism and other metabolic functions indicative of a mostly saprobic lifestyle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">fig. 2</xref>). In contrast, the Peronosporalean secretomes, although containing a diversity of proteins with putative metabolic functions, are characterized by an emergence of large pathogenic-functioning gene families (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">fig. 2</xref>). These large pathogenic gene families include CRN, NPP (likely acquired by HGT [<xref rid="evu276-B73" ref-type="bibr">Richards et al. 2011</xref>]), and RxLR effectors, all distinctive of hemibiotrophic and necrotrophic plant pathogens. Interestingly, these pathogenic genes do not appear to be derived from the AOS, but rather from secretome genes acquired later in the oomycete radiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">fig. 2</xref>). This functional shift from tightly regulated metabolic genes to large, highly divergent, pathogenic-trait associated gene families is characteristic of the change in evolutionary pressures associated with adopting a&#x02014;virulent&#x02014;pathogenic lifestyle (<xref rid="evu276-B60" ref-type="bibr">Morris et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B70" ref-type="bibr">Raffaele and Kamoun 2012</xref>). Even more extreme secretome specialization is seen in the obligate biotroph <italic>Al</italic>. <italic>candida</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F2">fig. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="evu276-T2">table 2</xref>). The <italic>Al</italic>. <italic>candida</italic> secretome features the highest number of outright gene family losses from the secretome, but also by far the highest number of redirection of cytosolic proteins to the secretome proteome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F1">fig. 1</xref>).</p><p>Examinations of the secretome of Peronosporaleans have concentrated on expansions in particular gene families (<xref rid="evu276-B56" ref-type="bibr">Martens and Van de Peer 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B1" ref-type="bibr">Adhikari et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B41" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al. 2013</xref>). Perhaps surprisingly, the secretomes of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> and <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> show very few expansions of AOS gene families outside of CAZy enzymes described below (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary file S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Therefore, it appears that the specializations associated with plant pathogenicity in the Peronosporaleans have been an enormous evolutionary driver of secretome specialization and expansion.</p><p>Additionally, these data suggest other mechanisms for lifestyle and host adaptation of the secretome, modification of existing proteins via the addition of signal peptides. All ten of the oomycetes in this study showed that some gene families were &#x0201c;gained&#x0201d; from the proteome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu276-F1">fig. 1</xref>). Although these &#x0201c;gains&#x0201d; are at the gene family level, it is intuitive to think some proteins would have had to acquire a signal peptide. <xref rid="evu276-B88" ref-type="bibr">Tonkin et al. (2008)</xref> demonstrated that signal peptides can originate via exon shuffling and random amino acid shuffling in <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> and it is possible that similar evolutionary mechanisms are occurring in the oomycetes.</p><p>However, it should be noted that secretome gene prediction is predicated on the presence of the proper N-terminus in the protein sequence and therefore is open to errors if poor protein models are utilized. Incomplete protein models will, potentially, lack the complete N-terminal sequence and would therefore be lost by this approach. An investigation of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> and <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> proteins revealed only 4.8% and 2.8% of these predicted proteins lacked a starting methionine, respectively. This figure is well within the boundaries of protein prediction from other oomycete genomes. After removing the approximately 20% of these proteins that have transmembrane domains from this subset and assuming no bias toward secretome proteins, the false negative rate is around 0.1% for <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic> and <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic>. Additionally, the absence of a start methionine does not exclude a protein from the secretome in this study, as all of the predicted secretomes include a low number of proteins lacking a start methionine.</p></sec><sec><title>HGT&#x02019;s Role in the Oomycete Secretome</title><p>Using a systematic phylogenetic analysis of the secretomes of <italic>Ac. hypogyna</italic> and <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>, we were able to assess the impact HGT has had on the origin and evolution of the oomycete secretome. We have identified six novel HGTs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) from bacterial or fungal lineages into oomycetes. Furthermore, we have identified three potential HGT events that produce complex evolutionary tree topologies (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary figs. S10&#x02013;S12</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). These genes could not be confidently assigned an origin. The number of HGTs described in this study significantly expands the number of secretome protein families that have HGT origins. Although the <xref rid="evu276-B73" ref-type="bibr">Richards et al. (2011)</xref> analyses included the entire predicted proteomes of four Peronosporalean oomycetes, it focused exclusively on HGT between fungi and oomycetes. Nonetheless, 17 of the 34 HGTs they identified included gene families that putatively encode secretome proteins. Four of the HGTs described here are specific to the Saprolegniaceae and imply that HGT between fungal and bacterial lineages played a role in genome evolution of the Saprolegniaceae. Fungal genes have played a key role in the secretome of plant pathogenic oomycetes, but with the exception of <xref rid="evu276-B4" ref-type="bibr">Belbahri et al. (2008)</xref>, HGT events involving prokaryotes remain systematically underexplored in the Peronosporaleans. Transferred prokaryotic genes may be responsible for novel functions, as demonstrated in other eukaryotic lineages (<xref rid="evu276-B47" ref-type="bibr">Keeling and Palmer 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B54" ref-type="bibr">Marcet-Houben and Gabaldon 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B80" ref-type="bibr">Slot and Rokas 2011</xref>) and here for saprolegnialean taxa.</p><p><xref rid="evu276-B41" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et. al. (2013)</xref> used a Hidden Markov Model approach to identify five putative horizontally transferred gene families in the <italic>S</italic>. <italic>parasitica</italic> genome. Using our phylogenetic pipeline, we reevaluated the five genes identified as HGTs in <italic>S</italic>. <italic>parasitica</italic> and found only one was identified in our analysis as a likely HGT with strong phylogenetic support (SPRG_08128; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S13</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Multiprotein alignments for a Laminin-like protein (SPRG_08424) and the Disintigren family (SPRG_14051) have low pairwise identity (6.7% and 12.1%, respectively) and low levels of identical sites (both 0.1%) to their hits in our phylogenetic database. These alignments result in phylogenetic tress with low bootstrap support values and their status as putative HGTs is not supported by our analysis. The CHAP protein family (SPRG_15528) has higher pairwise identity (averaging &#x0223c;34%) but the predicted protein in <italic>S</italic>. <italic>parasitica</italic> is 204 amino acids, whereas the most closely related sequences (and majority in the alignment) are three times that length. Although our pipeline does not identify SPRG_15528 as an HGT, we cannot exclude the possibility of HGT in the ancestry of this oomycete gene. The origin of the HylE gene (SPRG_04818) could not be determined, because the only identifiable homologs were from a handful of <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 3) and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 6) strains. Although the taxomic distribution of this gene family cannot exclude HGT, homology to proteins from only nine closely related prokaryotic strains is curious. There are no introns in this gene and it is encoded on a large contig with 276 other genes, suggesting the possibility of a recent transfer, but pairwise identity at the protein level with prokaryotic homologs is less than 22%. This is not be identified in our analysis as an HGT event.</p><p>Overall, the amount of HGT implicated in the oomycete secretome suggests that gene acquisition has played an important role in the evolution of the wider oomycete group. From their proposed ancestral forms as obligate pathogens of marine algae, oomycetes have diversified to be able to infect every major group of eukaryotes (<xref rid="evu276-B3" ref-type="bibr">Beakes et al. 2012</xref>). Combined with <xref rid="evu276-B73" ref-type="bibr">Richards et al. (2011)</xref>, <xref rid="evu276-B4" ref-type="bibr">Belbahri et al. (2008)</xref>, and <xref rid="evu276-B41" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al. (2013)</xref> data reported here bring the number of secreted gene families that have xenic origins in oomycetes to 25 (26 if the CHAP gene family is included). These three studies demonstrate the important role that HGT has played in the evolution of pathogenic oomycetes. HGT has expanded the capacity for these microbes to process and take up sugar in the external environment, which is potentially consistent from their ancestral shift from photo/phagotrophs to osmotrophs. However, HGT is only part of the complex evolutionary patterns of the secretome.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The evolution of the oomcyete secretome has been shaped by gene expansion by duplication, gene loss, and acquisition by HGT, much of which has occurred in response to changes in lifestyle and environment across the oomycetes. Based upon these analyses, the AOS was probably capable of supporting a free-living saprotroph, as there is little variance between gene families present in the AOS and the secretome of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>clavata</italic>. In contrast, the secretome of the obligate biotroph <italic>Al</italic>. <italic>candida</italic> contains numerous gene families not present in any of the other species investigated, supporting the notion that host/pathogen coevolution has had a profound effect on <italic>Al</italic>. <italic>candida&#x02019;s</italic> genome content and putative secreted proteome. Furthermore, flexibility in carbohydrate metabolism, shown by the fact that over one-third of the AOS are CAZys, is another feature that has factored in the diversity of oomycetes and their host range. Secreted CAZy diversity has been linked to host/parasite coevolution (<xref rid="evu276-B13" ref-type="bibr">Brunner et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evu276-B98" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al. 2013</xref>), and the distinction between the Saprolegnialean and Peronosporalean profiles underscores their importance for oomycetes. The description of the secretome from plant infecting members of the Saprolegnialeans and animal infecting members of the Peronosporaleans will make it possible to separate evolutionary trends with each lineage from host-induced effects.</p></sec><sec><title>Additional Data Files</title><p>The following additional data files are available with the online version of this paper. Additional data file 1 is a list of the genomes used in the phylogenetic analysis pipeline.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">Supplementary files S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">S2</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu276/-/DC1">figures S1&#x02013;S13</ext-link> are available at <italic>Genome Biology and Evolution</italic> online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/">http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/</ext-link>).</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Data</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_7_1_120__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_evu276_evu276_Figures_GBE.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"
xlink:href="supp_evu276_Supplementary_File_2.txt"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_evu276_Supplementary_file_1.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="supp_evu276_New_Microsoft_Office_Word_Document.docx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors express their thanks to two anonymous reviewers who provided helpful feedback in improving the manuscript. Funding for genome sequencing and analysis was provided by the University of Rhode Island College of the Environment and Life Sciences, as start-up money for C.E.L. This work was made possible, in part, by a USDA National Needs Fellowship to I.M. (grant no. 2008-38420-18737) and sequencing funded by the RI INBRE grant from NIH (no. 8P20GM103430-12). This research was also supported in part by the bioinformatics infrastructure enabled by National Science Foundation EPSCoR grant no. EPS-1004057, and the Division of Biology and Medicine, Brown University. This work was supported by Brown University through the use of the facilities of its Center for Computation and Visualization.</p></ack><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="evu276-B1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics reveals insight into virulence strategies of plant pathogenic oomycetes</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e75072</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24124466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adl</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The revised classification of eukaryotes</article-title><source>J Eukaryot Microbiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23020233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beakes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Glockling</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolutionary phylogeny of the oomycete &#x0201c;fungi&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Protoplasma</source><year>2012</year><volume>249</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21424613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belbahri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Calmin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of the cutinase gene family: evidence for lateral gene transfer of a candidate Phytophthora virulence factor</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2008</year><volume>408</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18024004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Accurate whole human genome sequencing using reversible terminator chemistry</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>456</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18987734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>PRJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oomycete RXLR effectors: delivery, functional redundancy and durable disease resistance</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18511334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>PRJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Towards understanding the virulence functions of RXLR effectors of the oomycete plant pathogen <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic></article-title><source>J Exp Bot.</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>1140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19204033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blein</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutos-Thevenot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponchet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From elicitins to lipid-transfer proteins: a new insight in cell signalling involved in plant defence mechanisms</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>2002</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12119165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boissy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The 2.1 A structure of an elicitin-ergosterol complex: a recent addition to the Sterol Carrier Protein family</article-title><source>Protein Sci.</source><year>1999</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1191</fpage><lpage>1199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10386869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oomycete RXLR effectors: structural basis of avirulence and virulence in <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic> AVR3a</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2007</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>S145</fpage><lpage>S145</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braaksma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Martens-Uzunova</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Punt</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaap</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An inventory of the Aspergillus niger secretome by combining in silico predictions with shotgun proteomics data</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>584</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20959013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Antoniw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The predicted secretome of the plant pathogenic fungus <italic>Fusarium graminearum</italic>: a refined comparative analysis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e33731</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22493673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Torriani</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Croll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stukenbrock</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coevolution and life cycle specialization of plant cell wall degrading enzymes in a hemibiotrophic pathogen</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1337</fpage><lpage>1347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23515261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Beakes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of zoospore and cyst surface-structure in saprophytic and fish pathogenic <italic>Saprolegnia</italic> species (oomycete fungal protists)</article-title><source>Protoplasma</source><year>1994</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>163</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantarel</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MAKER: an easy-to-use annotation pipeline designed for emerging model organism genomes</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18025269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantarel</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The carbohydrate-active enzymes database (CAZy): an expert resource for glycogenomics</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>D233</fpage><lpage>D238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18838391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capella-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Silla-Martinez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>trimAl: a tool for automated alignment trimming in large-scale phylogenetic analyses</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1972</fpage><lpage>1973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Segregation of random amplified DNA markers in F1 progeny of conifers</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet.</source><year>1991</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24202358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavalier-Smith</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny and megasystematics of phagotrophic heterokonts (kingdom Chromista)</article-title><source>J Mol Evol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>388</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16557340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cerenius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000f6;derh&#x000e4;ll</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemotaxis in <italic>Aphanomyces astaci</italic>, an arthropod-parasitic fungus</article-title><source>J Invertebr Pathol.</source><year>1984</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>281</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoeckert</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OrthoMCL-DB: querying a comprehensive multi-species collection of ortholog groups</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>D363</fpage><lpage>D368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermunt</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing performance of orthology detection strategies applied to eukaryotic genomes</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e383</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17440619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the <italic>Pythium ultimum</italic> transcriptome using Sanger and Pyrosequencing approaches</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>542</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19014603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fungal secretome database: integrated platform for annotation of fungal secretomes</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>105</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20146824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Blast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics research</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3674</fpage><lpage>3676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16081474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darriba</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Taboada</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Doallo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ProtTest 3: fast selection of best-fit models of protein evolution</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1164</fpage><lpage>1165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21335321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Straminipilous Fungi: systematics of the Peronosporomycetes including accounts of the marine straminipilous protists, the plasmodiophorids and similar organisms</article-title><source>Dordrecht</source><year>2001</year><fpage> Kluwer Adademic Publishers</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbings</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hddderson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lastra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>18S rDNA for species of <italic>Leptolegnia</italic> and other Peronosporomycetes: justification for the subclass taxa Saprolegniomycetidae and Peronosporomycetidae and division of the Saprolegniaceae sensu lato into the Leptolegniaceae and Saprolegniaceae</article-title><source>Mycol Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>1119</fpage><lpage>1125</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Halldorsson</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernot</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A hybrid micro-macroevolutionary approach to gene tree reconstruction</article-title><source>J Comput Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16597243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MUSCLE: a multiple sequence alignment method with reduced time and space complexity</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2004a</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>113</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15318951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004b</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1792</fpage><lpage>1797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Locating proteins in the cell using TargetP, SignalP and related tools</article-title><source>Nat Protoc.</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>953</fpage><lpage>971</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17446895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting subcellular localization of proteins based on their N-terminal amino acid sequence</article-title><source>J Mol Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10891285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fefeu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouaziz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huet</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pernollet</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Guittet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three-dimensional solution structure of beta cryptogein, a beta elicitin secreted by a phytopathogenic fungus <italic>Phytophthora cryptogea</italic></article-title><source>Protein Sci.</source><year>1997</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2279</fpage><lpage>2284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9385630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B99"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gouy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SeaView version 4: A multiplatform graphical user interface for sequence alignment and phylogenetic tree building</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19854763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guerriero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chitin synthases from <italic>Saprolegnia</italic> are involved in tip growth and represent a potential target for anti-oomycete drugs</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog.</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e1001070</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20865175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lethiec</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Duroux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PHYML Online&#x02014;a web server for fast maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic inference</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>W557</fpage><lpage>559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome sequence and analysis of the Irish potato famine pathogen <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>461</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19741609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haldar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamoun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharje</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Ooij</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Common infection strategies of pathogenic eukaryotes</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>922</fpage><lpage>931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17088934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>WoLF PSORT: protein localization predictor</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>W585</fpage><lpage>587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17517783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Saprolegniosis in salmonids and their eggs in Japan</article-title><source>J Wildl Dis.</source><year>2001</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11272500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distinctive expansion of potential virulence genes in the genome of the oomycete fish pathogen <italic>Saprolegnia parasitica</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Genet.</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e1003272</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23785293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Govers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RXLR effector reservoir in two <italic>Phytophthora</italic> species is dominated by a single rapidly evolving superfamily with more than 700 members</article-title><source>Proc Nat Acad Sci U S A.</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>4874</fpage><lpage>4879</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Govers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of Phytophthora genes encoding secreted proteins reveals conserved synteny and lineage-specific gene duplications and deletions</article-title><source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact.</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1311</fpage><lpage>1321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17153915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>RHY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Whisson</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardham</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Govers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ancient origin of elicitin gene clusters in <italic>Phytophthora</italic> Genomes</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16237208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B45"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamoun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Deising</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The secretome of plant-associated fungi and oomycetes</article-title><source>Plant relationships</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>180</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Saprolegnia brachydanis</italic>, A new oomycete isolated from zebra fish</article-title><source>Mycopathologia</source><year>2009</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18853279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Horizontal gene transfer in eukaryotic evolution</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet.</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18591983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene finding in novel genomes</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15144565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Latijnhouwers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>PJGM</given-names></name><name><surname>Govers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oomycetes and fungi: similar weaponry to attack plants</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14557029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levesque</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome sequence of the necrotrophic plant pathogen <italic>Pythium ultimum</italic> reveals original pathogenicity mechanisms and effector repertoire</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>R73</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20626842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Links</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>De novo</italic> sequence assembly of <italic>Albugo candida</italic> reveals a small genome relative to other biotrophic oomycetes</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>503</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21995639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lomsadze</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ter-Hovhannisyan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernoff</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name><name><surname>Borodovsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene identification in novel eukaryotic genomes by self-training algorithm</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>6494</fpage><lpage>6506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16314312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madoui</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertrand-Michel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaulin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sterol metabolism in the oomycete <italic>Aphanomyces euteiches</italic>, a legume root pathogen</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19496952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcet-Houben</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acquisition of prokaryotic genes by fungal genomes</article-title><source>Trends Genet.</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19969385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margulies</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome sequencing in microfabricated high-density picolitre reactors</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>437</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16056220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Peer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hidden duplication past of the plant pathogen <italic>Phytophthora</italic> and its consequences for infection</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>353</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20525264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandepoele</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Peer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole-genome analysis reveals molecular innovations and evolutionary transitions in chromalveolate species</article-title><source>Proc Nat Acad Sci U S A.</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>3427</fpage><lpage>3432</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendoza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajello</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Life cycle of the human and animal oomycete pathogen <italic>Pythium insidiosum</italic></article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol.</source><year>1993</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2967</fpage><lpage>2973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8263182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Misner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sequence comparative analysis using networks: software for evaluating de novo transcript assembly from next-generation sequencing</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1975</fpage><lpage>1986</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23666209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiple horizontal gene transfer events and domain fusions have created novel regulatory and metabolic networks in the oomycete genome</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e6133</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19582169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noga</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dykstra</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oomycete fungi associated with ulcerative mycosis in menhaden, <italic>Brevoortia tyrannus</italic> (Latrobe)</article-title><source>J Fish Dis.</source><year>1986</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B100"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nowicki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Foolad</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowakowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozik</surname><given-names>EU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potato and tomato late blight caused by Phytophthora infestans: an overview of pathology and resistance breeding</article-title><source>Plant Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Connell</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lifestyle transitions in plant pathogenic Colletotrichum fungi deciphered by genome and transcriptome analyses</article-title><source>Nat Genet.</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>1060</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22885923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamoun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oomycetes RXLR effectors function as both activator and suppressor of plant immunity</article-title><source>Plant Pathol J.</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>215</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oidtmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaefers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerenius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Soderhall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of genomic DNA of the crayfish plague fungus <italic>Aphanomyces astaci</italic> (Oomycete) in clinical samples by PCR</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15145505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oidtmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbauer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental infection and detection of <italic>Aphanomyces invadans</italic> in European catfish, rainbow trout and European eel</article-title><source>Dis Aquat Org.</source><year>2008</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19244971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ospina-Giraldo</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mingora</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The CAZyome of <italic>Phytophthora</italic> spp.: a comprehensive analysis of the gene complement coding for carbohydrate-active enzymes in species of the genus <italic>Phytophthora</italic></article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>525</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20920201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panabieres</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponchet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Allasia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of border species among Pythiaceae: several <italic>Pythium</italic> isolates produce elicitins, typical proteins from <italic>Phytophthora</italic> spp</article-title><source>Mycol Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>1459</fpage><lpage>1468</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehal</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkin</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FastTree 2&#x02014;approximately maximum-likelihood trees for large alignments</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e9490</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20224823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Punta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Pfam protein families database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>D290</fpage><lpage>D301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22127870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raffaele</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamoun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome evolution in filamentous plant pathogens: why bigger can be better</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22565130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raffaele</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Win</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamoun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analyses of genome architecture and gene expression reveal novel candidate virulence factors in the secretome of <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic></article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>637</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21080964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Large-scale gene discovery in the oomycete <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic> reveals likely components of phytopathogenicity shared with true fungi</article-title><source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact.</source><year>2005</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15782637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Horizontal gene transfer facilitated the evolution of plant parasitic mechanisms in the oomycetes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>15258</fpage><lpage>15263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21878562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Horizontal gene transfer in osmotrophs: playing with public goods</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24018383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seidl</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Ackerveken</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Govers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Snel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstruction of oomycete genome evolution identifies differences in evolutionary trajectories leading to present-day large gene families</article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22230142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unusual oomycete infecting rotifer eggs</article-title><source>Mycologia</source><year>1973</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>944</fpage><lpage>948</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimodaira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An approximately unbiased test of phylogenetic tree selection</article-title><source>Syst Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12079646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimodaira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CONSEL: for assessing the confidence of phylogenetic tree selection</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1246</fpage><lpage>1247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slot</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Horizontal transfer of a large and highly toxic secondary metabolic gene cluster between fungi</article-title><source>Curr Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21194949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soanes</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genome analysis of filamentous fungi reveals gene family expansions associated with fungal pathogenesis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2008</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e2300</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18523684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soanes</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moving targets: rapid evolution of oomycete effectors</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18819803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A hidden Markov model for predicting transmembrane helices in protein sequences</article-title><source>Proc Int Conf Intell Syst Mol Biol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9783223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sosa</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Aphanomyces invadans</italic> and ulcerative mycosis in estuarine and freshwater fish in Florida</article-title><source>J Aquat Anim Health.</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18236628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RAxML-VI-HPC: maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic analyses with thousands of taxa and mixed models</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2688</fpage><lpage>2690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16928733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stassen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Ackerveken</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How do oomycete effectors interfere with plant life?</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21641854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stolzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inferring duplications, losses, transfers and incomplete lineage sorting with nonbinary species trees</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>i409</fpage><lpage>i415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22962460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tonkin</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evolution of malaria parasite plastid targeting sequences</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>4781</fpage><lpage>4785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18353992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B89"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torto</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EST mining and functional expression assays identify extracellular effector proteins from the plant pathogen <italic>Phytophthora</italic></article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1675</fpage><lpage>1685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12840044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B90"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapphoff</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Beutner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Niehaus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Colditz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of distinct defense-associated protein patterns in <italic>Aphanomyces euteiches</italic> (Oomycota)-elicited and-inoculated <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> cell-suspension cultures: a proteome and phosphoproteome approach</article-title><source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact.</source><year>2009</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19271957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B91"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics and genomics of the oomycete host interface</article-title><source>Trends Genet.</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11672843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B92"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unestam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the crayfish plague fungus <italic>aphanomyces astaci</italic> some factors affecting growth <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Physiol Plant.</source><year>1965</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>505</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B93"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van der Auwera</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The phylogeny of the Hyphochytriomycota as deduced from ribosomal RNA sequences of <italic>Hyphochytrium catenoides</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7659021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B94"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van West</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Saprolegnia parasitica</italic>, an oomycete pathogen with a fishy appetite: new challenges for an old problem</article-title><source>Mycologist</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>104</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B95"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vernot</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconciliation with non-binary species trees</article-title><source>J Comput Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>981</fpage><lpage>1006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18808330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B96"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Win</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanneganti</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Torto-Alalibo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamoun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational and comparative analyses of 150 full-length cDNA sequences from the oomycete plant pathogen <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic></article-title><source>Fungal Genet Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16380277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B97"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>dbCAN: a web resource for automated carbohydrate-active enzyme annotation</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>W445</fpage><lpage>W451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22645317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu276-B98"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The evolution and pathogenic mechanisms of the rice sheath blight pathogen</article-title><source>Nat Commun.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1424</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23361014</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>