<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4915528</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erw112</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Calcium impacts carbon and nitrogen balance in the filamentous cyanobacterium <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. PCC 7120</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>Julia</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>Fiona</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Battchikova</surname><given-names>Natalia</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aro</surname><given-names>Eva-Mari</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Gollan</surname><given-names>Peter J.</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><institution>Department of Biochemistry, Molecular Plant Biology, University of Turku</institution>, <addr-line>FI-20014 Turku</addr-line>, <country>Finland</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Correspondence: <email>peter.gollan@utu.fi</email></corresp><fn id="fn-100"><p>Editor: Markus Teige, University of Vienna</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>67</volume><issue>13</issue><issue-title>Special Issue: Plant Organellar Signalling</issue-title><fpage>3997</fpage><lpage>4008</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="precis"><title>Highlight</title><p>Calcium affects the primary cellular metabolism of <italic>Anabaena</italic> under conditions replete in both combined-nitrogen and inorganic carbon. Opposite transcriptome responses to calcium treatments occur for nitrogen- and carbon-related processes.</p></abstract><abstract><p>Calcium is integral to the perception, communication and adjustment of cellular responses to environmental changes. However, the role of Ca<sup>2+</sup> in fine-tuning cellular responses of wild-type cyanobacteria under favourable growth conditions has not been examined. In this study, extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> has been altered, and changes in the whole transcriptome of <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. PCC 7120 have been evaluated under conditions replete of carbon and combined nitrogen. Ca<sup>2+</sup> induced differential expression of many genes driving primary cellular metabolism, with transcriptional regulation of carbon- and nitrogen-related processes responding with opposing trends. However, physiological effects of these transcriptional responses on biomass accumulation, biomass composition, and photosynthetic activity over the 24h period following Ca<sup>2+</sup> adjustment were found to be minor. It is well known that intracellular carbon:nitrogen balance is integral to optimal cell growth and that Ca<sup>2+</sup> plays an important role in the response of heterocystous cyanobacteria to combined-nitrogen deprivation. This work adds to the current knowledge by demonstrating a signalling role of Ca<sup>2+</sup> for making sensitive transcriptional adjustments required for optimal growth under non-limiting conditions.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key words:</title><kwd>Anabaena</kwd><kwd>bicarbonate</kwd><kwd>calcium</kwd><kwd>cmpA</kwd><kwd>cyanobacteria</kwd><kwd>nirA</kwd><kwd>nitrogen</kwd><kwd>transcriptomics.</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cyanobacteria form a diverse clade of highly specialized bacteria able to perform oxygenic photosynthesis and thus are proclaimed to be the evolutionary ancestors of the chloroplasts of photoautotrophic eukaryotes (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Douglas, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Falcon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). They comprise five different groups based on their morphology and metabolic pathways (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Rippka <italic>et al.</italic>, 1979</xref>). For instance, there are unicellular cyanobacteria, such as the model organism <italic>Synechocystis</italic> sp. PCC 6803 (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Kaneko and Tabata, 1997</xref>), and multicellular (filamentous) cyanobacteria, of which <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. PCC 7120 (hereafter designated as <italic>Anabaena</italic>) is one of the common models (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Kaneko <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). <italic>Anabaena</italic> also represents the heterocystous cyanobacteria that can fix atmospheric nitrogen in conditions lacking combined nitrogen (<xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">Wolk, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Flores and Herrero, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Calcium (Ca<sup>2+</sup>) is well known to play an essential role as second messenger and signalling molecule in all living organisms (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Clapham, 1995</xref>). In plants, Ca<sup>2+</sup> pulses of specific magnitude, duration, frequency, and source are called Ca<sup>2+</sup> &#x02018;signatures&#x02019; and are triggered in response to many different environmental stimuli in order to activate response mechanisms (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Knight M. <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Knight H. <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Knight and Knight, 2000</xref>). However, besides the calcium signals, the cytosolic free Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>) is tightly regulated by Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding proteins, Ca<sup>2+</sup> pumps and other transporters to maintain low [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> levels of about 100nM in order to avoid toxic calcium phosphate precipitation within the cell.</p><p content-type="indent">Recently, an important role of Ca<sup>2+</sup> sequestration and signalling has been highlighted in regulating the activities of chloroplasts (<xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Stael <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011, 2012a</xref>, b; <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Rocha and Vothknecht, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Nomura and Shiina, 2014</xref>). Meanwhile, in cyanobacteria, the chloroplast ancestors, information concerning Ca<sup>2+</sup>-regulated processes is still rather scarce. Cyanobacteria have been shown to use Ca<sup>2+</sup> signalling under various environmental stimuli (<xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">Torrecilla <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Barr&#x000e1;n-Berd&#x000f3;n <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), but so far only one cyanobacteria-specific Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding protein (Ccbp in <italic>Anabaena</italic>) has been characterized (<xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Shi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Hu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Dominguez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Ccbp is involved in the signalling cascade resulting in the formation of nitrogen-fixing heterocysts (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Flores and Herrero, 2005</xref>). The concept of Ca<sup>2+</sup> being involved in atmospheric nitrogen fixation was reported as early as the 1930s by <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Burk <italic>et al.</italic> (1934)</xref>, and was supported several times over the following decades (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Allison <italic>et al.</italic>, 1936</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Allen and Arnon, 1955</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Mishra <italic>et al.</italic>, 1985</xref>). It is now known that Ca<sup>2+</sup> controls this process in <italic>Anabaena</italic> through the negative regulation of Ccbp by HetR and the transcription factor NtcA, by which the release of Ca<sup>2+</sup> induces the differentiation of vegetative cells into nitrogen-fixing heterocysts. The process of heterocyst formation in <italic>Anabaena</italic> was shown to be slightly enhanced in nitrogen-depleted conditions under elevated exogenous Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub>) up to 1&#x02013;2mM, while concentrations above that have inhibitory and toxic effects on cell growth and health (<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">Smith <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">Singh and Mishra, 2014</xref>). Despite the apparent impact of Ca<sup>2+</sup> on cell growth and development, changes in the amplitude and kinetics of Ca<sup>2+</sup> signatures evoked upon nitrogen starvation and increased [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> were shown to be minor (<xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">Torrecilla <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004a</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Ca<sup>2+</sup> effects have also been studied with respect to photosynthetic activity in cyanobacteria. Enhanced oxygen evolution resulted from increasing [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> in different cyanobacteria species, which may be linked to the involvement of Ca<sup>2+</sup> in the photosystem II (PSII) oxygen evolving complex (<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">Piccioni and Mauzerall, 1978</xref>). The link between Ca<sup>2+</sup> and photosynthesis has received much more attention in plants (see <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Hochmal <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref> for a recent review), where it is known that the transition from light to darkness triggers a cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> signal that inhibits the enzymes of the Calvin&#x02013;Benson&#x02013;Bassham cycle. This observation of a dark-induced calcium signal has also been demonstrated in <italic>Anabaena</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">Torrecilla <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004b</xref>). This signal is most likely dependent on the redox state of photosynthetic electron transport chain components in plants as well as in cyanobacteria.</p><p content-type="indent">In this work, the impact of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> on the induction of intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> signalling in <italic>Anabaena</italic> has been explored through the analysis of gene expression, cell fitness and development. Here, it was found that [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> affects the C:N balance through short-term and long-term reprogramming of carbon- and nitrogen-specific metabolism, including up- and down-regulation of transporters, photosynthetic genes and transcription regulators. Changes in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> impacted the accumulation of biomass and proteins, but had no significant effect on heterocyst differentiation in growth medium supplied with nitrate as a nitrogen source.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s3"><title>Cultures and growth conditions</title><p>
<italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. PCC 7120 cells were grown either in regular BG11 medium (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Rippka <italic>et al.</italic>, 1979</xref>) (low Ca<sup>2+</sup>; 0.25mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>) or in BG11 medium plus additional CaCl<sub>2</sub> (high Ca<sup>2+</sup>; 1mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>). Both media were supplemented with 10mM TES-KOH (pH 8.0). The cultures were cultivated under continuous low light (25&#x02013;35 &#x003bc;mol photons m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) at 30 &#x000b0;C and in 3% (vol/vol) CO<sub>2</sub>-containing air with mild shaking.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Calcium shift experiment</title><p>
<italic>Anabaena</italic> cells were grown under normal growth conditions in low and high Ca<sup>2+</sup> media. After reaching OD<sub>750</sub>=1.0, the cells were centrifuged and the cell pellets resuspended to OD<sub>750</sub>=0.8 in either low or high Ca<sup>2+</sup>; for the Ca<sup>2+</sup> treatments, pellets from high Ca<sup>2+</sup> were resuspended in low Ca<sup>2+</sup> medium (shifted from high to low) and pellets from low Ca<sup>2+</sup> were resuspended in high Ca<sup>2+</sup> medium (shifted from low to high). For the controls, pellets were resuspended in fresh medium with the same [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] (shifted from low to low or high to high). Afterwards, the cultures were again incubated under normal growth conditions. Over a time range of 24h (0, 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 24h post-shift), samples were taken for the determination of total proteins, carbohydrates, and biomass. Data were collected from three independent Ca<sup>2+</sup> shift experiments (<italic>n</italic>=3).</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Determination of the biomass</title><p>A 20ml culture volume was passed through a pre-washed, pre-dried and pre-weighed glass-fibre filter in a glass vacuum filtration apparatus and then washed with distilled water. Filters were dried at 60 &#x000b0;C for 24h, stored in a desiccator and then weighed.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Determination of the protein content</title><p>A 0.2ml volume of culture was taken in triplicate, centrifuged and washed with distilled water, and the pellets were frozen. The total protein content was determined according to a modified Lowry procedure (<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Markwell <italic>et al.</italic>, 1978</xref>). OD<sub>750</sub> was measured against a bovine serum albumin (BSA) standard curve with a Lambda 25 UV/VIS spectrometer (Perkin Elmer).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Determination of total sugars content</title><p>A 1.0ml volume of culture was taken in triplicate, spun down and washed with distilled water. The total sugar content was analysed by the colorimetric method described by <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">DuBois <italic>et al.</italic> (1956)</xref> after diluting the samples 1:1 with milliQ water.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>RNA isolation and next-generation sequencing</title><p>
<italic>Anabaena</italic> cultures were shifted between low and high Ca<sup>2+</sup> media as described above. Each of the four samples (low Ca<sup>2+</sup> to high Ca<sup>2+</sup>, high Ca<sup>2+</sup> to low Ca<sup>2+</sup>, and their controls) was represented by three independent biological replicates (<italic>n</italic>=3). One hour after the shift, the cultures were centrifuged (6000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic>, 6min, RT) and the pellets immediately resuspended in 0.2ml RNA resuspension buffer (0.3M saccharose+10mM sodium acetate, pH 4.5) and 60 &#x003bc;l 0.25M ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) was added. A 0.3ml volume of lysis buffer (2% sodium dodecyl sulfate+10mM sodium acetate, pH 4.5) was added, followed by 0.5ml of phenol:chloroform:iso-amyl alcohol (P:C:IAA=25:24:1). Then the samples were vortexed thoroughly, incubated for 5min at 95 &#x000b0;C and centrifuged for 15min at 15000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic>, 4 &#x000b0;C. The upper phase was collected, twice re-extracted with an equal volume of P:C:IAA and then extracted with C:IAA (24:1). The aqueous phase was supplemented with 10M lithium chloride to a concentration of 2.5M, and incubated overnight at &#x02013;20 &#x000b0;C. The next day, the samples were centrifuged as before and the pellets washed with 1ml 70% ethanol by gentle mixing. After centrifugation, the RNA pellets were air-dried and resuspended in small volumes of milliQ water at 65 &#x000b0;C for 15min. RNA isolates were treated with DNase. RNA samples were submitted to the Turku Centre for Biotechnology (Turku, Finland) for RNA sequencing using a HiSeq 2000 (Illumina).</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>RNAseq data analysis</title><p>RNAseq reads were aligned using the reference genome and annotations of <italic>Nostoc</italic> sp. PCC 7120, downloaded from Ensembl (EBI). Alignment was using the Tophat algorithm, and ORF calling and read-depth quantification were carried out using the open source analysis software Chipster (CSC, Finland). Significantly differentially expressed genes were identified using a false discovery rate (FDR: Benjamini&#x02013;Hochberg) cutoff of 0.05. Gene descriptions were collected from Cyanobase (genome.microbedb.jp/cyanobase/) and KEGG (<uri xlink:href="www.genome.jp/kegg/">www.genome.jp/kegg/</uri>).</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Photosynthetic activity measurements</title><p>Oxygen evolution rate was measured using a Clark-type oxygen electrode (Hansatech Oxytherm) and quantum yield of PSII (Y(II)) was measured using a Dual-PAM-100 (Walz). For both, samples were dark-adapted for 5min. For the gross oxygen evolution rate in light, the rates of oxygen consumption obtained in darkness were added to oxygen evolution rates obtained in saturating light (intensity: 400 &#x003bc;mol photons m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), and values were normalized to the chlorophyll content (chl a estimated in 90% methanol at OD<sub>665</sub>). For the determination of Y(II), samples were diluted to a chlorophyll concentration of 5 &#x003bc;g chl a ml<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> and the fluorescence parameters <italic>F</italic>
<sub>v</sub> and <italic>F</italic>
<sub>m</sub> determined according to <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Genty <italic>et al.</italic> (1989)</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Light and fluorescence microscopy</title><p>Bright-field and fluorescence images were taken using an AxioVert 200M fluorescence microscope (Zeiss) and a Wetzlar light microscope (Leitz) on &#x000d7;40 magnification. From active <italic>Anabaena</italic> filaments, 1000&#x02013;2000 cells were counted for each treatment and the heterocyst frequency calculated as a percentage of total cells counted.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Determination of nitrogen concentration</title><p>Nitrate concentration of filtered media was determined spectrophotometrically using a Spectroquant Nitrate Test kit (Merck).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Results</title><sec id="s14"><title>Calcium induces both short-term and long-term changes in gene expression</title><p>The response of <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. PCC 7120 to changes in external Ca<sup>2+</sup> conditions was studied by pre-growing cells to OD<sub>750</sub>=1.0 (over approximately 3 days) in either low or high Ca<sup>2+</sup> medium (0.25 and 1mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, respectively), and then replacing the medium with one of either the same Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration (acting as controls), or with an alternative Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration to create an up-shift (henceforth referred to as &#x02018;high Ca<sup>2+</sup>&#x02019;) or a down-shift (&#x02018;low Ca<sup>2+</sup>&#x02019;) in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. The transcriptomic reaction of <italic>Anabaena</italic> cells to the change in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] was analysed 1h post-shift by transcriptome sequencing. Gene expression in high Ca<sup>2+</sup> and low Ca<sup>2+</sup> were compared with the corresponding controls to identify genes that had a fold change (FC) &#x02265;2 (log<sub>2</sub> FC&#x02265;1) between treatment and control (FDR&#x0003c;0.05). Genes that were significantly differentially expressed after 1h in altered [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] were designated &#x02018;short-term Ca<sup>2+</sup>-responsive genes&#x02019; (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Genes were also identified that showed no significant short-term response to Ca<sup>2+</sup> (i.e. were not differentially expressed between the shifts and their corresponding controls), but showed strong differential regulation in response to the Ca<sup>2+</sup> conditions of the 3-day pre-culture. These genes were designated &#x02018;long-term Ca<sup>2+</sup>-responsive genes&#x02019; (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The absolute expression levels of genes in all four samples were hierarchically clustered to identify common expression profiles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Differential expression of selected short-term responsive Ca<sup>2+</sup>-regulated genes</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gene name</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Accession</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Description</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>log</bold>
<sub><bold>2</bold></sub>
<bold>fold change in high Ca</bold>
<sup><bold>2+<italic>a</italic></bold></sup>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>log</bold>
<sub><bold>2</bold></sub>
<bold>fold change in low Ca</bold>
<sup><bold>2+</bold></sup>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>FDR</bold>
<sup><bold><italic>b</italic></bold></sup>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gene Cluster</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Bicarbonate import/metabolism</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>cmpA</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr2877</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate-binding protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>cmpB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr2878</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate transport permease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>cmcC</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr2879</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate transport, ATP-binding protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>cmpD</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr2880</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate transport, ATP-binding protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>bicA</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1304</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low affinity bicarbonate Na<sup>+</sup> symporter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>NhaS3-like</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1303</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Na<sup>+</sup>:H<sup>+</sup> antiporter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>sbtB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all2133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate Na<sup>+</sup> symporter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>sbtA</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all2134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate Na<sup>+</sup> symporter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>mrpB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1837</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Na<sup>+</sup>:H<sup>+</sup> antiporter subunit B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>mrpA</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1838</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Na<sup>+</sup>:H<sup>+</sup> antiporter subunit A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>mnhG</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">asl1839</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Na<sup>+</sup>:H<sup>+</sup> antiporter subunit G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>mnhF</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">asl1840</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Na<sup>+</sup>:H<sup>+</sup> antiporter subunit F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>mnhE</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1841</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Na<sup>+</sup>:H<sup>+</sup> antiporter subunit E</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.785<sup><italic>b</italic></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>mrpD</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1842</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Na<sup>+</sup>:H<sup>+</sup> antiporter subunit D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Nitrate import/metabolism</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nirA</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0607</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferredoxin:nitrite reductase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nrtA</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0608</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrate/nitrite transport substrate- binding protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nrtB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0609</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrate/nitrite transport permease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nrtC</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0610</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrate/nitrite transport ATP-binding protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nrtD</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0611</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrate/nitrite transport ATP-binding protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>narB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0612</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferredoxin:nitrite reductase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>cphB2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all0571</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyanophycinase, dipeptidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Photosynthesis and carbon metabolism</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>psbAIII</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr4592</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSII core protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>psbAIV</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all3572</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSII core protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>psbH</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all4050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSII reaction centre protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>psaE</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">asl4098</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSI reaction centre subunit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>fbaB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all3735</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose-bisphosphate aldolase class I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>glgB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all0875</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha-glucanotransferase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>asr3089</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">asr3089</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transglycosylase-associated protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>alr1850</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr1850</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transketolase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Transcriptional regulators</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>rbcR1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all0862</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LysR-type regulator</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Stress-related genes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>alr3199</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr3199</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron- and oxygen-binding HHE domain protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>all0457</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all0457</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low temperature-induced protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>all0458</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all0458</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low temperature-induced protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>all0459</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all0459</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin-like protein, nutrient stress responsive</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>alr5182</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr5182</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short-chain dehydrogenase/reductase, desiccation responsive</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>alr0896</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0896</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown protein, induced by desiccation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>asr1134</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">asr1134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CsbD stress response protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>flv4</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all4446</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavodiiron protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>flv2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all4444</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavodiiron protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.735<sup><italic>b</italic></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Bidirectional hydrogenase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>alr0761</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0761</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptidase domain-containing protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>hoxU</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0762</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bidirectional hydrogenase subunit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.227<sup><italic>b</italic></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>alr0763</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0763</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>hoxY</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0764</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bidirectional hydrogenase subunit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>alr0765</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0765</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.818</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>alr0750</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0750</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>hoxE</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0751</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bidirectional hydrogenase, diophorase subunit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>hoxF</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0752</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bidirectional hydrogenase subunit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.136</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Other proteins</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>alr0198</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0198</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>alr0199</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr0199</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>alr3715</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr3715</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-01" fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic>a</italic></sup> Genes with log<sub>2</sub> expression fold change &#x02265;1 are considered to be differentially expressed. However, in some cases genes of special interest with log<sub>2</sub> &#x0003c;1 differential expression have been included.</p></fn><fn id="fn-02" fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic>b</italic></sup> Data with false discovery rate (FDR)&#x0003e;0.05 are included when a gene belongs to an operon with member genes that have statistically robust FDRs (&#x0003c;0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Selected genes with long-term expression response to Ca<sup>2+</sup>
</p><p>All genes shown were &#x0003c;2 FC differentially expressed between the high or low Ca<sup>2+</sup> shifts and their respective controls, and were &#x0003e;2 FC differentially expressed between both cultures originating from the high Ca<sup>2+</sup> pre-culture (low Ca<sup>2+</sup> and control for low Ca<sup>2+</sup>) and both of those originating from the low Ca<sup>2+</sup> pre-culture (high Ca<sup>2+</sup> and control for high Ca<sup>2+</sup>).</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gene name</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Accession</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Description</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>FDR</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cluster</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Up-regulated in high calcium/down-regulated in low calcium</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>hglE</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr5351</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterocyst glycolipid synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>hglD</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr5354</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterocyst glycolipid synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>hglC</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr5355</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterocyst glycolipid synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nifB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1440</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen fixation protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nifN</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1437</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogenase iron-molybdenum protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nifE</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1438</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen iron/molybdenum cofactor biosynthesis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nifK</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1440</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogenase iron-molybdenum protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nifH</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1455</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogenase iron protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nifU</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1456</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen fixation protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>nifS</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all1457</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogenase cofactor synthesis protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>chlN</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all5076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protochlorophyllide reductase subunit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>chlL</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all5078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protochlorophyllide reductase iron-sulfur ATP-binding protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>clhB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr3441</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protochlorophyllide reductase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>chlH</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all4365</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protoporphyrin IX magnesium chelatase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>all0156</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all0156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>all0157</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all0157</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>all0158</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all0158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Down-regulated in high calcium/up-regulated in low calcium</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>rpl14</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all4205</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50S ribosomal protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>rpl29</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">asl4207</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50S ribosomal protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>rpl16</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all4208</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50S ribosomal protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>rps3</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all4209</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30S ribosomal protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>rpl22</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all4210</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50S ribosomal protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>rps19</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">asl4211</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30S ribosomal protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>rpl2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all4212</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50S ribosomal protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>rpl23</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all4213</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50S ribosomal protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>rpl4</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all4214</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50S ribosomal protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>sigG</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr3280</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group 3 sigma factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>sigB2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">alr3800</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group 2 sigma factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Hierarchically clustered heatmap of gene expression in <italic>Anabaena</italic> cells treated with high and low Ca<sup>2+</sup>, as well as in the controls for each. Columns show the absolute expression of significantly differentially expressed genes from triplicate samples (<italic>n</italic>=3) for each condition. Major clusters are indicated with numbers corresponding to <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> (and are discussed in text). (A) Genes responsive to 1h of Ca<sup>2+</sup> treatment, called &#x02018;short-term responsive genes&#x02019;; (B) Genes resistant to short-term response but responsive to 3 days of Ca<sup>2+</sup> treatment, called &#x02018;long-term responsive genes&#x02019;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw112_f0001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Short-term Ca<sup>2+</sup> shifts modulate the expression of carbon and nitrogen transport and photosynthesis genes</title><p>Genes related to bicarbonate (HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02013;</sup>) uptake were among the most strongly affected short-term Ca<sup>2+</sup>-responsive genes. All eight components of the three known HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02013;</sup> transporters in <italic>Anabaena</italic>, which are encoded on three separate operons, underwent 4&#x02013;6.5 FC up-regulation (log<sub>2</sub> FC of 2&#x02013;2.6) in high Ca<sup>2+</sup> shift. Conversely, the same genes were strongly down-regulated in low Ca<sup>2+</sup> shift (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). According to their expression profile, the HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> transporter genes populate Cluster 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>), which also includes all subunits of the mrp Na<sup>+</sup>:H<sup>+</sup> antiporter complex and the LysR-type transcriptional regulator rbcR1 (<italic>all0862</italic>). Additionally, several Calvin cycle and metabolic enzymes, including fructose bisphosphate aldolase, transketolase and the petF ferredoxin (<italic>all4148</italic>), shared the Cluster 1 expression profile.</p><p content-type="indent">Cluster 2 genes were strongly up-regulated in the short-term response to high Ca<sup>2+</sup> and moderately down-regulated by low Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Several photosynthetic subunits were encoded in Cluster 2, as well as stress-responsive genes including a low-temperature induced operon (<italic>all0457&#x02013;all0459</italic>; <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Sato <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), an oxygen-binding HHE domain protein (<italic>alr3199</italic>), and a desiccation-responsive dehydrogenase (<italic>alr5182</italic>; <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Katoh, 2012</xref>). The cyanophycinase <italic>cphB2</italic> (<italic>all0571</italic>) was also strongly up-regulated in high Ca<sup>2+</sup>.</p><p content-type="indent">Operons encoding the subunits of the bidirectional &#x02018;hox&#x02019; hydrogenase were down-regulated in response to high Ca<sup>2+</sup> and up-regulated in low Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). These genes were included in expression Cluster 3 together with <italic>nifJ</italic> and <italic>hoxR</italic>, which had &#x0003c;2FC differential expression but were nonetheless clearly down-regulated in high Ca<sup>2+</sup> shift and up-regulated in low Ca<sup>2+</sup> in comparison with the controls.</p><p content-type="indent">The <italic>nir</italic> operon that encodes the nitrate/nitrite transporter complex was down-regulated in high Ca<sup>2+</sup>, and up-regulated in low Ca<sup>2+</sup> shift (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), although these genes had low expression in both high Ca<sup>2+</sup> and its control culture, and high expression in both low Ca<sup>2+</sup> and its control (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). This suggests that expression of the <italic>nir</italic> operon and other Cluster 4 genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>) was predominantly influenced by the conditions of the pre-culture, which were common for each shift and its control; however, these genes also demonstrated a short-term response to Ca<sup>2+</sup> that led to differential regulation 1h after the shift.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Calcium has a long-term effect on genes encoding nitrogen metabolism</title><p>Genes that were induced by long-term high Ca<sup>2+</sup> conditions and repressed by long-term low Ca<sup>2+</sup> included heterocyst glycolipid synthesis (<italic>hgl</italic>) genes and several members of the <italic>nif</italic> operon that encode the heterocyst-specific nitrogen fixing machinery in <italic>Anabaena</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Subunits of the light-independent protochlorophyllide reductase (DPOR) were also among long-term Ca<sup>2+</sup> up-regulated genes that are shown in Cluster 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). Cluster 6 genes that underwent significant repression and induction by long-term high and low Ca<sup>2+</sup> conditions, respectively, encoded nine proteins of the 50S and 30S ribosome, as well as the group 2 sigma factor <italic>sigB2</italic> (also called <italic>sigE</italic>) and ECF sigma factor <italic>sigG</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Effects of calcium on <italic>Anabaena</italic> growth and biomass composition</title><p>Biomass accumulation and total protein and total sugars content of <italic>Anabaena</italic> cells were followed for 24h after cultures were shifted to the same high and low Ca<sup>2+</sup> media and using the same control samples as described above. <italic>Anabaena</italic> cells shifted to low Ca<sup>2+</sup> resulted in a biomass penalty. These cells showed a decreasing trend in biomass accumulation throughout the experiment in comparison with the control, from a ratio of approximately 1 early in the experiment to less than 0.9 at 24h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). This was in contrast to no relative change in biomass observed for cells shifted to high Ca<sup>2+</sup>.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Biomass (A), total protein (B) and total sugars (C) composition of <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. PCC 7120 cells shifted to high Ca<sup>2+</sup> (0.25mM to 1mM) or low Ca<sup>2+</sup> (1mM to 0.25mM) relative to the controls. Data presented are averages of three biological replicates (<italic>n</italic>=3). Error bars show standard deviations. Significant differences between high Ca<sup>2+</sup> and low Ca<sup>2+</sup> samples are indicated with asterisks (<italic>t</italic>-test <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw112_f0002"/></fig><p content-type="indent">Whilst the low Ca<sup>2+</sup> medium penalized biomass accumulation over time, the relative protein composition of this biomass was higher than that of control cells throughout the 24h growth period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). The relative protein composition of cells in low Ca<sup>2+</sup> reached the highest ratio at 8h after the shift in Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration, which correlates with the observed up-regulation of nitrate transport genes. There was less variation in the relative protein composition of cells in high Ca<sup>2+</sup>, which remained fairly stable at around 1 until 16h, but was significantly lower than the low Ca<sup>2+</sup> shift at 24h.</p><p content-type="indent">The shift in Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration had no observable effect on the total sugars content of <italic>Anabaena</italic> cells in the current experiment, with the relative concentrations remaining close to 1 and similar between high and low Ca<sup>2+</sup> shifts throughout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Effects of calcium on the photosynthetic activity of <italic>Anabaena</italic>
</title><p>Fluorescence kinetics of PSII and oxygen evolution in <italic>Anabaena</italic> cultures shifted to low and high Ca<sup>2+</sup> conditions showed an increase in PSII yield in all cultures in the first 2h after the shift (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). After 2h, the PSII yield stabilized at 0.35&#x02013;0.38 for all cells, except in the low Ca<sup>2+</sup> control cells. These cells experienced a further 28% drop in PSII yield from 2 to 4h and then stabilized until the 24h time point. Consequently, a relatively higher photosynthetic yield was observed after 2h for the <italic>Anabaena</italic> cells shifted to high Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Similarly, a rapid increase in gross oxygen evolution was observed for all cells over the first 2h, resulting in an approximate doubling of recorded values followed by a slow decline throughout the remainder of the experiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Photosynthetic activity of <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. PCC 7120 cells shifted to high Ca<sup>2+</sup> (0.25mM to 1mM, open squares) or to low Ca<sup>2+</sup> (1mM to 0.25mM, open circles) and of the controls (for high Ca<sup>2+</sup>, closed squares; and for low Ca<sup>2+</sup>, closed circles). Dual-PAM measurements of PSII yield (A) and oxygen evolution rates (B) shown here are from single experiments (<italic>n</italic>=1) that represent photosynthetic response to change in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub>. Lines connecting data points are included to aid visualization of the series.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw112_f0003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Changes in calcium concentration have no effect on heterocyst differentiation in <italic>Anabaena</italic> in the presence of combined nitrogen</title><p>Heterocyst frequency was evaluated at 10h, 20h and 2 d after the change in Ca<sup>2+</sup> conditions, and was determined not to be statistically different between low and high Ca<sup>2+</sup> shifted cells (<italic>t</italic>-test, 0.95 confidence; <italic>P</italic>=0.32). Heterocyst frequency data are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw112/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online. To investigate this further, the combined nitrogen levels were determined in the filtered media taken from all time points, and shown to be approximately 200mg L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> NO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup>-N for both high and low Ca<sup>2+</sup> media.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Box and whisker plot showing the heterocyst frequency rates (A) and representative bright field and fluorescence micrographs of <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. PCC 7120 shifted to high Ca<sup>2+</sup> (0.25mM to 1mM; B) or to low Ca<sup>2+</sup> (1mM to 0.25mM; C) and corresponding controls (A only) 2 days post-shift. Arrows indicate nitrogen-fixing heterocysts.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw112_f0004"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s21"><title>External calcium affects the gene expression and primary metabolism of <italic>Anabaena</italic>
</title><p>The role of Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions in signal transduction is widely recognized in eukaryotic organisms (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Clapham, 1995</xref>) and has increasingly become a focus of study in prokaryotes in recent years (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Onek and Smith, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Norris <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Michiels <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Dominguez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). The maintenance of very low basal intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations by active efflux from the cell and through the activity of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding proteins (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Gangola and Rosen, 1987</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Carafoli <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Batistic and Kudla, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">Stael <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012b</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Dominguez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) allows increases in cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> to have a potent signalling effect. The intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration of the filamentous cyanobacterium <italic>Anabaena</italic> was shown to rise transiently as a result of increased external Ca<sup>2+</sup>, as well as in response to temperature and osmotic stress (<xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">Torrecilla <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000, 2001</xref>). However, the major signalling role of Ca<sup>2+</sup> is associated with the differentiation of vegetative cells into nitrogen-fixing heterocyst cells under nitrogen-limited conditions, through the activity of several regulator proteins that are sensitive to the metabolic status of the cell (<xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">Torrecilla <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004a</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Shi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; see <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref> for a review). In this work, a 4-fold increase in external Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration caused rapid and strong up-regulation of the HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02013;</sup> transporters Cmp (also called BCT1), Bic and Sbt, as well as the Mrp operon that is involved in supplying Na<sup>+</sup> to the latter two HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> symporters. These transporters are components of the carbon-concentrating mechanism (CCM) that also includes CO<sub>2</sub> transport machinery in the plasma and thylakoid membranes (<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Shibata <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Badger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Badger and Price, 2003</xref>). The opposite transcription response of HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> transporters occurred under a 4-fold decrease in Ca<sup>2+</sup>. In the unicellular cyanobacterium <italic>Synechocystis</italic> sp. PCC 7002, Cmp and Sbt are expressed in response to limiting C<sub>i</sub> conditions (<xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">Woodger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>); however, cultures used in the current study were grown under 3% CO<sub>2</sub> and did not experience C<sub>i</sub> limitation. Neither was this caused by any change in media pH, which measured 7.5&#x02013;8.0 throughout the experiment and was identical in all cultures. Low C<sub>i</sub>-induced expression of the Cmp operon in <italic>Anabaena</italic> is controlled by the LysR-type regulator All0862, which is itself up-regulated in response to low nitrogen (<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Lopez-Igual <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). In this work, the 2FC up-regulated expression of <italic>all0862</italic> observed in high Ca<sup>2+</sup> may explain up-regulation of the Cmp transporter, although these cultures were not under nitrogen deprivation (discussed below). Notably, translocation of extracellular HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> by the cmpA subunit requires co-binding of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> ions to cmpA (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Koropatkin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). It has not been established whether these Ca<sup>2+</sup> translocation cofactors are released into the cell; however, in this way increases in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> could rapidly translate to an internal signal through increasing the intracellular concentration of Cmp-transported HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, rather than directly through increased [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. A transient rise in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> in response to increased [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> was shown to be rapidly reversed in <italic>Anabaena</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">Torrecilla <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>), whereas an increase in HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> could induce a more long-term signal through metabolic intermediates such as 2-oxoglutarate (2-OG). Carbohydrate measurements in this study showed no difference between high and low Ca<sup>2+</sup> that would reflect the up- and down-regulation of HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> transporters. Rapid induction of several photosynthetic genes under high Ca<sup>2+</sup> may be connected with the increased uptake of HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, which is converted to CO<sub>2</sub> for photo-assimilation (reviewed in <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Burnap <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). However, analysis of O<sub>2</sub> evolution and PSII yield in this work did not provide evidence of an increased rate of photosynthesis under high Ca<sup>2+</sup>.</p><p content-type="indent">The concentration of Ca<sup>2+</sup> demonstrated a short-term effect on the expression of the <italic>nirA</italic> operon that encodes the nitrate assimilation machinery, which was induced in low Ca<sup>2+</sup> and repressed in high Ca<sup>2+</sup>. This correlates with the higher relative protein composition of cells shifted to low Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>), and was the opposite trend to that observed for HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> transport and photosynthesis genes. Expression of the <italic>nirA</italic> operon requires a lack of ammonium and is increased by both nitrate levels (indicated by extracellular or intracellularly generated nitrite) and by 2-OG, a metabolite which represents cellular C:N levels. These indicators respectively activate the ntcB and ntcA transcriptional activators of <italic>nirA</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Ohashi, 2011</xref>). NtcA, considered the global nitrogen regulator of cyanobacteria (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Herrero <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>), is crucial for the expression of the <italic>nirA</italic> operon across all cyanobacteria (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Maeda <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). NtcA activity is also increased by PipX, which is sequestered by the signalling protein PII under low 2-OG (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Espinosa <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Interestingly, modification of the PII protein was suggested to be influenced by Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), though evidence for this is lacking. PII is involved in cyanophycin distribution between vegetative cells and heterocysts (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Laurent <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>) and the up-regulation of cyanophycinase (<italic>cphB2</italic>) was observed under high Ca<sup>2+</sup> conditions in this study (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Thus it appears likely that Ca<sup>2+</sup> affects the sensing of intracellular nitrogen availability, possibly through interaction with PII, resulting in the differential regulation of the <italic>nirA</italic> operon.</p></sec><sec id="s22"><title>
<italic>Anabaena</italic> heterocyst differentiation is not affected by increased extracellular calcium under nitrate-replete conditions</title><p>It is interesting that the heterocyst-specific nitrogen fixing (<italic>nif</italic>) genes are up-regulated by high Ca<sup>2+</sup> in media replete with nitrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, Cluster 5), whilst the heterocyst frequency did not differ significantly between high and low Ca<sup>2+</sup> conditions. In <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. PCC 7120, nitrogenase is protected from oxygen-induced inactivation by being spatially segregated in specialized heterocyst cells where <italic>nif</italic> expression has been reported to occur late during heterocyst development, at 12&#x02013;24h after nitrogen deprivation (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Elhai and Wolk, 1990</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Golden <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Herrero <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Previous work has demonstrated that intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> is directly involved in heterocyst differentiation (<xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Shi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), but this has generally been studied under conditions of combined nitrogen deprivation. Under such conditions the levels of 2-OG are increased, and NtcA is activated and binds to the promoter of the cyanobacterial Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding protein (CcbP), decreasing <italic>ccbP</italic> expression and increasing free [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. Free [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> is also increased in heterocysts through the degradation of CcbP by HetR, the master regulator of heterocyst development. Collectively, the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> of heterocyst cells reaches concentrations severalfold higher than that of vegetative cells (<xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Shi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Unlike the effect on <italic>nif</italic> expression, significant effects of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> were not detected in this study for <italic>HetR</italic> or <italic>NtcA</italic> expression, which have been reported to occur in the early and intermediate stages of heterocyst development (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Herrero <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Nor was a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-mediated differential expression of <italic>PatS</italic> or <italic>HetN</italic> observed, both of which are involved in the negative regulation of heterocyst differentiation (<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Orozco <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). However, the expression level of these genes does not necessarily represent their activity. On the other hand, the effects of high [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> in the nitrate-replete conditions of the current work appear to act only on specific functional genes, including the heterocyst glycolipid synthase (<italic>hgl</italic>) gene cluster (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>), coding for a glycolipid layer deposited between the outer membrane and polysaccharide layer and required for preventing diffusion of oxygen into the heterocyst (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Fan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). This may indicate the structural and functional importance of heterocysts in maintaining a high [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> once differentiation has actually occurred.</p><p content-type="indent">Whilst <italic>nif</italic> and <italic>hgl</italic> genes demonstrated long term responses of up-regulation in high Ca<sup>2+</sup> and down-regulation in low Ca<sup>2+</sup>, sigma factors <italic>sigB2</italic> and <italic>sigG</italic>, which are both involved in, but not individually required for, heterocyst development (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Brahamsha and Haselkorn, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Khudyakov and Golden, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Ehira and Miyazaki, 2015</xref>), demonstrated opposite long-term responses to Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Additionally, <italic>nrra</italic>, another gene involved in early heterocyst development (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Ehira and Ohmori, 2006</xref>), was found to be strongly (but not significantly; FDR&#x0003e;0.05) down-regulated in high Ca<sup>2+</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="s23"><title>Ca<sup>2+</sup> influences C:N balance in <italic>Anabaena</italic>
</title><p>This study has found that changes in Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations lead to opposite regulation of C and N assimilation pathways that nonetheless do not lead to major changes in cellular biochemistry or development. This suggests that Ca<sup>2+</sup> signalling in <italic>Anabaena</italic> may have a role in fine-tuning the C:N balance of cells for optimal growth under fluctuating environmental conditions. One possible mechanism for this may be through modulating the activity of a transcriptional regulator. Given the central role of the NtcA regulator, which generally activates, but can also repress, genes involved in management of the C:N balance in <italic>Anabaena</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Herrero <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), the expression of approximately 40 known NtcA-regulated genes (<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Picossi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) was tested using RNAseq data from the current study. This analysis revealed no clear correlation between NtcA regulation and Ca<sup>2+</sup> treatment, although, several of these genes were significantly differentially expressed under shifted [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw112/-/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online).</p><p content-type="indent">Considering the tight regulation of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> in <italic>Anabaena</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">Torrecilla <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>), the up-regulation of nitrogen metabolism- and heterocyst-related genes as a long-term response to increased [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> may most likely be a metabolic adjustment in response to the up-regulation of carbon metabolism in the short term. In this case, the observed increase in <italic>nif</italic> expression may be induced through increased 2-OG levels as a consequence of increase of Cmp-transported HCO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup>. Nonetheless, the possibility that even trace quantities of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> can influence gene expression through Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding transcription regulators, despite strict [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> maintenance, should not be dismissed.</p></sec><sec id="s24"><title>Perspective</title><p>This work shows that Ca<sup>2+</sup> operates as a secondary messenger that affects the primary cellular metabolism of <italic>Anabaena</italic> under conditions replete in both combined-nitrogen and inorganic carbon. Transcriptomics data revealed distinctly and strikingly opposite trends in regulation of nitrogen-related and carbon-related processes in response to Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Given the elaborate and sensitive network of regulation of C:N balance in cyanobacteria, it is tempting to speculate that Ca<sup>2+</sup> has a prominent role in the initial stages of C:N balance adjustment, through regulation of cellular nutrient levels, photosynthesis and/or gene activation. This short-term effect of Ca<sup>2+</sup> likely prompts a cascade of gene expression to rebalance the C:N homeostasis of the cell. However, heterocyst differentiation and nitrogen fixation in <italic>Anabaena</italic> appear to require convergence of multiple signalling pathways in addition to Ca<sup>2+</sup>, including those instigated by genuine combined nitrogen deficiency. It will be most valuable to establish the identities of the cellular factors responsible for transforming the Ca<sup>2+</sup> signal to gene expression in <italic>Anabaena</italic>, especially metabolic intermediates such as 2-OG and protein receptors of Ca<sup>2+</sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s25"><title>Supplementary data</title><p>Supplementary data are available at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw112/-/DC1">Figure S1</ext-link>. Clustered heatmap showing the absolute expression of genes shown to interact with the transcriptional regulator NtcA (<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Picossi <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) in response to changes in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] in the expression data of the current study.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw112/-/DC1">Table S1</ext-link>. Heterocyst counts in Ca<sup>2+</sup> shift experiments.</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Data</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_67_13_3997__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_erw112_Supplementary_figure_S1.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_erw112_Supplementary_Table_S1.xlsx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors acknowledge financial support from the <funding-source>EU Marie Curie project</funding-source> CALIPSO GA 2013&#x02013;607607 (J.W.) and the <funding-source>Academy of Finland projects</funding-source> 271832 and 273870 (E-M.A.) and 26080341 (P.G.).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1955</year>
<article-title>Studies on nitrogen-fixing blue-green algae. 1. Growth and nitrogen fixation by Anabaena cylindrica Lemm</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>366</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>372</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16654787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1936</year>
<article-title>Physiological studies with the nitrogen fixing alga, Nostoc muscorum</article-title>. <source>Botanical Gazette</source>
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>463</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Evolution and diversity of CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanisms in cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Functional Plant Biology</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanisms in cyanobacteria: molecular components, their diversity and evolution</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>609</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>622</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12554704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr&#x000e1;n-Berd&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodea-Palomares</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Legan&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Pi&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Free Ca<sup>2+</sup> as an early intracellular biomarker of exposure of cyanobacteria to environmental pollution</article-title>. <source>Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry</source>
<volume>400</volume>, <fpage>1015</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1029</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20886207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batistic</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kudla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Analysis of calcium signaling pathways in plants</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>
<volume>1820</volume>, <fpage>1283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1293</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22061997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brahamsha</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haselkorn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Identification of multiple RNA polymerase sigma factor homologs in the cyanobacterium Anabaena sp. strain PCC 7120: Cloning, expression, and inactivation of the sigB and sigC genes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source>
<volume>174</volume>, <fpage>7273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7282</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1385387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lineweaver</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1934</year>
<article-title>The specific influence of acidity on the mechanism of nitrogen fixation by azotobacter</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>340</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16559703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnap</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagemann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Regulation of CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanism in cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Life</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>348</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>371</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25636131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carafoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santella</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Branca</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Generation, control, and processing of cellular calcium signals</article-title>. <source>Critical Reviews in Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>260</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11370791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clapham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Calcium signaling</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>80</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>268</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7834745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guragain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrauchan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Calcium binding proteins and calcium signaling in prokaryotes</article-title>. <source>Cell Calcium</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>165</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25555683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Plastid evolution: origins, diversity, trends</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Genetics and Development</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>655</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>661</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9914199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DuBois</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1956</year>
<article-title>Colorimetric method for determination of sugars and related substances</article-title>. <source>Analytical Chemistry</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>350</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>356</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Regulation of genes involved in heterocyst differentiation in the cyanobacterium Anabaena sp. strain PCC 7120 by a group 2 sigma factor SigC</article-title>. <source>Life</source> , <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>603</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25692906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohmori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>NrrA directly regulates expression of hetR during heterocyst differentiation in the cyanobacterium Anabaena sp strain PCC 7120</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source>
<volume>188</volume>, <fpage>8520</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8525</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17041048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elhai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Developmental regulation and spatial pattern of expression of the structural genes for nitrogenase in the cyanobacterium Anabaena</article-title>. <source>EMBO Journal</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>3379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3388</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2120040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Espinosa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forchhammer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burillo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Interaction network in cyanobacterial nitrogen regulation: PipX, a protein that interacts in a 2-oxoglutarate dependent manner with PII and NtcA</article-title>. <source>Molecular Microbiology</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>469</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16796668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Falcon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magallon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Dating the cyanobacterial ancestor of the chloroplast</article-title>. <source>Isme Journal</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>777</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>783</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20200567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lechno&#x02010;Yossef</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Clustered genes required for synthesis and deposition of envelope glycolipids in Anabaena sp. strain PCC 7120</article-title>. <source>Molecular Microbiology</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>243</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16164561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Nitrogen assimilation and nitrogen control in cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Biochemical Society Transactions</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>167</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15667295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gangola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Maintenance of intracellular calcium in Escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>
<volume>262</volume>, <fpage>12570</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12574</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2442165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Genty</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briantais</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>The relationship between the quantum yield of photosynthetic electron-transport and quenching of chlorophyll fluorescence</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>
<volume>990</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whorff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiest</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Independent regulation of nifHDK operon transcription and DNA rearrangement during heterocyst differentiation in the cyanobacterium Anabaena sp strain PCC 7120</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source>
<volume>173</volume>, <fpage>7098</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1938911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muro-Pastor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Nitrogen control in cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source>
<volume>183</volume>, <fpage>411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>425</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11133933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muro-Pastor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valladares</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Cellular differentiation and the NtcA transcription factor in filamentous cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiology Reviews</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>487</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15374662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Picossi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Gene expression during heterocyst differentiation</article-title>. <source>Advances in Botanical Research</source>
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>329</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochmal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trompelt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hippler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Calcium-dependent regulation of photosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>
<volume>1847</volume>, <fpage>993</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1003</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25687895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Structures of Anabaena calcium-binding protein CcbP: insights into Ca<sup>2+</sup> signaling during heterocyst differentiation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>
<volume>286</volume>, <fpage>12381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12388</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21330362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Complete genomic sequence of the filamentous nitrogen-fixing cyanobacterium Anabaena sp strain PCC 7120</article-title>. <source>DNA Research</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>213</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11759840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Complete genome structure of the unicellular cyanobacterium Synechocystis sp. PCC6803</article-title>. <source>Plant and Cell Physiology</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>1171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1176</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9435137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Desiccation-inducible genes are related to N<sub>2</sub>-fixing system under desiccation in a terrestrial cyanobacterium</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>
<volume>1817</volume>, <fpage>1263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1269</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22503828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Imaging spatial and cellular characteristics of low temperature calcium signature after cold acclimation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>1679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1686</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11053457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trewavas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Cold calcium signaling in Arabidopsis involves two cellular pools and a change in calcium signature after acclimation</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>503</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8721751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trewavas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Calcium signalling in Arabidopsis thaliana responding to drought and salinity</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1067</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1078</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9418048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trewavas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Transgenic plant aequorin reports the effects of touch and cold-shock and elicitors on cytoplasmic calcium</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>352</volume>, <fpage>524</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>526</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1865907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trewavas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Wind-induced plant motion immediately increases cytosolic calcium</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>89</volume>, <fpage>4967</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4971</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11536497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koropatkin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koppenaal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pakrasi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The structure of a cyanobacterial bicarbonate transport protein, CmpA</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>
<volume>282</volume>, <fpage>2606</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2614</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17121816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khudyakov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Identification and inactivation of three group 2 sigma factor genes in Anabaena sp. strain PCC 7120</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source>
<volume>183</volume>, <fpage>6667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6675</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11673438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mella-Herrera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Cyanobacterial heterocysts</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>a000315</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20452939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forchhammer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heulin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Cell-type specific modification of PII is involved in the regulation of nitrogen metabolism in the cyanobacterium Anabaena PCC 7120</article-title>. <source>FEBS Letters</source>
<volume>576</volume>, <fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>265</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15474048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Igual</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Picossi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Garrido</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>N and C control of ABC-type bicarbonate transporter Cmp and its LysR-type transcriptional regulator CmpR in a heterocyst-forming cyanobacterium, Anabaena sp</article-title>. <source>Environmental Microbiology</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>1035</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1048</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22221957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>cis-acting sequences required for NtcB-dependent, nitrite-responsive positive regulation of the nitrate assimilation operon in the cyanobacterium Synechococcus sp. strain PCC 7942</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source>
<volume>180</volume>, <fpage>4080</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4088</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9696753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Markwell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bieber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolbert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1978</year>
<article-title>Modification of Lowry procedure to simplify protein determination in membrane and lipoprotein samples</article-title>. <source>Analytical Biochemistry</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>206</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">98070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verhaert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanderleyden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>The functions of Ca<sup>2+</sup> in bacteria: a role for EF-hand proteins?</article-title>
<source>Trends in Microbiology</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11827810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1985</year>
<article-title>Involvement of calcium in nitrogen-fixation by Nostoc-Linckia</article-title>. <source>Current Science</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Calcium signaling in plant endosymbiotic organelles: mechanism and role in physiology</article-title>. <source>Molecular Plant</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1094</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24574521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freestone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canvin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trinei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Modha</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Calcium signalling in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source>
<volume>178</volume>, <fpage>3677</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3682</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8682765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takatani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aichi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Regulation of nitrate assimilation in cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>1411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1424</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21282331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Calmodulin and calcium mediated regulation in prokaryotes</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Microbiology</source>
<volume>138</volume>, <fpage>1039</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1049</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1527487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orozco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Risser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Epistasis analysis of four genes from Anabaena sp. strain PCC 7120 suggests a connection between PatA and PatS in heterocyst pattern formation</article-title>. <source>Journal of bacteriology</source>
<volume>188</volume>, <fpage>1808</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1816</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16484191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piccioni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mauzerall</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1978</year>
<article-title>Calcium and photosynthetic oxygen evolution in cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>
<volume>504</volume>, <fpage>384</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">102341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Picossi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>ChIP analysis unravels an exceptionally wide distribution of DNA binding sites for the NtcA transcription factor in a heterocyst-forming cyanobacterium</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>22</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24417914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rippka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deruelles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waterbury</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herdman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1979</year>
<article-title>Generic assignments, strain histories and properties of pure cultures of cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Microbiology</source>
<volume>111</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vothknecht</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>The role of calcium in chloroplasts &#x02013; an intriguing and unresolved puzzle</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source>
<volume>249</volume>, <fpage>957</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>966</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22227834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moriyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toyoshima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizusawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>The all0458/lti46.2 gene encodes a low temperature-induced Dps protein homologue in the cyanobacteria Anabaena sp PCC 7120 and Anabaena variabilis M3</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>158</volume>, <fpage>2527</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2536</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22837304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Regulation of intracellular free calcium concentration during heterocyst differentiation by HetR and NtcA in Anabaena sp PCC 7120</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>103</volume>, <fpage>11334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11339</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16849429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohkawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimoyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Two CO<sub>2</sub> uptake systems in cyanobacteria: four systems for inorganic carbon acquisition in Synechocystis sp strain PCC6803</article-title>. <source>Functional Plant Biology</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>129</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Regulation of calcium ion and its effect on growth and developmental behavior in wild type and ntcA mutant of Anabaena sp PCC 7120 under varied levels of CaCl<sub>2</sub>
</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>246</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hobson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Evidence for calcium-mediated regulation of heterocyst frequency and nitrogenase activity in Nostoc 6720</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>
<volume>105</volume>, <fpage>531</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>541</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stael</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kmiecik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vothknecht</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teige</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Arabidopsis calcium-binding mitochondrial carrier proteins as potential facilitators of mitochondrial ATP-import and plastid SAM-import</article-title>. <source>FEBS Letters</source>
<volume>585</volume>, <fpage>3935</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3940</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22062157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stael</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wimberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anrather</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vothknecht</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teige</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>a. <article-title>Cross-talk between calcium signalling and protein phosphorylation at the thylakoid</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>63</volume>, <fpage>1725</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1733</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22197893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stael</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wurzinger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehlmer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vothknecht</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teige</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>b. <article-title>Plant organellar calcium signalling: an emerging field</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>63</volume>, <fpage>1525</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1542</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22200666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0064"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrecilla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Legan&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonilla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Pi&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Use of recombinant aequorin to study calcium homeostasis and monitor calcium transients in response to heat and cold shock in cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>123</volume>, <fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10806234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0065"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrecilla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Legan&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonilla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Pi&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Calcium transients in response to salinity and osmotic stress in the nitrogen-fixing cyanobacterium Anabaena sp PCC7120, expressing cytosolic apoaequorin</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell and Environment</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>641</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>648</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0066"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrecilla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Legan&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonilla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Pi&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>a. <article-title>A calcium signal is involved in heterocyst differentiation in the cyanobacterium Anabaena sp PCC7120</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>150</volume>, <fpage>3731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3739</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15528659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0067"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrecilla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Legan&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonilla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Pi&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>b. <article-title>Light-to-dark transitions trigger a transient increase in intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> modulated by the redox state of the photosynthetic electron transport chain in the cyanobacterium Anabaena sp PCC7120</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell and Environment</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>810</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>819</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0068"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Heterocyst formation</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Genetics</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0069"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Transcriptional regulation of the CO<sub>2</sub>-concentrating mechanism in a euryhaline, coastal marine cyanobacterium, Synechococcus sp strain PCC 7002: Role of NdhR/CcmR</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source>
<volume>189</volume>, <fpage>3335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3347</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17307862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0070"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Heterocyst differentiation and pattern formation in cyanobacteria: a chorus of signals</article-title>. <source>Molecular Microbiology</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>367</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>375</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16390435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0071"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>CcbP, a calcium-binding protein from Anabaena sp PCC 7120 provides evidence that calcium ions regulate heterocyst differentiation</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>5744</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5748</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15811937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>