<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5159998</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3378</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-3378-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Expansion and diversification of the MSDIN family of cyclic peptide genes in the poisonous agarics <italic>Amanita phalloides</italic> and <italic>A. bisporigera</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pulman</surname><given-names>Jane A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Childs</surname><given-names>Kevin L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sgambelluri</surname><given-names>R. Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>Jonathan D.</given-names></name><address><email>walton@msu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Plant Biology, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI 48824 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Center for Genomics-Enabled Plant Science, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI 48824 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI 48824 USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Energy Plant Research Laboratory, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI 48824 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>1038</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p>The cyclic peptide toxins of <italic>Amanita</italic> mushrooms, such as &#x003b1;-amanitin and phalloidin, are encoded by the &#x0201c;MSDIN&#x0201d; gene family and ribosomally biosynthesized. Based on partial genome sequence and PCR analysis, some members of the MSDIN family were previously identified in <italic>Amanita bisporigera</italic>, and several other members are known from other species of <italic>Amanita</italic>. However, the complete complement in any one species, and hence the genetic capacity for these fungi to make cyclic peptides, remains unknown.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Draft genome sequences of two cyclic peptide-producing mushrooms, the &#x0201c;Death Cap&#x0201d; <italic>A. phalloides</italic> and the &#x0201c;Destroying Angel&#x0201d; <italic>A. bisporigera</italic>, were obtained. Each species has ~30 MSDIN genes, most of which are predicted to encode unknown cyclic peptides. Some MSDIN genes were duplicated in one or the other species, but only three were common to both species. A gene encoding cycloamanide B, a previously described nontoxic cyclic heptapeptide, was also present in <italic>A. phalloides</italic>, but genes for antamanide and cycloamanides A, C, and D were not. In <italic>A. bisporigera</italic>, RNA expression was observed for 20 of the MSDIN family members. Based on their predicted sequences, novel cyclic peptides were searched for by LC/MS/MS in extracts of <italic>A. phalloides</italic>. The presence of two cyclic peptides, named cycloamanides E and F with structures cyclo(SFFFPVP) and cyclo(IVGILGLP), was thereby demonstrated. Of the MSDIN genes reported earlier from another specimen of <italic>A. bisporigera</italic>, 9 of 14 were not found in the current genome assembly. Differences between previous and current results for the complement of MSDIN genes and cyclic peptides in the two fungi probably represents natural variation among geographically dispersed isolates of <italic>A. phalloides</italic> and among the members of the poorly defined <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> species complex. Both <italic>A. phalloides</italic> and <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> contain two prolyl oligopeptidase genes, one of which (POPB) is probably dedicated to cyclic peptide biosynthesis as it is in <italic>Galerina marginata</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The MSDIN gene family has expanded and diverged rapidly in <italic>Amanita</italic> section <italic>Phalloideae</italic>. Together, <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> and <italic>A. phalloides</italic> are predicted to have the capacity to make more than 50 cyclic hexa-, hepta-, octa-, nona- and decapeptides.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12864-016-3378-7) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Amatoxin</kwd><kwd>Amanitin</kwd><kwd>Phallotoxin</kwd><kwd>Phalloidin</kwd><kwd>Phallacidin</kwd><kwd>Poisonous mushroom</kwd><kwd>Cyclic peptide</kwd><kwd>Cycloamanide</kwd><kwd>Antamanide</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>GM088274</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>Jonathan D.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000001</institution-id><institution>National Science Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>IOS&#x02013;1126998</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Childs</surname><given-names>Kevin L.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000015</institution-id><institution>U.S. Department of Energy</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>DE-FG02-91ER20021</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Background</title><p>The characteristic toxins of poisonous agarics (mushrooms; Agaricales) in the genus <italic>Amanita</italic> include the amatoxins such as &#x003b1;-amanitin and the phallotoxins such as phalloidin. Both families of toxins are bicyclic peptides biosynthesized on ribosomes as precursor peptides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. These were the first ribosomally encoded post-translationally modified peptides (RiPPs) to be described from the Kingdom Mycota [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Additional fungal RiPPs have subsequently been discovered in filamentous fungi (Ascomycota) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p>From a partial genomic sequence obtained by 454 pyrosequencing, it was shown that the genes for &#x003b1;-amanitin and phallacidin belong to a family of at least 15 genes in <italic>Amanita bisporigera</italic> (<italic>Ab</italic>) called the &#x0201c;MSDIN&#x0201d; family for the first five conserved amino acids in the precursor peptides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The MSDIN precursor peptides are 33&#x02013;37 amino acids in length and comprise two conserved regions, a 10-amino acid &#x0201c;leader&#x0201d; and a 17-amino acid &#x0201c;follower&#x0201d;, flanking a highly variable &#x0201c;core&#x0201d; region of 6&#x02013;10 amino acids that contains the amino acids present in the mature toxins.</p><p>Subsequent to its discovery in <italic>Ab</italic>, the MSDIN family has been found in other cyclic peptide toxin-producing species of <italic>Amanita</italic>, including <italic>A. ocreata, A. phalloides</italic> (<italic>Ap</italic>), and <italic>A. exitialis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The MSDIN family is absent from fungi that do not produce amatoxins or phallotoxins, including species of <italic>Amanita</italic> outside section <italic>Phalloideae</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. <italic>Galerina marginata</italic> (<italic>Gm</italic>), an agaric not closely related to <italic>Amanita</italic>, also produces &#x003b1;-amanitin on ribosomes but does not possess an extended gene family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The &#x003b1;-amanitin gene in <italic>Gm</italic> is the same length (35 amino acids) as the homolog in <italic>Ab</italic>, but its primary amino acid sequence is divergent outside the core region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p>The initial post-translational processing step of the &#x003b1;-amanitin precursor peptide in <italic>Gm</italic> is catalyzed by GmPOPB, a specialized member of the prolyl oligopeptidase family of serine proteases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. POPB first cleaves at the carboxy side of a highly conserved Pro residue at the C-terminus of the 10-amino acid leader sequence and then transpeptidates at a second Pro (which remains in the final product) to produce a homodetic cyclic octapeptide. Studies with synthetic peptides have elucidated the general sequence and structural requirements of the precursor peptide for processing by POPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. A dedicated POP most likely also processes the cyclic peptide precursor peptides in <italic>Amanita</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p>In order to more fully understand the genomic potential for cyclic peptide production by <italic>Amanita</italic> section <italic>Phalloideae</italic>, we have generated draft genome sequences of <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic>. We show that each species contains ~30 members of the MSDIN family, only three of which are in common between the two fungi. Furthermore, two specimens within the <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> species complex have different complements of MSDIN genes. These results illuminate the deep genetic potential of the <italic>Amanita</italic> toxin biosynthetic pathway to produce a range of modified and unmodified cyclic peptides by the same biosynthetic pathway.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Genome and transcriptome assembly of <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic></title><p>The sequencing and assembly statistics for the genomes for <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. After an initial assembly of the <italic>Ap</italic> genome, Blobology analysis identified 18 contigs that were contaminated with non-fungal reads [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The raw reads associated with the contaminated contigs were removed before reassembling the genome. The genome assembly of <italic>Ap</italic> contained 1465 contigs greater than 1&#x000a0;kb and a total size of ~40&#x000a0;Mb with an N50 scaffold size of 54&#x000a0;kb. Using a basidiomycete single-copy core protein database, analysis with BUSCO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] resulted in the identification of 92% complete and 3.6% fragmented protein sequences in the <italic>Ap</italic> genome assembly. Only 4.3% of the core basidiomycete core proteins were missing.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Basic statistics for the genome assemblies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>
<italic>A. phalloides</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>A. bisporigera</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Assembly size</td><td>40&#x000a0;Mb</td><td>75&#x000a0;Mb</td></tr><tr><td>Predicted fold coverage</td><td>69X</td><td>74X</td></tr><tr><td>Number of contigs</td><td>5,437</td><td>23,572</td></tr><tr><td>Contig N50</td><td>21,781&#x000a0;bp</td><td>5,866&#x000a0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Number of Scaffolds</td><td>1,465</td><td>10,390</td></tr><tr><td>Scaffold N50</td><td>54,288&#x000a0;bp</td><td>13,906&#x000a0;bp</td></tr><tr><td>Coverage of complete BUSCO basidomycete genes</td><td>92%</td><td>73%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p>For <italic>Ab</italic>, analysis of an initial genome assembly with Blobology indicated that 163 contigs were contaminated with non-fungal sequences. Raw reads aligned to these sites of contamination were removed, and the remaining reads were reassembled. The final <italic>Ab</italic> genome assembly had a total size of ~75&#x000a0;Mb with 10,390 scaffolds with an N50 scaffold size of 13.9&#x000a0;kb (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The genome contained 73% of the complete proteins in the BUSCO basidiomycete single-copy core protein dataset, 9.2% of fragmented proteins, and was missing 17% of the core proteins. Transcript assembly of <italic>Ab</italic> RNA-seq reads with Trinity yielded 67,879 transcripts, including isoforms.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>MAKER annotation of <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> genomes</title><p>The annotation of <italic>Ap</italic> resulted in 10,221 gene models of which 8177 were supported by protein alignments and/or known Pfam domains (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. These gene models were used as the high-quality gene set for functional annotation and downstream ortholog analysis. The average predicted transcript length was 1494&#x000a0;bp, with a unimodal GC distribution ranging from 31 to 68 with a peak at 49 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1).</p><p>The annotation of <italic>Ab</italic> resulted in 22,189 gene models of which 14,886 were supported by transcript alignments, protein alignments, and/or known Pfam domains (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). This set of 14,886 gene models was retained as the high-quality gene set for functional annotation and downsteam ortholog analysis. The average transcript length was 1182&#x000a0;bp, with a unimodal GC distribution ranging from 17&#x02013;67 with a peak at 48 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>MSDIN gene search and annotation</title><p>No MSDIN genes were annotated by the MAKER annotation pipeline even after the minimum protein length parameter was reduced to 150&#x000a0;bp. We also trained SNAP and AUGUSTUS to find short genes by using only short genes in the training sets, but this also resulted in no MSDIN gene predictions (data not shown). Finally, by using known members of the MSDIN family as tblastn queries, 33 MSDIN genes were manually identified in <italic>Ap</italic>, of which 29 were unique (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The predicted proteins of 23 of them started with the canonical sequence &#x0201c;MSDIN&#x0201d;, and the others with some single amino-acid variant of MSDIN, i.e., MSDMN, MSDVN, MSDIK, MSEIN, MSDTN or MSNIN. All had the two canonical Pro residues required for processing by prolyl oligopeptidase B (POPB), except one predicted protein (Apha_msdin_31) was missing the Pro residue immediately upstream of the variable region and another (Apha_msdin_30) was missing the second Pro residue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The latter precursor peptide sequence also lacked the terminal Cys residue that is probably required for processing by POPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Among the <italic>Ap</italic> MSDIN genes were three (Apha_msdin_26, 29, and 33) encoding phalloidin (AWLATCP) from three separate scaffolds. Two genes (Apha_msdin_12 and 14) encoded &#x003b2;-amanitin (IWGIGCDP). There were single genes for phallacidin and &#x003b1;-amanitin (Apha_msdin_1 and 13, respectively). The Apha_msdin_27 gene encoded cycloamanide B, which is an unmodified monocyclic heptapeptide of sequence SFFFPIP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Predicted peptide sequences of the MSDIN family members in <italic>A. phalloides</italic> (<italic>Ap</italic>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_3378_Tab2_HTML" id="MO1"/><table-wrap-foot><p>Core regions are underlined. Spaces were introduced after some of the core sequences to emphasize alignments of the follower sequences</p><p>Notes:</p><p>1. Core region previously reported from <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]</p><p>2. Core region previously reported from <italic>A. exitialis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]</p><p>3. Core region previously reported from <italic>A. rimosa</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</p><p>4. First reported in this paper</p><p>*indicates a stop codon</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>The MSDIN genes from <italic>Ap</italic> were found in many clusters on numerous scaffolds. Scaffold_220 contained six MSDIN genes, all of which had different core sequences (Apha_msdin_16 through Apha_msdin_21) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Three scaffolds (Scaffold_260, Scaffold_318, and Scaffold_901) each had two unique MSDIN genes. Scaffold_1281 had six MSDIN genes; two (Apha_msdin_3 and 4) had identical core regions (IILAPIIP), and four others, Apha_msdin_5 through Apha_msdin_8, were unique. The three genes encoding &#x003b1;-amanitin and &#x003b2;-amanitin were clustered on Scaffold_1430.</p><p>The MSDIN genes from <italic>Ab</italic> also required manual annotation. The <italic>Ab</italic> genome assembly contained 31 MSDIN genes of which 27 were unique (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The predicted proteins of 24 <italic>Ab</italic> MSDIN genes started with the canonical &#x0201c;MSDIN&#x0201d; sequence. The first Pro residue adjacent to the variable region of these predicted MSDIN genes was conserved in all of the predicted proteins, but three (Abis_msdin_17, 18, and 27) lacked the second Pro residue. Additionally, four gene products (Abis_msdin_7, 11, 30, and 31) did not contain a terminal Cys residue that is essential for cyclization by POPB (Luo et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]) but instead contained the similar amino acid Ser.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Predicted peptide sequences of the MSDIN family members in <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> (<italic>Ab</italic>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_3378_Tab3_HTML" id="MO2"/><table-wrap-foot><p>Core regions are underlined. Spaces were introduced after some of the core sequences to emphasize alignments of the follower sequences. &#x0201c;Transcript&#x0201d; indicates whether the sequence was found by RNAseq in the transcriptome of <italic>Ab</italic>
</p><p>Notes:</p><p>1. Core region previously reported from <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]</p><p>2. Core region previously reported from <italic>A. exitialis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]</p><p>3. Core region previously reported from <italic>A. rimosa</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</p><p>4. Core region previously reported from <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</p><p>*indicates a stop codon</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>Many of the <italic>Ab</italic> MSDIN genes were clustered in the genome (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Abis_msdin_4 and 5, both encoding phallacidin, were found on Scaffold_1670. Scaffold_6767 had four MSDIN genes including Abis_msdin_15 and 16, both of which encode &#x003b1;-amanitin. Three genes with identical core sequences (IIFEPIIP) were found on Scaffold_8371. Two genes on Scaffold_9849 (Ab_msdin_30 and 31), encoded nearly identical core regions (IWWYIYFP and IFWYIYFP). Scaffold_3610 contained two MSDIN genes with dissimilar core sequences, Abis_msdin_11 and 12.</p><p>In both <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic>, a number of additional sequences were identified that showed some similarity to the MSDIN family but that were truncated or considered excessively divergent to be conclusively identified as members of the family. However, of possible significance to the evolution of the MSDIN gene family, two nearly identical sequences in <italic>Ab</italic> lacked any core sequences whatsoever (MSGINAARLP/AVGDDVEMVLRRGKR and MSGINAARLP/AVGDDVEMVLRRGER; the slash indicates where the core sequence would be). Despite the similarities to MSDIN genes, these loci were left unannotated.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Orthology between <italic>Ap, Ab</italic>, and <italic>A. muscaria</italic></title><p>
<italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> are both in sect. <italic>Phalloideae</italic> of subgenus <italic>Lepidella</italic>, and <italic>A. muscaria</italic> is in sect. <italic>Amanita</italic> of subgenus <italic>Amanita</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The orthology analysis resulted in a total of 7843 ortholog groups of which 4464 contained at least one protein from each of the three species. There were 892 ortholog groups that contained proteins from only <italic>Am</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic>, 591 groups with proteins only from <italic>Am</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic>, and 379 groups consisting of proteins only from <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab.</italic> The remaining 1517 groups each contained proteins from only one species. Both the POP genes and the MSDIN genes were clustered within the ortholog groups (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2). One group containing eight proteins included both POPA and POPB from both <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> and one protein from <italic>A. muscaria</italic> (jgi|Amamu1|74086|e_gw1.11.99.1) (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2). This protein is annotated as a prolyl oligopeptidase by JGI and a blastp search against the NCBI nr database shows it shares 77% identity with POPA from <italic>Ab</italic> (ADN19204.1) and 66% identity with POPA from <italic>Gm</italic> (AEX26937.2). The <italic>A. muscaria</italic> gene is therefore probably the ortholog of POPA, the &#x0201c;housekeeping&#x0201d; POP (see below).</p><p>An additional twelve orthologous groups were found to contain MSDIN proteins. Seven of these contained proteins from a single species (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2). One of these groups contained two copies of phalloidin in <italic>Ap</italic> (Apha_msdin_26 and 29). In another of these single species ortholog groups, cycloamanide B (Apha_msdin_27) was predicted to be an ortholog of Apha_msdin_25, the only difference being a single amino acid subsitution (SFFFPVP to SFFFPIP) in the core region. The remaining five ortholog groups all contained proteins from both <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic>. One contained two identical core regions, Apha_msdin_9 and Abis_msdin_20, a presumptive peptide shared between the species. One group contained three identical core regions identified as phallacidin, two from <italic>Ab</italic> and one from <italic>Ap</italic>. &#x003b1;-Amanitin in <italic>Ap</italic> (Apha_msdin_15) grouped with one MSDIN from <italic>Ab</italic> (Abis_msdin_19) as well as a second <italic>Ap</italic> protein (Apha_msdin_2). The final two groups contained orthologs from both <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic> with one or more differences within the core regions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Comparison of the MSDIN family in <italic>Ap</italic>, <italic>Ab</italic>, and other <italic>Amanita</italic> species</title><p>
<italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> together contained a total of 64 MSDIN sequences representing 54 unique core regions (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Only &#x003b1;-amanitin, phallacidin, and one unnamed predicted octapeptide (Aph_msdin_9 and Abis_msdin_20, with core region sequence ISDPTAYP) were common between <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic>. Overall, <italic>Ap</italic> has 29 non-duplicate core regions and <italic>Ab</italic> has 27.</p><p>Tryptathione, the cross-bridge formed between Trp and Cys, is a hallmark of the amatoxins and phallotoxins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Only one gene (Abis_msdin_26) encodes a novel peptide capable of containing tryptathionine, i.e., core sequence AWLAECP. It differs by one amino acid from phalloidin, having Glu instead of Thr at amino acid #5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. In having an acidic residue at position #5, it resembles phallacidin. This core sequence was also present in <italic>Amanita rimosa</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. All of the other MSDIN genes probably encode monocyclic peptides.</p><p>The MSDIN family in <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> has some overlap with the MSDIN family in <italic>A. exitialis</italic>, a mushroom implicated in multiple human poisonings in China [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In addition to &#x003b1;-amanitin, &#x003b2;-amanitin, and phallacidin, the transcriptome of <italic>A. exitialis</italic> contains genes encoding LFFPPDFRPP (Abis_msdin_8) and IFWFIYFP (Apha_msdin_28). Neither <italic>Ab</italic> nor <italic>Ap</italic> contains a gene for the nonapeptide amanexitide, cyclo(VFSLPVFFP), which was isolated from <italic>A. exitialis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Expression of the novel MSDIN family members</title><p>To determine whether any of the novel MSDIN family members were expressed, RNASeq was performed with mRNA extracted from <italic>Ab</italic> basidiocarps. Transcripts for 20 unique (i.e., counting duplicated genes only once) MSDIN sequences were detected (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), including phallacidin and &#x003b1;-amanitin. In every case, the transcript sequences confirmed the presence of an intron interrupting the fourth from the last codon (including the stop codon). The strong consensus for the last two amino acids of the MSDIN family precursor peptides was Leu-Cys (see below).</p><p>It was of particular interest whether any of the novel MSDIN genes were expressed at the level of actual cyclic peptides. <italic>Ap</italic> is known to produce cyclic peptides other than the bicyclic amatoxins and phallotoxins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. These include the cycloamanides and antamanide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The four known cycloamanides are monocyclic hexa-, hepta-, or octapeptides, and antamanide is a monocyclic decapeptide. Other than being cyclized, none have the post-translational modifications characteristic of the amatoxins and phallotoxins such as tryptathionine bridge formation, hydroxylation, and &#x003b1;-carbon epimerization. Although the cycloamanides are considered to be non-toxic to mammals, some have immunosuppressive activity, and antamanide (cyclo[FFVPPAFFPP]) protects mice against the toxic effects of phallotoxins and blocks mitochondrial pore formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. <italic>Ap</italic> had a gene (Apha_msdin_27) encoding cycloamanide B, cyclo(SFFFPIP). We did not find genes for any of the other cycloamanides or antamanide in <italic>Ap</italic> or <italic>Ab</italic>. However, predicted decapeptides related to antamanide were present in both <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab. Ap</italic> contained FFFPPFFIPP (Apha_msdin_21), IRLPPLFLPP (Apha_msdin_18), LRLPPFMIPP (Apha_msdin 19), and FIFPPFIIPP (Apha_msdin_20). <italic>Ab</italic> contained FFQPPEFRPP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and LFFPPDFRPP (Abis_msdin_8) and LFYPPDFRPP (Abis_msdin_9). The consensus for these seven decapeptide sequences (XXXPPXXXPP) contains two pairs of Pro residues.</p><p>To determine if any of the novel predicted peptides were produced, extracts of <italic>Ap</italic> were fractionated by high performance LC, and the masses of the unknown cyclic peptides in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> were monitored by mass spectrometry (MS). Masses corresponding to the cyclized versions with zero to four hydroxylations were extracted based on analogy to the phallotoxins and amatoxins, which can each have up to four hydroxylations.</p><p>&#x003b1;-Amanitin, &#x003b2;-amanitin, phalloidin, phallacidin, and several minor toxins (&#x003b3;-amanitin, amanin, phallisacin, and others) were detectable by LC/MS in <italic>Ap</italic> extracted by the standard 50% methanol procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. All of the known amatoxins and phallotoxins can be encoded by just four genes, corresponding to core peptide sequences IWGIGCNP, IWGIGCDP, AWLVDCP, and AWLATCP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. No compounds with the predicted masses of any of the hypothetical peptides with novel core sequences were detected in the methanol extracts except one compound of M&#x02009;+&#x02009;H<sup>+</sup> of m/z 893, which could correspond to cyclo(ISDPTAYP) with three hydroxylations. On the basis of its mass, this compound was purified by two steps of reverse phase chromatography. Its relative UV absorbances at 257, 280, 295, and 305&#x000a0;nm were consistent with the presence of Tyr. However, the high resolution monoisotopic mass of the compound as determined by ToF/MS was 892.3201, giving a most probable elemental formula of C<sub>34</sub>H<sub>52</sub>N<sub>8</sub>O<sub>20</sub>. The elemental composition of the putative trihydroxylated derivative of cyclo(ISDPTAYP) would be C<sub>39</sub>H<sub>56</sub>N<sub>8</sub>O<sub>16</sub>, giving a monoisotopic mass of 892.3814. The mass discrepancy (68&#x000a0;ppm), supported by the relative heights of the <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>12</sup>C signals, precluded the novel compound from being the predicted cyclic peptide. Elucidation of the structure of the compound of m/z 892.32 is in progress.</p><p>Many of the predicted novel peptides have a preponderance of hydrophobic amino acids, and the cycloamanides were originally found in the lipophilic extracts of <italic>Ap</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Hydrophobicity is an important pharmacokinetic property because it affects both the water solubility and the membrane permeability of a peptide. Therefore, ethanol/chloroform extracts of <italic>Ap</italic> were also analyzed by LC/MS. Nominal masses corresponding to some of the predicted unmodified cyclized peptides in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> were detected. One of m/z 822.4 could correspond to Apha_msdin_25, cyclo(SFFFPVP), which differs by one amino acid from cycloamanide B. This compound was analyzed in more detail by MS/MS and mMass [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The elemental composition (C<sub>45</sub>H<sub>56</sub>N<sub>7</sub>O<sub>9</sub>) was consistent with this structure (predicted m/z 822.4190; m/z observed 822.4218; 3.4&#x000a0;ppm mass discrepancy). Furthermore, the MS/MS fragmentation pattern and analysis by mMass strongly supported the predicted amino acid composition and sequence, i.e., sequential loss of Val, Pro, Phe, Phe, and Phe and giving overlapping peptide fragments for full coverage of the cyclic backbone (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S2). This new compound, predicted from the genome sequence, has been named cycloamanide E. LC/MS/MS also indicated the presence of another novel cycloamanide, Apha_msdin_5, with a structure of cyclo(IVGILGLP). This compound, eluting at 14.97&#x000a0;min, had a mass of 763.5118 (predicted m/z 763.5076, 5.5&#x000a0;ppm mass discrepancy) and mMass analysis indicated the expected amino acid composition and sequence (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S3).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Amino acid distribution in the core regions</title><p>As previously reported for <italic>Ab</italic> based on its partial genome sequence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], the core regions of the MSDIN family in the full genomic complement of both <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic> were more variable than the leader and follower sequences (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The predicted core peptides ranged in size from 6 to 10 amino acids with a mean of 8.2 in <italic>Ap</italic> and 8.4 in <italic>Ab</italic> and a mode of 8 in both (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>WebLogo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] alignment of MSDIN sequences from the genomes of <bold>a</bold>
<italic>A. phalloides</italic> and <bold>b</bold>
<italic>A. bisporigera</italic>. <bold>c</bold> Alignment of predicted precursor peptides from the transcriptome of <italic>A. bisporigera</italic>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_3378_Fig1_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p><p>The distribution of amino acids in the core regions of the MSDIN family were similar in <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3). Every proteinogenic amino acid was found in at least one MSDIN family member. Pro was the most abundant amino acid in the core regions of both species. This was due to not just the conserved terminal Pro required for processing by POPB but also to a disproportionately high number of internal Pro residues. There was also an overall bias towards the hydrophobic amino acids Ile and Phe and against charged and polar residues such as Thr, Arg, and Ser (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Observed vs. expected amino acid distribution in the core regions of the MSDIN peptides from <italic>Ap</italic>. Hydrophobic amino acids are shown in red and polar/charged amino acids in green. The line indicates a slope&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 (no bias). Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3 shows the results for <italic>Ab</italic>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_3378_Fig2_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Conservation in the leader and follower sequences</title><p>In addition to the two Pro residues required for processing by POPB, two Leu residues in the C-terminus, seven residues apart, are highly conserved in the MSDIN precursor peptides (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Although the C-terminus of the &#x003b1;-amanitin gene (<italic>AMA1</italic>) of <italic>Gm</italic> is highly divergent from that of <italic>Ab</italic>, both have Leu and either Leu (in the case of <italic>Ab</italic>) or the similar amino acid Ile (in the case of <italic>Gm</italic>) at the same positions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. These observations are consistent with the importance of an amphipathic &#x003b1;-helix in the C-terminal portion of the precursor peptide for correct cyclization by POPB, as was hypothesized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p>Changing the terminal Cys to Ala inhibits cyclization by GmPOPB of the &#x003b1;-amanitin precursor peptide GmAMA1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Several of the precursor peptides predicted end in Ser rather than the canonical Cys (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). However due to their chemically similar side chains it is possible that Ser can functionally subsitute for Cys.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>MSDIN peptides previously reported from the genome of <italic>Ab</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] but not found in the current genome sequence. ILMLAILP (#6) was also reported by Zhou et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] from <italic>Ab</italic>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_3378_Tab4_HTML" id="MO5"/></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Determination of the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region sequences in <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic></title><p>The ITS sequences of both <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic> were obtained from the genome sequences using the ITS sequence of <italic>Ab</italic> as query (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figures S4 and S5). The <italic>Ap</italic> ITS sequence showed 100% identity with GenBank accessions GQ250407, EU909444, KF535946, GQ221841, and U909441, as well as many others, all of which are annotated as <italic>A. phalloides</italic>. The ITS region of the specimen of <italic>Ab</italic> sequenced in the current work was 100% identical to GenBank accessions GQ166893 and KJ638292, both of which are annotated as <italic>A. bisporigera</italic>, and 99% identical to KP221303, KJ466421, and several others annotated as <italic>A. suballiacea</italic>. The ITS region was also 98&#x02013;99% identical to GenBank accessions annotated as <italic>Amanita</italic> sp. &#x02018;sp-O01&#x02019;, <italic>Amanita</italic> sp. &#x02018;5 ZLY-2014&#x02019;, <italic>A. virosa</italic>, or <italic>A. ocreata</italic>. Most of these sequences and the specimens from which they were obtained have not been described outside of GenBank. The ITS of the specimen of <italic>Ab</italic> sequenced in this paper was 92% identical to the ITS sequence of the specimen of <italic>Ab</italic> sequenced earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], which was deposited in GenBank in 2004 with accession number AY550243. Since then, many additional <italic>Amanita</italic> ITS sequences have been deposited in GenBank. As of this writing, AY550243 shows 99&#x02013;100% identity with sequences annotated as <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> (KR919771 and KR919772), <italic>A. virosa</italic> (HQ539860 and HQ539756), <italic>A. phalloides</italic> (HQ539826, HQ539722, and DQ071721), <italic>A. marmorata</italic> (HQ539813), and <italic>A. verna</italic> (HQ539859). That is, there appear to be many discrepancies between ITS sequences and fungal nomenclature in regard to <italic>Ab</italic> and its close relatives.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>MSDIN gene family differences within <italic>Ab</italic></title><p>Based on a partial genome sequence, 14 members of the MSDIN family were earlier described from <italic>Ab</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. The genome of <italic>Ab</italic> described in the current work has 31 total and 27 unique MSDIN family members (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Surprisingly, 9 of the 14 sequences described in Hallen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] were not found in the current genome sequence (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). In contrast, all eight of the previously described MSDIN sequences from <italic>Ap</italic> were present in the current <italic>Ap</italic> genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. A possible explanation for the result with <italic>Ab</italic> comes from consideration of the relatively low identity of the ITS regions (92%) of the specimen sequenced here compared to the one sequenced earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. That is, despite their morphological similarity and having been collected in the same location, the specimen sequenced earlier and the one sequenced in this paper are sufficiently different that it is reasonable to consider them to be distinct species, and this is reflected in their different complement of MSDIN sequences.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Annotation and analysis of prolyl oligopeptidase (POP) genes</title><p>The initial post-translational processing of the MSDIN precursor peptides is catalyzed in <italic>Gm</italic> by a specialized prolyl oligopeptidase called POPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. GmPOPB differs from GmPOPA and from other POPs from other organisms in several respects. First, GmPOPB can act on larger peptides (at least 35 amino acids) compared to other POPs, which are limited to peptides of ~30 amino acids. Second, it poorly utilizes the model substrate <italic>Z</italic>-Gly-Pro-<italic>p</italic>-nitroanilide compared to other POPs. Third, it can catalyze not only peptide bond hydrolysis but also transpeptidation, thereby converting the 35-amino acid &#x003b1;-amanitin precursor peptide to cyclo(IWGIGCNP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p>The intron/exon structures of the POPA and POPB genes of <italic>Ab</italic> (<italic>AbPOPA</italic> and <italic>AbPOPB</italic>, respectively) had been experimentally determined previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Predicted POPA and POPB proteins from <italic>A. muscaria</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> were aligned to the draft <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic> genome assemblies, and these alignments along with SNAP and AUGUSTUS <italic>ab initio</italic> gene predictions were used to guide manual annotation of the <italic>Ap</italic> POP genes. <italic>ApPOPA</italic> was found on Scaffold_578, and <italic>ApPOPB</italic> on Scaffold_897. <italic>AbPOPA</italic> was found on Scaffold_8964. <italic>AbPOPB</italic> was on Scaffold_1287, but the underlying sequence contains several gaps. The POP gene models were added to the final annotation, protein, and transcript files.</p><p>Searching all Ascomycota and Basidiomycota sequences in the JGI databases using BLASTP and either POPA or POPB as queries indicated that POP genes are present throughout the Basidiomycota but there are no clear POP homologs in any species in the Ascomycota. The lack of POP genes in the Ascomycota is surprising because POPs are clearly present in all other branches of life, including bacteria, plants, and animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Most Basidiomycota have a single POP gene, including <italic>A. muscaria</italic> and <italic>A. thiersii</italic>, which do not have the MSDIN gene family and do not produce known cyclic peptide toxins. However, the cyclic peptide-producing fungi that have been sequenced (i.e., <italic>Ab</italic>, <italic>Ap</italic>, and <italic>Gm</italic>) each have two POPs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. When aligned, the POPAs of the toxin-producing fungi and the single POP proteins of <italic>A. muscaria</italic> and <italic>A. thiersii</italic> formed one clade and the POPBs formed another (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). This is consistent with POPA representing a &#x0201c;housekeeping&#x0201d; enzyme, albeit of unknown function, and POPB being a POP dedicated to cyclic peptide biosynthesis. Despite the greater taxonomic distance between <italic>Galerina</italic> (family Strophariaceae) and <italic>Amanita</italic> (family Amanitaceae) than between <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic>, POPA of <italic>Gm</italic> more closely aligned with the POPAs of the two <italic>Amanita</italic> species than to its own POPB (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The POPBs showed the same relationship. The clustering of POPBs with each other and POPAs with each other was also true when just the catalytic domains or just the propeller domains were aligned (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S6). This suggests that both domains contribute to the unique catalytic properties of POPB.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree based on alignment of POP proteins from species of <italic>Amanita</italic>, <italic>Galerina marginata</italic>, and porcine (<italic>Sus scrofa</italic>). Ap, <italic>A. phalloides</italic>; Ab<italic>, A. bisporigera</italic>; Amusc, <italic>A. muscaria</italic>; Athier<italic>, A. thiersii</italic>; Gm, <italic>G. marginata</italic>. GenBank acession numbers of AbPOPA, AbPOPB, GmPOPA, and GmPOPB are ADN19204, ADN19205, AEX26937, and AEX26938, respectively. JGI identifiers for AmuscPOP and AthierPOP are Amamu1|74086 and Amath1|193040, respectively. POPB proteins are in red and underlined. Protein alignments and tree construction were performed using UPGMA within ClustalW and 500 bootstrap replicates in MEGA version 6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_3378_Fig3_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Gene clustering of MSDIN genes and POPB genes</title><p>In <italic>Gm</italic>, POPB is clustered with one of the two copies of <italic>AMA1</italic>, encoding the precursor peptide of &#x003b1;-amanitin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. A 15-kb genomic lambda clone from the specimen of <italic>Ab</italic> sequenced earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] contained the <italic>AbPOPB</italic> gene and one of the MSDIN family members (variable region GAYPPVPMP, which was present in the earlier <italic>Ab</italic> genome survey sequence but not in the current <italic>Ab</italic> genome) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Otherwise, the current results did not reveal any further evidence of clustering of POPB with any member of the MSDIN family in either <italic>Ab</italic> or <italic>Ap</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Based on their complete genomes, <italic>Amanita phalloides</italic> (<italic>Ap</italic>) and <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> (<italic>Ab</italic>) together have the genetic capacity to encode more than 50 unique small, cyclic peptides on the same biosynthetic scaffold that they use to biosynthesize the amatoxins and phallotoxins. Additional members of the MSDIN gene family have been described in other species of <italic>Amanita</italic> sect. <italic>Phalloideae</italic>, including <italic>A. ocreata</italic>, <italic>A. exitialis</italic>, <italic>A. rimosa</italic>, and others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], indicating that collectively this taxon has a large capacity to make a diversity of small peptides. Most of them are predicted to be cyclic but otherwise unmodified, like the cycloamanides, but it is possible that some of them are further modified by, e.g., hydroxylations, like the amatoxins and phallotoxins.</p><p>There is little overlap in the complement of MSDIN genes between species. <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic> have only three MSDIN genes in common (&#x003b1;-amanitin, phallacidin, and Apha_msdin_9/Abis_msdin_20). <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>A. exitialis</italic> (whose complete genome has not yet been reported) have three known genes in common (&#x003b1;-amanitin, phallacidin, and Abis_msdin_8). <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>A. exitialis</italic> have four genes in common: &#x003b1;-amanitin, &#x003b2;-amanitin, phallacidin, and Apha_msdin_28. Because the genome assemblies that we have prepared for <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> are draft quality assemblies, it is possible that additional MSDIN genes are present in the genomes of the two species.</p><p>Surprisingly, the majority of the MSDIN genes found earlier in <italic>Ab</italic> were not present in the current <italic>Ab</italic> genome. The ones in common were &#x003b1;-amanitin, phallacidin, and three unknowns. The most plausible explanation for this is that the two specimens, both identified on morphological criteria as &#x0201c;<italic>A. bisporigera</italic>&#x0201d;, are, in fact, different species. This is supported by comparison of their ITS sequences. Considering the high degree of variation between the MSDIN complement of <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic> and between both specimens of <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>A. exitialis</italic>, the degree of variation we observed between the two specimens of <italic>Ab</italic> seems consistent with them being distinct species. This result also suggests that within <italic>Amanita</italic> sect. <italic>Phalloideae</italic> the MSDIN gene family is even larger than our current taxonomic understanding would indicate.</p><p>In contrast to <italic>Ab</italic> sensu lato, analyses of the toxins and MSDIN genes of <italic>Ap</italic> are consistent with it being a single, discrete species. Li et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] identified six MSDIN genes by PCR from a specimen of <italic>Ap</italic> collected in Italy. All six genes were present in our isolate of <italic>Ap</italic> collected in California. The genomic similarity between Italian and California isolates of <italic>Ap</italic> is consistent with their similar chemical profiles and the recent introduction of <italic>Ap</italic> from Europe into North America [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p><p>Of the known chemically characterized cyclic peptides from <italic>Ap</italic>, genes encoding &#x003b1;-amanitin, &#x003b2;-amanitin, phalloidin, phallacidin, and cycloamanide B were present in the <italic>Ap</italic> genome. These five compounds are historically known to be made by specimens of <italic>Ap</italic> from Germany [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. However, we did not find genes for cycloamanide A, C, and D, nor a gene for the cyclic decapeptide antamanide. The absence of these genes could be due to gaps in our genome assemblies or to natural variation.</p><p>Among all the species of <italic>Amanita</italic> whose MSDIN genes have been studied, most members of this family are unique to one species, and only a few are common to more than one. The most widely distributed gene throughout sect. <italic>Phalloideae</italic> encodes &#x003b1;-amanitin. &#x003b1;-Amanitin is highly toxic to insects, mammals, nematodes, and other organisms, and is responsible for &#x0003e;95% of the human deaths from mushroom poisoning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Although the biological rationale for its production is not known, its strong activity and widespread occurrence suggests that it confers a strong selective advantage to the producing fungi. &#x003b2;-Amanitin, phalloidin, and phallacidin are also common, but not universal, in <italic>Amanita</italic> sect. <italic>Phalloideae</italic>. &#x003b2;-Amanitin is as toxic to mammals as &#x003b1;-amanitin, and although the phallotoxins are not toxic to mammals when consumed orally, they might be toxic to other mycovores such as insects.</p><p>The genomic information predicted the existence of multiple novel cyclic peptides. Two of them were found in the lipophilic fractions from extracts of <italic>Ap</italic>. The novel compounds, cyclo(SFFFPVP) and cyclo(IVGILGLP), are rich in hydrophobic amino acids. Following the earlier naming of cycloamanides A-D, we have given them the trivial names cycloamanide E and F, respectively. This result is another example demonstrating the utility of genomics for the discovery of novel secondary metabolites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. We predict that many of the other MSDIN genes in <italic>Ap</italic>, <italic>Ab</italic>, and other <italic>Amanita</italic> species will also be expressed at the chemical level. Although cycloamanides A, B, and E are not post-translationally modified other than by cyclization, cycloamanides C and D contain oxidized methionine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. It is therefore possible that some of the other chemical products of the MSDIN family might also be post-translationally modified, which would make their detection by LC/MS more difficult.</p><p>Within the genus <italic>Amanita</italic>, the MSDIN family is found only in section <italic>Phalloideae</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. However, &#x003b1;-amanitin is also produced by other agarics including some species of <italic>Galerina</italic> and <italic>Lepiota</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Like <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic>, <italic>Gm</italic> produces &#x003b1;-amanitin on ribosomes as a 35-amino acid precursor peptide. However, outside the core region itself the primary sequences of the &#x003b1;-amanitin genes of <italic>Gm</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> are highly divergent, although both are predicted to form amphipathic &#x003b1;-helices in their C-termini (i.e., follower) regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. This conserved secondary structure might be important for correct processing by POPB. Another difference betwen <italic>Gm</italic> and toxin-producing species of <italic>Amanita</italic> is that the genome of <italic>Gm</italic> has only two copies of the gene for &#x003b1;-amanitin and no extended MSDIN-like family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The genes for &#x003b1;-amanitin have not yet been described from any species of <italic>Lepiota</italic>.</p><p>Known biological activities of the MSDIN family to date include inhibition of RNA polymerase II (amatoxins), stabilization of F-actin (phallotoxins), immunosuppression (cycloamanides), protection of hepatocytes against phallotoxins and amatoxins (antamanide), and blocking the mitochondrial permeability transition pore (antamanide) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. It is unknown what, if any, biological activities the other predicted cyclic peptides in the genomes of <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> might have, but their evolutionary persistence suggests that they confer some selective advantage to the producing fungi. Furthermore, the observation that the core regions of the MSDIN family show strong amino acid bias suggests that the core sequences are not mutating randomly. That is, if they were mainly nonexpressed and conferred no advantage to the producing fungi, the core regions would not show any amino acid bias. An adaptive function implies that they have biological activities at the molecular level, which are as yet unknown. The natural function of none of the <italic>Amanita</italic> cyclic peptides are known, but could perhaps protect the fruiting bodies against mycophagy by insects, nematodes, or gastropods.</p><p>Currently, only small quantities of the known minor peptides such as the cycloamanides are available because cyclic peptide-producing fungi are obligately ectomycorrhizal and are difficult or impossible to culture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. However, it may be possible to make compounds such as cycloamanide E in vitro from 25mer or 35mer linear precursors using the macrocyclase activity of POPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Two toxic species of <italic>Amanita </italic>have large but essentially non-overlapping potential for cyclic peptide biosynthesis. The MSDIN family of ribosomally encoded peptides is evolving rapidly in <italic>Amanita </italic>section <italic>Phalloideae</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec18"><title>Biological materials and nucleic acid extraction</title><p>An individual basidiocarp of <italic>A. phalloides</italic> (<italic>Ap</italic>) was collected in Alameda County, California, in the winter of 2011, and an individual basidiocarp&#x000a0;of <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> (<italic>Ab</italic>) was collected in Ingham County, Michigan, in the summer of 2010. The <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> specimen used in this work was collected in the same location as the <italic>A. bisporigera</italic> specimen earlier analyzed by pyrosequencing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. DNA and RNA were extracted using cetyltrimethyl ammonium bromide (CTAB), phenol, and chloroform and sequenced by Illumina MiSeq technology. RNA from the same specimen of <italic>Ab</italic> was reverse-transcribed and sequenced by Illumina HiSeq technology.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Sequencing and assembly</title><p>Paired-end DNA libraries for both <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> were preprocessed to remove sequencing adaptors and low quality reads using Trimmomatic version 0.32 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Leading and trailing low quality bases (below quality score 20) were trimmed, and reads with a length of less than 100&#x000a0;bp were removed. In addition, the three mate-pair libraries (2&#x000a0;kb, 4&#x000a0;kb and 6&#x000a0;kb nominal insert sizes) for <italic>Ap</italic> were trimmed by Trimmomatic and by NextClip version 1.3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], removing duplicates and discarding those reads that did not contain the adaptor in either read within the pair. For both <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic>, reads were assembled using Velvet version 1.2.10 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] (additional compiling to allow four libraries for <italic>Ap</italic>) with scaffolding enabled for both. The following parameters were used: a kmer length of 99, an expected coverage of 39X, and a coverage cutoff of 9. In addition, for the <italic>Ap</italic> assembly, Gapcloser was also used in gap close mode (asm_flags&#x02009;=&#x02009;4) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The resulting assemblies were assessed for contamination using the Blobology pipeline (version 20151102) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Raw reads linked to contamination were removed and the remaining reads reassembled with the same parameters. All contigs less than 1&#x000a0;kb were removed. The final assemblies were assessed for completeness using BUSCO version 2 with a beta version of the basidomycete-specfic database in genome mode [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p><p>For transcript sequences from <italic>Ab</italic>, a paired end RNA-seq library was preprocessed to remove sequencing adaptors and low quality reads using Trimmomatic, requiring a minimum length of 50&#x000a0;bp and trimming leading and trailing low quality bases that had quality scores less than 20. The reads were assembled using Trinity version 2.0.6 with default settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Annotation</title><p>The genome assemblies of <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic> were annotated using the MAKER pipeline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. A custom repeat library for <italic>Ap</italic> was created and used for repeat masking for both fungi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Publicly available proteins from NCBI for <italic>Amanita muscaria</italic>, <italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>, and <italic>Laccaria bicolor</italic> along with all manually curated fungal protein sequences from SwissProt were used as evidence to aid gene prediction within MAKER. Trinity transcript assemblies from <italic>Ab</italic> were also used in the annotation of the <italic>Ab</italic> genome. Genes were predicted by Augustus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], SNAP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] and GeneMark [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] within the MAKER pipeline, and where multiple predictions were made for a single locus, MAKER picked the prediction that was most concordant with the alignment evidence as the final gene model for that locus. GeneMark was run in both its ES and ET fungal-specific modes. High-quality gene models with transcript or protein alignment support or with predicted proteins containing a Pfam domain were retained for the final annotated gene set.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Functional annotation</title><p>The protein and transcript sequences from the final high-quality gene models were assigned functional annotation using the Trinotate version 2.0.2 pipeline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Functional annotation involved BLAST searches of both the transcripts and proteins against the Swissprot database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Protein domains, signal peptides and transmembane regions were predicted using HMMER v2.3.2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], SignalP version 4.1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], and tmHMM version 2.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The results of these searches were loaded into a Trinotate pre-generated SQLite database, and an annotation report was produced by the report function of Trinotate.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Annotation of MSDIN and POP genes</title><p>Alignments of known MSDIN genes were made within MAKER and used to manually annotate gene models for known and novel MSDIN and MSDIN-like genes. Manual annotation was facilitated with JBrowse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] for both <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> with tracks for MAKER-predicted gene models, protein alignments for <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic>, and transcript alignments for <italic>Ab</italic> as well as the known MSDIN blastp alignments. For both <italic>Ap</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic> predicted protein sequences from previous studies were used to help guide the gene predictions. When searching using known MSDIN peptide sequences in tblastn, the e-value cutoff was set to 100.</p><p>Previously elucidated POPA and POPB protein sequences were aligned within the MAKER pipeline to aid with manual annotation of POP gene models. MAKER gene predictions for POP loci were used as initial gene models that were hand-annotated based on transcript and POP protein alignments. The original MAKER-predicted gene models that overlapped the predicted POP genes were removed, and new manually created gene models were added.</p><p>Protein alignments and tree construction were performed using MEGA version 6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Alignments were performed with ClustalW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], and the tree was made using the UPGMA method with 500 bootstrap replicates.</p><p>All known MSDIN genes whose structures have been confirmed by sequencing of corresponding cDNA molecules have an intron interrupting the fourth from the last codon (including the stop codon), and most have Leu-Cys as the last two amino acids. For <italic>Ab</italic>, transcript evidence was also used to help elucidate intron/exon boundaries within MSDIN genes.</p><p>The majority of the <italic>Ab</italic> MSDIN genes had canonical intron acceptor/donor sequences, but the introns of four genes had non-canonical GC-AG acceptor/donor sequences (Abis_msdin_3, 4, 11, and 28). Lengths of the single exon-interrupting intron ranged between 52&#x02013;58&#x000a0;bp.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Ortholog and syntolog analysis between <italic>Ap, Ab</italic> and <italic>A. muscaria</italic></title><p>An ortholog search was executed using OrthoMCL version 1.4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] comparing the predicted proteins of <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ap</italic> with the published proteins from <italic>Amanita muscaria</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. During the alignment step, a BLAST e-value cutoff of 1e-10 was used. The resulting orthoMCL output file was parsed to identify ortholog groups containing genes from all three species, from only two <italic>Amanita</italic> species, or from only a single species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Toxin extraction and analysis</title><p>Lyophilized <italic>Ap</italic> basidiocarps were frozen in liquid nitrogen, ground with a mortar and pestle to a fine powder, and then extracted by one of two methods. In the first method, the powder was suspended in 50% H<sub>2</sub>O&#x02009;+&#x02009;40% HPLC-grade methanol&#x02009;+&#x02009;10% 0.1&#x000a0;M HCl at a concentration of 1&#x000a0;g mushroom tissue/50&#x000a0;ml. Extracts were analyzed by HPLC/MS using an Agilent 1200 HPLC system and a Higgins PROTO 300 C18 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m column (250 &#x000d7; 4.6&#x000a0;mm). Mobile phase A was 90% 0.02&#x000a0;M ammonium acetate, pH&#x000a0;5&#x02009;+&#x02009;10% acetonitrile, and mobile phase B was 76% 0.02&#x000a0;M ammonium acetate, pH&#x000a0;5&#x02009;+&#x02009;24% acetonitrile. The gradient program consisted of 0 to 8% B from 0&#x02013;4&#x000a0;min, 8 to 18% B from 4&#x02013;10&#x000a0;min, and 18 to 100% B from 10&#x02013;30&#x000a0;min. Eluant was monitored by UV absorbance and an in-line Agilent 6120 mass spectrometer in positive ESI mode. Capillary voltage was 5&#x000a0;kV and the drying gas (N<sub>2</sub>) temperature was 350&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C at a flow rate of 12&#x000a0;L/min. The scan range was m/z 580&#x02013;2000.</p><p>In the second method, the powder was resuspended in 90% ethanol at a concentration of 1&#x000a0;g/50&#x000a0;ml. After stirring for one hour at room temperature, the ethanol was removed under vacuum and the residue dissolved in CHCl<sub>3</sub>. The CHCl<sub>3</sub> was removed by evaporation and the residual oil redissolved in 50% acetontrile. This extract was analyzed using a Waters Xevo G2-XS QToF HPLC/MS/MS interfaced to a Waters Acquity UPLC system. Five microliters were injected onto a BEH C18 UPLC column (2.1&#x000a0;mm &#x000d7; 50&#x000a0;mm, 1.7-&#x003bc;m particle size; Waters Corp.). Column temperature was maintained at 30&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The flow rate was 0.3&#x000a0;mL/min with starting conditions at 95% solvent A (10&#x000a0;mM ammonium formate in water) and 5% solvent B (acetonitrile). The 30-min gradient profile for elution was as follows: starting at 5% solvent B and holding for 3&#x000a0;min, then a linear gradient to 99% B at 27&#x000a0;min, holding at 99% B for 1&#x000a0;min to 28&#x000a0;min, at 28.01&#x000a0;min returning to 95% A/5% B, and maintaining until 30&#x000a0;min. The MS settings were electrospray ionization in positive-ion mode, 3&#x000a0;kV capillary voltage, 100&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C source temperature, 350&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C desolvation temperature, 600&#x000a0;L/h desolvation nitrogen gas flow rate, and 35&#x000a0;V cone voltage. Data were acquired using an MS<sup>e</sup> method having two separate acquisition functions where function 1 was performed with no collision energy and function 2 was performed with a collision energy ramp from 60&#x02013;100&#x000a0;V. For both functions, the scan range was 50&#x02013;1500&#x000a0;m/z with a scan rate of 0.2&#x000a0;s per function. Data were analyzed using Masslynx v4.1 (Waters) and mMass v5.5.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p></sec></sec></body><back><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec25"><title>Additional file</title><p>
<media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_3378_MOESM1_ESM.docx" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1: Table S1.</label><caption><p>Maker annotation statistics for <italic>A. phalloides</italic> and <italic>A. bisporigera</italic>. <bold>Table S2</bold> OrthoMCL data comparing <italic>A. phalloides</italic>, A. bisporigera, and <italic>A. muscaria</italic>, showing only the ortholog groups that contain MSDIN or POP genes. Species are shown in parentheses: A.bis&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>A. bisporigera</italic>, A.pha&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>A. phalloides</italic> and A.mus&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>A. muscaria</italic>. <bold>Table S3</bold> Distribution of amino acids in the core regions of the MSDIN peptides in Ab and Ap. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the results for Ap graphically. <bold>Figure S1</bold> Distribution of MAKER standard gene model GC content for A. phalloides and A. bisporigera. Both species show unimodal GC distribution with peaks at 49 and 48%, respectively. <bold>Figure S2</bold> MS/MS spectrum for the compound eluting at 13.62 min (cycloamanide E). Insert: mMass report for the b-ion series [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. <bold>Figure S3</bold> MS/MS spectrum for the compound eluting at 14.97 min (cycloamanide F) and mMass report for the b-ion series [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. <bold>Figure S4</bold> Sequence of the ITS region of <italic>A. phalloides</italic>. <bold>Figure S5</bold> Sequence of the ITS region of <italic>A. bisporigera</italic>. <bold>Figure S6</bold> Phylogenetic tree of the catalytic (cat) and propeller (prop) regions of prolyl oligopeptidases (POPs) from species of <italic>Amanita</italic> and <italic>Galerina</italic>. POPAs are shown in black and POPBs in red. Ab, <italic>A. bisporigera</italic>; Ap, <italic>A. phalloides</italic>; Ath, <italic>A. thiersii</italic>; Am, <italic>A. muscaria</italic>; Gm, <italic>G. marginata</italic>. (DOCX 581 kb)</p></caption></media>
</p></sec></app></app-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term><italic>Ab</italic></term><def><p>
<italic>Amanita bisporigera</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>Ap</italic></term><def><p>
<italic>A. phalloides</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>Gm</italic></term><def><p>
<italic>Galerina marginata</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LC</term><def><p>Liquid chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MS</term><def><p>Mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>POP</term><def><p>Prolyl oligopeptidase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ToF</term><def><p>Time of flight</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Kevin Carr and the MSU Research Technical Support Facility for 454 and Illumina genome and transcriptome sequencing bioinformatics support, Heather Hallen-Adams (University of Nebraska-Lincoln) and Rod Tulloss (Herbarium Amanitarum Rooseveltensis) for discussions about <italic>Amanita</italic> taxonomy and nomenclature, and Dan Jones and Tony Schilmiller of the RTSF Mass Spectrometry and Metabolomics Core Facility at Michigan State University for help with the MS analyses. The chloroform extracts of <italic>Ap</italic> were supplied by Richard Ransom (Funite, LLC).</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was supported by grant GM088274 to JDW from the U.S. National Institutes of Health General Medical Sciences and grant IOS&#x02013;1126998 to KLC from the U.S. National Science Foundation. Additional support came from Grant DE-FG02-91ER20021 to the Plant Research Laboratory from the Division of Chemical Sciences, Geosciences and Biosciences, Office of Basic Energy Sciences, U.S. Department of Energy.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>DNA and RNA Illumina sequence files used for the work described here have been deposited in the Sequence Read Archive at the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) under accession numbers SRR4041347, SRR4041817, SRR4041818, SRR4041819, SRR4041820 and SRR4041946. The genome assembly data have been placed in the NCBI Assembly database under accession numbers MEHY00000000 and MIPV00000000. Annotation GFF3 files and functional annotation files as well as transcript, protein, and genome assembly fasta files have also been deposited in the Dryad data repository (doi:10.5061/dryad.8k7jd).</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>JAP and KLC performed the bioinformatics analyses. JDW prepared the DNA and helped analyze the data and prepare the manuscript. RMS performed the LC/MS analyses. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>This article does not contain any studies with human participants or animals performed by any of the authors.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hallen</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott-Craig</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene family encoding the major toxins of lethal <italic>Amanita</italic> mushrooms</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>19097</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0707340104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18025465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18025465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnison</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bibb</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bierbaum</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bugni</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulaj</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ribosomally synthesized and post-translationally modified peptide natural products: overview and recommendations for a universal nomenclature</article-title><source>Nat Prod Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C2NP20085F</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23165928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23165928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umemura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Koke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the biosynthetic gene cluster for the ribosomally synthesized cyclic peptide ustiloxin B in <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic></article-title><source>Fung Genet Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2014.04.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Umemura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Izumikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Class of cyclic ribosomal peptide synthetic genes in filamentous fungi</article-title><source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2015.12.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26703898?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26703898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Donk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthetic investigation of phomopsins reveals a widespread pathway for ribosomal natural products in Ascomycetes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2016</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>3521</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1522907113</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26979951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26979951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular diversity of toxin gene families in lethal <italic>Amanita</italic> mushrooms</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><year>2014</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxicon.2014.02.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24613547?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24613547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallen</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott-Craig</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ribosomal biosynthesis of &#x003b1;-amanitin in <italic>Galerina marginata</italic></article-title><source>Fung Genet Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2011.12.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Floudas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Held</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extensive sampling of basidiomycete genomes demonstrates inadequacy of the white rot/brown rot paradigm for wood decay fungi</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>9923</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1400592111</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24958869?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24958869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sgambelluri</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peptide macrocyclization catalyzed by a prolyl oligopeptidase involved in &#x003b1;-amanitin biosynthesis</article-title><source>Chem Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1610</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chembiol.2014.10.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25484237?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25484237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallen-Adams</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott-Craig</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Co-localization of amanitin and a candidate toxin-processing prolyl oligopeptidase in <italic>Amanita</italic> basidiocarps</article-title><source>Eukaryot Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1891</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/EC.00161-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20889720?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20889720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Koutsovoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaxter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blobology: exploring raw genome data for contaminants, symbionts and parasites using taxon-annotated GC-coverage plots</article-title><source>Front Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>237</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2013.00237</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24348509?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24348509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sim&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriventseva</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BUSCO: assessing genome assembly and annotation completeness with single-copy orthologs</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3210</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv351</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26059717?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26059717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantarel</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Robb</surname><given-names>SMC</given-names></name><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarado</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yandell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MAKER: an easy-to-use annotation pipeline designed for emerging model organism genomes</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.6743907</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18025269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18025269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Moghe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hufnagel</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MAKER-P: a tool-kit for the rapid creation, management, and quality control of plant genome annotations</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.230144</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24306534?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24306534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Peptides of poisonous Amanita mushrooms</source><year>1986</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Buscot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Convergent losses of decay mechanisms and rapid turnover of symbiosis genes in mycorrhizal mutualists</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3223</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25706625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25706625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tryptathionine bridges in peptide synthesis</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>2007</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>714</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bip.20807</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17626299?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17626299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Illumina-based de novo transcriptome sequencing and analysis of <italic>Amanita exitialis</italic> basidiocarps</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2013</year><volume>532</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2013.09.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24050899?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24050899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclopeptides from <italic>Amanita exitialis</italic></article-title><source>Nat Prod Bioprospect</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13659-011-0013-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gauhe A, Wieland T. Die Cycloamanide, monocyclische Peptide; Isolierung und Strukturaufkl&#x000e4;rung eines cyclischen Heptapeptids (CyA B) und zweier cyclischer Oktapeptide (CyA C und CyA D). Liebigs Ann Chem. 1977:859&#x02013;68.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wieczorek</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemion</surname><given-names>IZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimecki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolewska-Pedyczak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunosuppressive activity in the series of cycloamanide peptides from mushrooms</article-title><source>Peptides</source><year>1993</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0196-9781(93)90003-Y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8441706?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8441706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azzolin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Antolini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Calderan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruzza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sciacovelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antamanide, a derivative of <italic>Amanita phalloides</italic>, is a novel inhibitor of the mitochondrial permeability transition pore</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>e16280</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0016280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sgambelluri</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Epis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassera</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelos</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Profiling of amatoxins and phallotoxins in the genus <italic>Lepiota</italic> by liquid chromatography combined with UV absorbance and mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Toxins</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2336</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins6082336</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25098279?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25098279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niedermeyer</surname><given-names>THJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Strohalm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mMass as a software tool for the annotation of cyclic peptide tandem mass spectra</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e44913</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044913</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23028676?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23028676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallen-Adams</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Processing of the phalloidin proprotein by prolyl oligopeptidase from the mushroom <italic>Conocybe albipes</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>18070</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.006460</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19389704?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19389704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nallu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guhlin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting small plant peptides using SPADA (Small Peptide Alignment Discovery Application)</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>335</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-14-335</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24256031?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24256031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szeltner</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Polg&#x000e1;r</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure, function and biological relevance of prolyl oligopeptidase</article-title><source>Curr Protein Pept Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/138920308783565723</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18336325?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18336325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution and abundance of the introduced ectomycorrhizal fungus <italic>Amanita phalloides</italic> in North America</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2010</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.03097.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20002314?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20002314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bresinsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Besl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>A colour atlas of poisonous fungi</source><year>1990</year><publisher-loc>Regensburg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wolfe</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohimani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pevzner</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dereplication, sequencing and identification of peptidic natural products: from genome mining to peptidogenomics to spectral networks</article-title><source>Nat Prod Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5NP00050E</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26497201?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26497201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production and characterization of amanitin toxins from a pure culture of <italic>Amanita exitialis</italic></article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2005</year><volume>252</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.femsle.2005.08.049</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16198510?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16198510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2114</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu170</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24695404?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leggett</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clavijo</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clissold</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Caccamo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NextClip: an analysis and read preparation tool for Nextera long mate pair libraries</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt702</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24297520?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24297520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zerbino</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Velvet: algorithms for de novo short read assembly using de Bruijn graphs</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>821</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.074492.107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18349386?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18349386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SOAPdenovo2: an empirically improved memory-efficent short-read de novo assembler</article-title><source>GigaScience</source><year>2012</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>18</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2047-217X-1-18</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23587118?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23587118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amit</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-seq data without a reference genome</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1883</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21572440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Waack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene prediction with a hidden Markov model and a new intron submodel</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>ii215</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg1080</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14534192?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14534192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene finding in novel genomes</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-5-59</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15144565?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15144565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borodovsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomsadze</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eukaryotic gene prediction using GeneMark.hmm-E and GeneMark-ES</article-title><source>Curr Protoc Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>610</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>UniProt Consortium</collab></person-group><article-title>Activities at the Universal Protein Resource (UniProt)</article-title><source>Nucl Acids Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>D191</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24253303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HMMER web server: interactive sequence similarity searching</article-title><source>Nucl Acids Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>W29</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr367</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21593126?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21593126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Neilsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SignalP 4.0 discriminating singal peptides from transmembrane regions</article-title><source>Nature Meth</source><year>2011</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>785</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden Markov Model: application to complete genomes</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>305</volume><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.2000.4315</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11152613?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzilov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mungall</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>JBrowse: a next-generation genome browser</article-title><source>Gen Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1630</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.094607.109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0.</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2725</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst197</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24132122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackshields</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chenna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McGettigan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McWilliam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clustal W and Clustal X Version 2.0.</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>2947</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm404</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17846036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17846036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoeckert</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OrthoMCL: identification of ortholog groups for eukaryotic genomes</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2178</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.1224503</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12952885?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12952885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crooks</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandonia</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WebLogo: a sequence logo generator</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1188</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.849004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15173120?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15173120</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>