<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4407355</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">485</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-015-0485-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis of conglutin seed storage proteins across lupin species using transcriptomic, protein and comparative genomic approaches</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>Rhonda C</given-names></name><address><email>Rhonda.Foley@csiro.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jimenez-Lopez</surname><given-names>Jose C</given-names></name><address><email>Jose.Jimenez-Lopez@uwa.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kamphuis</surname><given-names>Lars G</given-names></name><address><email>Lars.Kamphuis@csiro.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hane</surname><given-names>James K</given-names></name><address><email>James.Hane@curtin.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Melser</surname><given-names>Su</given-names></name><address><email>su.melser@csiro.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Karam B</given-names></name><address><email>Karam.Singh@csiro.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>CSIRO Agriculture Flagship, Centre for Environment and Life Sciences, Floreat, WA Australia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>The UWA Institute of Agriculture, University of Western Australia, Crawley, WA Australia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Current address: Curtin Institute for Computation and Centre for Crop &#x00026; Disease Management, Department of Environment &#x00026; Agriculture, Curtin University, Bentley, Western Australia Australia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>106</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Foley et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p>The major proteins in lupin seeds are conglutins that have primary roles in supplying carbon, sulphur and nitrogen and energy for the germinating seedling. They fall into four families; &#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, &#x003b3; and &#x003b4;. Interest in these conglutins is growing as family members have been shown to have beneficial nutritional and pharmaceutical properties.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>An in-depth transcriptome and draft genome from the narrow-leafed lupin (NLL; <italic>Lupinus angustifolius</italic>) variety, Tanjil, were examined and 16 conglutin genes were identified. Using RNAseq data sets, the structure and expression of these 16 conglutin genes were analysed across eight lupin varieties from five lupin species. Phylogenic analysis suggest that the &#x003b1; and &#x003b3; conglutins diverged prior to lupin speciation while &#x003b2; and &#x003b4; members diverged both prior and after speciation. A comparison of the expression of the 16 conglutin genes was performed, and in general the conglutin genes showed similar levels of RNA expression among varieties within species, but quite distinct expression patterns between lupin species. Antibodies were generated against the specific conglutin families and immunoblot analyses were used to compare the levels of conglutin proteins in various tissues and during different stages of seed development in NLL, Tanjil, confirming the expression in the seed. This analysis showed that the conglutins were expressed highly at the mature seed stage, in all lupin species, and a range of polypeptide sizes were observed for each conglutin family.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study has provided substantial information on the complexity of the four conglutin families in a range of lupin species in terms of their gene structure, phylogenetic relationships as well as their relative RNA and protein abundance during seed development. The results demonstrate that the majority of the heterogeneity of conglutin polypeptides is likely to arise from post-translational modification from a limited number of precursor polypeptides rather than a large number of different genes. Overall, the results demonstrate a high degree of plasticity for conglutin expression during seed development in different lupin species.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12870-015-0485-6) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Seed storage</kwd><kwd>Seed development</kwd><kwd>Legumes</kwd><kwd>Seed transcriptome</kwd><kwd>Lupin varieties</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Background</title><p>Legumes form a very important group of crop plants for both animal and human consumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The genus <italic>Lupinus</italic> comprises between 200 and 600 species, the majority of which have not been domesticated. <italic>Lupinus</italic> are part of the genistoid clade which is quite distinct from other legume sister clades and are the least exploited group of legumes. Interest in lupins is growing as they have a number of attractive nutritional attributes relating to their high protein and dietary fibre contents and negligible starch. Recently, studies have also associated lupins with playing positive roles in health in areas such as combating obesity, diabetes and cardiovascular disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. For example, studies have demonstrated that &#x003b3; conglutin has an ability to reduce glycaemia to levels comparable to those obtained with metformin, a widely used hypoglycaemic drug [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Lupins are also valuable in sustainable agricultural systems through their ability to fix nitrogen, they also contribute high organic matter to the soil and are effective in breaking disease cycles for other crops such as cereals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Cultivation of lupins has occurred for thousands of years, and extensive boiling and steeping were required to rid the grain of their bitter and poisonous alkaloids. Modern lupins have been bred to have reduced alkaloid levels and are referred to as sweet lupins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p>The main seed storage proteins in lupins, referred to as conglutins, have been classified into four families; &#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, &#x003b3; and &#x003b4; conglutins. &#x003b1; conglutins have been shown to be degraded proteolytically at germination, confirming their role as a classical seed storage protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. &#x003b2; conglutins are abundant seed proteins as verified by quantitating protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] and transcript expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The bean &#x003b2; conglutin homolog, phaseolin, degrades during germination in a phosphorylation-dependent manner [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. As well as having a seed storage protein function, metabolism of &#x003b2; conglutins also acts to release lectins during germination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. &#x003b2; conglutins have also been shown to be potential allergens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. &#x003b3; conglutins may not fall into the classical seed storage category as the protein is not degraded like traditional seed storage proteins during germination, and &#x003b3; conglutins may also possess lectin-like activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Although &#x003b3; conglutins share structural similarities to xyloglucan-specific endo-beta-1,4-glucanase inhibitors, they lack the functional activity of glucanase inhibitors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. &#x003b4; conglutins have been the least studied conglutin family. They are small proteins that are localised in the vacuole [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], and have low-digestibility properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p><p>In this study we analysed the conglutins in a number of lupin species. <italic>L. angustifolius,</italic> (narrow-leafed lupin, NLL) is currently the most extensively cultivated lupin crop and is grown predominantly in South-Western Australia. Three NLL varieties were used in this study; P27255 is a wild variety available prior to domestication of NLL within Australia; Unicrop was one of the first domesticated Australian NLL varieties (released in 1973) as a sweet, non-shattering pod variety, and Tanjil is a more recent variety (released in 1998). Tanjil has resistance to the fungal pathogen, anthracnose (<italic>Colletotrichum spp</italic>.) and has emerged as the reference NLL/lupin variety for which a number of genomic resources have/are being developed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p><italic>L. albus</italic> (white lupin), is the lupin of preference in Europe and much of the nutritional work has been done on this species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The two varieties of <italic>L. albus</italic> used in this study were the Kiev mutant, a Ukrainian bred variety, and Andromeda, a variety with intermediate resistance to anthracnose. Similarly to <italic>L. angustifolus</italic> and <italic>L. albus</italic>, <italic>L. luteus</italic> is an &#x02018;Old World&#x02019;-smooth seeded species<italic>. L. luteus</italic> (yellow lupin) originates from the Mediterranean coastal regions and was domesticated as a grain legume in Europe by selecting for low alkaloid content, non-shattering pods and soft seeds. The <italic>L. luteus</italic> variety, Pootalong, used in this study is well adapted to acidic soils and the species is favoured by the aquaculture industry because of the high protein content. A <italic>L. luteus&#x02019;</italic> transcriptome has been generated using 454-expressed sequence tag libraries, and comparative studies using model legume species have identified a comprehensive set of molecular markers for yellow lupin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. In addition, a comprehensive seed-protein catalog has been developed for <italic>L. luteus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> (Andean or Pearl Lupin) is known as a &#x02018;New World&#x02019; lupin as it originated from South America. <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> has high oil, low alkaloid levels and high protein content. The <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> variety, ID13 was chosen for this study. <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> Guss (sandplain blue lupin) is referred to as an &#x02018;Old World&#x02019; &#x02013; rough seeded lupin and originated from North Africa. It grows prolifically in coastal South Western Australia. Breeding of this variety to produce a sweeter version developed the variety, Erregulla used in this study. However Erregulla, was highly susceptible to aphids and anthracnose and therefore was not released commercially.</p><p>This work expands on the study of NLL lupin conglutins reported by Foley et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], and adds new information on their gene structure and RNA and protein expression patterns both in NLL and other lupin species. Previously we reported the identification of sixteen individual seed storage protein genes and investigation of their expression in the species NLL cv Tanjil using EST sequencing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In this study, analysis of an in-depth Tanjil transcriptomic and draft genome sequence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] did not reveal any additional conglutins in Tanjil. The 16 Tanjil conglutin genes were used to identify homologous genes in seven other lupin varieties from five different lupin species using RNAseq data, which was also used to compare their respective RNA expression levels in seeds. Antibodies designed specifically against each conglutin family were used to analyse the protein levels of these four conglutin protein families in different tissues and at specific stages of seed development. In addition, the levels of these proteins among lupin varieties were compared.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Identification of conglutins sequence reads in lupin species</title><p>Transcriptomic studies using RNAseq data are valuable in identifying homologous sequences and RNA expression levels. In NLL a total of three &#x003b1; conglutins, seven &#x003b2; conglutins, two &#x003b3; conglutins and four &#x003b4; conglutins were previously identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. A draft genome survey assembly and comprehensive transcriptome assembly for Tanjil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] were searched to confirm the sequences of these conglutins and to potentially identify any additional conglutins with sequence similarity (&#x0003c;1<sup>e-5</sup>). This analysis confirmed the sequences of all &#x003b1;, &#x003b3; and &#x003b4; conglutins identified previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] and did not identify any additional conglutins in the NLL cv. Tanjil. In the case of the &#x003b2; conglutins, sequences for BETA1, 2, 5 and 7 were identified, whereas BETA3, 4 and 6 appeared to be mis-assembled in the survey genome assembly and formed contigs with alternate isoforms in the transcriptome assembly, which is most likely due to their high sequence similarity (85-99 % identity) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. As the genome survey only comprises 521&#x000a0;Mb of an estimated 924&#x000a0;Mb of genome sequence there remains the possibility that some additional conglutins have not been identified in the genome sequence. However, given that the Tanjil transcriptome, which contained a wide range of different developmental seed stages, and the additional seed transcriptome sequencing for Tanjil presented herein did not show any other transcripts with homology to the conglutins identified previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], it would appear unlikely that other conglutins are present in NLL cv. Tanjil.</p><p>The conglutins from NLL cv. Tanjil were subsequently used as reference sequences to assemble homologous sequences from transcriptome datasets generated for NLL cv. Unicrop and wild accession P27255, as well as other species in the genus <italic>Lupinus</italic>. This allowed consensus sequences for the eight lupin varieties/species to be retrieved by aligning the RNA seq data for each variety to the 16 Tanjil conglutin sequences. In the case of Tanjil, the extracted 16 conglutin consensus sequences from the RNAseq dataset were compared to the published NLL Tanjil sequences and these aligned very closely (99.6% -100% identity). In some instances stretches of unknown nucleotides were generated from the consensus extraction for other species, likely because of stretches of weaker alignment to Tanjil conglutins.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Phylogenetic relationships among conglutins from different lupin species</title><p>Each family of conglutin sequences generated from the eight varieties were aligned using the K-mer program within the CLC Genomics Workbench as shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. With respect to the &#x003b1; family, each lupin variety had three &#x003b1; sequences that were assembled against the Tanjil reference genes. In all instances, the &#x003b1; conglutins were able to be subdivided into three subgroups; ALPHA1, ALPHA2 or ALPHA3 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). This is in agreement with our previous observations which showed that the &#x003b1; conglutin, also known as 11S globulin subgroups, have duplicated and diverged prior to speciation in soybean, pea, peanut, medicago and NLL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Alignment using the Kmer program of <bold>A)</bold> ALPHA (1-3), <bold>B)</bold> BETA (1-7), <bold>C)</bold> GAMMA (1-2) and <bold>D)</bold> DELTA (1-4) DNA sequences extracted from RNAseq data sets from <italic>L. albus</italic> Andromeda (LalbA<italic>), L. albus</italic> Kiev (LalbK<italic>), L. angustifolus</italic> P27255 (LangP), <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Tanjil (LangT), <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Unicrop (LangU), <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> Erregulla (LcosE), <italic>L. luteus</italic> Pootalong (LlutP) and <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> ID13 (LmutI). The branch numbers and relative distance of the tree represent the amount of evolutionary divergence between two nodes in the tree, which was calculated using a k-mer based method in the CLC Genomics WorkBench v7.5.1</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_485_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p>In contrast to the &#x003b1; conglutins, the &#x003b2; conglutin sequence relationships were not as clear cut (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). While there are some &#x003b2; conglutins that appear to have diverged prior to lupin speciation (for example, BETA1 and BETA2), other examples suggest that the &#x003b2; conglutins are most closely aligned with each other within a species (e.g. <italic>L. mutabilis, L. albus</italic> and <italic>L. luteus</italic>), indicating that they diverged after speciation. Whether these different &#x003b2; sequences are distinct genes or alleles remain to be determined. When comparing &#x003b2; conglutin-like protein (or 7S globulins) relationships in legumes such as soybean, pea, peanut, medicago and NLL, gene duplication in each legume species appeared to have occurred after speciation.</p><p>As observed with the &#x003b1; conglutins the &#x003b3; conglutins fall into two classes among nearly all the lupin varieties examined; GAMMA1 and GAMMA2, with the closest homology found within species (e.g. <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> and <italic>L. albus</italic>) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C). Interestingly, <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> GAMMA1 and GAMMA2 did not fall neatly into the two classes with most sequence homology found with each other rather than respective members of the GAMMA1 and GAMMA2 orthologs.</p><p>The phylogenic relationships among &#x003b4; conglutins is more complex compared to &#x003b1; and &#x003b3; conglutins (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>D). DELTA4 appeared to have arisen prior to speciation, while for <italic>L. cosentinii, L. luteus</italic> and <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> the other three &#x003b4; conglutins have most homology to the &#x003b4; conglutins within their own species. For <italic>L. albus</italic> and <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> DELTA2 conglutins show strong sequence similarity between the two species, whereas DELTA1 and DELTA3 conglutins show stronger homology to each other, within the respective species. The phylogenic tree thus illustrates that varieties within the same species are most similar to each other and among the lupin species examined <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> appears most phylogenetically distinct. These results are in agreement with previous findings using ITS sequencing and mass spectrometric fingerprints of seed proteins for defining <italic>Lupinus</italic> spp. relationships [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>RNAseq vs ESTseq: Analysis of conglutin RNA expression in narrow-leafed lupin cv Tanjil</title><p>Gene expression has been studied through a variety of methods including northern blots, quantitative reverse transcriptase-PCR, microarray analyses and most recently, RNAseq. RNAseq has the advantage over previous techniques in that it is more sensitive, is not limited to a set of predetermined probes and also detects transcriptional modification such as alternative splicing and gene fusion. A standard method of describing transcript expression in RNAseq datasets is to express the number of sequence reads as <italic>r</italic>eads <italic>p</italic>er <italic>k</italic>ilobase per <italic>m</italic>illion reads (RPKM), [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. However, there have been concerns that the accuracy of the calculation of RPKM used in RNAseq may be influenced by gene length, GC content and dinucleotide frequencies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p><p>RNAseq analysis was used to study the expression of the conglutins in NLL cv. Tanjil. The RPKM for the data retrieved for Tanjil was compared to the data obtained from sequencing 3017 clones from a cDNA library, which generated 2381 sequence-readable ESTs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] from the same stage of seed development and was expressed as <italic>r</italic>eads <italic>p</italic>er <italic>m</italic>illion (RPM) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). The comparison between the two techniques resulted in 32% more reads for &#x003b1;, 7% more reads for &#x003b2;, 36% more reads for &#x003b3; and over three times more reads for &#x003b4; using RNAseq compared to ESTseq. This resulted in conglutin genes representing 63% of the total reads using RNAseq compared to 42% using ESTseq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The differences may be due to biological variation, as even though the experiment was replicated as closely as possible, differences may have been introduced unintentionally. For example, plant nutrition and environmental conditions have been shown to greatly affect seed storage protein composition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Interestingly, the two data sets have similar expression reads if the EST data is also divided by the gene size (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). This suggests that the library construction for the EST data set may be proportionally biased towards larger clones and that the RNAseq datasets generated in this study are a more useful means of comparing conglutin gene expression in and across different lupin species.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Transcription expression of the four conglutin families from <italic>L. angustifolius</italic>, Tanjil. The RNAseq data was compared to ESTseq data from the same stage of seed development. The EST sequences are represented as <bold>A)</bold> Reads per million (RPM) and <bold>B)</bold> reads per kilobase per million (RPKM).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_485_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Comparison of conglutin RNA expression among lupin species</title><p>The transcriptomic studies allowed us to directly compare conglutin RNA expression across the five lupin species studied. The RPKM for each family of conglutins in the different lupin species is displayed in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. As expected, the three varieties of <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> and the two varieties of <italic>L. albus</italic> have similar expression patterns within their respective species. There were some striking differences in conglutin RNA levels between the lupin species. For example, <italic>L. luteus</italic> and <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> have high levels of expression of &#x003b4; conglutins, with over 60% of conglutin transcripts being &#x003b4;. In contrast in <italic>L. albus</italic> &#x003b4; expression was lower and only constituted around 17% of total conglutin transcripts. &#x003b2; conglutins also showed marked differences between lupin species, with &#x003b2; being the most abundant family (&#x0003e;35% of total conglutin transcripts) in <italic>L. angustifolius</italic>, <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> and <italic>L. albus,</italic> while in contrast there were extremely low levels in <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> (less than 2%). While &#x003b1; expression was quite similar across lupin species, &#x003b3; expression was also quite variable, with high expression in <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> and <italic>L. albus</italic> (~30%) but low expression in the other species (&#x0003c;5%).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The <italic>r</italic>eads <italic>p</italic>er <italic>k</italic>ilobase per <italic>m</italic>illion reads (RPKM) for each tested lupin species/variety for each family of conglutins (ALPHA, BETA, GAMMA and DELTA). The lupin varieties were <italic>L. albus</italic> Andromeda (LalbA<italic>), L. albus</italic> Kiev (LalbK<italic>), L. angustifolus</italic> P27255 (LangP), <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Tanjil (LangT), <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Unicrop (LangU), <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> Erregulla (LcosE), <italic>L. luteus</italic> Pootalong (LlutP) and <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> ID13 (LmutI).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_485_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p>The conglutin expression profile can be further analysed to examine the expression of individual conglutin genes. In the case of the &#x003b1; family, ALPHA2 was the major &#x003b1; conglutin expressed in <italic>L. albus</italic> and <italic>L. cosentinii,</italic> but in the other lupin species examined, the different &#x003b1; conglutins were more evenly expressed (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A). Individual &#x003b2; family members shared substantial differences in their expression levels between lupin species (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B). For example, BETA7 while being the most abundant in <italic>L. albus</italic> and <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> was one of the least abundant in <italic>L. angustifolius</italic>. Interestingly, a <italic>L. albus</italic> &#x003b2; conglutin sequence has been previously submitted to Genbank as gi:62867685 and this shows greatest identity to BETA7 in <italic>L. albus</italic> Andromeda (98%) and the <italic>L. albus</italic> Kiev mutant (98%). As this is the most abundant &#x003b2; in this species, it was not surprising that this sequence was the first <italic>L. albus</italic> &#x003b2; conglutin sequence reported.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The RPKM for each tested lupin species/variety for each member of the conglutin families. RPKM for conglutin members <bold>A)</bold> Alpha, <bold>B)</bold> Beta, <bold>C)</bold> Gamma and <bold>D)</bold> Delta. The lupin varieties were <italic>L. albus</italic> Andromeda (LalbA<italic>), L. albus</italic> Kiev (LalbK<italic>), L. angustifolus</italic> P27255 (LangP), <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Tanjil (LangT), <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Unicrop (LangU), <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> Erregulla (LcosE), <italic>L. luteus</italic> Pootalong (LlutP) and <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> ID13 (LmutI).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_485_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p>In the case of the &#x003b3; conglutins, GAMMA1 was the most abundant in <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> and <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> while GAMMA2 was more abundant in the other lupin species (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C). In the case of the &#x003b4; conglutins, with the exception of DELTA4, which was expressed at very low levels in all lupin species, the other &#x003b4; on the whole showed relatively similar proportional expression levels in the different lupin species although DELTA1 expression was much lower in the <italic>L. albus</italic> Kiev mutant than in the <italic>L. albus</italic> Andromeda cultivar (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Protein and transcript level comparison in mature seeds</title><p>A number of factors affect protein abundance, including transcription, translation and protein- turnover. To determine if the transcript numbers were correlated with the total protein abundance, the protein concentration in relation to the dry weight of the mature seed was measured. As shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, the cultivars ranged from 30-44% protein content. In the case of <italic>L. albus, L. angustifolius</italic> and <italic>L. luteus</italic>, there was a good correlation between the levels of conglutin transcripts in maturing seeds and the protein abundance in the mature seed, a stage where conglutin transcripts make up a major portion of the total seed transciptome in NLL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. However, this correlation was not maintained in <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> and <italic>L.mutabilis</italic> where <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> had the highest level of conglutin transcripts but the lowest percentage protein, while <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> was the opposite. There can be a number of explanations, for example translational regulation, post-translational modification and protein turnover. Moreover, a variety of seed components contribute to the weight of the seed (eg fibre, oil, etc), and these may differentially contribute to the final seed weight in some lupin species. For example, <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> it is known to have relatively high oil levels. Transcript expression of seed storage proteins in <italic>Lotus japonicas</italic> during seed development has been correlated to other genes including oleosins, seed maturation proteins, a late embryogenesis protein and 16 transcription factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Protein concentrations (% dry weight) of mature seed and total conglutin transcript levels (RPKM) of <italic>L. albus</italic> Andromeda (LalbA)<italic>, L. albus</italic> Kiev (LalbK), <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> P27255 (LangP), <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Tanjil (LangT), <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Unicrop (LangU), <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> Guss (LcosG), <italic>L. luteus</italic> Pootalong (LlutP) and <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> ID13 (LmutI).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_485_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Conglutin protein analysis during seed development in L. angustifolius, cv Tanjil</title><p>In <italic>L. angustifolius,</italic> cv Tanjil, transcription levels of the conglutin genes was demonstrated to increase during seed development quite dramatically from 4 to 30 <italic>D</italic>ays <italic>A</italic>fter <italic>A</italic>nthesis (DAA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. It was therefore of interest to see if this was reflected in protein abundance, and the relative expression of conglutins in a variety of tissue types. Immunoblot analysis at different stages of seed development and for different tissues types were performed using polyclonal antibodies raised against synthetic peptides derived from each of the conglutin sequences in Tanjil. Comparison of protein expression of the four families of conglutins demonstrate strong tissue specificity with high expression in the seed and no detection in the leaf, petiole, root and stem tissue from two- month old plants (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A). In addition, protein from commercially available NLL lupin flour and wheat were also tested, demonstrating the proteins remain intact during lupin milling and emphasising the specificity of the antibodies, since no proteins were detected in wheat flour (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A). Seeds were collected from the pods at six time points that ranged from 4 DAA to mature seed. 20-26 DAA was the developmental stage used for EST sequencing and RNAseq reported in this study. Equal amounts of protein were loaded for each sample and the extracted protein profiles were separated by SDS-PAGE. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B illustrates that protein bands similar in size to the predicted pro-protein molecular weight range for &#x003b1; (56&#x000a0;kDa) and &#x003b2; (~70&#x000a0;kDa). In the case of BETA conglutins, the expression of pro-protein of predicted size of ~70 kD is higher at the mid-developmental range, and in later time points there is more expression of smaller polypeptides, suggesting post-translation processing is occurring within the maturing seed. GAMMA and DELTA proteins are expressed at higher levels in middle and later developmental seed stages (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Western blot of 5 ug protein extracts from various lupin samples. The blots were probed using antibodies generated against ALPHA conglutin (expected size 56 kD), BETA conglutin (68-72 kD), GAMMA conglutin (49 kD &#x02013; uncleaved, 33 kD cleaved), and DELTA conglutin (18 kD&#x02013; uncleaved, 12 kD cleaved) peptides, and the commercially available PEPC antibody to illustrate similar protein loading. <bold>A)</bold> Protein expression of conglutins in <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Tanjil and wheat flour. <bold>B)</bold> Protein expression in developmental stages of <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Tanjil seeds. <bold>C)</bold> Protein expression of conglutin in mature seeds of various lupin species/varietie.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2015_485_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p>A 2D analysis of the <italic>L. albus</italic> seed proteome found that 37 out of 40 spots fell into the &#x003b1;, &#x003b2; or &#x003b3; conglutin families, with many of the proteins having a large size range and several endoproteolytically cleaved subunits could be identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Our results are in agreement with this previous study, where we have observed a range of peptides with different molecular weights in our immunoblot analysis corresponding to the species, <italic>L. angustifolius</italic>. In addition, the heterogeneity of peptides corresponding to &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; conglutins have also been observed from purified conglutins in <italic>L. albus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. As the genomic and transcriptomic analyses have identified a fixed number of conglutin genes, this further supports that the majority of the heterogeneity of conglutin polypeptides is from post-translational modification from a limited number of precursor polypeptides rather than a large number of different genes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Analysis of protein expression patterns in different lupin species</title><p>The expression profiles of conglutin protein were also analysed in mature seed for the different lupin species/varieties used in the RNAseq studies. Sequence comparisons over the region of the target conglutin peptide used for antibody production, across the lupin species analysed, demonstrated high homology and therefore a high likely hood that the antibodies would recognise conglutins from all tested lupin species (data not shown). Similar levels of total protein were extracted from mature seeds and separated by SBS-PAGE as demonstrated by staining with Coomassie Brilliant blue (data not shown), and using an antibody against phosphoenolpyruvate caroxylase (PEPC). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>C illustrates that differences occur in the protein profile for the different lupin species, although varieties from the same species often showed similar protein profiles, for example, <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> varieties Tanjil and Unicrop. There was no obvious correlation of conglutin transcript expression with final conglutin protein levels. For example, <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> exhibited the highest levels of proteins recognised by the &#x003b2; conglutin antisera but only had average &#x003b2; conglutin transcript expression levels, suggesting that post-transcriptional control is an important factor in conglutin expression in lupin species.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study has provided substantial information on the complexity of the four conglutin families in a range of lupin species in terms of their gene structure, phylogenetic relationships and their relative RNA and protein abundance during seed development. These results will provide a good foundation for further research to elucidate the function and nutritional aspects of these seed storage proteins, that in turn will provide the knowledge to try and alter lupin seed protein composition to optimize the health properties of lupins. It was interesting to note that the different lupin species had large variations in conglutin RNA expression. These variations in RNA levels did not appear to have any obvious deleterious effects with regards to seed germination and development. There is evidence to support the plasticity of seed protein expression, for example the ability of sulphur and nitrogen supply to affect seed storage composition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Interestingly, genetically manipulating seed storage proteins in soybean, using RNA interference or mutation results in rebalancing of the proteome thereby maintaining overall wild-type levels of overall seed storage proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Future work in lupins may involve manipulating seed proteins for optimum nutrition and growth. For example, as &#x003b2; conglutins have been demonstrated to have some allergenic properties, it may be possible to reduce these proteins in favour of &#x003b3; conglutins that may have higher nutritional benefits.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Plant growth</title><p>Lupin plants were grown in a growth cabinet at 22&#x000b0;C/18&#x000b0;C over a 14&#x000a0;h/10&#x000a0;h&#x000a0;day/night schedule under 600 Photosynthetically Active Radiation &#x003bc;mol m<sup>-2</sup>&#x000a0;s<sup>-1</sup> lights. For the transcriptomic comparisons, seeds were collected 20-26 <italic>D</italic>ays <italic>A</italic>fter <italic>A</italic>nthesis (DAA) for, <italic>L. albus</italic> cv Andromeda, <italic>L. albus</italic> cv Kiev mutant, <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> cv P27255, <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Tanjil, <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> cv Unicrop, <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> cv Erregulla <italic>L. luteus</italic> cv Pootalong,and <italic>L. mutabilis</italic> cv ID13. For the protein level analysis, eight grams of mature seed was supplied to the ChemCentre (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chemcentre.wa.gov.au">www.chemcentre.wa.gov.au</ext-link>) of the above cultivars, except <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> cv Gus was used instead of <italic>L. cosentinii</italic> cv Erregulla, as the Erregulla variety lost its viability to germinate. Determination of protein levels was measured by the amount of nitrogen using thermal conductivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. For the immunoblot analysis, seeds were collected from the pods 4 DAA to 53 DAA (mature seed) from <italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Tanjil. Commercially available lupin flour (Irwin Valley. <italic>L. angustifolius</italic>) was also obtained.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>RNA isolation, library preparation, sequencing and quality control</title><p>RNA was isolated using the Trizol method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] as followed: for each of the eight lupin samples approximately 150&#x000a0;mg of maturing seed (20-26 DAA) was ground to a fine powder under a stream of liquid nitrogen. The ground powder was homogenised in 1.5&#x000a0;mL Eppendorf tubes using two-times 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L Trizol reagents (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), followed by a 15&#x000a0;min incubation period at room temperature. After centrifugation at 12000&#x000a0;g and 4&#x000b0;C for 10&#x000a0;min the supernatant was mixed with 200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L chloroform, followed by another centrifugation step at 12000&#x000a0;g and 4&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min. The upper phase was mixed with 300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of high salt precipitation buffer (0.8&#x000a0;M sodium citrate/1.2&#x000a0;M NaCl) and 300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of isopropanol and incubated on ice for at least 10&#x000a0;min to selectively precipitate total RNA. Precipitated RNA was centrifuged (10&#x000a0;min 12000&#x000a0;g and 4&#x000b0;C) and washed twice in 75% ethanol. RNA was dissolved in diethylpyrocarbonate treated water. Quality and quantity was assessed by both BioAnalyzer (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA) and Qubit assays (Invitrogen).</p><p>One &#x003bc;g of total RNA was used to generate TruSeq RNA libraries (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations. The eight Lupin TruSeq RNA libraries were pooled evenly and sequenced on a single lane of an Illumina HiSeq1000 on a 2&#x000d7; 100&#x000a0;bp Paired End run.</p><p>Raw RNA-Seq data for libraries were trimmed for low quality (&#x0003c;Q30) and Illumina sequencing primer and adaptor sequences (Truseq v2) via Cutadapt 1.1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] (overlap 10, times 3, minimum length 25). Reads trimmed to less than 25&#x000a0;bp were discarded and reads with a discarded pair were retained as singleton reads. Transcriptome sequencing and subsequent trimming resulted in quality-controlled RNAseq data ranging from 1.38 to 2.69 Gb per library (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). The RNAseq and conglutin EST sequences used in this study were submitted to the Sequence Read Archive and dbEST at NCBI under bioproject accession PRJNA271721.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Data analysis</title><p>The conglutin gene sequences identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] were used to search the Tanjil survey genome and transcriptome assembly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], using BLASTN and tBLASTX in CLC Genomics WorkBench 6.0 (CLC Bio, Aarhus, Denmark) to confirm the presence of the conglutins in the genome and transcriptome assembly and to identify if any additional conglutin family members were present.</p><p>The Illumina trimmed sequencing reads were sorted into paired and unpaired groups and aligned to the 16 NLL conglutin genes, using CLC Genomics Workbench 6.0. Following the alignment to 16 NLL conglutin reference genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] the consensus generated homologous sequence was extracted for each conglutin gene from each variety. The extracted consensus sequences were aligned within each family using K-mer based tree construction (using CLC Genomics Workbench 6). The <italic>r</italic>eads <italic>p</italic>er <italic>k</italic>ilobase per <italic>m</italic>illion reads (RPKM) values were determined for each of the 16 consensus sequences for each lupin variety using the RNAseq datasets and the RNAseq analysis function in CLC Genomics WorkBench 6.0.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Antibodies</title><p>Synthetic peptides for production of the polyclonal serum against &#x003b1; conglutin, &#x003b4; conglutin and &#x003b2; conglutin were from Mimotopes Pty Ltd, (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mimotopes.com">www.mimotopes.com</ext-link>), and &#x003b3; conglutin from Agrisera (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.agrisera.com">www.agrisera.com</ext-link>). All peptides were conjugated to keyhole limpet hemocyanin as carrier with a maleimidocaproyl-N-hydroxysuccinimide linker and produced to immunograde purity. The sequences for each peptide synthesized were: &#x003b1; conglutin: (NH2)- CRETYEEPQEQEQG (-CONH2), &#x003b2; conglutin: (NH2-) CVDEGEGNYELVGIR (-CONH2), &#x003b3; conglutin: (NH2)- CSSTYQAPFCHSTQCSRAN -amidated and &#x003b4; conglutin: (NH2)- CRAILQQIYESQSEQ (-CONH2). Polyclonal antibodies were raised in rabbits at the following facilities: IMVS Pathology, Veterinary Services Division, University of Adelaide, Australia (&#x003b2; conglutin), Agrisera, (&#x003b3; conglutin), and the Monoclonal Antibody Facility, Harry Perkins Institute of Medical Research (&#x003b1; conglutin, &#x003b4; conglutin). Anti-PEPC antiserum was purchased from Agrisera.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Protein extraction, SDS-PAGE and immunoblot analyses</title><p>Seed material (0.5&#x000a0;g) was grounded into a fine powder in a mortar and pestle using liquid nitrogen, and resuspended in a solution containing 100&#x000a0;mM KPO<sub>4</sub> (pH&#x000a0;7.4), 1&#x000a0;mM EDTA, 1% Triton X-100, 10% glycerol, 1/200 proteinase inhibitor cocktail (Sigma: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sigmaaldrich.com">www.sigmaaldrich.com</ext-link>), 0.5&#x000a0;mM phenylmethanesulfonylfluoride (Sigma) and 1&#x000a0;mM DTT at a concentration of 50% (w/v). After a 15&#x000a0;min spin (14,000&#x000a0;rpm), the supernatant was recovered and measured for protein concentration using the Qubit Protein Assay kit (Invitrogen: Invitrogen.com.au).</p><p>Total protein (5 ug per lane) were loaded and separated by SDS-PAGE on a 4-20% acrylamide Mini Protean &#x000ae;TGX gel (Biorad: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bio-rad.com">www.bio-rad.com</ext-link>) using Mini Protean &#x000ae;Tetra Cell apparatus (Biorad). To verify protein quantification, one gel was stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue (Bio-Rad) according to manufacturer&#x02019;s procedures. The second gel was used for immunoblot analysis.</p><p>Proteins were electroblotted onto a PVDF member (Bio-Rad) using a Mini-Trans-Blot Electrophoretic Transfer Cell sysem (Bio-Rad). Western blots were performed using standard techniques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] with an overnight incubation of 1/1000 dilution of rabbit serum containing polyclonal antibodies followed by TBS washes and a 2&#x000a0;h incubation of goat anti-rabbit IgG horseradish peroxidise conjugate (Bio-Rad). The chemiluminescence signal was detected using Western Lightning Plus-ECL substrate (Perkin Elmer: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.perkinelmer.com">www.perkinelmer.com</ext-link>) following the manufacturers&#x02019; instructions and Xray film (Kodak; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kodak.com">www.kodak.com</ext-link>) detection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Availability of supporting data</title><p>The RNAseq and conglutin EST sequences used in this study have been submitted to the Sequence Read Archive and dbEST at NCBI under bioproject accession PRJNA271721.</p></sec></sec></body><back><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec18"><title>Additional file</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2015_485_MOESM1_ESM.doc" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1: Table S1.</label><caption><p>RNAseq data information.</p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>DAA</term><def><p>Days after anthesis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EST</term><def><p>Expressed sequence tag</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LalbA</term><def><p><italic>L. albus</italic> Andromeda</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LalbK</term><def><p><italic>L. albus</italic> Kiev</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LangP</term><def><p><italic>L. angustifolus</italic> P27255</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LangT</term><def><p><italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Tanjil</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LangU</term><def><p><italic>L. angustifolius</italic> Unicrop</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LcosE</term><def><p><italic>L. cosentinii</italic> Erregulla</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LlutP</term><def><p><italic>L. luteus</italic> Pootalong</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LmutI</term><def><p><italic>L. mutabilis</italic> ID13</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NLL</term><def><p>Narrow-leafed lupin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPKM</term><def><p>Reads per kilobase per million reads</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPM</term><def><p>Reads per million</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p>The authors declare they have no competing interests.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; contributions</bold></p><p>RF participated in experimental design, material preparation, bioinformatic analysis and interpretation, immunoblotting and drafting the manuscript. JJ assisted in immunoblotting and drafting the manuscript. LK participated in sequence preparation, sequencing, bioinformatics and drafting the manuscript. JH participated in bioinformatic analysis. SM provided the antibody raised against gamma conglutin. KS conceived the study, participated in the design and co-ordination and drafting the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We thank Hayley Casarotto and Elaine Smith for valuable technical assistance and Linda Tabe and Ling-Ling Gao for helpful comments on the manuscript. The lupin seeds were kindly provided by Dr Jon Clements, Department of Agriculture and Food, Western Australia. This research was supported by the European Marie Curie Research Program (FP7-PEOPLE-2011-IOF), under the Grant Ref. Number PIOF-GA-2011-301550 to JL and KS and by CSIRO to RF, LK, JH, SM and KS.</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Legumes: Importance and constraints to greater use</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>131</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>872</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.017004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12644639?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12644639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Puddey</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sipsas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackland</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Beilin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dove</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlyon</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayaseena</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of lupin-enriched foods on body composition and cardiovascular disease risk factors: a 12-month randomized controlled weight loss trial</article-title><source>Int J Obes</source><year>2010</year><volume>35</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>810</fpage><lpage>819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ijo.2010.213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duranti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morazzoni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutraceutical properties of lupin seed proteins A great potential still waiting for full exploitation</article-title><source>Agro Food Ind Hi-Tech</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Accardo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morazzoni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarafoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Duranti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conglutin gamma, a lupin seed protein, binds insulin in vitro and reduces plasma glucose levels of hyperglycemic rats</article-title><source>J of Nutritional Biochem</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jnutbio.2004.06.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddique</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeuffroy</surname><given-names>M-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Alghamdi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innovations in agronomy for food legumes. A review</article-title><source>Agron Sustain Dev</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13593-011-0021-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gladstones</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lupins as crop plants</article-title><source>Field Crop Abstracts</source><year>1970</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>148</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamphuis</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Buirchell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The essential role of genetic resources in narrow-leafed lupin improvement</article-title><source>Crop &#x00026; Pasture Science</source><year>2013</year><volume>64</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/CP13092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duranti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cucchetti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerletti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in composition and subunits in the storage proteins of germinating lupine seeds</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>1984</year><volume>32</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>490</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf00123a018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duranti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Restani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Poniatowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerletti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The seed globulins of <italic>Lupinus albus</italic></article-title><source>Phytochem</source><year>1981</year><volume>20</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2071</fpage><lpage>2075</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0031-9422(81)80087-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Spriggs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Soo</surname><given-names>LYC</given-names></name><name><surname>Goggin</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PMC</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterisation of seed storage protein transcripts from <italic>Lupinus angustifolius</italic></article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-11-59</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21457583?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21457583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez-Pedrouso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zapata</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for phosphorylation of the major seed storage protein of the common bean and its phosphorylation-dependent degradation during germination</article-title><source>Plant Molecular Biology</source><year>2014</year><volume>84</volume><issue>4-5</issue><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-013-0141-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24142381?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24142381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>dosRamos</surname><given-names>PCR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>ARN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accumulation of a lectin-like breakdown product of beta-conglutin catabolism in cotyledons of germinating <italic>Lupinus albus</italic> L seeds</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1997</year><volume>203</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9299789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duranti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gius</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarafoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lectin-like activity of lupin seed conglutin-gamma, a gylcoprotein previously referred to as a storage protein</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>1995</year><volume>46</volume><issue>287</issue><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/46.6.725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scarafoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Duranti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>gamma-Conglutin, the Lupinus albus XEGIP-like protein, whose expression is elicited by chitosan, lacks of the typical inhibitory activity against GH12 endo-glucanases</article-title><source>Phytochem</source><year>2010</year><volume>71</volume><issue>2-3</issue><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2009.11.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gayler</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wachsmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolivas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and Characterisation of Protein Bodies in Lupius angustifolius</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1989</year><volume>91</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1425</fpage><lpage>1431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.91.4.1425</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16667196?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16667196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogihara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunairi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcaino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of a Low Digestibility delta-Conglutin in Yellow Lupin (<italic>Lupinus luteus</italic> L.) Seed Meal for Atlantic Salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic> L.) by Coupling 2D-PAGE and Mass Spectrometry</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>11</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hane</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamphuis</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>B-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of genomic resources for the narrow-leafed lupin (<italic>Lupinus angustifolius</italic>): construction of a Bacterial Artificial Chromosome (BAC) library and BAC-end sequencing</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>521</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-12-521</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22014081?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22014081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ksiazkiewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyrwa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Szczepaniak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rychel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Majcherkiewicz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Przysiecka</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics of <italic>Lupinus angustifolius</italic> gene-rich regions: BAC library exploration, genetic mapping and cytogenetics</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>79</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-14-79</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23379841?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23379841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Moolhuijzen</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boersma</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chudy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesniewska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellgard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Swiecicki</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolko</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aligning a New Reference Genetic Map of <italic>Lupinus angustifolius</italic> with the Genome Sequence of the Model Legume, Lotus japonicus</article-title><source>DNA Research</source><year>2010</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dsq001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20133394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20133394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Peel</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcript and proteomic analysis of developing white lupin (<italic>Lupinus albus</italic> L.) roots</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-9-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19123941?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19123941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweetingham</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Buirchell</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid development of molecular markers by next-generation sequencing linked to a gene conferring phomopsis stem blight disease resistance for marker-assisted selection in lupin (<italic>Lupinus angustifolius</italic> L.) breeding</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>126</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-012-1997-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23086512?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23086512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweetingham</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Draft genome sequence, and a sequence-defined genetic linkage map of the legume crop species <italic>Lupinus angustifolius</italic> L</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>5</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamphuis</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hane</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome sequencing of different narrow-leafed lupin tissue types provides a comprehensive uni-gene assembly and extensive gene-based molecular markers</article-title><source>Plant Biotech J</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parra-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Aravena-Abarzua</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro-Navarro</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Udall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Maughan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvo-Garrido</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Maureira-Butler</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yellow lupin (<italic>Lupinus luteus</italic> L.) transcriptome sequencing: molecular marker development and comparative studies</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>425</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-13-425</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22920992?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22920992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogihara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunairi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivos-Trujillo</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Maureira-Butler</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>HE</surname><given-names>S-G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteomic characterization of seeds from yellow lupin (<italic>Lupinus luteus</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Proteomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1543</fpage><lpage>1546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.201300511</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24723484?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24723484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ainouche</surname><given-names>A-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic Relationships in Lupinus (Fabaceae: Papilionoideae) based on Internal Transcribed Spacer Sequences (ITS) of nuclear ribosomal DNA</article-title><source>Am J of Bot</source><year>1999</year><volume>86</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>590</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2656820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10205079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Appels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mass spectrometric fingerprints of seed protein for defining Lupinus spp. relationships</article-title><source>Genetic Resources and Crop Evolution</source><year>2013</year><volume>60</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>952</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10722-012-9890-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1226</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18516045?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurement of mRNA abundance using RNA-seq data: RPKM measure is inconsistent among samples</article-title><source>Theory in Biosci</source><year>2012</year><volume>131</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12064-012-0162-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>TJV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasticity of seed protein composition in response to nitrogen and sulfur availability</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5266(02)00252-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11960738?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11960738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourgeois</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacquin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Savois</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommerer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Labas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Burstin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissecting the proteome of pea mature seeds reveals the phenotypic plasticity of seed protein composition</article-title><source>Proteomics</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.200700903</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19086096?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19086096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verdier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres-Jerez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Andriankaja</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishment of the Lotus japonicus Gene Expression Atlas (LjGEA) and its use to explore legume seed maturation</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2013</year><volume>74</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12119</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23452239?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23452239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarafoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Herndl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Prinsi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Espen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Duranti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combined 2D electrophoretic approaches for the study of white lupin mature seed storage proteome</article-title><source>Phytochem</source><year>2007</year><volume>68</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2007.01.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duranti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Consonni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Magni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarafoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The major proteins of lupin seed: Characterisation and molecular properties for use as functional and nutraceutical ingredients</article-title><source>Trends in Food Science &#x00026; Technology</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>624</fpage><lpage>633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2008.07.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbazuk</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>WX</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolau</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silencing of soybean seed storage proteins results in a rebalanced protein composition preserving seed protein content without major collateral changes in the metabolome and transcriptome</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2011</year><volume>156</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.173807</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21398260?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21398260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a plant introduction soybean line with genetic lesions affecting two distinct glycinin subunits and evaluation of impacts on protein content and composition</article-title><source>Mol Breed</source><year>2013</year><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-013-9870-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sosulski</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Imafidon</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amino-acid-composition and nitrogen-to-protein conversion factors for animial and plant foods</article-title><source>J Agricl and Food Chem</source><year>1990</year><volume>38</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf00096a011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>AOAC</collab></person-group><source>Official Methods of Analysis of AOAC International</source><year>2000</year><edition>17</edition><publisher-loc>Suite 500, 481 North Fredric Ave Gaithersburg, Maryland 20877-2417 USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>AOAC Int</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cutadapt removes adapter sequences from high-throughput sequencing reads</article-title><source>EMBnetjournal</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Western and south-western library screens</article-title><source>Molecular plant biology: A practical approach Volume One</source><year>2002</year><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>221</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>