<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4230025</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2164-15-501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24948464</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-501</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sex- and tissue-specific profiles of chemosensory gene expression in a herbivorous gall-inducing fly (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>Martin N</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>martin_n.andersson@biol.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Videvall</surname><given-names>Elin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>elin.videvall@biol.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Walden</surname><given-names>Kimberly KO</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>k-walden@life.illinois.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>Marion O</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>marion.harris@ndsu.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>Hugh M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>hughrobe@uiuc.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name><surname>L&#x000f6;fstedt</surname><given-names>Christer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>christer.lofstedt@biol.lu.se</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Biology, Lund University, Lund SE-223 62, Sweden</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Entomology, University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, IL 61801, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Entomology, North Dakota State University, Fargo, ND 58108-6050, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Andersson et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Andersson et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2164/15/501"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The chemical senses of insects mediate behaviors that are closely linked to survival and reproduction. The order Diptera contains two model organisms, the vinegar fly <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> and the mosquito <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>, whose chemosensory genes have been extensively studied. Representing a third dipteran lineage with an interesting phylogenetic position, and being ecologically distinct by feeding on plants, the Hessian fly (<italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic> Say, Diptera: Cecidomyiidae) genome sequence has recently become available. Among plant-feeding insects, the Hessian fly is unusual in &#x02018;reprogramming&#x02019; the plant to create a superior food and in being the target of plant <italic>resistance</italic> genes, a feature shared by plant pathogens. Chemoreception is essential for reproductive success, including detection of sex pheromone and plant-produced chemicals by males and females, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We identified genes encoding 122 odorant receptors (OR), 28 gustatory receptors (GR), 39 ionotropic receptors (IR), 32 odorant binding proteins, and 7 sensory neuron membrane proteins in the Hessian fly genome. We then mapped Illumina-sequenced transcriptome reads to the genome to explore gene expression in male and female antennae and terminal abdominal segments. Our results reveal that a large number of chemosensory genes have up-regulated expression in the antennae, and the expression is in many cases sex-specific. Sex-specific expression is particularly evident among the <italic>Or</italic> genes, consistent with the sex-divergent olfactory-mediated behaviors of the adults. In addition, the large number of <italic>Ors</italic> in the genome but the reduced set of <italic>Grs</italic> and divergent <italic>Irs</italic> suggest that the short-lived adults rely more on long-range olfaction than on short-range gustation. We also report up-regulated expression of some genes from all chemosensory gene families in the terminal segments of the abdomen, which play important roles in reproduction.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>We show that a large number of the chemosensory genes in the Hessian fly genome have sex- and tissue-specific expression profiles. Our findings provide the first insights into the molecular basis of chemoreception in plant-feeding flies, representing an important advance toward a more complete understanding of olfaction in Diptera and its links to ecological specialization.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Hessian fly</kwd><kwd><italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic></kwd><kwd>Gene expression</kwd><kwd>Genome</kwd><kwd>Transcriptome</kwd><kwd>Odorant receptor</kwd><kwd>Ionotropic receptor</kwd><kwd>Gustatory receptor</kwd><kwd>Odorant binding protein</kwd><kwd>Sensory neuron membrane protein</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Insects comprise the largest group of animals on Earth and most species are heavily dependent on chemoreception for survival and reproduction. Due to ecological adaptations, the gene families involved in chemoreception have evolved, both in terms of gene numbers and sequences, to become highly divergent across different insect taxa[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Furthermore, in a particular species, expression of the genes is regulated differently depending on, for instance, sex, tissue, life stage, or physiological state. The sequencing of insect genomes and more recently also of transcriptomes from chemosensory appendages, have paved the way for identification and characterization of the gene families that are important for chemoreception e.g.
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>Several multi-gene families encode proteins with crucial roles in olfaction and taste, including both receptors and non-receptor proteins. Receptors encoded by three large gene families are involved in chemoreception and expressed in sensory neurons, located mainly on the antennae and to a lesser extent on other sensory appendages
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. These families encode the odorant receptors (OR), gustatory receptors (GR), and ionotropic receptors (IR)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. The ORs and GRs belong to the same receptor superfamily
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. While the ORs detect volatile chemicals (odors), the GRs are responsible for contact chemoreception and also for detection of carbon dioxide
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. The IRs constitute a more ancient family of chemoreceptors
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], including both conserved "antennal" IRs involved in olfaction, as well as "divergent" IRs that seem to play a role in taste
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The sensory neuron membrane proteins (SNMP) are expressed in pheromone-responding neurons in <italic>Drosophila</italic> and Lepidoptera, and have in some cases been shown to be important for proper pheromone responses
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Finally, the odorant binding proteins (OBP) are small soluble proteins, highly abundant in the sensillum lymph
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. OBPs bind odor molecules, most of which are hydrophobic, and transport them through the hydrophilic environment in the sensillum to the membrane-bound receptor. OBPs have also been shown to improve the specificity of pheromone-detecting neurons
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], but see
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p><p>Chemosensory gene families of insects have been most extensively studied in two model organisms that both belong to the order Diptera (flies), namely <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>, which feeds on yeast and sugar both as larva and adult, and <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>, which feeds on organic material as an aquatic larvae and on blood as an adult female or nectar as a male e.g.
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]<italic>.</italic> The herbivores are a third major group within the Diptera in which the chemosensory genes so far had not been studied. Here we performed the first analysis of the chemosensory gene families in a herbivorous dipteran species, namely the Hessian fly, <italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic> Say (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae). The large gall midge family Cecidomyiidae (&#x0003e;6000 species) is an example of a group of flies that uses plants as food and contains a large number of important pests of agriculture and forestry
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Cecidomyiids belong to the suborder Nematocera (the &#x02018;lower&#x02019; Diptera) and are phylogenetically interesting because they are positioned between mosquitoes, also in the Nematocera, and <italic>Drosophila</italic>, in the other suborder of the Diptera, the Brachycera
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Plant-feeding cecidomyiid larvae have highly specialized antagonistic relationships with host plants and have been called &#x02018;reprogrammers of plant genomes&#x02019;
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] because of their ability to manipulate the plant to create a specialized nutritive tissue that provides a superior diet for the larva
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>], a trait that is thought to have contributed to adaptive radiation
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. Most gall midges have a very narrow host range
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Other characteristics of cecidomyiids are a very short adult lifespan of 1&#x02013;2 days or less, during which all reproductive activities must be completed, and mate location by the male is mediated by species-specific female-produced sex pheromones
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. Cecidomyiids are also special in that adults either do not feed or only rarely feed on water or perhaps nectar
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p><p>The Hessian fly is a serious pest on wheat (<italic>Triticum</italic> spp.) in many of the world&#x02019;s major wheat-growing regions
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. It is one of the most thoroughly studied plant-feeding insect species, with particular attention on behavioral and sensory ecology, genetics contributing to plant interactions, pheromone communication, pest management, and plant resistance
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. The Hessian fly larva has an interaction with plants that is common for plant pathogens but rare for insects, being the target of a &#x02018;gene-for-gene&#x02019; plant defense, mediated by <italic>resistance</italic> genes to which it can adapt via mutations in a matching <italic>avirulence</italic> gene
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Like other gall midges, adults of <italic>M. destructor</italic> have a maximum lifespan of 1&#x02013;2 days, which limits their behavioral repertoire
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Essentially, males emerge from pupation sites in or near the soil and take flight to find virgin females, whereas females emerge with a full complement of mature eggs, release a pheromone to attract a mate, and then continuously search for and lay eggs on a large number of plants until death occurs
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. Chemical cues are crucial for mate finding, host finding, and oviposition behavior and are, thus, clearly essential for the reproductive success of the Hessian fly.</p><p>By having an interesting phylogenetic position between <italic>Drosophila</italic> and mosquitoes, as well as very different behavioral and ecological traits, the Hessian fly is an attractive model for studies of the chemosensory gene families that underlie pheromone detection and host plant finding and assessment. The Hessian fly genome sequence has recently become available (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://agripestbase.org/hessianfly">http://agripestbase.org/hessianfly</ext-link>). Within the framework of the Hessian fly Genomics Consortium, we annotated a total of 228 genes involved in chemoreception (including genes encoding ORs, GRs, IR, SNMPs, and OBPs), corresponding to the first identification of the chemosensory gene families in the Cecidomyiidae. In the present study, we used Illumina RNAseq to sequence transcriptomes of the male and female antennae and terminal abdominal segments, the latter being involved in mating and in the female also in sex pheromone production and host selection behavior. The generated reads were then mapped to the genome sequence to examine the expression profiles of the chemosensory genes in these four tissues. We also analyzed global expression profiles of predicted transcripts and performed gene ontology (GO) annotation. In particular, our results reveal that most of the chemosensory genes have up-regulated expression in the antennae, while a few have up-regulated expression in the terminal abdominal tissues. In addition, a strikingly large number of genes, especially <italic>Or</italic> genes<italic>,</italic> have sex-specific antennal expression, which is likely to reflect the sex-divergent behaviors of adult Hessian flies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Mapping and transcript prediction</title><p>We performed Illumina sequencing and subsequently mapped the sequenced reads to the current Hessian fly genome assembly to predict transcripts and analyze gene expression profiles. The sequencing yielded ca. 314&#x000a0;M read-pairs, of which ca. 82&#x000a0;M were derived from the male antennal library, 75&#x000a0;M from female antennae, 77&#x000a0;M from female terminal abdomens, and 79&#x000a0;M from male terminal abdomens. The Illumina reads have been submitted to the Sequence Read Archive (SRA) at NCBI (BioProject accession: SRP041173). The proportion of reads that successfully mapped to the Hessian fly genome assembly was high in all four transcriptomes, ranging from 75% to 80%, despite strict mapping parameters that allowed for only 2&#x000a0;bp mismatches to account for the high sequence similarity among recently duplicated chemosensory genes. The mapping results were used by Cufflinks to predict 27 044 transcripts expressed in female antennae (N50&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 211&#x000a0;bp), 24 769 transcripts in male antennae (N50&#x02009;=&#x02009;3252&#x000a0;bp), 19 877 in female terminal abdomen (N50&#x02009;=&#x02009;3094&#x000a0;bp), and 23 691 in male terminal abdomen (N50&#x02009;=&#x02009;2967&#x000a0;bp). Based on these transcripts, 27 029 genes and 36 459 isoforms were predicted. The GC content was 34-35% in all transcriptomes.</p></sec><sec><title>Global transcriptome profiling</title><sec><title>Gene ontology annotation</title><p>GO annotation
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>], using Blast2GO (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.blast2go.com/b2ghome">http://www.blast2go.com/b2ghome</ext-link>)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], was performed to compare the four transcriptomes with regards to the frequency of transcript-associated GO terms. The proportion of transcript sequences with significant BLAST hits was similar in the four transcriptomes, i.e. 57% (15 371 transcripts) for female antennae, 59% (14 539) for male antennae, 65% (13 001) for female terminal abdomen, and 60% (14 265) for male terminal abdomen. The top-hit species distribution (Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>) showed that most hits were represented by sequences from the yellow-fever mosquito (<italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>), followed by the Southern house mosquito (<italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>) and the malaria mosquito (<italic>A. gambiae</italic>). The vinegar fly (<italic>D. melanogaster</italic>) came fourth despite the fact that ca. five times as many protein sequences from <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> have been deposited in the nr database as compared to sequences from <italic>A. aegypti</italic> (Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). The top BLAST hits for all predicted transcripts as well as their FPKM (Fragments Per Kilobase of transcript per Million mapped reads
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]) values and genome locations are given in Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>.</p><p>For the female antennae, 41% of the total transcripts had assigned GO terms in addition to BLAST hits. Corresponding numbers in the other transcriptomes were 43% for male antennae, 50% for female terminal abdomen, and 44% for male terminal abdomen. The four transcriptomes turned out to be very similar, both with respect to "Molecular Function" (Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>) and "Biological Process" (Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>) GO annotation. The only notable differences were found in the Molecular Function annotation where the "odorant binding" term only was present in the two antennal tissues, and the "signal receptor activity" term was almost twice as abundant in the two antennal tissues as compared to the two terminal abdominal tissues (Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). This result is likely to reflect the (chemo)-sensory role of the main sensory organ, the antenna. However, it also indicates that genes coding for proteins with functions (represented by GO-terms) common to all tissue types dominate in this type of analysis that provides no information on the expression levels of the individual genes themselves.</p></sec><sec><title>Pair-wise transcriptome comparisons</title><p>The expression levels of the 27 029 genes predicted by Cufflinks were used for global transcriptome profiling. Transcriptomes were compared pair-wise, i.e. male antennae <italic>vs.</italic> female antennae; male terminal abdomen <italic>vs.</italic> female terminal abdomen; male antennae <italic>vs.</italic> male terminal abdomen; and female antennae <italic>vs.</italic> female terminal abdomen. The male and female antennal transcriptomes had very similar global expression profiles, whereas male and female terminal abdomens were more different, both from each other as well as from the two antennal transcriptomes (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). When divergence based on FPKM values was analyzed using Jensen-Shannon (JS) distance, male and female antennae showed a low level of differentiation (a JS distance of only ca. 0.09). In contrast, the distances in all other pair-wise comparisons were larger, ranging from ca. 0.15 to 0.19 (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A). The global expression profile similarity between male and female antennae, and their distinctiveness from the other transcriptomes were confirmed in a principle component analysis (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>B), and in pair-wise regression analyses. The latter analyses indicated that the female and male terminal abdominal segments had an overall higher expression than the female and male antennae, respectively (female antennae <italic>vs.</italic> female terminal abdomen: regression slope coefficient&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.57, R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.51, Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>C; male antennae <italic>vs.</italic> male terminal abdomen: slope&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.78, R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.64, Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>D). The male antennae had a similar global expression profile as the female antennae, as shown by a close to 1:1 relationship between the expression levels (slope&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.97, R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.90, Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>E). In general, higher expression was found in the female terminal abdomen as compared to the male terminal abdomen (slope&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.66, R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.61, Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>F).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Comparison of global transcriptome expression profiles.</bold> The overall expression levels of the 27 029 genes predicted from the four transcriptomes were compared using Jensen-Shannon (JS) distance <bold>(A)</bold> and principle component analysis <bold>(B)</bold>, both indicating the high similarity between the male and female antennal transcriptomes. In <bold>(B)</bold>, PC 1 and PC 2 explained 55.8% and 32.2% respectively of the overall gene expression level variation in the four transcriptomes (black dots represent the predicted genes). Both the direction and length (length&#x02009;=&#x02009;within-transcriptome variation) of the eigenvectors (red arrows) show that the male and female antennal transcriptomes had highly similar variation in expression levels, both in relation to PC 1 and PC 2. In contrast, the variation in expression levels differed between the two terminal abdominal transcriptomes, which were also different from the two antennal transcriptomes (as indicated by the different lengths and directions of the eigenvectors). The difference between transcriptomes was explained (mainly) by the expression variation encompassed by PC 2 (i.e. as shown by the position of the four arrow heads). In addition, 1:1 plots (dashed line&#x02009;=&#x02009;1:1 relationship) in combination with linear regression analyses (blue solid lines) were used to compare transcriptomes pair-wise. The female and male terminal abdomen both had an overall higher expression of the predicted genes compared to the antennae of females <bold>(C)</bold> and males <bold>(D)</bold>, respectively. As indicated by the slope coefficients and relatively low R<sup>2</sup> values, the expression did not follow a 1:1 relationship in these comparisons. In contrast, expression in the male antennae was similar to that in the female antennae, following a close to 1:1 relationship <bold>(E)</bold>. Finally, the female terminal abdomen had an overall higher expression than the male terminal abdomen, i.e. the relationship between the two transcriptomes was relatively far from 1:1 <bold>(F)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-1"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Expression of the chemosensory genes</title><sec><title>Overall expression profiles</title><p>Based on our manual annotation of the Hessian fly genome, a total of 228 chemosensory genes from five gene families (<italic>Ors</italic>, <italic>Grs</italic>, <italic>Irs</italic>, <italic>Snmps</italic>, and <italic>Obps</italic>) were predicted. Predicted amino acid sequences of these genes are available in Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>, and phylogenies will be included in the forthcoming publication of the Hessian fly genome (Hessian fly Genomics Consortium, in prep).</p><p>In contrast to the global comparison where the male and female antennal transcriptomes demonstrated the most similar expression profiles, the female and male terminal abdomens had the most similar profiles when only the 228 chemosensory-related genes were included (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A, B). Regression analysis demonstrated a close to 1:1 relationship between the expression levels of the chemosensory genes in the two terminal abdominal tissues (regression slope coefficient&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.98, R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.80, Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>F), although the overall expression level was low in these tissues. Most of the chemosensory genes had the highest expression in the female or male antennae as compared to the female or male terminal abdomens (female antennae <italic>vs.</italic> female terminal abdomen: slope&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.35, R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.42, Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C; male antennae <italic>vs.</italic> male terminal abdomen: slope&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.42, R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.53, Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>D), respectively, although a few genes had higher expression in the terminal abdominal tissues (see below for details). In contrast to the global analysis, the expression profiles of the male and female antennal tissues were clearly different when only the 228 genes related to chemosensation were included in the analysis (slope&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.80, R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.60, Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>E). FPKM values for the chemosensory genes in the four tissues are presented in Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Comparison of expression profiles of the 228 chemosensory genes.</bold> Expression level profiles of the 228 genes involved in olfaction or taste in the four tissues were compared using <bold>(A)</bold> Jensen-Shannon (JS) distance, and <bold>(B)</bold> principle component analysis. In contrast to the global analysis (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), the female and male terminal abdomen tissues had the most similar expression profiles, whereas the male and female antennae were more different from each other. In <bold>(B)</bold>, PC 1 and PC 2 explained 66.0% and 20.1% respectively of the overall expression level variation among the chemosensory genes in the four tissues. Both the direction and length (length&#x02009;=&#x02009;within-transcriptome variation) of the eigenvectors (red arrows) indicate that the chemosensory genes (black dots) in the male and female terminal abdominal tissues had highly similar variation in expression levels, both in relation to PC 1 and PC 2. In contrast, the variation in expression levels differed between the male and female antennae, and these tissues were also different from the terminal abdominal tissues (as indicated by differences in length and direction of the eigenvectors). The difference in expression of the chemosensory genes between the four tissues was explained (mainly) by the variation encompassed by PC 2 (i.e. as shown by the position of the four arrow heads). In addition, 1:1 plots (dashed line&#x02009;=&#x02009;1:1 relationship) in combination with linear regression analyses (blue solid lines) indicate an overall up-regulation of expression of the 228 genes in the antennae of both sexes, compared to the female <bold>(C)</bold> or male terminal abdomen <bold>(D)</bold>, respectively. The antennae of males and females expressed many of these genes differently <bold>(E)</bold>. Overall, the female and male terminal abdomen had low expression of these genes and the expression was closer to a 1:1 relationship than in the other pair-wise comparisons <bold>(F)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Odorant receptors</title><p>Based on our annotation, the current assembly of the Hessian fly genome contains 122 <italic>Or</italic> genes, including a gene for the conserved co-receptor ORCO and six pseudogenes. Our transcriptome analysis showed that 99 of the <italic>Or</italic> genes were expressed in at least one of the analyzed tissues. Thus, almost 20% (23 genes) of the <italic>Or</italic> genes were not expressed (i.e. genes with less than 10 mapped read-pairs were regarded as having no or biologically insignificant expression). A substantially larger number of <italic>Or</italic> genes were represented by reads in the female antennae (94 <italic>Or</italic> genes) as compared to in the male antennae (64 <italic>Or</italic> genes) (Table&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Thus, while a large proportion (77%) of the <italic>Or</italic> genes in the genome was expressed in the antennae of the female, only ca. half (52%) of them were expressed in the antennae of the male. Female and male terminal abdomens expressed 24 and 30 <italic>Or</italic> genes, respectively, including <italic>Orco</italic> (Table&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Thus, relatively large numbers of <italic>Or</italic> genes were expressed outside of the main olfactory organ in both sexes, although the expression level was low in general (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>; Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). The <italic>Orco</italic> gene had the highest level of expression in both sexes, followed by <italic>Or116</italic> for which the FPKM value in the male antennae was 90% of the FPKM value for <italic>Orco</italic>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The number of genes in each chemosensory gene family with detected expression in the four transcriptomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Gene family</bold><sup>
<bold>a</bold>
</sup><hr/></th><th colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Expressed genes</bold><sup>
<bold>b</bold>
</sup><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left"><bold>Female antennae</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Male antennae</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Female abdomen</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Male abdomen</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Odorant receptor, OR (122)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">94<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">64<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">22<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">30<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gustatory receptor, GR (28)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">14<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">13<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">7<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">11<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Ionotropic receptor, IR (39)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">21<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">21<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">11<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">15<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Sensory neuron membrane protein, SNMP (7)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">7<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">7<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Odorant binding protein, OBP (32)</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">25</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Numbers within brackets refer to the number of annotated genes of each chemosensory gene family in the Hessian fly genome.</p><p><sup>b</sup>Expression defined as genes having at least 10 mapped read-pairs.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Phylogenetic relationships of the odorant receptors (OR) and their expression profiles in </bold><bold><italic>M. destructor</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> A distance-corrected neighbor-joining tree (bootstrap consensus, topology only) based on <italic>M. destructor</italic> OR amino acid sequences and rooted by MdORCO. The tree was constructed using Mega 5 after multiple sequence alignment in ClustalX. Numbers on branches indicate bootstrap support (1000 iterations) and are only displayed if &#x0003e;70 and on major branches. Expression levels of the <italic>Or</italic> genes in the four transcriptomes are represented in a heat plot based on log-transformed FPKM values. Zero expression is represented by the lightest yellow color. Suffixes to gene names are explained in the Methods section.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-3"/></fig><p>In the pair-wise comparison between the female antennae and the female terminal abdomen, 85 <italic>Or</italic> genes had higher expression in the antenna (defined by a &#x0003e;3-fold higher FPKM value in combination with a significant chi<sup>2</sup> &#x02013; test result, using a Bonferroni-corrected p-value at &#x0003c;2.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup>), whereas two <italic>Or</italic> genes, <italic>Or36</italic> and <italic>Or37</italic>, had higher expression in the terminal abdomen (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>; a list of all the differentially expressed chemosensory genes in the four pair-wise comparisons are presented in Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>). In the corresponding comparison for the male (i.e. antennae <italic>vs.</italic> terminal abdomen), 47 <italic>Or</italic> genes were expressed at a higher level in the antennae, whereas four <italic>Or</italic> genes (<italic>Or4</italic>, <italic>Or7</italic>, <italic>Or35</italic>, and <italic>Or67</italic>) had higher expression in the terminal abdomen. When comparing expression in the antennae of males <italic>vs.</italic> females, 50 <italic>Or</italic> genes showed higher expression in females, whereas 12 were more highly expressed in males. In addition, several of the OR subfamilies in our dendrogram contained receptors of which the majority showed either female or male antennal up-regulation (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). For instance, the genes for most of the receptors within the clades formed by OR86-97, OR98-100, and OR102-110 were more highly expressed in the female antennae as compared to the male antennae, whereas most of the receptor genes within the clade formed by OR111-121 were more highly expressed in the male antennae. Furthermore, 27 of the <italic>Or</italic> genes showed no expression in the antennae of either males or females, while 33 <italic>Or</italic> genes were similarly expressed in the antennae of the two sexes. Finally, five <italic>Or</italic> genes showed higher level of expression in the female terminal abdomen as compared to the male terminal abdomen, whereas seven <italic>Or</italic> genes had higher expression in the male terminal abdomen in relation to the female terminal abdomen (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>; Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Gustatory receptors</title><p>We annotated 28 members of the <italic>Gr</italic> gene family in the genome, including genes for the conserved carbon dioxide receptors (<italic>Gr1-3</italic>)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], three putative sugar receptor genes (<italic>Gr4-6</italic>), and three pseudogenes. However, only 15 of the <italic>Gr</italic> genes were expressed in the tissues analyzed here (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>; Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). These included the genes for the three putative carbon dioxide receptors and the three sugar receptors. Only slightly larger numbers of <italic>Gr</italic> genes were expressed in the antennae as compared to the terminal abdominal tissues (Table&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Three of the <italic>Gr</italic> genes (<italic>Gr7</italic>, <italic>Gr10</italic> and <italic>Gr21</italic>) had similar levels of expression in all four tissues (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Expression profiles of the genes coding for gustatory receptors (GR) in </bold><bold><italic>M. destructor</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> Expression levels of the <italic>Gr</italic> genes in the four transcriptomes represented as heat plots based on log-transformed FPKM values. Zero expression is represented by the lightest yellow color. Suffixes to gene names are explained in the Methods section.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-4"/></fig><p>In the females, six <italic>Gr</italic> genes had up-regulated expression in the antennae as compared to the terminal abdomen. These included the genes for the carbon dioxide receptors (<italic>Gr1-3</italic>) that had the highest expression of all the <italic>Gr</italic> genes, and the putative sugar receptor gene <italic>Gr6</italic>. In contrast, another putative sugar receptor gene, <italic>Gr4</italic>, had up-regulated expression in the female terminal abdomen as compared to the female antennae (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>; Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>). Similar to the females, <italic>Gr1-3</italic> and <italic>Gr6</italic> had higher expression in the male antennae as compared to the male terminal abdomen, whereas <italic>Gr4</italic> had higher expression in the terminal abdomen (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>; Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>). In contrast to the female, the expression of <italic>Gr9</italic> was also up-regulated in the male antennae as compared to terminal abdomen, whereas <italic>Gr28</italic> (up-regulated in the female antennae) was expressed at a similar level in the male antennae and terminal abdomen. <italic>Gr9</italic> was also the only <italic>Gr</italic> gene that was differentially expressed between the two antennal transcriptomes. Finally, four <italic>Gr</italic> genes, including the putative sugar receptor genes <italic>Gr4-5</italic> were more highly expressed in the male terminal abdomen than in the female terminal abdomen. None of the <italic>Gr</italic> genes were more highly expressed in the female terminal abdomen than in the male terminal abdomen.</p></sec><sec><title>Ionotropic receptors</title><p>In total, 39 <italic>Ir</italic> genes, including four pseudogenes were annotated in the Hessian fly genome. Of these, 16 genes encoded "antennal" IRs and 23 encoded "divergent" IRs. We found Hessian fly orthologues for most of the conserved antennal <italic>Ir</italic> genes identified in other Diptera
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], including <italic>Ir8a</italic>, <italic>Ir21a</italic>, <italic>Ir25a</italic>, <italic>Ir41a</italic>, <italic>Ir60a</italic>, <italic>Ir64a</italic>, <italic>Ir68a</italic>, <italic>Ir76b</italic>, <italic>Ir93a</italic>, and seven members of the <italic>Ir75</italic> group. However, <italic>Ir31a</italic>, <italic>Ir40a</italic>, and <italic>Ir92a</italic>, which are found in other Diptera, were not present in the Hessian fly genome and could also not be identified in our transcriptome data. The remaining 23 <italic>MdIr</italic> genes were regarded as members of the divergent class of insect <italic>Irs</italic>.</p><p>Twelve of the identified <italic>Ir</italic> genes (all divergent) were not expressed, whereas all the antennal <italic>Ir</italic> genes showed expression in at least one of the analyzed tissues (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>; Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). Larger numbers of <italic>Ir</italic> genes were expressed in the antennal tissues as compared to the terminal abdominal tissues (Table&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The gene for the broadly occurring co-receptor IR25a had the highest expression of all the <italic>MdIr</italic> genes. Expression of this gene was high in the antennae of both sexes and in the male terminal abdomen.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Expression profiles of the genes coding for ionotropic receptors (IR) in </bold><bold><italic>M. destructor</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> Expression levels of the <italic>Ir</italic> genes in the four transcriptomes represented as heat plots based on log-transformed FPKM values. Zero expression is represented by the lightest yellow color. Suffixes to gene names are explained in the Methods section.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-5"/></fig><p>Expression of 18 <italic>Ir</italic> genes was higher in the female antennae as compared to the female terminal abdomen. Of these genes, 14 encoded antennal IRs and four encoded divergent IRs (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>; Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>). Although IR60a is classified as an "antennal" IR, its gene showed a non-significant tendency for higher expression in the female terminal abdomen than in the female antennae. Apart from that, only one of the divergent <italic>Ir</italic> genes (<italic>Ir116a</italic>) was significantly up-regulated in the female terminal abdomen. In the males, 14 <italic>Ir</italic> genes (13 antennal and 1 divergent) had higher expression in the antennae as compared to the terminal abdomen, while three <italic>Ir</italic> genes had higher expression in the terminal abdomen. Similar to the females, <italic>Ir116a</italic> was one of them, but also <italic>Ir87b</italic> and <italic>Ir87c</italic>.</p><p>Only one of the <italic>Ir</italic> genes, <italic>Ir75c</italic>, had up-regulated expression in the female antennae compared to those of the male, representing the only example of differential <italic>Ir</italic> gene expression between the antennae of the two sexes. Comparing the two terminal abdominal tissues, five <italic>Ir</italic> genes, including both antennal and divergent receptor genes, had higher expression in the male terminal abdomen, whereas expression of two <italic>Ir</italic> genes was higher in the female terminal abdomen (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>; Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Sensory neuron membrane proteins</title><p>The Hessian fly genome assembly contained 6 orthologues of <italic>Snmp1</italic> and one <italic>Snmp2</italic>. All of them were expressed in the antennae, and six of them (all but <italic>Snmp1a</italic>) were expressed in both terminal abdominal tissues (Table&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>; Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>; Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). In general, the <italic>Snmp</italic> genes had high expression, and the most highly expressed gene (<italic>Snmp1e</italic>) had a higher FPKM value than <italic>Orco</italic>.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Expression profiles of the genes coding for sensory neuron membrane proteins (SNMP) in </bold><bold><italic>M. destructor</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> Expression levels of the <italic>Snmp</italic> genes in the four transcriptomes represented as heat plots based on log-transformed FPKM values. Zero expression is represented by the lightest yellow color. Suffixes to gene names are explained in the Methods section.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-6"/></fig><p>In the females, <italic>Snmp1a-c</italic>, <italic>e</italic> and <italic>f</italic> had up-regulated expression in the antennae as compared to the terminal abdomen, while one (<italic>Snmp1d</italic>) was up-regulated in the terminal abdomen, both in relation to the female antennae and to the male terminal abdomen (Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>). Furthermore, <italic>Snmp2</italic> had slightly higher expression in the female terminal abdomen than in the female antennae, but the difference was not significant. The highest expression of <italic>Snmp2</italic> was found in the male terminal abdomen. In the males, <italic>Snmp1b-f</italic> had up-regulated expression in the antennae as compared to the terminal abdomen. Comparing expression of <italic>Snmp</italic> genes between the antennae of the two sexes, <italic>Snmp1a</italic> was greatly up-regulated (260X) in the female. In contrast, <italic>Snmp1b</italic> and <italic>1f</italic> had male-biased antennal expression, while <italic>Snmp1b</italic>, <italic>1c</italic>, and <italic>1e</italic> were similarly expressed in the antennae of the two sexes (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Odorant binding proteins</title><p>We annotated 32 <italic>Obp</italic> genes in the Hessian fly genome assembly, including two pseudogenes. Generally, OBPs are classified into different phylogenetic groups depending on the number of conserved cysteine residues. Classic OBPs have six cysteine residues, whereas members of the Plus-C class have additional cysteines and one characteristic proline
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. Five of the Hessian fly OBPs (OBP8-12) belonged to the Plus-C class.</p><p>All but one (<italic>Obp12</italic>) of the 32 <italic>MdObp</italic> genes showed expression in at least one of the analyzed tissues (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>; Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). Essentially all <italic>Obp</italic> genes were expressed in the antennae of both sexes, while slightly lower numbers of genes were expressed in the terminal abdominal tissues (Table&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Overall, the most highly expressed <italic>Obp</italic> genes had much higher expression levels (2&#x02013;3 orders of magnitude) than the most highly expressed <italic>Or</italic> or <italic>Snmp</italic> genes (Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). The Plus-C class of <italic>Obp</italic> genes (i.e. <italic>Obp8-12</italic>) had comparatively low expression levels in all four tissues (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>).</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Expression profiles of the genes coding for odorant binding proteins (OBP) in </bold><bold><italic>M. destructor</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> Expression levels of the <italic>Obp</italic> genes in the four transcriptomes represented as heat plots based on log-transformed FPKM values. Zero expression is represented by the lightest yellow color. Suffixes to gene names are explained in the Methods section.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-7"/></fig><p>In the female, most (23) of the <italic>Obp</italic> genes were more highly expressed in the antennae as compared to the terminal abdomen. Only one <italic>Obp</italic> gene (<italic>Obp31</italic>) showed a higher level of expression in the female terminal abdomen than in the female antennae (Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>), but the overall expression level of this gene was comparatively low. The males were similar to the females by having 20 <italic>Obp</italic> genes with higher expression in the antennae as compared to the terminal abdomen. These included most of the genes that also were antennally up-regulated in the female. Three <italic>Obp</italic> genes (<italic>Obp11</italic>, <italic>Obp24</italic> and <italic>Obp32</italic>) had higher expression in the male terminal abdomen as compared to the male antennae. However, despite the fact that most <italic>Obp</italic> genes had their highest expression in the two antennal tissues, their expression level in the terminal abdomen tissues was in general much higher than the expression of the other chemosensory gene families in the abdominal tissues (Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>).</p><p>A few <italic>Obp</italic> genes showed differential expression between the male and female antennae (Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>; Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>). Only two <italic>Obp</italic> genes (<italic>Obp1</italic> and <italic>Opb32</italic>) showed higher levels of expression in the female antennae, whereas six genes (<italic>Obp2</italic>, <italic>Opb17</italic>-<italic>18</italic>, <italic>Opb22</italic>, and <italic>Opb26-27</italic>) had higher expression in the male antennae. Nine of the <italic>Obp</italic> genes showed differential expression levels between the two terminal abdominal tissues; five of them (<italic>Obp1</italic>-<italic>3, Opb21</italic>, and <italic>Opb25</italic>) were more highly expressed in the female, while four (<italic>Obp10</italic>-<italic>11</italic>, <italic>Opb24</italic>, and <italic>Opb32</italic>) were more highly expressed in the male.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Chemosensory genes in the Hessian fly in relation to <italic>Drosophila</italic> and mosquitoes</title><p>The chemosensory gene families have been extensively studied in various <italic>Drosophila</italic> and mosquito species
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>], but had not been analyzed in plant-feeding dipterans, such as gall midges. The Hessian fly in the Cecidomyiidae family is both phylogenetically
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] and ecologically
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] well separated from flies and mosquitoes. The specific habits and highly evolved relationship to its host also makes studies of the Hessian fly chemosensory genes interesting for a more complete understanding of olfaction in Diptera. The current Hessian fly genome assembly contains genes for 122 ORs, 28 GRs, 39 IRs, 7 SNMPs, and 32 OBPs. In comparison to <italic>Drosophila</italic> and mosquitoes, the number of Hessian fly <italic>Or</italic> genes is relatively large, whereas the number of genes encoding taste receptors (GRs and divergent IRs) is small
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>], suggesting that olfaction is the dominant chemical sense in this species. This might be related to the short adult lifespan, with olfaction being a more time-efficient modality for host and mate assessment, occurring during flight at a distance rather than after landing via contact chemoreception. While clear orthologues of ORs are rarely found in distantly related species, the antennal IRs appear conserved across insect species
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. However, the Hessian fly genome lacked genes for three antennal IRs (<italic>Ir31a</italic>, <italic>Ir40a</italic>, and <italic>Ir92a</italic>) that are present in other Diptera, suggesting that also some olfactory functions have been lost in this herbivorous species. Insects generally have two <italic>Snmp</italic> genes (<italic>Snmp1</italic> and <italic>Snmp2</italic>), but some species have multiple paralogues of <italic>Snmp1</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. SNMP1 has been shown to be important for pheromone detection in <italic>Drosophila</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. The Hessian fly genome contains six <italic>Snmp1</italic> genes, which is the largest number identified in any insect so far. It is possible that this large number reflects the use of a multi-component sex pheromone in the Hessian fly
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>], and that the detection of the individual pheromone components requires specific OR-SNMP1 combinations.</p></sec><sec><title>Sex-specific antennal expression of chemosensory genes</title><p>Transcriptome profiling using RNAseq data has been shown to accurately predict gene expression levels
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>], and has recently been used to analyze the expression of chemosensory genes in several other insect species, including <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> and the <italic>A. gambiae</italic> mosquito
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. Here, we used a transcriptome profiling approach to analyze sex- and tissue specific expression in the Hessian fly. Our global transcriptome analysis that included all the ca. 27 000 predicted genes indicated that the gene expression profiles of the male and female antennae were highly similar to each other, while expression profiles of the antennae were different from the terminal abdominal tissues. In addition, the GO annotation also indicated very similar frequencies of transcript-associated GO terms in the two antennal transcriptomes. In fact, the results from the latter analysis were also similar to previous results from GO annotation of antennal transcriptomes of two bark beetle species and the moth <italic>Manduca sexta</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], suggesting that "transcript frequencies" in terms of presence/absence are conserved across insect orders.</p><p>When only the 228 chemosensory genes were included in the analysis, the expression profile differed widely between the four tissues. The majority of the chemosensory genes had up-regulated expression levels in the antennae as compared to the terminal abdominal tissues. Furthermore and in contrast to the global analysis, a clear difference in gene expression between the antennae of males and females was found. Although all analyzed chemosensory gene families contained some genes with expression levels that differed between the sexes, the most striking difference was found among the <italic>Or</italic> genes, for which ca. 62% of the genes with any expression showed at least a three-fold significant difference between male and female antennae, and ca. 50% of them showed at least a ten-fold difference, with the majority being female-biased. Thus, the proportion of <italic>Or</italic> genes with sex-biased expression was substantially larger than previously found in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]<italic>,</italic> a species in which both sexes feed (and females oviposit) on the same food, but similar to <italic>A. gambiae</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], where males and females feed on entirely different food. Similar to the mosquito, the sex-biased expression in the Hessian fly is likely to reflect the different ecological interests of males and females
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. In both sexes, the gene for the co-receptor ORCO
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>] had the highest expression levels of all <italic>Or</italic> genes. This is consistent with its broad expression and role in forming heteromeric complexes with the conventional ORs, required for the odor response of the neuron and localization of the OR in the cell membrane
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>].</p><p>During their ca. 18&#x000a0;h adult existence, male Hessian flies do just one thing, namely search for and mate with virgin females, carrying enough sperm to fertilize up to 35 females
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>]. Finding females is accomplished by long-range attraction to a female-produced sex pheromone, comprised of five to seven compounds
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>]. Similar to moths e.g.
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>], it is likely that the subfamily formed by the receptors with male-biased expression in the Hessian fly (i.e. OR112-121; Figure&#x000a0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) includes the receptors for the pheromone compounds. We currently test this hypothesis using heterologous assays. Interestingly, two of the <italic>MdOr</italic> genes (<italic>Or112</italic> and <italic>Or115</italic>) in the clade with putative pheromone receptors had high expression levels also in the females, and other receptors in this clade had moderate female expression. Thus, if these ORs are the pheromone receptors, it is likely that females also are able to detect some of their pheromone compounds.</p><p>In contrast to the males, for which there is no evidence in cecidomyiids of attraction to host plants
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>], adult females depend on plant chemicals to find and select host plants for their offspring
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>]. Females, during their ca. 9&#x02013;24&#x000a0;h existence, crawl from an eclosion site in the soil to a perch where they extend the abdominal segments to release a sex pheromone and, after mating, fly to find host plants for their eggs. Attraction to host plants is mediated by an array of volatile chemicals
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>] and discrimination between host and non-host plants would presumably require a larger and different set of ORs as compared to detection of the pheromone. Thus, it is likely that the 50 <italic>Or</italic> genes with female-biased expression are involved in host plant recognition. Similar to the Hessian fly, most of the <italic>Ors</italic> with sex-biased expression in <italic>A. gambiae</italic> were up-regulated in the female, i.e. the sex that blood-feeds and finds sites for oviposition
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>Interestingly, the <italic>Or</italic> gene expression profiles in the Hessian fly antennae were often correlated to the phylogenetic position of the ORs in the tree, i.e. the majority of the receptors within a phylogenetic subfamily showed male- or, in most cases, female-biased antennal expression. It is possible that ORs with similar sequences detect structurally similar chemicals. Thus, this result might also reflect the relative importance of host odors for females versus the pheromone compounds for males. A correlation between sex-specific expression bias and position in the phylogeny was also found for the ORs in a recent study on two ant species
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]. This is likely to represent adaptations that enable individuals to carry out the tasks that are specific to their sex or caste.</p><p>The majority of the conserved antennal <italic>MdIr</italic> genes had relatively high expression in the antennae, but only one of them (<italic>Ir75c</italic>) showed a clear difference in expression level between the sexes. This suggests that in contrast to the ORs, receptors in this more ancient family
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] detect compounds that might be of general importance for insects, regardless of sex. Of the antennal <italic>Ir</italic> genes, <italic>MdIr60a</italic> was not expressed in the antenna. Similarly, Benton et al.
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] did not detect expression of <italic>Ir60a</italic> in antennal samples of <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>. To our knowledge, a ligand for this receptor has not been identified yet in any species.</p><p>The carbon dioxide receptor genes <italic>MdGr1-3</italic> had high expression in the antennae (in both sexes), suggesting that this organ is responsible for carbon dioxide detection, which is similar to <italic>Drosophila</italic> (although <italic>Drosophila</italic> uses an heterodimer receptor, lacking the GR2 subunit)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>], but different from mosquitoes that detect this gas with the maxillary palps
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>]. Only one <italic>Gr</italic> gene, <italic>MdGr9</italic>, had male antennal-biased expression. In a phylogenetic analysis (Hessian fly Genomics Consortium, in prep), this receptor (together with MdGR7-8) grouped together with DmGR43a, which has been shown to monitor fructose levels in the fly brain
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>]. The reason why a tentative fructose receptor would have high expression in the antenna of male Hessian fly is not clear, but this receptor could possibly be important if males do feed on nectar
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p><p>Since SNMP1 is important for pheromone detection in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], we expected to find the highest expression levels of the <italic>MdSnmp1</italic> genes in the male antennae of the Hessian fly. However, only two (<italic>Snmp1b</italic> and <italic>1f</italic>) of the six <italic>Snmp1</italic> orthologues present in the Hessian fly genome had higher expression in the male antennae as compared to the female antennae. These two <italic>Snmps</italic> were also relatively highly expressed in the female antennae. Interestingly, <italic>Snmp1a</italic> had &#x0003e;200-fold higher expression in the female antennae as compared to the male antennae. Expression of <italic>Snmp</italic> genes in females might, again, suggest that females also are able to detect components of the sex pheromone, or alternatively, that the role of SNMP1 might not be restricted to detection of sex pheromones. Expression of <italic>Snmp1</italic> in the antennae of both sexes has also been found in other dipteran and non-dipteran species
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>].</p><p>In general, the <italic>MdObp</italic> genes had the highest expression levels of all analyzed chemosensory gene families, and the majority of them were most highly expressed in the antennae. Only a few <italic>Obp</italic> genes were differentially expressed between the antennae of males and females, which is similar to <italic>A. gambiae</italic> and the yellow fever mosquito, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>]. Similar to the other gene families, the <italic>MdObp</italic> genes that did show sex-biased expression might be important for the detection of compounds that elicit sex-specific behaviors.</p></sec><sec><title>Expression in terminal abdominal tissues</title><p>All chemosensory gene families in the Hessian fly contained several genes that were represented by reads also in the terminal abdominal samples. The <italic>Obp</italic> gene family was the most broadly expressed, followed by the <italic>Snmps</italic>, while the <italic>Or</italic> gene family had the most antennal-specific expression. Nevertheless, all gene families contained genes that were significantly more highly expressed in the male or female terminal abdominal segments as compared to the antennae. In the male, these included four <italic>Ors</italic>, two <italic>Grs</italic>, three <italic>Irs</italic>, one <italic>Snmp</italic>, and three <italic>Obps.</italic> In the female, two <italic>Or</italic> genes and one gene from each of the other families were more highly expressed in the terminal abdomen than in the antennae. These observations suggest that chemosensation is not restricted to the antennae of gall midges. Female Hessian flies examine the leaf surface with the tip of the abdomen prior to oviposition
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>], and oviposition is induced by chemical cues from host plants
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>], consistent with the expression of chemoreceptors in this tissue. Similarly, the gustatory sense of <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> in not restricted to head appendages and taste sensilla are present on the legs, wings, and female genitalia (in association with the ovipositor)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>]. In addition, <italic>Or59b</italic> in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> is predominantly expressed in the male accessory gland (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://flyatlas.org/atlas.cgi?name=CG3569-RA">http://flyatlas.org/atlas.cgi?name=CG3569-RA</ext-link>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>]), and a recent study showed that several <italic>Or</italic> genes are expressed in the testes of <italic>A. gambiae</italic> and that ORCO is involved in chemical-induced sperm activation
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>]. These results are consistent with the expression of several <italic>MdOrs</italic> including <italic>MdOrco</italic> in the male terminal abdominal tissue analyzed here.</p><p>Similar to the present study, other studies have reported that <italic>Snmp1</italic> and <italic>Snmp2</italic> as well as the <italic>Obps</italic> can be expressed in variety of tissues in addition to the chemosensory organs, suggesting that these proteins can have physiological roles independent of olfaction
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">86</xref>]. The <italic>Snmps</italic> and <italic>Obps</italic> that were expressed in the female Hessian fly terminal abdominal segments where the pheromone gland is found
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>], might be involved in the binding and transport of pheromone molecules before these are volatilized and released.</p><p>The GR and divergent IR families contained the largest proportions of genes for which we did not detect expression in the present study. Similarly, the five genes (<italic>MdObp8-12</italic>) of the Plus-C class of OBPs showed only low levels of expression. It is possible that these genes are expressed mainly in legs or wings, or in yet other tissues
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">88</xref>], which we did not analyze. Indeed, several <italic>Ir</italic> genes and Plus-C <italic>Obp</italic> genes showed high expression in the labella and tarsi of <italic>A. aegypti</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>]. Alternatively, these and the other "non-expressed" chemosensory genes might be expressed only in the larvae
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">91</xref>], which are likely to use contact chemical cues in order to locate a suitable feeding site inside the wheat plant
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>By conducting a comprehensive manual gene annotation and transcriptome analysis we found clear sex- and tissue-specific expression patterns of the chemosensory genes in the Hessian fly. While many studies of these genes have been performed on Diptera, especially <italic>Drosophila</italic> and mosquitoes, this is the first of a fly that feeds on plants. The expression profile difference between male and female Hessian fly was more pronounced than that observed in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>, but similar to <italic>A. gambiae</italic>, a species that also displays sex-divergent chemically-mediated behaviors. We found the most extreme sex-specific expression difference among the <italic>Or</italic> genes, which is likely to reflect the sex-divergent olfactory behaviors of the short-lived adults. In addition, the relatively large number of <italic>Or</italic> genes in the genome in combination with the few <italic>Gr</italic> genes and divergent <italic>Ir</italic> genes, suggest that long-range attraction to hosts and mates is more important than contact assessment in this species, in which the adults have reduced mouthparts and feeding behavior has not been documented. We also found that several genes of each gene family had expression that was not restricted to the antennae, indicating that they serve multiple and tissue-specific physiological roles. Future studies should focus on characterizing the function of the proteins encoded by these differentially expressed chemosensory genes in order to consolidate the link between the genetics and ecology of Hessian fly olfaction.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Identification of chemosensory genes in the genome</title><p>Full details of our manual annotation protocol for the genes encoding the ORs, GRs, IRs, SNMPs, and OBPs in the Hessian fly genome will be included in the publication of the genome (Hessian fly Genomics Consortium, in prep). In brief, reciprocal tBLASTn searches against the <italic>M. destructor</italic> genome sequence (assembly 1.0, available at the Agricultural Pest Genomics Resource Database:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.agripestbase.org">http://www.agripestbase.org</ext-link>) were conducted to identify the chemosensory genes<italic>.</italic> Removal of introns and identification of start and stop codons were performed manually, aided by a multiple sequence alignment and a Trinity <italic>de novo</italic> transcriptome assembly based on our Illumina reads. Genes only partially assembled in the genome were corrected/extended manually and suffixes added to the name of such genes: "FIX" was added to manually extended genes; "JOI" to joined fragments of the same gene (with support from transcriptome data), but assembled on two or three scaffolds; "NTE" and "CTE" to genes with missing N or C terminus, respectively; "PSE" to pseudogenes; and "INT" to genes with internal exons missing. One-letter abbreviations were used for genes with multiple suffixes, (i.e. F, J, N, C, and I). These suffixes are used also in the present study.</p></sec><sec><title>Insects and RNA isolation</title><p>The Hessian fly was reared using methods described in
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B92">92</xref>]. Strains of Hessian fly differ in their ability to live on wheat genotypes with resistance mediated by <italic>H</italic> genes
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B93">93</xref>]. We used the &#x02018;Great Plains&#x02019; biotype, which is avirulent (i.e. dies) on any wheat genotype that carries an <italic>H</italic> gene. It is also the same biotype that was used for genome sequencing. Females laid eggs on 1&#x02013;2 leaf seedlings of susceptible &#x02018;Roblin&#x02019; spring wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) planted in large pots (20&#x000a0;cm diam.) in a greenhouse (21-24&#x000b0;C, 60-85% RH). Puparia were removed from the plant and put on moist soil in Plexiglas cages under controlled environmental conditions (20&#x000b0;C, 70% relative humidity, 16:8&#x000a0;h light:dark photoperiod) for the adults to emerge.</p><p>Male and female antennae, as well as the 8<sup>th</sup>-10<sup>th</sup> female and male terminal abdominal segments, the latter including ovipositor and pheromone gland tissue in the females
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>], and the clasper in the males, were excised from newly emerged adults and put in separate tubes held at -80&#x000b0;C. In total, body parts from 283 males (566 antennae) and 320 females (640 antennae) were collected and used for RNA isolation. Tissues were homogenized using a rotor-stator homogenizer (Tissue-tearor model 985370&#x02013;395, Biospec Products Inc., USA), and total RNA extracted using the RNeasy Mini kit (Qiagen), following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The extraction yielded 3.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g total RNA from male antennae, 2.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g from female antennae, 6.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g from female terminal abdomen, and 5.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g from male terminal abdomen.</p></sec><sec><title>Illumina sequencing</title><p>The RNAseq libraries were prepared from cDNA averaging 230&#x000a0;nt using Illumina&#x02019;s TruSeq RNAseq Sample Prep kit. The four transcriptome libraries were pooled in equimolar concentration, quantified by qPCR, and sequenced from both ends of the fragment (100&#x000a0;bp reads) using a TruSeq SBS sequencing kit (version 3). Two lanes were sequenced on a HiSeq2000 at the University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, Il, USA. The data were analyzed with Casava 1.8 (pipeline 1.8)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">94</xref>], which also filtered out low-quality reads. Adaptor sequences were also removed from the dataset. The sequencing yielded ca. 314&#x000a0;M read-pairs from the four transcriptomes and for the two lanes in total.</p></sec><sec><title>Read mapping, transcript and gene prediction</title><p>The genome sequence (assembly 1.0) of <italic>M. destructor</italic> was downloaded from
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://agripestbase.org/hessianfly/?q=download">http://agripestbase.org/hessianfly/?q=download</ext-link>. Subsequently, the Illumina reads from the four transcriptomes were mapped separately to the genome assembly using TopHat (v. 2.0.8, with parameters for shorter introns)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B95">95</xref>], allowing for two base-pair mismatches. Strict mapping criteria were used in order to account for the high sequence similarity among several of the recently duplicated chemosensory genes (mainly <italic>Ors</italic>). Cufflinks (v. 2.1.1)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>] with multi-mapped read correction was then used to predict transcripts based on the mapping results, and estimation of gene expression levels in FPKM values (Fragments Per Kilobase of transcript per Million mapped reads). Cuffmerge and Cuffdiff
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>] were then used for prediction of genes by merging the predicted transcripts in the four tissues, allowing for comparison of FPKM values in the four transcriptomes at each predicted gene locus.</p></sec><sec><title>Gene ontology annotation</title><p>For an assessment of the transcript populations predicted by Cufflinks in the four tissues, we performed gene ontology (GO) annotation with Blast2GO (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.blast2go.com/b2ghome">http://www.blast2go.com/b2ghome</ext-link>)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. Blast2GO uses hierarchical vocabularies to assign genes or transcripts GO terms related to Biological Process, Cellular Component or Molecular Function, allowing for meta-analysis of gene populations
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. In the GO annotation, we included all procedures recommended to achieve the highest accuracy and most comprehensive GO annotation
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], all of which are provided in the Blast2GO software
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. The initial BLASTx step was performed with an E-value cut-off at 10<sup>-3</sup>, the mapping step using default settings, and the annotation step with an E-value cut-off at 10<sup>-3</sup>, and default settings for both GO-weight (5) and annotation cut-off (55). Subsequently, to increase the number of annotated transcripts, all transcripts with BLAST hits were included in InterProScan searches at the EBI (including the following applications: BlastProDom, FPrintScan, HMMPIR, HMMPfam, HMMSmart, HMMTigr, ProfileScan, HAMAP, PatternScan, SuperFamily, SignalPHMM, TMHMM, HMMPanther, Gene3D, Phobius, and Coils
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B96">96</xref>]). These results were then merged to the existing GO annotations via the "merge" step in Blast2GO (as described in
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]). The annotations were then further augmented using the ANNEX procedure, which verifies and adds "related" GO terms to transcripts that already have assigned GO terms, and the subsequent Blast2GO validation step (for details see
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]). In the present study, merging the InterProScan results to the GO annotation increased the number of annotated transcripts by 9&#x02013;11% in the four transcriptomes, whereas the ANNEX step increased the number of GO terms with 7&#x02013;8%.</p></sec><sec><title>Expression level analysis</title><p>The Cufflinks-predicted transcripts and genes and their FPKM values were used for whole transcriptome profiling. However, some of the chemosensory gene transcripts were not accurately predicted by Cufflinks, probably due the high sequence similarity of tandemly duplicated genes. Therefore, HTSeq (v. 0.5.3p9)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">97</xref>] and subsequently DESeq (v. 1.12.0)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">98</xref>] were used for more accurate expression estimations of the chemosensory genes, for which the exact genome coordinates were known. Thus, expression levels (in FPKM values) of the chemosensory genes are based on the number of paired reads mapped to the genome from the first nucleotide of the start codon to the third nucleotide of the stop codon of each gene.</p><p>Differences in expression levels for each of the chemosensory genes were analyzed pair-wise between the four transcriptomes using chi<sup>2</sup> tests that were based on weighted read-pair counts i.e. the number of mapped read-pairs for each gene in relation to the total number of mapped read-pairs in each transcriptome. The following comparisons were made: (i) female antennae <italic>vs.</italic> male antennae, (ii) female antennae <italic>vs.</italic> female terminal abdomen, (iii) male antennae <italic>vs.</italic> male terminal abdomen, and (iv) female terminal abdomen <italic>vs.</italic> male terminal abdomen. We used strict criteria for claiming differential expression; a gene was regarded as being differentially expressed (or "up-regulated" in relation to its expression in the other transcriptome in the pair-wise comparison) only if its FPKM value differed by at least 3-fold between the two analyzed transcriptomes, in combination with a significant Bonferroni-corrected p-value at &#x0003c;2.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup>. Genes with less than 10 mapped read-pairs in both of the transcriptomes under comparison were not analyzed for differential expression, since we considered expression of these genes too low for accurate estimates. Instead, these genes were considered as having no or biologically insignificant expression.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Availability of supporting data</title><p>All data supporting the results of this article are included in the additional files. The read sequences from the four transcriptomes have been submitted to the Sequence Read Archive (SRA) at NCBI under accession number SRP041173 and can be accessed at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/?term=SRP041173">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/?term=SRP041173</ext-link>. The phylogenetic tree (ORs) and underlying alignment file have been deposited at LabArchives (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.labarchives.com">http://www.labarchives.com</ext-link>): DOI 10.6070/H4251G56.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>FPKM: Fragments per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads; GO: Gene ontology; GR: Gustatory receptor; IR: Ionotropic receptor; OBP: Odorant binding protein; OR: Odorant receptor; SNMP: Sensory neuron membrane protein.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>MNA, HMR, and CL initiated the project, conceived and coordinated the study. MNA, KKOW, and HMR performed gene annotation and bioinformatics. MNA performed RNA isolation, gene ontology analysis, and drafted the manuscript. EV performed read-mapping, transcript prediction, and gene expression analysis. KKOW carried out transcriptome assemblies. MOH reared the insects, provided biological material and contributed substantially to manuscript preparation. MNA, EV, KKOW, HMR, and CL analyzed and interpreted the data. All authors contributed to study design and manuscript preparation. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>Top BLAST-hit species distribution for all predicted transcripts in the four transcriptomes.</bold> Hits for 15 371 transcripts from female antennae, 14 539 transcripts from male antennae, 13 001 transcripts from female terminal abdomen, and 14 265 transcripts from male terminal abdomen.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-S1.zip"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>Genome locations, FPKM values and top BLAST hits for all transcripts predicted by Cufflinks.</bold> Included are data for 27 044 predicted transcripts from female antennae, 24 769 transcripts from male antennae, 19 877 transcripts from female terminal abdomen, and 23 691 from male terminal abdomen.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-S2.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3</title><p><bold>Results from Gene Ontology (GO) Molecular Function annotation.</bold> Representation of transcript sequences based on frequency of associated Molecular Function (MF) GO terms at level 3 GO categorization for: <bold>(A)</bold> 11 015 annotated transcripts in female antennae (22 318 MF terms in total), and <bold>(B)</bold> 9 922 transcripts in female terminal abdomen (22 664 MF terms). The annotation was done separately for each of the four transcriptomes, but since the GO results were essentially identical in the two sexes, only the female results are shown for simplicity. GO terms relevant for chemosensation that differed in abundance between the antennae and terminal abdomen are underlined and highlighted in bold.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-S3.zip"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional file 4</title><p><bold>Results from Gene Ontology (GO) Biological Process annotation.</bold> Representation of transcript sequences based on frequency of associated Biological Process (BP) GO terms at level 2 GO categorization for: <bold>(A)</bold> 11 015 GO annotated transcripts in female antennae (38 314 BP terms in total), and <bold>(B)</bold> 9 922 transcripts in female terminal abdomen (43 892 BP terms). The annotation was done separately for each of the four transcriptomes, but since the GO results were essentially identical in the two sexes, only the female results are shown for simplicity.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-S4.zip"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5"><caption><title>Additional file 5</title><p><bold>Predicted amino acid sequences of the chemosensory genes.</bold> Included are odorant receptors, gustatory receptors, ionotropic receptors, sensory neuron membrane proteins, and odorant binding proteins identified in the Hessian fly genome.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-S5.zip"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S6"><caption><title>Additional file 6</title><p><bold>FPKM values for the 228 chemosensory genes in the four transcriptomes.</bold> Included are values for 122 odorant receptors (OR), 28 gustatory receptors (GR), 39 ionotropic receptors (IR), 7 sensory neuron membrane proteins (SNMP), and 32 odorant binding proteins (OBP). Suffixes to gene names are explained in the Methods section.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-S6.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S7"><caption><title>Additional file 7</title><p><bold>Lists of chemosensory genes differentially expressed among the four transcriptomes.</bold> Expression levels in the following tissues were compared: female antennae <italic>vs.</italic> female terminal abdomen, male antennae <italic>vs.</italic> male terminal abdomen, female antennae <italic>vs.</italic> male antennae, and female terminal abdomen <italic>vs.</italic> male terminal abdomen. Differential expression was defined by at least a 3-fold difference in the FPKM value of a gene in a comparison between two transcriptomes in addition to a significant Bonferroni-corrected p-value at &#x0003c;2.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>-4</sup> after a chi<sup>2</sup> test. Suffixes to gene names are explained in the Methods section.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-15-501-S7.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We acknowledge Sharon R. Hill for valuable discussion, and Kirk Anderson for rearing of Hessian flies. We thank Katharina Schneeberg and Alexey Polilov for kindly providing the cover image. MNA acknowledges the Swedish Research Council (VR, grant # 623-2011-704) and the Royal Physiographic Society for funding. MOH was funded by the National Institute of Food and Agriculture, Agriculture and Food Research Initiative- Foundational Program, grant #2011-67013-30211, "Insect effectors in molecular plant-insect interactions". The project was also supported by grants from the Swedish Research Council (VR) to CL (grants # VR-621-2010-5430 and VR-621-2013-4355).</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Niimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nozawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>The evolution of animal chemosensory receptor gene repertoires: roles of chance and necessity</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>963</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19002141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosse-Wilde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillbur</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlyter</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Antennal transcriptome analysis of the chemosensory gene families in the tree killing bark beetles, <italic>Ips typographus</italic> and <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> (Coleoptera: Curculionidae: Scolytinae)</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><issue>198</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23323973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grosse-Wilde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuebler</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bucks</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wicher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><article-title>Antennal transcriptome of <italic>Manduca sexta</italic></article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>7449</fpage><lpage>7454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21498690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Luetje</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Soriano-Agat&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanks</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><article-title>Sequencing and characterizing odorant receptors of the cerambycid beetle <italic>Megacyllene caryae</italic></article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22504490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Bruyne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><article-title>Odor detection in insects: volatile codes</article-title><source>J Chem Ecol</source><year>2008</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>882</fpage><lpage>897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18535862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinker</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwiebel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>Transcriptome profiling of chemosensory appendages in the malaria vector <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> reveals tissue- and sex-specific signatures of odor coding</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>271</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21619637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular architecture of smell and taste in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source><year>2007</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17506643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vannice</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Diaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><article-title>Variant ionotropic glutamate receptors as chemosensory receptors in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19135896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Clyne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Warr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lessing</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JC</given-names><suffix>JR</suffix></name><article-title>A novel family of divergent seven-transmembrane proteins: candidate odorant receptors in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>1999</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10069338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><article-title>Evolution of the gene lineage encoding the carbon dioxide receptor in insects</article-title><source>J Insect Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Warr</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular evolution of the insect chemoreceptor gene superfamily in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>14537</fpage><lpage>14542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14608037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Croset</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rytz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Budd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brawand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaessmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Ancient protostome origin of chemosensory ionotropic glutamate receptors and the evolution of insect taste and olfaction</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e1001064</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20808886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vannice</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><article-title>An essential role for a CD36-related receptor in pheromone detection in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2007</year><volume>450</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17943085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Litvack</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fandino</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Staples</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickens</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><article-title>The insect SNMP gene family</article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19364529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><article-title>SNMP is a signaling component required for pheromone sensitivity in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>10996</fpage><lpage>11001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18653762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Gracia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular evolution of the major chemosensory gene families in insects</article-title><source>Heredity</source><year>2009</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19436326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Blomquist G, Vogt RG</person-group><article-title>Biochemical diversity of odor detection: OBPs, ODEs and SNMPs</article-title><source>Insect pheromone biochemistry and molecular biology</source><year>2003</year><publisher-name>San Diego: Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>445</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gro&#x000df;e-Wilde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouch&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Breer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Candidate pheromone receptors provide the basis for the response of distinct antennal neurons to pheromonal compounds</article-title><source>Eur J Neurosci</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2364</fpage><lpage>2373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17445234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gro&#x000df;e-Wilde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Svato&#x00161;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>A pheromone-binding protein mediates the bombykol-induced activation of a pheromone receptor <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Chem Senses</source><year>2006</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16679489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><article-title>Odorant reception in insects: Roles of receptors, binding proteins, and degrading enzymes</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>2012</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23020622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chrystal</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cravchik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwiebel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>G protein-coupled receptors in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>298</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12364795</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barmina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><article-title>Evolution of gene expression in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> olfactory system</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1081</fpage><lpage>1092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18296696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rinker</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwiebel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>Blood meal-induced changes to antennal transcriptome profiles reveal shifts in odor sensitivities in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>8260</fpage><lpage>8265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23630291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Gagn&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><source>The plant-feeding gall midges of North America</source><year>1989</year><publisher-name>Ithaca, New York: Cornell University press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohfritsch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><article-title>Grasses and gall midges: Plant defense and insect adaptation</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>2003</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12460937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lambkin</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pape</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Courtney</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Skevington</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeates</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Blagoderov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiegmann</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><article-title>The phylogenetic relationships among infraorders and superfamilies of Diptera based on morphological evidence</article-title><source>Syst Entomol</source><year>2013</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>179</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yeates</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiegmann</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><article-title>Congruence and controversy: toward a higher-level phylogeny of Diptera</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>1999</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McClintock</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>The significance of responses of the genome to challenge</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1984</year><volume>226</volume><fpage>782</fpage><lpage>801</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohfritsch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><article-title>Virulent Hessian fly (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae) larvae induce a nutritive tissue during compatible interactions with wheat</article-title><source>Ann Entomol Soc Am</source><year>2006</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>316</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeannotte</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M-S</given-names></name><article-title>Hessian fly (<italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic>) attack causes a dramatic shift in carbon and nitrogen metabolism in wheat</article-title><source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><year>2008</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18052884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Rohfritsch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Shorthouse J, Rohfritsch O</person-group><article-title>Patterns in gall development</article-title><source>Biology of insect-induced galls</source><year>1992</year><publisher-name>New York: Oxford University Press</publisher-name><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>86</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>The adaptive significance of insect gall morphology</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>522</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Amarawardana</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Francke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Boddum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillbur</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>The chemical ecology of cecidomyiid midges (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae)</article-title><source>J Chem Ecol</source><year>2012</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22215563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berzonsky</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>RIH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohm</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Peairs</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><article-title>Breeding wheat for resistance to insects</article-title><source>Plant Breed Rev</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>296</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bouhssini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nsarellah</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nachit</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentika</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Benlahbib</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lhaloui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>First source of resistance in durum wheat to Hessian fly (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae) in Morocco</article-title><source>Genet Resour Crop Evol</source><year>1999</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>109</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gagn&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><article-title>A catalog of the Cecidomyiidae (Diptera) of the world</article-title><source>Mem Entomol Soc Wash</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>408</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Haftmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambron</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Francke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillbur</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of sex pheromone components of the Hessian fly, <italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic></article-title><source>J Chem Ecol</source><year>2009</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19067080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergh</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><article-title>Aspects of pheromone biosynthesis in the Hessian fly, <italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic> (Say)</article-title><source>J Insect Physiol</source><year>1991</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>899</fpage><lpage>906</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandanayaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Oviposition preferences of the Hessian fly and their consequences for the survival and reproductive potential of offspring</article-title><source>Ecol Entomol</source><year>2001</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>486</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rausher</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><article-title>Co-evolution and plant resistance to natural enemies</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>411</volume><fpage>857</fpage><lpage>864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11459070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boddum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Skals</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillbur</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Gall midge olfaction: Pheromone sensitive olfactory neurons in <italic>Contarinia nasturtii</italic> and <italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic></article-title><source>J Insect Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1306</fpage><lpage>1314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20416312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Hunter W, Kole C</person-group><article-title>Hessian fly</article-title><source>Genome mapping and genomics in arthropods</source><year>2008</year><publisher-name>Berlin: Springer</publisher-name><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><article-title>Gall midges (Hessian flies) as plant pathogens</article-title><source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source><year>2012</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22656645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Hardie J, Minks A</person-group><article-title>Gall midges</article-title><source>Pheromones of non-lepidopteran insects associated with agricultural plants</source><year>1999</year><publisher-name>Oxford, UK: CAB International</publisher-name><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>49</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Malsch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>The role of vision in the host plant&#x02012;finding behaviour of the Hessian fly</article-title><source>Physiol Entomol</source><year>1993</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolinski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwight</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eppig</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Issel-Tarver</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasarskis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matese</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringwald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Consortium</surname><given-names>TGO</given-names></name><article-title>Gene Ontology: tool for the unification of biology</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;tz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Terol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tal&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Blast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics research</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3674</fpage><lpage>3676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16081474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>G&#x000f6;tz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Terol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaraj</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nueda</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tal&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dopazo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>High-throughput functional annotation and data mining with the Blast2GO suite</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>3420</fpage><lpage>3435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18445632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauvageau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinn</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Differential analysis of gene regulation at transcript resolution with RNA-seq</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23222703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>van Baren</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hekmat-Scafe</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Scafe</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>McKinney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanouye</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of the odorant-binding protein gene family in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1357</fpage><lpage>1369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12213773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arensburger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Megy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrudan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Amedeo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Antelo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartholomay</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bidwell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Caler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Camara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Casola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandramouliswaran</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Christley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Costas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenstadt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Feschotte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser-Liggett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Guigo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemingway</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Howarth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Sequencing of <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> establishes a platform for mosquito comparative genomics</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>330</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20929810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bohbot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000fc;tzler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwiebel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular characterization of the <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> odorant receptor gene family</article-title><source>Insect Mol Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17635615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwiebel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular basis of odor coding in the malaria vector mosquito <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>4418</fpage><lpage>4423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20160092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hallem</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><article-title>Coding of odors by a receptor repertoire</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16615896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rinker</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwiebel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>Antennal transcriptome profiles of anopheline mosquitoes reveal human host olfactory specialization in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>749</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24182346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><article-title>The SNMP/CD36 gene family in Diptera, Hymenoptera and Coleoptera: <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>, <italic>D. pseudoobscura</italic>, <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>, <italic>Apis mellifera</italic>, and <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18342246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of genes expressed in the sex pheromone gland of the black cutworm Agrotis ipsilon with putative roles in sex pheromone biosynthesis and transport</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>636</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24053512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Slone</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwiebel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>Phylogenetic and transcriptomic analysis of chemosensory receptors in a pair of divergent ant species reveals sex-specific signatures of odor coding</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e1002930</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22952454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shiao</surname><given-names>M-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M-YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W-H</given-names></name><article-title>Transcriptional profiling of adult <italic>Drosophila</italic> antennae by high-throughput sequencing</article-title><source>Zool Stud</source><year>2013</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>42</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Chemical, color, and tactile cues influencing oviposition behavior of the Hessian fly (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae)</article-title><source>Environ Entomol</source><year>1990</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>308</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><article-title>A unified nomenclature system for the insect olfactory coreceptor</article-title><source>Chem Senses</source><year>2011</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21441366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Touhara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Insect olfactory receptors are heteromeric ligand-gated ion channels</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>452</volume><fpage>1002</fpage><lpage>1006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18408712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wicher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;fer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauernfeind</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stensmyr</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinemann</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Drosophila</italic> odorant receptors are both ligand-gated and cyclic-nucleotide-activated cation channels</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>452</volume><fpage>1007</fpage><lpage>1011</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18408711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Michnick</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><article-title>Atypical membrane topology and heteromeric function of <italic>Drosophila</italic> odorant receptors <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>257</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Domingos</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiappe</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><article-title>Or83b encodes a broadly expressed odorant receptor essential for <italic>Drosophila</italic> olfaction</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2004</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15339651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bergh</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Factors inducing mated behavior in female Hessian flies (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae)</article-title><source>Ann Entomol Soc Am</source><year>1992</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>233</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of the sex pheromone of the Hessian fly, <italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic> (Say)</article-title><source>Naturwissenschaften</source><year>1991</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>131</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosse-Wilde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Raming</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Breer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Genes encoding candidate pheromone receptors in a moth (<italic>Heliothis virescens</italic>)</article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>11845</fpage><lpage>11850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15289611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Touhara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Broadly and narrowly tuned odorant receptors are involved in female sex pheromone reception in <italic>Ostrinia</italic> moths</article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20044000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>V&#x000e1;squez</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grozinger</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Differential expression of odorant receptor genes involved in the sexual isolation of two <italic>Heliothis</italic> moths</article-title><source>Insect Mol Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20946534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gagn&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><article-title>The distinction between <italic>Dasineura</italic> spp. (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae) from apple and pear</article-title><source>Proc Entomol Soc Wash</source><year>1998</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>448</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><article-title>Foliar chemicals of wheat and related grasses influencing oviposition by Hessian fly, <italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic> (Say) (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae)</article-title><source>J Chem Ecol</source><year>1992</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1965</fpage><lpage>1980</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24254776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahanukar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><article-title>The molecular basis of CO2 reception in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>3574</fpage><lpage>3578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Aghajanian</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019; Connell</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigton</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><article-title>Electrophysiological responses of receptor neurons in mosquito maxillary palp sensilla to carbon dioxide</article-title><source>J Comp Physiol A</source><year>1995</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7674195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutzler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Loon</surname><given-names>JJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Takken</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zweibel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>Odor coding in the maxillary palp of the malaria vector mosquito <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1533</fpage><lpage>1544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17764944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Slone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>A fructose receptor functions as a nutrient sensor in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> brain</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>1113</fpage><lpage>1125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23178127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbrecht</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><article-title>Expression of SNMP-1 in olfactory neurons and sensilla of male and female antennae of the silkmoth <italic>Antheraea polyphemus</italic></article-title><source>Cell Tissue Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>303</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11320659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohbot</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickens</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><article-title>The genetics of chemoreception in the labella and tarsi of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24582661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Temporal changes in the egglaying behaviour of the Hessian fly</article-title><source>Entomol Exp Appl</source><year>1989</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of 1-octacosanal and 6-methoxy-2-benzoxazolinone from wheat as ovipositional stimulants for Hessian fly, <italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic></article-title><source>J Chem Ecol</source><year>2000</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>873</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><article-title>The organization of the chemosensory system in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>: a rewiew</article-title><source>Cell Tissue Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8118845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chintapalli</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dow</surname><given-names>JAT</given-names></name><article-title>Using FlyAtlas to identify better <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> models of human disease</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17534367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Malpartida</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwiebel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>Odorant receptor-mediated sperm activation in disease vector mosquitoes</article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>2566</fpage><lpage>2571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24550284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Galindo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><article-title>A large family of divergent <italic>Drosophila</italic> odorant-binding proteins expressed in gustatory and olfactory sensilla</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2001</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>1059</fpage><lpage>1072</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11729153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pelosi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ban</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Soluble proteins in insect chemical communication</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>1658</fpage><lpage>1676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16786224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Solinas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Isidoro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>Functional anatomy of female sex pheromone gland of <italic>Mayetiola destructor</italic> Say (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae)</article-title><source>Entomologica</source><year>1996</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>54</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rytz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Croset</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Ionotropic Receptors (IRs): Chemosensory ionotropic glutamate receptors in <italic>Drosophila</italic> and beyond</article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>888</fpage><lpage>897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23459169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Engsontia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walden</surname><given-names>KKO</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>The red flour beetle's large nose: An expanded odorant receptor gene family in <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18342245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kreher</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><article-title>The molecular basis of odor coding in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> larva</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2005</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15882644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Buscariollo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwiebel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>The molecular and cellular basis of olfactory-driven behavior in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> larvae</article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>6433</fpage><lpage>6438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18427108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohfritsch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><article-title>Hessian fly Avirulence gene loss of function defeats plant resistance without compromising the larva's ability to induce a gall tissue</article-title><source>Entomol Exp Appl</source><year>2012</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>249</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohfritsch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><article-title>H-gene-mediated resistance to Hessian fly exhibits features of penetration resistance to fungi</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2010</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20128702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Illumina Inc</collab><source>CASAVA v1.8 User Guide</source><year>2011</year><publisher-name>San Diego, California, USA: Illumina Inc</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><article-title>TopHat2: accurate alignment of transcriptomes in the presence of insertions, deletions and gene fusions</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>R36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23618408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Labarga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Web services at the European bioinformatics institute</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><issue>suppl 2</issue><fpage>W6</fpage><lpage>W11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17576686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>HTSeq: Analysing high-throughput sequencing data with Python</article-title><year>2010</year><comment>URL
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.huber.embl.de/users/anders/HTSeq/doc/overview.html">http://www.huber.embl.de/users/anders/HTSeq/doc/overview.html</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>R106</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>