<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Transl Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Transl Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Translational Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1479-5876</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4676172</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">743</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-015-0743-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>HERC5</italic> is a prognostic biomarker for post-liver transplant recurrent human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Feng</given-names></name><address><email>fengxue6879@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Higgs</surname><given-names>Brandon W.</given-names></name><address><phone>301-398-5014</phone><email>higgsb@medimmune.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Jiaqi</given-names></name><address><email>jiaqihuang94041@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morehouse</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name><address><email>morehousec@medimmune.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><address><email>weizhu365@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Xin</given-names></name><address><email>yaox@medimmune.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brohawn</surname><given-names>Philip</given-names></name><address><email>brohawnp@medimmune.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Zhan</given-names></name><address><email>xiaoz@medimmune.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sebastian</surname><given-names>Yinong</given-names></name><address><email>sebastiany@medimmune.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Zheng</given-names></name><address><email>zheng.r.liu@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Yun</given-names></name><address><email>yunxia@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Dong</given-names></name><address><email>shend@medimmune.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuziora</surname><given-names>Mike</given-names></name><address><email>kuzioram@medimmune.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Zhengwei</given-names></name><address><email>Harvey.Dong@astrazeneca.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Hulin</given-names></name><address><email>Hulin.Han@astrazeneca.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><address><email>Yi.Gu@astrazeneca.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Jianren</given-names></name><address><email>nlorg@public.sta.net.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Qiang</given-names></name><address><email>xiaqiang@medmail.com.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Yihong</given-names></name><address><email>oliver_67@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Liver Surgery and Liver Transplantation, Renji Hospital, Shanghai Jiaotong University School of Medicine, Shanghai, 201203 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Translational Bioinformatics, MedImmune, Gaithersburg, MD 20878 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Asia and Emerging Markets iMed, AstraZeneca R&#x00026;D, 199 Liangjing Road, Shanghai, 201203 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Shanghai Cancer Institute, Renji Hospital, Shanghai Jiaotong University School of Medicine, Shanghai, 201203 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>379</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Xue et al. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background and aims</title><p>Orthotopic liver transplantation (OLT) can be an effective treatment option for certain patients with early stage hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) meeting Milan, UCSF, or Hangzhou criteria. However, HCC recurrence rates post-OLT range from 20 to 40&#x000a0;%, with limited follow-up options. Elucidating genetic drivers common to primary and post-OLT recurrent tumors may further our understanding and help identify predictive biomarkers of recurrence&#x02014;both to ultimately help manage clinical decisions for patients undergoing OLT.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Whole exome and RNA sequencing in matched primary and recurrent tumors, normal adjacent tissues, and blood from four Chinese HCC patients was conducted. SiRNA knockdown and both qRT-PCR and Western assays were performed on PLCPRF5, SNU449 and HEPG2 cell lines; immunohistochemistry and RNA Sequencing were conducted on the primary tumors of Chinese HCC patients who experienced tumor recurrence post-OLT (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9) or did not experience tumor recurrence (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In three independent HCC studies of patients undergoing transplantation (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;21) or surgical resection (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;242, n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;44) of primary tumors (total n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;307), <italic>HERC5</italic> mRNA under-expression correlated with shorter: time to tumor recurrence (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.007 and 0.02) and overall survival (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0063 and 0.023), even after adjustment for relevant clinical variables. <italic>HERC5</italic> loss drives CCL20 mRNA and protein over-expression and associates with regulatory T cell infiltration as measured by FOXP3 expression. Further, matched primary and recurrent tumors from the 4 HCC patients indicated clonal selection advantage of Wnt signaling activation and CDKN2A inactivation.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>HERC5 plays a crucial role in HCC immune evasion and has clinical relevance as a reproducible prognostic marker for risk of tumor recurrence and survival in patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12967-015-0743-2) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Hepatocellular carcinoma</kwd><kwd>Orthotopic liver transplantation</kwd><kwd>Whole exome</kwd><kwd><italic>HERC5</italic></kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p>Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is the most common primary liver malignancy and third leading cause of cancer deaths worldwide, with Hepatitis B virus a major etiological factor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Beyond sorafenib (Bayer HealthCare Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Onyx Pharmaceuticals, Inc, Germany) which is only effective in a small patient population, there is no approved treatment for HCC. Patients have limited options, and orthotopic liver transplantation (OLT) is viable for certain early stage HCC cases, though it is only efficacious in a subset meeting Milan, Toronto, or UCSF clinical criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The HCC recurrence rates after OLT range from 20 to 40&#x000a0;%, and treatment options after recurrence are limited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. To date, certain clinicopathologic variables such as tumor size and absence of macroscopic vascular invasion are used to predict risk of recurrence, though success of these factors vary from study-to-study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In an effort to improve the prediction of HCC recurrence, molecular profiling has been applied in many studies.</p><p>Multiple transcriptomic and proteomic studies have been conducted to help understand the link between molecular mediators and factors of etiology, tumorigenesis, disease course, and/or other variables related to survival and recurrence in HCC. In fact, from 2003 to 2010, over 14 studies have identified gene signatures from a minimum of 12 genes or proteins to 186, totally more than 934 genes for purposes of predicting survival and/or recurrence in HCC patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. More recently, Kim et al., developed a 233 gene signature to discern early from late tumor recurrence in primarily HBV-positive HCC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], while Zheng et al., combined a 122 gene hepatic stellate cell signature with clinical variables for a prognostic index to predict overall survival in HCV-positive cirrhosis or HCC patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In contrast to gene or protein signatures, single analyte prognostic gene expression markers such as TNF-related apoptosis-inducing ligand (<italic>TRAIL</italic>) mRNA was shown to associate with tumor growth and survival, though the latter result did not show statistical significance, and melanoma-associated antigen-D2 (<italic>MAGE</italic>-<italic>D2</italic>)&#x000a0;mRNA was identified by Hashimoto et al., as a prognostic factor for disease-specific survival following curative hepatectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] The commonality of genes across these studies is low, primarily due to factors of: heterogeneity within HCC populations, degraded RNA isolated from formalin-fixed tissues, differences in clinical stages and etiologies, small sample sizes, lack of independent validation, and basic analytical strategy used to identify predictive genes. Beyond gene or protein expression patterns shown in these studies, the underlying genetic role in HCC recurrence and how it influences pathway modulation has not been explored&#x02014;something that can greatly enhance our ability to accurately predict tumor recurrence in HCC.</p><p>Recent sequencing studies have advanced our knowledge of genetic oncodrivers in HCC, identifying the most recurrent functional impacting mutations in genes and frequently modulated pathways such as Wnt signaling, G1/S cell cycle signaling, apoptosis, and JAK/STAT signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Additional work has helped elucidate both sites and functional effects of the viral-host genome integration for HBV within HCC patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. These studies have provided a foundation for the genetic landscape of primary tumors in HCC patients though the genetic basis leading to tumor recurrence remains poorly understood, particularly somatic variation shared between the primary and recurring tumors and mechanisms supporting certain predictors of survival or disease recurrence, beyond statistical correlates.</p><p>In this study, we used an integrated omics strategy to identify a hemizygous DNA deletion and concordant mRNA under-expression of <italic>HERC5</italic>, an IFN-induced HECT-type E3 protein ligase gene associated with shorter: time to tumor recurrence and overall survival in HCC patients. The downstream immune-pathological impact from loss of <italic>HERC5</italic> was also determined. Additionally, this study indicates a clonal selection advantage in the genetic changes in Wnt signaling in the recurrent tumors, relative to primary tumors of HCC patients. Assessing risk of such outcomes in HCC is a significant unmet need and a predictive biomarker to help manage clinical decisions has high relevance for patients potentially undergoing OLT.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Patients and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Patients and samples</title><p>To adhere to REporting recommendations for tumour MARKer prognostic studies (REMARK) reporting of clinical specimens, 21 patients within the Hangzhou criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] who underwent OLT at Renji Hospital from 2008 to 2012 were retrospectively included in this study. No stratification or matching was used for patient inclusion in this study. Informed written consent was obtained from each patient and the study protocol conformed to the ethical guidelines of the 1975 Declaration of Helsinki as reflected in a priori approval by the Ethics Committee of Renji Hospital. No donor organs were obtained from executed prisoners or other institutionalized persons. Within 24&#x000a0;months after OLT, 9 patients had recurrent liver tumors or remote metastasis following OLT, while the remaining 12 patients were tumor free. All clinical variables considered are provided in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and further detailed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S1. The primary tumor (P<sub>T</sub>) and normal adjacent tissue (P<sub>NAT</sub>) were collected from all patients (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;21). The recurrent tumor (R<sub>T</sub>), normal adjacent tissue from donor (R<sub>NAT</sub>), and recipient blood (P<sub>B</sub>) were collected from 4 of 9 recurrent patients.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>The summary of clinical information for 21 Chinese HCC patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Patient</th><th align="left">Recurrent with 24&#x000a0;months&#x000b1;</th><th align="left">Sex</th><th align="left">Age</th><th align="left">Primary tumor grade</th><th align="left">Child</th><th align="left">BCLC</th><th align="left">Primary tumor size (cm)</th><th align="left">Criteria (Milan&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1; UCSF&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2; Exceed&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3)</th><th align="left">AFP (ng/mL)</th><th align="left">MELD</th><th align="left">Time of recurrent after OLT (month)</th><th align="left">Recurrent tumor organ</th><th align="left">HBV (pre-OLT)</th><th align="left">HBV (post-OLT)</th><th align="left">MULT&#x000b1;</th><th align="left">SAT&#x000b1;</th><th align="left">ENCAP&#x000b1;</th><th align="left">CIRR&#x000b1;</th><th align="left">VES&#x000b1;</th><th align="left">THROMB&#x000b1;</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">HCC1*</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">M</td><td char="." align="char">48</td><td align="left">III</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">A3</td><td align="left">5*5*3</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">2935.9</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">Liver</td><td align="left">Positive</td><td align="left">Negative</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCC4*</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">M</td><td char="." align="char">59</td><td align="left">II</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">B</td><td align="left">8*6*5.5</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td align="left">6.5</td><td align="left">Liver</td><td align="left">Positive</td><td align="left">Positive</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="left">1</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCC5*</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">M</td><td char="." align="char">67</td><td align="left">II</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">B</td><td align="left">5*4*3</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">&#x0003e;3000</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">Liver</td><td align="left">Negative</td><td align="left">Negative</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCC11*</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">F</td><td char="." align="char">57</td><td align="left">II&#x02013;III</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">B</td><td align="left">0.5&#x02013;2.5</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">1581.6</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">Lung</td><td align="left">Negative</td><td align="left">Negative</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCC2</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">M</td><td char="." align="char">43</td><td align="left">II</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">B</td><td align="left">9*8*6</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">1461.1</td><td char="." align="char">21</td><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">Liver</td><td align="left">Positive</td><td align="left">Negative</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCC3</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">M</td><td char="." align="char">42</td><td align="left">III</td><td align="left">B</td><td align="left">B</td><td align="left">6*6*2.5, 10*8*4</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">&#x0003e;3000</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td align="left">14.5</td><td align="left">Liver</td><td align="left">Positive</td><td align="left">Negative</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCC6</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">M</td><td char="." align="char">41</td><td align="left">III</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">B</td><td align="left">7*5*4</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">126</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">Lung</td><td align="left">Positive</td><td align="left">Negative</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCC8</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">M</td><td char="." align="char">42</td><td align="left">III</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">B</td><td align="left">10*10*7</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">&#x0003e;3000</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">Liver</td><td align="left">Positive</td><td align="left">Negative</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">N/A</td><td char="." align="char">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCC10</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">M</td><td char="." align="char">59</td><td align="left">III</td><td align="left">A</td><td align="left">A3</td><td align="left">4*3.5*3.5</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">1888.2</td><td char="." align="char">15</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">Liver</td><td align="left">Positive</td><td align="left">Negative</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C2</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>55</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>I&#x02013;II</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>C</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>D</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>5.5*5*4.5*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>2</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>5.2</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>4</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Negative</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C6</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>51</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>II</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A3</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>3*2.5*2*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>137.5</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>13</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Negative</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C8</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>64</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>I</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A3</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>5*1.5*1.5*, 3*2*2*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>3</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>62.5</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>13</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C9</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>40</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>II</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A3</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>1*1*1*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>9.2</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>3</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C11</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>62</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>I</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A3</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>3*3*2*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>5.4</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>9</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Negative</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C12</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>40</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>II&#x02013;III</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A2</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>2.5*1.5*1*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>210.8</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>4</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C13</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>49</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>I&#x02013;II</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>C</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>3*2.5*2.5*; 2*2*2*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>4.3</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>4</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Negative</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C14</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>59</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>II</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>7*5*5*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>3</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>240.7</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>20</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C15</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>49</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>II</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>5*4*2*; 5*4.5*3*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>3</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>NA</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>4</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Negative</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C16</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>49</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>II&#x02013;III</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A3</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>5*5*4*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>128.9</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>11</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C18</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>57</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>I</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A2</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>5*4*4*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>6.6</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>2</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Negative</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>HCC-C19</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>M</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>41</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>II&#x02013;III</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>4*2.5*2*, 3*2*1.8*</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>2</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>220.9</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>2</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>N/A</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>Positive</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>1</italic>
</td><td align="left">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">
<italic>0</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Patient OLT inclusion criteria included: ECOG (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status) score 0&#x02013;2, tumor within Hangzhou criteria and no major vascular invasion or extra hepatic metastases from imaging studies. Exclusion criteria included absolute contradictions of: involvement of the surrounding tissue or distant metastasis, co-current non-curable extra hepatic malignancies, active infection; relative contraindications included: pulmonary hypertension, symptomatic ischemic heart disease, severe renal insufficiency, and mental disorders</p><p>
<italic>AFP</italic> alpha-fetoprotein, <italic>HBV</italic> hepatitis B virus, <italic>MULT</italic> multiplicity, <italic>ENCAP</italic> encapsulated, <italic>CIRR</italic> cirrhosis, <italic>THROMB</italic> thrombosis, <italic>OLT</italic> orthotopic liver transplantation, <italic>BCLC</italic> barcelona Clinical Liver Cancer staging, <italic>SAT</italic> satellite, <italic>VES</italic> vessel, <italic>Child</italic> Child-Pugh score, <italic>MELD</italic> Model for End-Stage Liver Disease, <italic>&#x000b1;1</italic> Yes, <italic>0</italic> No</p><p>*&#x000a0;These 4 patients have matched primary and recurrent tumor specimens, normal adjacent tissue from the primary and recurrent tumors, and recipient blood specimens (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20 total specimens)</p><p>Italicized rows indicate patients who did not experience tumor recurrence post-OLT (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12), while non-italicized rows indicate patients who did experience tumor recurrence post-OLT (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>DNA sequence, read mapping and variant calling</title><p>DNA exome sequencing (WES) was generated by Beijing Genomics Institute (BGI) using the Illumina standard library preparation and sequencing protocols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Paired-end 90mer sequence FASTQs for both data types were provided to MedImmune. WES data was available from four patients, all of whom experienced tumor recurrence post-OLT with the following specimens: P<sub>T</sub>, R<sub>T</sub>, P<sub>NAT</sub>, R<sub>NAT</sub>, and P<sub>B</sub>. QC and both patient-level and summarized variants results are provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Tables&#x000a0;S2&#x02013;S5. Detailed explanations of somatic and germline variant and indel calling is provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>, in addition to the following methods: Patient identity, Clonal relationship value derivation, Donor tissue presence in recurrent tumors, Somatic copy number variation (CNV) analysis, Specificity of HERC5 prognostic correlation among genes in chr4q, and Integrated pathway analysis (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Tables&#x000a0;S6&#x02013;S8).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>RNASeq read mapping and differential expression analysis</title><p>RNASeq data was generated by BGI using the Illumina standard library preparation and sequencing protocols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Paired end 90mer sequence FASTQs were provided to MedImmune. Sequence data was QCd using FastQC (v0.10.1), with average read count per mate 50 million. Reads were mapped to reference (UCSC hg19; Feb 2009 release; Genome Reference Consortium GRCh37) using TopHat2 (v2.0.9; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>) using the human reference gtf annotation file (GRCh37.68). Transcript counts were calculated/normalized using htseq-count and DESeq (v1.12.1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>). DESeq&#x02019;s negative binomial distribution was used to calculate p-values and fold changes between P<sub>T</sub> and P<sub>NAT</sub> as well as R<sub>T</sub> and R<sub>NAT</sub> using p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01 and |fold| &#x0003e;2 as a threshold for the four patients. These results were used in the pathway analyses and combined with the same genes harboring copy number (CN) amplified or deleted regions (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref> for CN calling methods). Unadjusted p-values were utilized to simply identify the most differential transcripts within a single patient (P<sub>T</sub> vs. P<sub>NAT</sub>) using the fold change magnitude as a primary gene ranking. Since <italic>p</italic> value calculations were conducted within each patient, there was no replication and statistical power was not adequate to warrant multiple testing adjustment. Tumor cell prevalence was evaluated using ABSOLUTE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] and verified against pathology assessments for each tumor. RNASeq data was available from 21 patients (9 experienced tumor recurrence post-OLT and 12 did not) with the following specimens: P<sub>T</sub> and P<sub>NAT</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Time-to-event analyses</title><p>Time-to-event analyses were used to correlate the expression of the four genes (<italic>NAA11</italic>, <italic>HERC5</italic>, <italic>DDX60</italic>, and <italic>HERC6)</italic> identified with tumor recurrence among the 21 Chinese patients&#x02019; primary tumors from this study (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9 experienced tumor recurrence; n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12 did not experience tumor recurrence). The expression of each gene in the normal adjacent tissue was subtracted from the tumor expression for each patient (P<sub>T</sub>-P<sub>NAT</sub>) individually, then each gene was cut at the median into high or low expression groups. In alignment with REMARK criteria, Kaplan&#x02013;Meier (KM) analysis, univariate Cox proportional hazards (PH) regression, and multivariate Cox PH regression analyses were conducted adjusting for HBV status post-OLT, age (binary), gender, and tumor grade. These four variables were the most relevant for potential confounding factors with a molecular prognostic. Cirrhosis status was positive for all but one patient, so this variable was not used in the analysis of these 21 patients. <italic>HERC5</italic> was the only significant correlate (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) with tumor recurrence among the four genes using a KM model (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Univariate Kaplan&#x02013;Meier (KM) and Cox proportional hazards (PH) models and multivariate Cox PH models for the 21 Chinese HCC patients in this study, HCC patients from Roessler et al. study, and HCC patients from Boyault et al. study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">21 Chinese patients</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Recurrence (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;21; 9 events)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">HR (95&#x000a0;% CI)</th><th align="left">p value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Univariate Cox PH</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;HBV pre-OLT (Yes, No)</td><td align="left">0.285 (0.06, 1.48)</td><td align="left">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Tumor grade (GI, GII GIII)</td><td align="left">1.27 (0.63, 2.01)</td><td align="left">4.50E&#x02212;02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Age (&#x0003c;49)</td><td align="left">2.33 (0.62, 8.68)</td><td align="left">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Gender (M, F)</td><td align="left">0.29 (0.03, 2.47)</td><td align="left">0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>HERC5</italic> (Low, High)</td><td align="left">10.34 (1.28, 83.55)</td><td align="left">0.029</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Univariate KM</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>HERC5</italic> (Low, High)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Multivariate Cox PH</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>HERC5</italic> (Low)</td><td align="left">7.29</td><td align="left">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;HBV pre-OLT (Yes, No)</td><td align="left">0.26</td><td align="left">0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Tumor grade</td><td align="left">2.41</td><td align="left">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Age (&#x0003c;49)</td><td align="left">2.08</td><td align="left">0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Gender (M, F)</td><td align="left">1.86</td><td align="left">0.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Roessler et al. study</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Survival (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;224; 86 events)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Recurrence (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;224; 125 events)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">HR (95&#x000a0;% CI)</th><th align="left">p value</th><th align="left">HR (95&#x000a0;% CI)</th><th align="left">p value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Univariate Cox PH</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;HBV (AVR-CC, CC, No)</td><td align="left">1.32 (0.86, 2.03)</td><td align="left">0.212</td><td align="left">1.24 (0.86, 1.79)</td><td align="left">0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;TNM Staging (I, II, III)</td><td align="left">2.34 (1.77, 3.09)</td><td align="left">2.18E&#x02212;09</td><td align="left">1.76 (1.41, 2.20)</td><td align="left">7.81E&#x02212;07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Age (&#x0003c;50)</td><td align="left">1.26 (0.84, 1.88)</td><td align="left">0.262</td><td align="left">1.01 (0.72, 1.42)</td><td align="left">0.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Gender (M, F)</td><td align="left">1.86 (0.09, 3.83)</td><td align="left">0.0933</td><td align="left">2.36 (1.24, 4.50)</td><td align="left">0.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Cirrhosis (No, Yes)</td><td align="left">0.20 (0.05, 0.80)</td><td align="left">0.0227</td><td align="left">0.50 (0.23, 1.07)</td><td align="left">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>HERC5</italic> (Low, High)</td><td align="left">1.79 (1.17, 2.74)</td><td align="left">0.00706</td><td align="left">1.55 (1.07, 2.24)</td><td align="left">0.021</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Univariate KM</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>HERC5</italic> (Low, High)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.0063</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.0198</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Multivariate Cox PH</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>HERC5</italic> (Low)</td><td align="left">2.02</td><td align="left">0.004</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Gender (M, F)</td><td align="left">1.36</td><td align="left">0.42</td><td align="left">2.07</td><td align="left">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Cirrhosis (No, Yes)</td><td align="left">0.28</td><td align="left">0.076</td><td align="left">0.56</td><td align="left">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Age (&#x0003c;50)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0.99</td><td align="left">1.01</td><td align="left">0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;HBV (AVR-CC, CC, No)</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">1.36</td><td align="left">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;TNM Staging (I, II, III)</td><td align="left">2.32</td><td align="left">1.06E&#x02212;08</td><td align="left">1.74</td><td align="left">2.21E&#x02212;06</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Boyault et al. study</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Survival (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;41; 20 events)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">PFS (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;41; 20 events)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">HR (95&#x000a0;% CI)</th><th align="left">p value</th><th align="left">HR (95&#x000a0;% CI)</th><th align="left">p value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Univariate Cox PH</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;HBV (Yes, No)</td><td align="left">1.32 (0.51, 3.40)</td><td align="left">0.57</td><td align="left">1.02 (0.44, 2.38)</td><td align="left">0.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Gender (M, F)</td><td align="left">1.01 (0.34, 3.03)</td><td align="left">9.88E&#x02212;01</td><td align="left">1.30 (0.49, 3.41)</td><td align="left">6.01E&#x02212;01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Age (&#x0003c;65)</td><td align="left">1.10 (0.45, 2.67)</td><td align="left">0.85</td><td align="left">1.48 (0.70, 3.17)</td><td align="left">0.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>HERC5</italic> (Low, High)</td><td align="left">2.69 (1.11, 6.51)</td><td align="left">0.029</td><td align="left">1.96 (0.95, 4.05)</td><td align="left">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Univariate KM</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>HERC5</italic> (Low, High)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.023</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Multivariate Cox PH</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>HERC5</italic> (Low)</td><td align="left">3.31</td><td align="left">0.018</td><td align="left">3.8</td><td align="left">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;HBV (Yes, No)</td><td align="left">1.28</td><td align="left">0.63</td><td align="left">1.16</td><td align="left">0.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Gender (M, F)</td><td align="left">1.22</td><td align="left">0.74</td><td align="left">1.32</td><td align="left">0.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Age (&#x0003c;65)</td><td align="left">1.02</td><td align="left">0.42</td><td align="left">1.02</td><td align="left">0.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Models indicate predictions of survival, PFS, or HCC recurrence with <italic>HERC5</italic> mRNA expression and other relevant clinical factors</p><p>Tumor grade is defined by American Joint Committee on Cancer.&#x000a0;<italic>AJCC Cancer Staging Manual</italic>. 7th ed. New York, NY: Springer; 2010; TNM staging levels are defined by the TNM combinations corresponding to one of five stages (stages I&#x02013;V)</p><p>
<italic>AVR-CC</italic> active viral replication chronic carrier, <italic>CC</italic> chronic carrier, <italic>No</italic> no HBV</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Then, correlation between under-expression of <italic>HERC5</italic> and both progression-free survival (PFS) and overall survival was conducted in a publically available HCC microarray dataset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, E-TABM-36]. This <italic>HERC5</italic> under-expression was also tested again with both HCC recurrence and overall survival in an additional publically available microarray dataset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, GSE14520]. As was conducted for the 21 HCC patients in this study, the three different analysis models (KM model, univariate Cox PH regression, and multivariate Cox PH regression) were used to test association of <italic>HERC5</italic> under-expression with outcomes in these additional studies (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). For study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], liver tissue from healthy donors was available, so <italic>HERC5</italic> (219863_at) was divided into high or low patient groups using mean-2 standard deviations (SD) of the normal liver distribution (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;239) as the cut point (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;62 and 180 HCC patients in low or high groups, respectively [18 patients were missing clinical data]). The difference between these groups was assessed using the grouping coefficient p-value, hazard ratio, and likelihood ratio test, in multivariate Cox PH regression with the available variables of age, cirrhosis (binary), gender (binary), HBV/HCV status (active viral replication chronic carrier&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2; chronic carrier&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1; no&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0), and TNM staging (I, II, or III). The same variables were also assessed individually in univariate Cox PH regression. Both overall survival and time to tumor recurrence were assessed in two separate analyses (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). For study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], no normal healthy tissue (matched nor independent subject as in study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]) was available, so <italic>HERC5</italic> was cut into high or low groups using the median of the HCC primary tumor expression values (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20 and 24 HCC patients in low or high groups, respectively [four patients were missing clinical data]). Then overall survival and PFS between high and low patient groups was computed adjusting for the available variables of gender (binary), age, and HBV (titer negative&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0; titer positive&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1) status (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Note that all available clinical variables in both microarray validation studies were analyzed with both univariate and multivariate Cox PH regressions with <italic>HERC5</italic> to assess contribution of these variables to prognostic outcomes. All model summaries are reported in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Biological significance of HERC5 loss in HCC</title><p>HERC5 siRNA transfection experiments, Microarray study of HERC5 siRNA knockdown in HCC cell lines, qRT-PCR (TaqMan) Validation, and Cell culture, ELISA assays and FOXP3 IHC assay on P<sub>T</sub> and P<sub>NAT</sub> samples are described in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Identification of tumor origin and estimation of donor cell contamination in the recurrent tumors of HCC patients post-OLT</title><p>Cases of donor-transmitted malignancies in cadaveric organ transplants are very rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] in that recurrent HCC cases post-OLT are likely tumors derived from the recipient, thus the recurrent tumor (R<sub>T</sub>) genetic composition should match the primary tumor (P<sub>T</sub>). Previous studies have used microsatellite markers or CNVs to answer this question of tumor origin post-OLT or resection in HCC, as it has important implications for clinical and therapeutic strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. We implemented a derivation of the clonal relationship value [CR, 39] to determine the tumor origin in the R<sub>T</sub>s for the four patients&#x02014;all four were of recipient origin (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure&#x000a0;S5).</p><p>Single nucleotide variants (SNVs) were used to assess donor tissue contamination within each R<sub>T</sub>. Since all four R<sub>T</sub>s were determined to originate from the recipient, any clonality difference between the P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s, such as clonal frequencies is due to purity of the R<sub>T</sub> biopsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Donor cell contamination in the capture of the R<sub>T</sub> can dilute the magnitude of somatic differences. Elimination of recipient versus donor-identified differences [normal adjacent tissue from donor (R<sub>NAT</sub>) vs. recipient blood (P<sub>B</sub>)] controls for some of this contamination, though the distribution of cancer clones will still vary between the P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s. The malignancy in patient HCC11 occurred in the lung, thus, both primary and metastatic tumors were of recipient origin, serving as a negative control against the other three patients. Using two independent approaches&#x02014;somatic SNVs or germline SNPs, for each patient (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>), we estimated the proportion of donor cell contamination in the R<sub>T</sub>s as: HCC1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;72&#x02013;86&#x000a0;%; HCC4&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3&#x02013;9&#x000a0;%; HCC5&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;48&#x02013;64&#x000a0;%; and HCC11&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0&#x000a0;% (recipient&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;donor; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S6A&#x02013;B).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Somatic single nucleotide variant and insertion/deletion identification in primary and recurrent tumors of 4 HCC patients</title><p>We first asked whether there were potential major drivers shared between the P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s in HCC. Following quality control of the WES and RNASeq data (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figures&#x000a0;S2, S3), we identified 1,145 somatic variants using a stringent selection approach and controlling for donor-recipient differences (i.e. elimination of R<sub>NAT</sub> vs. P<sub>B</sub> variants; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>) in both P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s including 616 somatic nonsilent (nonsynonymous, stop-gain, stop-loss, or frameshift substitution) SNVs or insertion/deletions (indels) affecting 567 genes (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Tables&#x000a0;S3&#x02013;S5). On average 123 and 121 nonsilent somatic SNVs and 5 and 4.3 indels were identified, respectively in the P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s&#x02014;an average of 96 SNVs and 3.5 indels shared between these tumors (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S3). The somatic SNV distribution in P<sub>T</sub> and R<sub>T</sub> specimens had highest occurrences of C&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;T/G&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;A and lowest occurrences of T&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;G/A&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;C (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure&#x000a0;S4), consistent with a previous HCC report of coding exons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], and P<sub>T</sub> and R<sub>T</sub> pairs for each patient had similar distributions of transition/transversion substitutions, though it is interesting that HCC11 showed highest prevalence of T&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;A/A&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;T. The nonsilent-to-silent SNV rate was average of 2.8 in the P<sub>T</sub>s and 2.3 in the R<sub>T</sub>s&#x02014;a lower ratio in the R<sub>T</sub>s due to donor-tissue contamination ( Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S3, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). Nonsilent variants shared between P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s had a higher proportion of clones compared to each unique set (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure&#x000a0;S1A-D) and variant allele frequencies (Vfs) for these shared SNVs were significantly higher (mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;39.4) than those unique to P<sub>T</sub>s (mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;23.4; p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001 all four patients; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S3; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure&#x000a0;S1E), suggesting shared somatic mutations to likely be driver mutations. The SNVs in the P<sub>T</sub>s called using WES were confirmed at certain loci with adequate depth and quality using WGS and RNASeq data (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S4).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Somatic copy number variant (CNV) detection in the primary, recurrent, and shared tumors of HCC patients</title><p>Somatic copy number (CN) amplifications or deletions were selected for uniqueness to the P<sub>T</sub>, R<sub>T</sub>, or shared between the two, all within at least 3 of 4 patients (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>; &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Patients and methods</xref>&#x0201d;). Among the hemizygous (hemi) or homozygous (homo) amplifications identified, those that have been observed in a previous study of primary tumors in HCC using comparative genomic hybridization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] are indicated by an asterisk (*). Those amplifications that were common to both the P<sub>T</sub> and R<sub>T</sub> in this study included: 1q* (hemi in all patients), 6p* (homo in 2 patients; hemi in 1 patient), 8q* (homo in 1 patient; hemi in 2 patients), 17q* (hemi in 3 patients), and 20p* (hemi in 3 patients). Common hemi or homo deletions identified in P<sub>T</sub> and R<sub>T</sub> included: 4q* (hemi in 3 patients) and 17p* (hemi in 3 patients), and amplified regions unique to R<sub>T</sub>s included 17q (hemi in all patients) and 20q (hemi in all patients). Thus, the vast majority of somatic CN amplifications or deletions were shared between the P<sub>T</sub> and R<sub>T</sub>, with two short regions having unique CN amplifications in the R<sub>T</sub>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Somatic copy number amplifications (<italic>red</italic>), deletions (<italic>green</italic>), or neutral (<italic>yellow</italic>) identified in the primary (inner track) and recurrent (outer track) tumors of <bold>a</bold> HCC1, <bold>b</bold> HCC4, <bold>c</bold> HCC5, and <bold>d</bold> HCC11; <bold>e</bold> both shared and unique regions of CN amplifications or deletions in 3/4 patients across the genome. <italic>Color code</italic> is as follows: unique to primary tumors (<italic>red</italic> amplification; <italic>blue</italic> deletion); unique to recurrent tumors (<italic>brown</italic> amplification); and shared by the primary and recurrent tumors (<italic>green</italic> amplification; <italic>purple</italic> deletion)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2015_743_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>An integrated genetics and genomics analysis identifies Wnt-signaling pathway activation and tumor suppressor gene CDKN2A inactivation shared in both P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s of HCC patients</title><p>Using somatic variants, CNVs, and gene expression from P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure&#x000a0;S7; &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Patients and methods</xref>&#x0201d;), Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling was identified as the most altered pathway in both P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s across all four patients (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S6). Although few affected genes were shared between patients, all identified genetic changes had the potential to prevent ubiquitin-mediated degradation of beta-catenin in the cytoplasm, drive activation of beta-catenin in the nucleus (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), and subsequent loss of cell-cycle control by inactivation of CDKN2A.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling and directly related pathways affected by genetic-driven and/or gene expression activation or suppression in primary and/or recurrent tumors of 4 HCC patients. Determination of this pathway as <italic>most activated</italic> using genetic and genomic data is described in &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Patients and methods</xref>&#x0201d; while other top ranked pathways are presented in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S6. Each of the 4 patients&#x02019; primary or recurrent tumors are represented as a quadrant on each pathway node</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2015_743_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p>Specifically, deleterious somatic genetic or genomic alterations shared between P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s included: HCC1: nonsilent mutations in <italic>TP53</italic> and <italic>AKT2,</italic> with activation of upstream gene signatures in <italic>CTNB1, E2F1</italic>and <italic>TCF4</italic> and suppression of <italic>CDKN2A</italic> upstream gene signature; HCC4: <italic>CDH11</italic> and <italic>TGFBR3</italic> stop codon mutations, DNA amplification in <italic>POU5F1</italic> and <italic>UBD</italic>, and DNA deletion in <italic>GNAO1</italic>with activation of <italic>E2F1</italic> and <italic>TXB2</italic> upstream gene signatures and suppression of upstream gene signatures <italic>CDKN2A</italic> and <italic>RB1</italic>; HCC5: DNA deletion in <italic>CDH1</italic> and a nonsilent mutation in <italic>TP53</italic> with activation of <italic>E2F1</italic> and <italic>MYC</italic> upstream gene signatures and suppression of upstream gene signatures <italic>CDKN2A</italic> and <italic>TP53</italic>; HCC11: activating mutation S45Y in <italic>CTNNB1</italic>, a stop codon mutation in <italic>LRP1</italic>, and a nonsilent mutation in the ANK2 domain of <italic>CDKN2A</italic>, with DNA amplification in <italic>SOX9</italic>. All four patients converge on shared inactivation of a key cell-cycle control tumor suppressor gene <italic>CDKN2A</italic> in P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s Using the same strategy to identify the most enriched pathways unique to R<sub>T</sub>s in all patients, cell cycle signaling was identified (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S7).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>HERC5 within chromosome 4q somatic CN deletion shows mRNA under-expression and predicts risk of survival and tumor recurrence in the primary tumors of HCC patients</title><p>Next we focused on the largest region of somatic CN deletion shared in both the P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s on chromosome 4q (~107 Mbp). Genes were evaluated within this region to identify a single molecular biomarker to predict HCC tumor recurrence and survival. WES and RNASeq from the four patients as well as RNASeq from P<sub>T</sub>s and P<sub>NAT</sub>s from a larger population of HCC Chinese patients who experienced tumor recurrence (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9 including the 4 described above) or did not (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12) were used to identified a predictor of tumor recurrence and survival. Using RNASeq data from the 21 P<sub>T</sub>s and P<sub>NAT</sub>s, DESeq-normalized log<sub>2</sub> gene counts in the P<sub>T</sub>s were scaled by the matched P<sub>NAT</sub>s within each patient. Then these fold changes for each patient were used in a contrast between patients that experienced tumor recurrence (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9) and patients who did not (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12). A total of 273 genes were identified with |fold|&#x000a0;&#x0003e;2 and p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S9). To provide a large enough set of genes trending with under-expression in the recurrent patients, no multiple testing was implemented on these raw p-values. Further, the small sample sizes did not allow multiple testing corrections. Then genes within regions of DNA deletions in matched P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s in chromosome 4q (542 genes) and the 110 genes under-expressed (of the 273 genes both under- and over-expressed) in the P<sub>T</sub>s of HCC patients who experienced tumor recurrence (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9), relative to those who did not (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S9) were intersected. From this analysis, the following genes were identified: <italic>NAA11</italic>, <italic>HERC5</italic>, <italic>DDX60</italic>, and <italic>HERC6</italic> which were evaluated individually for association with tumor recurrence using the 21 Chinese patient primary tumors.</p><p>For each of the four genes, the 21 Chinese patients were categorized into high/low gene groups using the median fold change expression (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). Kaplan&#x02013;Meier log-rank tests indicated a significantly shorter time to recurrence in the gene <italic>HERC5</italic> low group (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.007), while the other three genes did not significantly correlate with time to recurrence (p&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;0.05), and after adjustment for HBV status pre-OLT, tumor grade, age, and gender, the trend remained for <italic>HERC5</italic> (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.07; HR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7.29 CI<sub>95</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;[0.85, 62.62]; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a; &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Patients and methods</xref>&#x0201d;).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>
<bold>a</bold>
<italic>left HERC5</italic> distribution of fold change values (log<sub>2</sub> scale) for 21 Chinese patient primary tumors, <italic>blue line</italic> median of patients; <italic>right</italic> Kaplan&#x02013;Meier (KM) curves comparing <italic>HERC5</italic> low (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11) to high expression (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;10) predicting recurrence; <bold>b</bold>
<italic>left HERC5</italic> distribution between normal liver (<italic>red</italic>; n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;239) and HCC tumors (<italic>green</italic>; n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;247; <italic>19</italic>), <italic>blue line</italic> mean(normals)-2SD; <italic>middle</italic> Kaplan&#x02013;Meier (KM) curves comparing <italic>HERC5</italic> low (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;62) to high expression (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;180) predicting recurrence; <italic>right</italic> Same as <italic>middle</italic> predicting overall survival; <bold>c</bold>
<italic>left HERC5</italic> distribution for HCC tumors, <italic>blue line</italic> median of 65 patients (<italic>20</italic>); <italic>middle</italic> KM curves comparing <italic>HERC5</italic> low (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20) to high expression (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;24) predicting PFS; <italic>right</italic> Same as <italic>middle</italic> predicting overall survival. <italic>p</italic> log-rank test, <italic>p*</italic> Cox PH regression model, <italic>HR</italic> hazard ratio</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2015_743_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p>Two additional independent HCC datasets including primary tumors from patients who underwent resection were then evaluated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] where <italic>HERC5</italic> expression was categorized into high/low patient groups using healthy control liver tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] or the median of the HCC patient distribution (no normal liver tissue was available in this study) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. After adjustment for cirrhosis status, gender, HBV/HCV status and TNM staging, <italic>HERC5</italic> was a significant predictor of overall survival (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.004; HR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.02 CI<sub>95</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;[1.26, 3.25]) and HCC recurrence (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.004; HR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.80 CI<sub>95</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;[1.20, 2.69]) in one dataset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] with median time to recurrence in the <italic>HERC5</italic> low group&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;23&#x000a0;months versus <italic>HERC5</italic> high group&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;49&#x000a0;months (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Then in another independent HCC patient cohort [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], after adjustment for age, gender, and HBV status, <italic>HERC5</italic> under-expression was associated with shorter overall survival (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.02; HR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.31 CI<sub>95</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;[1.22, 8.96]) and PFS (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.01; HR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.80 CI<sub>95</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;[1.38, 10.43]) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). To verify that the lack of correlation between the other three candidate genes alternative to <italic>HERC5</italic> (i.e. <italic>NAA11</italic>, <italic>DDX60</italic>, and <italic>HERC6</italic>) and outcomes was not due to the small sample size used in the first patient dataset (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;21), similar analyses were conducted on each gene independently using both larger HCC patient cohorts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] and no significant associations were observed for any of these three genes with any of the outcomes. An additional evaluation of specificity of the <italic>HERC5</italic> correlation with prognosis was conducted among all genes that were located within the deleted region of chromosome 4q using study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). A total of 262 genes were both within the chromosome 4q region and present on the microarray from this study, of which 118 were under-expressed in the HCC tumor biopsies compared to tissue from the normal controls. A multivariate Cox PH model was calculated independently on each of the 118 genes, where each gene was cut into high or low groups based on the same criteria that was described previously (mean-2 SD of the normal liver distribution). <italic>HAND2</italic> had the most significant association with HCC recurrence, although it had a highly unbalanced distribution of high/low patients (3.6&#x000a0;% of patients in the low group). <italic>HERC5</italic> was the second most significant correlate with HCC recurrence (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure&#x000a0;S8), demonstrating biological specificity of this gene independent of other genes with CN deletions in chromosome 4q.</p><p>In a separate study of HCV-positive cirrhosis patients, molecular subgroupings of patients were identified and shown to correlate with good versus poor prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. <italic>HERC5</italic> was significantly over-expressed (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001) in the good prognosis (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;109) compared to poor prognosis group (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;107) (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure&#x000a0;S9).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>HERC5 loss induces CCL20 mRNA and protein and associates with FOXP3 positive Treg infiltration in HCC</title><p><italic>HERC5</italic> loss was next evaluated for biological significance in HCC. By studying the whole transcriptome expression profile of the HCC cell line PLCPRF5 with <italic>HERC5</italic> siRNA knockdown, <italic>CCL20</italic> was the most over-expressed transcript (fold&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.8), and genes coding classic regulators of <italic>CCL20</italic> such as <italic>TNF, NFKB1,</italic> or <italic>TRIM32</italic> showed no change (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S10, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). TaqMan qRT-PCR and ELISA assays confirmed the overexpression of CCL20 at the transcript and protein level with two additional HCC cell lines (SNU449 and HEPG2; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The difference of under-expression in <italic>HERC5</italic> in the recurrent patient P<sub>T</sub>s (mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.3 fold) was significantly lower than that of P<sub>T</sub>s from patients who did not recur (mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.1 fold; p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.001), confirming the results from the previous two array studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] in this modest-sized study of Chinese patients. In addition, <italic>HERC5</italic> and <italic>CCL20</italic> mRNAs were significantly negatively correlated (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0003) in the P<sub>T</sub>s of HCC patients who experienced tumor recurrence and not in the P<sub>T</sub>s of HCC patients who did not experience tumor recurrence (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.49; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). Immunostaining of FOXP3 in the primary tumors of the 21 HCC patients indicated significantly higher expression in the patients who experienced recurrence as compared to those who did not (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c; p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.05).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Up-regulated CCL20 expression after <italic>HERC5</italic> siRNA knockdown in HCC cell lines. <bold>a</bold> qRT-PCR analysis of <italic>HERC5</italic> mRNA expression in three HCC cell lines 96&#x000a0;h after transfection of negative control siRNA and <italic>HERC5</italic> siRNA. Shown is relative expression as copy numbers per 10<sup>6</sup> endogenous control genes (average of expression levels of ACTB, GAPDH, and UBC); <bold>b</bold> qRT-PCR analysis of <italic>CCL20</italic> mRNA expression in three HCC cell lines 96&#x000a0;h after transfection of negative control siRNA and <italic>HERC5</italic> siRNA; <bold>c</bold> Secreted CCL20 in HCC cell culture medium was measured by ELISA 96&#x000a0;h after siRNA transfection. Standard deviations are represented for each <italic>bar</italic>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2015_743_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Negative correlation between <italic>HERC5</italic> and <italic>CCL20</italic> mRNA and the association of Tregs infiltration in P<sub>T</sub>s of recurrent patients. <bold>a</bold> Log<sub>2</sub> fold changes <italic>HERC5</italic> and <italic>CCL20</italic> mRNA between and P<sub>NAT</sub>s in the patients who experienced tumor recurrence (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9) or the patients who did not (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12). A Student&#x02019;s paired t-test between <italic>HERC5</italic> and <italic>CCL20</italic> log<sub>2</sub> fold change values for the recurrent patients have p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0003 and p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.49 for the non-recurrent patients. Negative correlation between <italic>HERC5</italic> and <italic>CCL20</italic> mRNA is present in the recurrent patients and not observed in the patients who did not recurrent. <bold>b</bold> Examples of FOXP3 IHC in P<sub>T</sub>s and P<sub>NAT</sub>s of a recurrent patient and a non-recurrent patient at &#x000d7;20 magnification (530&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;460&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m in size per field). <bold>c</bold> FOXP3 IHC scores were calculated using the average numbers of FOXP3 positive stained lymphocytes in10 randomly selected fields at &#x000d7;20 magnification (530&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;460&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m in size per field) in hepatocellular carcinoma for each sample. FOXP3 IHC score in P<sub>T</sub>s of recurrent patients (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9) were significantly higher than that in non-recurrent patients (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9) by Welch&#x02019;s modified t-test (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.05)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2015_743_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our results describe the genetic and genomic heterogeneity between patients with HCC and demonstrate clonal persistence in tumor recurrence post-OLT. A unique study design inclusive of P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s (plus normal adjacent tissue and recipient blood), with an integration of somatic SNVs, CNVs, and transcript profiling and well-defined phenotypic spectrum allowed us to elucidate key cancer driver genes and delineate those critical gatekeepers of cancer initiation and progression. This study is the first to show a clonal advantage in R<sub>T</sub>s post-OLT compared to P<sub>T</sub>s in HCC, where Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling activation and tumor suppressor gene <italic>CDKN2A</italic> inactivation occurs in both tumors.</p><p>DNA CN loss at chromosome 4q was identified as one of the only two hemizygous deleted regions shared between the primary and recurrent tumors in 3 of 4 Chinese HCC patients. This region accounts for ~107 Mbp in length and similar deletions have been associated with either poor prognosis or advanced disease stages in pancreatic, colorectal, non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC), and HCC tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Within NSCLC specifically, FISH assays identified the primary region of 4q21.2-22.1 to be associated with poor prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], and a recent study from this same group showed that hypermethylation of <italic>HERC5</italic> promoter (located at 4q22.1), and thus under-expression of the gene correlated with: positive disseminated tumor cells in the bone marrow, brain metastasis, and poor survival in both stage I adenocarcinoma and metastatic lung cancer patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Our results presented here in primary tumors of HCC patients are in agreement with these reports, underscoring the prognostic significance of <italic>HERC5</italic> under-expression, as we have demonstrated with microarray or RNASeq technologies in primary tumors of three independent cohorts of HCC patients.</p><p>Cancer cells can avoid an immune response by disabling components of the immune system&#x02014;a process well known as immune evasion. These cells can paralyze activated immune effector cells such as infiltrating cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs) and natural killer (NK) cells by secreting TGF-&#x003b2; or other immunosuppressive factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] such as the cell-cycle control tumor suppressor gene <italic>CDKN2A</italic>. However, the genetic basis behind recruitment of inflammatory cells that are actively immunosuppressive, such as regulatory T cells (Tregs) and myeloid-derived suppressor cells (MDSCs) is largely unknown. CCL20 has been shown to be the only chemokine significantly up-regulated in HCC tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], where it can selectively recruit Tregs to the tumor, contributing to an immunosuppressive tumor microenvironment and leading to poor prognosis in HCC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], Both the genetic basis and mechanism for the source of highly secreted CCL20 in HCC still remains to be elucidated. Our results suggest that loss of HERC5 is the genetic precursor for CCL20 over-expression and associates with increased Treg infiltration in HCC, one of the underlying mechanisms of immune evasion in HCC. Further, pathway analysis of the top induced genes (|fold|&#x000a0;&#x0003e;2, 129 up-regulated/78 down-regulated) following knockdown of <italic>HERC5</italic> indicated activation of the IL17A pathway, as driven by over-expression of chemokine genes <italic>CXCL13</italic>, <italic>CXCL15</italic>, and <italic>CXCL16</italic>, with suppression of the Th2 cytokine IL-5, supported by the down-regulation of genes <italic>TMF1</italic>, <italic>PDIA6</italic>, <italic>ELL2</italic> and <italic>APT1B1</italic>. Elevated serum IL17 levels in primary HCC patients have been shown to correlate with risk of tumor recurrence following curative hepatectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], while suppressed IL5 mRNA expression was correlated with poor survival in cervical cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. The modulation of such pathways when <italic>HERC5</italic> is silenced support an immunosuppressed environment for patients, thus influencing poor prognosis. HERC5 is an interferon-induced HECT-type E3 protein ligase that mediates type I interferon-induced ISGylation of protein targets; reduction in endogenous HERC5 blocks the IFN-induced ISG15 conjugation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Thus host anti-viral responses are activated by the presence of HERC5 and reduced by its absence, suggesting an association with regulation of innate immune responses, a potential critical function leading to tumor recurrence in HCC. This hypothesis requires rigorous evaluation in future studies.</p><p>Unlike multiple transcriptomic studies that have developed gene signatures to predict tumor recurrence or survival in HCC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], <italic>HERC5</italic> was not solely identified as a statistical correlate with outcome, rather, this gene is located within a large somatic copy number deletion on chromosome 4q in both P<sub>T</sub>s and R<sub>T</sub>s and was suppressed in HCC patients who experienced tumor recurrence, compared to those who did not. Unfortunately in this study, <italic>HERC5</italic> DNA loss was only evaluated in the 4 HCC patients with matched primary and recurrent tumor specimens, since DNA sequencing was not conducted on the remaining 17 HCC patients. Although, a recent study of 185 HCC patients showed that 28&#x000a0;% of patients&#x02019; primary tumors had a DNA deletion in <italic>HERC5</italic>, confirming a similar prevalence to patients with mRNA under-expression in this study (26&#x000a0;%; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure&#x000a0;S9). Three independent studies with available comprehensive clinical and either RNASeq or microarray data were used to validate this clinical association totally 307 HCC patients. Taken together, these data confirm the robustness of our findings. <italic>HERC5</italic> is also not present in any gene signature among the 14 catalogued in the Liverome database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p><p>Studies have shown varied levels of consistency for classifying patients with high risk for HCC recurrence using clinicopathologic variables such as tumor size, vascular invasion, tumor state, tumor grade, and alpha-fetoprotein levels and data presented here suggest a single transcript as an important variable to couple to these relevant clinical factors for identifying HCC candidates for OLT. A single transcript also provides a pragmatic diagnostic assay for clinical use.</p><p>In a disease with no established adjuvant treatments, substantial shortage of donor organs, and high financial burden, identifying eligible patients for OLT with low recurrence risk at the molecular level accompanied by current clinical criteria, has potential to significantly improve patient clinical outcomes. This study is a first in HCC using comprehensive genetics and genomics patient profiling supported by large independent patient cohorts to provide evidence for such a biomarker and characterize the shared genetic drivers between primary and recurrent HCC. We believe that the translational study design and analytical strategy presented in this work will inspire other genetics studies beyond HCC recurrence and into other primary malignancies where metastases to other organs systems are observed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study provides evidence for a clonal selection advantage in the recurrent tumor, as compared to primary tumor in HCC patients and Wnt/&#x003b2;-catenin signaling was identified as the most regulated oncodriver pathway in matched primary and recurrent tumors. <italic>HERC5</italic> was also identified as a prognostic biomarker for both survival and tumor recurrence in HCC patients in three independent HCC patient cohorts. Genetic- and genomic-driven under-expression of this gene is associated with <italic>CCL20</italic> induction, suggested to increase Treg infiltration and ultimately poor prognosis in HCC patient post-OLT.</p></sec></body><back><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec17"><title>Additional files</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12967_2015_743_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM1"><caption><p>
10.1186/s12967-015-0743-2 Supplementary Methods.</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12967_2015_743_MOESM2_ESM.docx" id="MOESM2"><caption><p>
10.1186/s12967-015-0743-2 Supplementary Figures.</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12967_2015_743_MOESM3_ESM.docx" id="MOESM3"><caption><p>
10.1186/s12967-015-0743-2 Supplementary Tables.</p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>HCC</term><def><p>hepatocellular carcinoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>P<sub>T</sub></term><def><p>primary tumor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>P<sub>NAT</sub></term><def><p>primary normal adjacent tissue</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>P<sub>B</sub></term><def><p>recipient blood</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>R<sub>T</sub></term><def><p>recurrent tumor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>R<sub>NAT</sub></term><def><p>recurrent normal adjacent tissue</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HBV</term><def><p>hepatitis B virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCV</term><def><p>hepatitis C virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OLT</term><def><p>orthotopic liver transplantation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WES</term><def><p>whole exome sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNASeq</term><def><p>RNA sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Vf</term><def><p>variant frequency</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNV</term><def><p>single nucleotide variant</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>indel</term><def><p>insertion or deletion</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CNV</term><def><p>copy number variation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HR</term><def><p>hazard ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p>confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UCSF</term><def><p>University of California San Francisco</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CR</term><def><p>clonal relationship value</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WGS</term><def><p>whole genome sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Qphred</term><def><p>Phred sequence value score</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VCF</term><def><p>variant call format</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LRR</term><def><p>Log<sub>2</sub> R ratios</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BAF</term><def><p>B-allele frequency</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CTLs</term><def><p>cytotoxic T lymphocytes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NK</term><def><p>natural killer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Tregs</term><def><p>regulatory T cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDSCs</term><def><p>myeloid-derived suppressor cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HERC5</term><def><p>HECT And RLD Domain Containing E3 Ubiquitin Protein Ligase 5</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CCL20</term><def><p>chemokine ligand 20</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p>Feng Xue, Brandon W. Higgs and Jiaqi Huang contributed equally to this work</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>YY, FX, QX, JG, ZD, YG: study concept and design, acquisition of data, study supervision; BWH, JH, CM, WZ, XY, PB, YS, DS, MK: analysis and interpretation of data, statistical analysis; BWH, JH: drafting manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing interests</title><p>BWH, JH, CM, WZ, XY, PB, ZX, YS, ZL, DS, MK, ZD, HH, YG, YY: full time employees of MedImmune/Astra Zeneca and own stock in Astra Zeneca. FX, YX, JG, QX: no conflicts to declare.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Serag</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatocellular carcinoma: epidemiology and molecular carcinogenesis</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2007</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>2557</fpage><lpage>2576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2007.04.061</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17570226?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17570226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The global health burden of infection-associated cancers in the year 2002</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>3030</fpage><lpage>3044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.21731</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16404738?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16404738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Decreased incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma in hepatitis B vaccines: a 20-year follow-up study</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2009</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>1348</fpage><lpage>1355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djp288</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19759364?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19759364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Liver transplantation for hepatocellular carcinoma: Hangzhou experiences</article-title><source>Transplantation</source><year>2008</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>1726</fpage><lpage>1732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/TP.0b013e31816b67e4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18580463?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18580463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welker</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bechstein</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeuzem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrent hepatocellular carcinoma after liver transplantation&#x02014;an emerging clinical challenge</article-title><source>Transpl Int</source><year>2013</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1432-2277.2012.01562.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22994652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22994652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghobrial</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiatt</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Busuttil</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma following liver transplantation: a review of preoperative and postoperative prognostic indicators</article-title><source>Arch Surg.</source><year>2008</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archsurg.2007.39</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18283144?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18283144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoshida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Villanueva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peix</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression in fixed tissues and outcome in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>359</volume><fpage>1995</fpage><lpage>2004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa0804525</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18923165?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18923165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iizuka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada-Okabe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oligonucleotide microarray for prediction of early intrahepatic recurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma after curative resection</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2003</year><volume>361</volume><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(03)12775-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12648972?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12648972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iizuka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamesa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different molecular pathways determining extrahepatic and intrahepatic recurrences of hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1137</fpage><lpage>1142</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17016605?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17016605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurokawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Matoba</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Takemasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular-based prediction of early recurrence in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2004</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2004.04.031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15288478?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15288478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvisi</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Roskams</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Durnez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Classification and prediction of survival in hepatocellular carcinoma by gene expression profiling</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2004</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.20375</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15349906?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15349906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikaelyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvisi</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Application of comparative functional genomics to identify best-fit mouse models to study human cancer</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1306</fpage><lpage>1311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1481</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15565109?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15565109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matoba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Iizuka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gondo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada-Okabe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamesa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tumor HLA-DR expression linked to early intrahepatic recurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2005</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.20860</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15688398?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15688398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Utsunomiya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakiyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuzawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Specific gene-expression profiles of noncancerous liver tissue predict the risk for multicentric occurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma in hepatitis C virus-positive patients</article-title><source>Ann Surg Oncol</source><year>2006</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>947</fpage><lpage>954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/ASO.2006.07.018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16788756?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16788756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogushi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aurora kinase B is a predictive factor for the aggressive recurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma after curative hepatectomy</article-title><source>Br J Surg</source><year>2008</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>619</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bjs.6011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18311747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18311747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kono</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusyn</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene expression in nontumoral liver tissue and recurrence-free survival in hepatitis C virus-positive hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Mol Cancer</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>74</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-4598-9-74</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20380719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20380719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and validation of a novel gene signature associated with the recurrence of human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>6275</fpage><lpage>6283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-06-2236</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17975138?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17975138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheon</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression-based recurrence prediction of hepatitis B virus-related human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2056</fpage><lpage>2064</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-07-1473</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18381945?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18381945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yokoo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Okano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosuge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protein expression associated with early intrahepatic recurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma after curative surgery</article-title><source>Cancer Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1349-7006.2007.00441.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17391314?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17391314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takemasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kittaka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular prediction of early recurrence after resection of hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>2009</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>881</fpage><lpage>889</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejca.2008.12.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19167881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19167881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lee L, Wang K, Li G, Xie Z, Wang Y, Xu J, et al. Liverome: a curated database of liver cancer-related gene signatures with self-contained context information. BMC Genomics 2011;12 Suppl 3:S3-2164-12-S3-S3.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S-B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y-Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic Predictors for recurrence patterns of Hepatocellular Carcinoma: model derivation and validation</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e1001770</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001770</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25536056?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25536056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Goossens</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name><surname>Altunkaynak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A hepatic stellate cell gene expression signature associated with outcomes in hepatitis C cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma after curative resection</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piras-Straub</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Khairzada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Trippler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TRAIL expression levels in human hepatocellular carcinoma have implications for tumor growth, recurrence and survival</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2015</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>E154</fpage><lpage>E160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.29139</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25123818?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25123818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Oya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aberrant expression of melanoma-associated antigen-D2 serves as a prognostic indicator of hepatocellular carcinoma outcome following curative hepatectomy</article-title><source>Oncol Lett</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>1206</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25663882?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25663882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Totoki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Boroevich</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosoda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole-genome sequencing of liver cancers identifies etiological influences on mutation patterns and recurrent mutations in chromatin regulators</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>760</fpage><lpage>764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2291</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22634756?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22634756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Totoki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosoda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-resolution characterization of a hepatocellular carcinoma genome</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.804</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21499249?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21499249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole-genome sequencing identifies recurrent mutations in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1422</fpage><lpage>1433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.154492.113</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23788652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23788652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Choti</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inactivating mutations of the chromatin remodeling gene ARID2 in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>828</fpage><lpage>829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.903</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21822264?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21822264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole-genome and whole-exome sequencing of bladder cancer identifies frequent alterations in genes involved in sister chromatid cohesion and segregation</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1459</fpage><lpage>1463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2798</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24121792?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24121792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jhunjhunwala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haverty</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennemer</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effects of hepatitis B virus integration into the genomes of hepatocellular carcinoma patients</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.133926.111</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22267523?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22267523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TopHat2: accurate alignment of transcriptomes in the presence of insertions, deletions and gene fusions</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>R36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23618408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23618408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>R106</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20979621?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cibulskis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Helman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zack</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Absolute quantification of somatic DNA alterations in human cancer</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2012</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2203</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22544022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22544022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyault</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rickman</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>de Reynies</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Balabaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebouissou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeannot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome classification of HCC is related to gene alterations and to new therapeutic targets</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.21467</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17187432?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17187432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roessler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Budhu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Forgues</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A unique metastasis gene signature enables prediction of tumor relapse in early-stage hepatocellular carcinoma patients</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>10202</fpage><lpage>10212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-10-2607</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21159642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21159642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Woreta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Limketkai</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagher</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Donor-transmitted malignancy in a liver transplant recipient: a case report and review of literature</article-title><source>Dig Dis Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1185</fpage><lpage>1190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10620-012-2501-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23242807?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23242807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cankovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarbo</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of microsatellite analysis in detection of tumor lineage as a cause of death in a liver transplant patient</article-title><source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16594745?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16594745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromosomal changes and clonality relationship between primary and recurrent hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2000</year><volume>119</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/gast.2000.9373</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10930378?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10930378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Myron</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherikh</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Spain</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Roza</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transplant tumor registry: donor related malignancies</article-title><source>Transplantation</source><year>2002</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007890-200208150-00011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12177614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoshida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Villanueva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangiovanni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sole</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic gene expression signature for patients with hepatitis C-related early-stage cirrhosis</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2013</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>1024</fpage><lpage>1030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2013.01.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23333348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23333348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of loss of heterozygosity on chromosome 4q in hepatocellular carcinoma using high-throughput SNP array</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2010</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/or_00000802</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20043106?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20043106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danner</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Enders</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liersch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of chromosomal aberrations in primary colorectal carcinomas to their pulmonary metastases</article-title><source>Cancer Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cancergen.2010.12.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21504711?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21504711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wrage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruosaari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eijk</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaifi</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollm&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yekebas</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic profiles associated with early micrometastasis in lung cancer: relevance of 4q deletion</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1566</fpage><lpage>1574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-08-2188</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19208797?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19208797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luebke</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baudis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthaei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vashist</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name><surname>Verde</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosch</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Losses at chromosome 4q are associated with poor survival in operable ductal pancreatic adenocarcinoma</article-title><source>Pancreatology</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pan.2011.11.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22487468?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22487468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wrage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemming</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzunoglu</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Riethdorf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Effenberger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of HERC5 and its potential role in NSCLC progression</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2015</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>2264</fpage><lpage>2272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.29298</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25353388?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25353388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uzunoglu</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dethlefsen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanssen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wrage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Deutsch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Harms-Effenberger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss of 4q21.23-22.1 is a prognostic marker for disease free and overall survival in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e113315</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0113315</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25501003?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25501003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGF-beta and immune cells: an important regulatory axis in the tumor microenvironment and progression</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.it.2010.04.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20538542?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20538542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kourtis</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomei</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of lymphoidlike stroma and immune escape by tumors that express the chemokine CCL21</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1185837</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20339029?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20339029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Frick</surname><given-names>VO</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced expression and clinical significance of CC-chemokine MIP-3 alpha in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Scand J Immunol</source><year>2006</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3083.2006.001766.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16764701?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16764701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemokines and hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>World J Gastroenterol</source><year>2010</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1832</fpage><lpage>1836</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v16.i15.1832</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20397259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20397259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High expression of CCL20 is associated with poor prognosis in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma after curative resection</article-title><source>J Gastrointest Surg</source><year>2012</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>828</fpage><lpage>836</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11605-011-1775-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22072303?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22072303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Elevated pretherapy serum IL17 in primary hepatocellular carcinoma patients correlate to increased risk of early recurrence after curative hepatectomy</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e50035</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23227158?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23227158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Punt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Houwing</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulkens</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thijssen</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Osse</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>de Kroon</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A high IL6/IL17 ratio combined with low IL5 expression is correlated with poor survival in squamous cervical cancer</article-title><source>J Immunotherap Cancer</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>P232</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2051-1426-2-S3-P232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pung</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sze</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HERC5 is an IFN-induced HECT-type E3 protein ligase that mediates type I IFN-induced ISGylation of protein targets</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>10735</fpage><lpage>10740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0600397103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16815975?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16815975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guichard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaddeo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Imbeaud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ladeiro</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Maad</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated analysis of somatic mutations and focal copy-number changes identifies key genes and pathways in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2256</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22561517?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22561517</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>