<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4033193</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2014.00210</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research Article</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The effect of NGATHA altered activity on auxin signaling pathways within the Arabidopsis gynoecium</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>Irene</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sanch&#x000ed;s</surname><given-names>Sof&#x000ed;a</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://community.frontiersin.org/people/u/158506"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marini</surname><given-names>Naciele</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://community.frontiersin.org/people/u/142685"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balanz&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Vicente</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://community.frontiersin.org/people/u/156808"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ballester</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Navarrete-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>Marisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>Antonio C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://community.frontiersin.org/people/u/128514"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>Lucia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://community.frontiersin.org/people/u/110200"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ferr&#x000e1;ndiz</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://community.frontiersin.org/people/u/27457"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas - Instituto de Biolog&#x000ed;a Molecular y Celular de Plantas (CSIC-UPV)</institution><country>Valencia, Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Plant Sciences, Faculdade de Agronomia Eliseu Maciel, Plant Genomics and Breeding Center, Universidade Federal de Pelotas</institution><country>Pelotas, Brasil</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Dipartimento di Biologia, Universita degli Studi di Milano</institution><country>Milano, Italia</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Robert G. Franks, North Carolina State University, USA</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Pablo Daniel Jenik, Franklin &#x00026; Marshall College, USA; Anna N. Stepanova, North Carolina State University, USA</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Cristina Ferr&#x000e1;ndiz, Instituto de Biolog&#x000ed;a Molecular y Celular de Plantas (CSIC-UPV), Campus de la UPV- Ciudad Polit&#x000e9;cnica de la Innovaci&#x000f3;n edif 8E, Av. de los Naranjos s/n, 46022 Valencia, Spain e-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">cferrandiz@ibmcp.upv.es</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Evolution and Development, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>210</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Mart&#x000ed;nez-Fern&#x000e1;ndez, Sanch&#x000ed;s, Marini, Balanz&#x000e1;, Ballester, Navarrete-G&#x000f3;mez, Oliveira, Colombo and Ferr&#x000e1;ndiz.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The four <italic>NGATHA</italic> genes (<italic>NGA)</italic> form a small subfamily within the large family of B3-domain transcription factors of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. <italic>NGA</italic> genes act redundantly to direct the development of the apical tissues of the gynoecium, the style, and the stigma. Previous studies indicate that <italic>NGA</italic> genes could exert this function at least partially by directing the synthesis of auxin at the distal end of the developing gynoecium through the upregulation of two different <italic>YUCCA</italic> genes, which encode flavin monooxygenases involved in auxin biosynthesis. We have compared three developing pistil transcriptome data sets from wildtype, <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants, and a <italic>35S::NGA3 line</italic>. The differentially expressed genes showed a significant enrichment for auxin-related genes, supporting the idea of <italic>NGA</italic> genes as major regulators of auxin accumulation and distribution within the developing gynoecium. We have introduced reporter lines for several of these differentially expressed genes involved in synthesis, transport and response to auxin in <italic>NGA</italic> gain- and loss-of-function backgrounds. We present here a detailed map of the response of these reporters to <italic>NGA</italic> misregulation that could help to clarify the role of <italic>NGA</italic> in auxin-mediated gynoecium morphogenesis. Our data point to a very reduced auxin synthesis in the developing apical gynoecium of <italic>nga</italic> mutants, likely responsible for the lack of <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> reporter activity observed in these mutants. In addition, NGA altered activity affects the expression of protein kinases that regulate the cellular localization of auxin efflux regulators, and thus likely impact auxin transport. Finally, protein accumulation in pistils of several ARFs was differentially affected by <italic>nga</italic> mutations or <italic>NGA</italic> overexpression, suggesting that these accumulation patterns depend not only on auxin distribution but could be also regulated by transcriptional networks involving NGA factors.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>gynoecium development</kwd><kwd>NGATHA</kwd><kwd>auxin synthesis</kwd><kwd>auxin transport</kwd><kwd>AUXIN RESPONSE FACTORS</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="43"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="8619"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The carpel is the female reproductive organ of the angiosperm flower and its most distinctive feature. Carpels typically occur at the center of the flower forming the gynoecium, most commonly fused into a single pistil (a syncarpic gynoecium) or less frequently as individual organs that collectively form an apocarpic gynoecium composed of several pistils. The gynoecium confers major advantages to flowering plants: provides protection for the ovules; enables pollen capture and pollen tube guidance and supports self- and inter-specific incompatibility; finally, after fertilization of the ovules, the gynoecium develops into a fruit, which protects the developing seeds and facilitates seed dispersal (Ferrandiz et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). To accomplish these roles, gynoecium development involves the differentiation of specialized functional modules: stigma forms at the apex of pistils to capture and germinate pollen grains; immediately below, the style is rich in transmitting tissues that conduct pollen tubes to the ovary, which is a basal structure that contains the ovules. In addition to these specialized tissues, other structures also develop in some pistils, such as those that will form the dehiscence zones in shattering fruits, or the septa that divide the ovary in locules (Sundberg and Ferr&#x000e1;ndiz, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Ferrandiz et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>To achieve differentiation and coordinated growth of the functional modules found in pistils, a suite of regulatory networks has to be in place. Most of our current knowledge on the major players in these networks comes from work carried out in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. A number of transcription factors have been identified with a role in the differentiation of the specialized tissues found in gynoecia or in the specification of polarity axes, and, while the picture is far from complete, we are now beginning to understand how their regulatory hierarchies and functional interactions work (reviewed in Balanz&#x000e1; et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Ferrandiz et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). In addition to transcriptional regulation, the phytohormone auxin has been regarded as one of the major morphogens instructing gynoecium patterning and post-fertilization developmental events (Alabadi et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Larsson et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Local auxin maxima and minima have been shown to be instrumental for valve margin development and dehiscence (Sorefan et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Most importantly, it is also known that auxin controls polarity in the apical-basal axis of the developing gynoecium. More than one decade ago, (Nemhauser et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>) proposed a model for auxin-dependent distribution of tissues based on the phenotypes of <italic>ettin (ett)</italic> mutants, affected in the <italic>AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR 3</italic> gene; the phenotypes of mutants defective in auxin transport such as <italic>pinoid (pid)</italic> or <italic>pin-formed1 (pin1)</italic>; and on the effects of inhibiting polar auxin transport (PAT) in gynoecium morphology. According to this model, auxin would be produced in the apical end of the pistil and transported basipetally, creating a gradient along the apical-basal axis that would be translated into the differentiation of the different functional modules: high apical auxin levels would direct the differentiation of style and stigma, intermediate levels would specify the ovary, and low basal levels, the gynophore. The Nemhauser model has been very useful to frame the role of different players in Arabidopsis carpel development, but conclusive proof of the proposed auxin gradient has never been obtained. Actually, detailed descriptions of auxin accumulation throughout gynoecium development using a <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> reporter have shown that auxin maxima are formed in the apical domain, first as isolated foci and later as a continuous apical ring, while the proposed gradient cannot be observed (Girin et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Marsch-Martinez et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>; Larsson et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In addition, several recent studies indicate that the dynamics of auxin accumulation, homeostasis and response within the developing gynoecium are highly complex and we are still far from fully comprehending how positional information is translated into developmental outputs in gynoecium differentiation (Sohlberg et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; St&#x000e5;ldal et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; St&#x000e5;ldal and Sundberg, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Marsch-Martinez et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2012b</xref>). In any case, although detailed understanding of these mechanisms is still lacking, the pivotal role of auxin in apical-basal gynoecium patterning is widely acknowledged.</p><p>Among the transcriptional regulators directing carpel patterning, two small families of unrelated factors have been shown to be essential for apical tissue differentiation. The four <italic>NGATHA</italic> genes belong to the RAV clade of the large B3-domain transcription factor family and are redundantly required for the specification of style and stigma. <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants form apparently undisturbed ovaries but completely lack style and stigma, and the gynoecium ends apically as an open structure with several protrusions of valve-like tissue (Alvarez et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Almost identical phenotypes are found in multiple mutants of the SHI/STY family of RING finger-like zinc finger motif transcription factors (Kuusk et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). <italic>NGA</italic> and <italic>SHI/STY</italic> genes also share similar expression patterns, which include the apical domain of developing gynoecia from stage 6 to stage 11&#x02013;12, when style and stigma specification and differentiation take place (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C&#x02013;F</xref>) (Kuusk et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Alvarez et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Interestingly, both NGA and SHI/STY factors have important connections to auxin. STY1 has been shown to directly regulate <italic>YUCCA4 (YUC4)</italic>, a gene encoding a flavin monooxygenase-like enzyme involved in auxin synthesis (Eklund et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Likewise, <italic>YUC4</italic> and <italic>YUC2</italic> are not expressed in the gynoecium apex of lines where <italic>NGA</italic> genes were downregulated, a regulatory interaction that appears to be conserved also in other dicot species (Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Fourquin and Ferrandiz, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Moreover, <italic>NGA3</italic> overexpression carpel phenotypes resemble the effects of PAT inhibition and of weak <italic>ett</italic> mutant alleles, and also affect other auxin-related processes in the plant, such as apical dominance, leaf morphology, or secondary root development, suggesting that <italic>NGA</italic> genes may interact with auxin signaling at multiple levels (Alvarez et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). In this study, we aim to characterize in detail the response of several components of the auxin signaling network to altered levels of NGA activity in the gynoecium, hoping to clarify the mechanisms of NGA action in auxin-mediated carpel morphogenesis.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Gynoecium development in Arabidopsis and NGA-related mutants. (A)</bold> Scanning electron micrographs of wildtype gynoecia at different stages of development. <bold>(B)</bold> Phenotypes at anthesis of <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> (left) and <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutant pistils (right). <bold>(C&#x02013;F)</bold> Expression of <italic>NGA3</italic> in gynoecia at the same stages shown in <bold>(A)</bold>, revealed by the histochemical activity of a GUS reporter gene directed by <italic>NGA3</italic> regulatory sequences (Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-05-00210-g0001"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Plant material</title><p><italic>nga1-4</italic> (line WiscDsLox429G06), <italic>nga2-2</italic> (line SM.20993) <italic>nga3-3</italic> (AMAZE En-1 line 6AAi79), and <italic>nga4-3</italic> (AMAZE En-1 line 6AAB133i) alleles were used to generate <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants. Genotyping was performed as previously described (Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). All reporter lines used in this study have been previously described: <italic>YUC8::GUS</italic> (Rawat et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), <italic>TAA1::GFP:TAA1</italic> (Stepanova et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>), <italic>AMI1::GUS</italic> (Hoffmann et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> (Benkov&#x000e1; et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>), <italic>PID::GUS</italic>, <italic>PID::PID:GFP</italic> (Lee and Cho, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), <italic>WAG2::GUS</italic> (Santner and Watson, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), <italic>PIN3::PIN3:GFP</italic> (Lee and Cho, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), <italic>ARF8::GUS</italic>, <italic>ARF11::ARF11:GFP, ARF18::ARF18:GFP</italic> (Rademacher et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>RNAseq analysis</title><p>Arabidopsis carpels between stages 8&#x02013;13 from wildtype, <italic>nga</italic> mutant and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> plants were collected manually from 15 developing inflorescences and stored transiently in cold extraction buffer of the Qiagen RNA extraction kit. RNA extraction was made with the Qiagen RNA extraction kit. RNA was analyzed for yield and quality on a Bioanalyzer 2100 (Agilent 2100). Libraries for sequencing were prepared from 2&#x02013;4 &#x003bc;g total RNA using Illumina TruSeq RNA kits and sequenced with Illumina HiSeq2000. Quality control on the raw sequence data was done using FastQC (Babraham Bioinformatics). Reads were aligned to whole genome sequences from the TAIR10 A. thaliana database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org">www.arabidopsis.org</ext-link>) and analyzed using the CLC Genomics workbench (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clcbio.com">www.clcbio.com</ext-link>). RPKM (reads per kilobase per million) was considered as expression values. Two biological replicates for wildtype and three for <italic>nga</italic> and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> were used for sequencing. After normalization, Bagerley's test and a FDR correction were used for statistical analysis of samples. Genes with a corrected FDR <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.05 and with a fold change &#x0003e;1.4 or &#x0003c;-1.4 were selected for gene ontology analysis with the agriGO toolkit (Du et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Reporter activity detection</title><p>GUS histochemical detection was performed as previously described (Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>For GFP detection, fluorescent images were captured using an LSM 780 confocal scanning laser inverted microscope (Zeiss). GFP was excited using a 488 nm line of an argon ion laser. GFP emission spectra were collected between 500&#x02013;550 nm and plastid autofluorescence was collected between 601 and 790 nm.</p></sec><sec><title>Auxin micro-application</title><p>For the micro-application experiment, 80 mg of indolacetic acid (IAA) (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) were dissolved in 2 mL of ethanol. IAA, or ethanol for mock treatment, was added to 10 gr of lanolin containing 2.5% liquid paraffin. The lanolin paste was applied to the apical end of stage 8&#x02013;10 gynoecia using plastic pipette tips under a dissecting microscope, resulting in apical parts completely covered by lanolin paste. The gynoecia were observed after 2 weeks and photographed under a dissecting scope.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>To identify genes involved in gynoecium development that are expressed under the control of NGA factors, we compared the expression profiles in stage 8&#x02013;13 dissected pistils from wildtype, quadruple <italic>nga</italic> mutants and plants overexpressing <italic>NGA3</italic> (stages defined after Smyth et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>; Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A,B</xref>). We selected transcripts with a fold change of &#x0003e;1.4 or &#x0003c;-1.4 and a corrected FDR <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.05. With those thresholds, we identified 1889 genes differentially expressed between wildtype and the quadruple <italic>nga</italic> mutant, 554 between wildtype and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> and 637 between the quadruple <italic>nga</italic> mutant and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic>. Combining the results of the three comparisons, a list of 2449 genes were identified as putative targets of NGA regulation. With this final list we conducted a gene ontology analysis with the agriGO toolkit, finding that auxin-related genes were overrepresented in the dataset of differentially expressed transcripts (Suppl. Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref>). Among them, genes related to auxin synthesis, transport, and response were identified, confirming previous reports of a functional relationship of NGA and auxin signaling (Alvarez et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), and suggesting that this interaction could occur at multiple levels.</p><p>To characterize in more detail how altered NGA activity influenced the spatial and temporal patterns of expression of their putative auxin-related targets, we introduced in <italic>nga</italic> mutants and in the <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> line reporter lines for several of these differentially expressed and other related genes, as well as markers for auxin accumulation.</p><sec><title>NGA mutations affect the expression of genes involved in auxin synthesis</title><p>It has been reported that <italic>nga</italic> mutations severely modify the expression patterns of <italic>YUC2</italic> and <italic>YUC4</italic> genes in the apical gynoecium (Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). <italic>YUC</italic> enzymes catalyze the rate- limiting step in Trp-dependent auxin biosynthesis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>) (Zhao et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Mano and Nemoto, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Only <italic>YUC2</italic> and <italic>YUC4</italic> have been shown to be strongly expressed in the apical developing gynoecium, suggesting that they could be essential contributors to auxin synthesis in this domain (Cheng et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). However, <italic>yuc2 yuc4</italic> double mutants show no evident phenotypes in floral development, indicating that other <italic>YUC</italic> genes may also be important to direct auxin synthesis in the pistil (Cheng et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). In the RNAseq dataset, the expression of one additional <italic>YUC</italic> gene, <italic>YUC8</italic>, was found to be strongly reduced in the quadruple <italic>nga</italic> mutant. In <italic>YUC8::GUS</italic> lines, expression could be observed in the ovules and in two small foci in the basal part of the style in stage 11&#x02013;12 wildtype pistils (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). This expression was completely absent in <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>), while appeared unchanged or slightly increased in <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> pistils (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>). At later stages (13&#x02013;15), expression in ovules was maintained in wildtype and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> fruits (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E&#x02013;G</xref>), although GUS activity was clearly stronger in the overexpression lines. These results confirm that <italic>YUC8</italic> is also upregulated by NGA factors at least in the apical gynoecium and likely in the ovules.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of NGA altered activity on the expression of genes involved in local auxin synthesis. (A)</bold> Simplified scheme of the presumptive pathways for IAA biosynthesis studied in this work, adapted from Mano and Nemoto (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Genetic functions analyzed in this work are noted in blue. Question mark on the TRP&#x0003e;IAA pathway denotes that the conversion of TRP to IAM has not been demonstrated in plants <bold>(B&#x02013;G)</bold> Histochemical detection of GUS activity driven by the <italic>YUC8</italic> promoter in wildtype <bold>(B,E)</bold>, <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants <bold>(C,F)</bold> and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> gynoecia <bold>(D,G)</bold> at stage 11 <bold>(B&#x02013;D)</bold> and at anthesis <bold>(E&#x02013;G)</bold>. <bold>(H&#x02013;P)</bold><italic>TAA1::GFP:TAA1</italic> expression in wildtype <bold>(H,K,N)</bold>, <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants <bold>(I,L,O)</bold>, and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> gynoecia <bold>(J,M,P)</bold> at stage 10 <bold>(H&#x02013;J)</bold> and stage 12 <bold>(K&#x02013;M)</bold>. <bold>(N&#x02013;P)</bold> show close up views of the valve margins in the ovary region of anthesis pistils. <bold>(Q&#x02013;X)</bold> Histochemical detection of GUS activity driven by the <italic>AMI1</italic> promoter in wildtype <bold>(Q,T,W)</bold>, <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants <bold>(R,U)</bold> and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> gynoecia <bold>(S,V,X)</bold> at stage 11 <bold>(Q&#x02013;R)</bold>, at anthesis <bold>(T&#x02013;V)</bold>, and post-fertilization, at around stage 16 <bold>(W&#x02013;X)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-05-00210-g0002"/></fig><p>In addition to <italic>YUC8</italic>, RNAseq data revealed that expression of <italic>TAA1</italic> was also affected by <italic>NGA</italic> loss of function. <italic>TAA1</italic> encodes an enzyme that catalyzes the conversion of Trp to IPA, the proposed substrate for YUC enzymes (Mano et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Stepanova et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). In wildtype developing gynoecia, a <italic>TAA1::GFP:TAA1</italic> reporter showed strong expression in the apical domain and in two longitudinal bands at medial positions in the developing gynoecial cylinder at stage 9&#x02013;10 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2H</xref>). Later in development (st. 11), expression became restricted to a cell layer at the style/stigma junction and to the medial vascular bundles and the vascular veins of the funiculi (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2K</xref>). In post-anthesis young fruits, expression was detected in the developing dehiscence zone at both sides of the replum (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2N</xref>). <italic>TAA1::GFP:TAA1</italic> expression was reduced but not absent from the apical and medial domains of <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants at stage 8&#x02013;9 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2I</xref>). In stage 11 <italic>nga</italic> gynoecia, since style and stigma do not form properly, the single cell layer of GFP expression below stigmatic cells could not be detected, but GFP accumulated at the tips of the valve protrusions and was mostly unchanged in other domains (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2L,O</xref>). In <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> pistils, <italic>TAA1::GFP:TAA1</italic> expression was found in the same spatial pattern as in wildtype, although GFP signal appeared to be stronger in all domains and maintained for longer (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2J,M</xref>). Thus, stage 11 <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> gynoecia still showed GFP signal in the medial region (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2M</xref>), and in post-anthesis young <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> fruits, strong expression could be detected in the funiculi and expanding to the valves (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2P</xref>).</p><p><italic>AMIDASE1 (AMI1)</italic> encodes an enzyme that catalyzes the conversion of IAM to IAA and it has been proposed to contribute to auxin synthesis through an alternative pathway to the TAA1/YUC route (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>) (Mano et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). An <italic>AMI1::GUS</italic> reporter line showed <italic>AMI1</italic> promoter to be active in most floral organs. In the gynoecium, GUS activity could be detected at medium levels throughout the gynoecial tube, while in the style region it accumulated strongly from stages 10&#x02013;11 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2Q</xref>). In anthesis flowers, GUS signal was very high in the style and it could also be detected in the vascular bundles (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2T</xref>). Apical expression disappeared in developing fruits, while in the ovary, low levels of expression could still be detected (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2W</xref>). In <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants, the strong expression in apical gynoecium typical of wildtype pistils was absent in preanthesis or anthesis pistils (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2R,U</xref>). Conversely, <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> lines showed stronger GUS signal that was maintained in developing <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> fruits (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2S,V,X</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Auxin accumulation is reduced in the apical domain of the NGA mutant gynoecia</title><p>Altogether, our results pointed to a greatly reduced or absent auxin synthesis in the apical domain of <italic>nga</italic> mutants and possibly a sustained increased auxin synthesis in the overexpression lines. If this was true, we could expect a reduced auxin accumulation in the apical domain of <italic>nga</italic> developing gynoecia and higher auxin levels in pistils and fruits. To test this hypothesis, we compared the activity of a <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> reporter in wildtype (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A&#x02013;C</xref>), <italic>nga</italic> quadruple (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D&#x02013;F</xref>) and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> backgrounds (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G&#x02013;I</xref>). <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> activity during Arabidopsis gynoecium development has been described (Benkov&#x000e1; et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Girin et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Marsch-Martinez et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>; Larsson et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). GFP expression is first detected as two lateral apical foci (stage 7), which at stage 8 also comprise two additional medial apical foci (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>), and at stage 9 extends as a continuous apical ring (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). In <italic>nga</italic> gynoecia, the apical foci in stage 7&#x02013;8 could be barely detected (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>), and the formation of the apical ring was never observed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref>). Surprisingly, in <italic>35S::NGA</italic> pistils, <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> activity was very similar to wildtype, indicating that in spite of the apparently increased auxin synthesis that could be expected from the stronger expression of <italic>TAA1</italic>, <italic>YUC8</italic>, or <italic>AMI1</italic>, the response of the reporter was not enhanced (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G&#x02013;I</xref>). Interestingly, when <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> activity in ovule primordia of wildtype and <italic>nga</italic> mutants was compared, a reduction of GFP levels in <italic>nga</italic> ovules was observed, but not the absence of the distal auxin maxima (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3J&#x02013;M</xref>). This result suggested that, in spite of the absence of <italic>YUC8</italic> expression in <italic>nga</italic> ovules, the persisting expression of <italic>YUC4</italic> previously reported in this domain (Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) was sufficient to direct auxin synthesis and allow ovule development.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of NGA altered activity on <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> expression in gynoecium development. (A&#x02013;C)</bold>
<italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> in wildtype pistil development. <bold>(A)</bold>
<italic>DR5rev:GFP</italic> is detected as discrete foci in stage 8 gynoecium <bold>(B)</bold> GFP is detected as a continuous apical ring in stage 9 gynoecium and in longitudinal strands at sites of main vascular development. <bold>(C)</bold> At stage 10, apical GFP expression is barely detected and signal is only clear in the funiculi of ovules. <bold>(D&#x02013;F)</bold>
<italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> expression in <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants. GFP is virtually undetectable at stage 8 <bold>(D)</bold>, stage 9 <bold>(E)</bold>, or stage 10 <bold>(F)</bold> gynoecia. <bold>(G&#x02013;I)</bold>
<italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> expression in <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> gynoecia. GFP expression is detected in similar patterns as wildtype in stage 8 <bold>(G)</bold> and stage 9 <bold>(H)</bold> gynoecia, while it appears to be slightly more persistent in the apical cells of stage 10 pistils <bold>(I)</bold>. <bold>(J,K)</bold>
<italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> expression in ovules of stage 10 wildtype <bold>(J,K)</bold> and nga quadruple mutants <bold>(L,M)</bold>. Note the reduced but detectable GFP activity at the tip of <italic>nga</italic> developing ovules. <bold>(N,O)</bold> Effect of micro-application of auxin to the apical end of <italic>nga</italic> mutant pistils. <bold>(N)</bold> Mock treated pistils, showing completely unfused apical ends with no signs of style or stigma development. <bold>(O)</bold> IAA-treated pistils show apical closure and very limited style development, but no stigmatic cells are able to develop.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-05-00210-g0003"/></fig><p>Low auxin levels have been related to the <italic>nga</italic> phenotypes in style and stigma. Thus, reduced apical tissues were observed in a transgenic line where the <italic>NGA3</italic> promoter drove the expression of <italic>iaaL,</italic> a bacterial gene that encodes an enzyme that inactivates free auxin (Jensen et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). To test whether exogenous auxin treatments could restore style and stigma development, we performed micro-applications of IAA dissolved in droplets of lanolin to the tip of young developing <italic>nga</italic> gynoecia (stages 9&#x02013;10). A limited partial rescue of the <italic>nga</italic> phenotypes was observed, with restored apical closure of the gynoecium, but no development of style or stigma typical cells, suggesting that the lack of auxin accumulation in this domain was probably not the only factor causing the <italic>nga</italic> phenotypes (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3N,O</xref>).</p><p>In summary, auxin synthesis was likely very reduced in the apical domain of <italic>nga</italic> mutants, both through the TAA/YUC pathway and the presumptive AMI1 pathway, thus leading to low auxin levels in the distal region of <italic>nga</italic> developing pistils as deduced from the greatly reduced activity of the of <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> reporter. However, <italic>NGA3</italic> overexpression did not have a high impact in distal auxin accumulation, suggesting that NGA factors could also be interfering with other components of the auxin transport/response pathways.</p></sec><sec><title>NGA mutations affect the expression of genes involved in auxin transport</title><p>Members of the PIN protein family of auxin efflux regulators have been shown to mediate various developmental processes, including carpel patterning. Polar, subcellular localization of PIN proteins determines the direction of auxin flux (reviewed in Friml, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>) and this localization is partially regulated by their phosphorylation status, which depends on the antagonistic action of the PP2AA phosphatases, and kinases such as PINOID, WAG1, WAG2, and PID2 (Santner and Watson, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Michniewicz et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). <italic>PID</italic> and <italic>WAG2</italic> expression has been reported in apical tissues of Arabidopsis developing gynoecia (Girin et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Moreover, <italic>pid</italic> mutants show severe carpel patterning phenotypes similar to those found in <italic>pin1</italic> or <italic>pin3 pin7</italic> mutants (Okada et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Bennett et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>; Benkov&#x000e1; et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). RNAseq analyses revealed altered expression levels of both <italic>PID</italic> and <italic>WAG2</italic> in either <italic>nga</italic> or <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> pistils, and therefore, we introduced <italic>PID</italic> and <italic>WAG2</italic> reporters into these backgrounds. <italic>PID::GUS</italic> activity was weakly detected in the style of stage 11 wildtype carpels (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). In <italic>nga</italic> mutants, expression could still be detected in the apical protrusions typical of <italic>nga</italic> gynoecia (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>), while in <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> pistils, expression was absent in the style but present in the stigma (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>). Moreover, a <italic>PID::PID:GFP</italic> reporter line showed a substantially reduced GFP signal in <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> lines when compared to wildtype, suggesting that NGA3 could be preventing PID accumulation (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D&#x02013;G</xref>). <italic>WAG2::GUS</italic> showed early expression in the distal end of the stage 9 gynoecial tube in wildtype, <italic>nga</italic>, or <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4H&#x02013;J</xref>). This apical expression was maintained until stage 11 in wildtype or <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> pistils (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4K,M</xref>), while clearly reduced in <italic>nga</italic> mutants (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4L</xref>). These results suggested that NGA factors could regulate <italic>PID</italic> and <italic>WAG2</italic> in opposite directions, repressing <italic>PID</italic> while activating <italic>WAG2</italic>, similarly to what it has been described for the bHLH transcription factors INDEHISCENT and SPATULA (Girin et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of NGA altered activity on the expression of protein kinases involved in the regulation of PIN subcellular polarization. (A&#x02013;C)</bold> Histochemical detection of GUS activity driven by the <italic>PID</italic> promoter in wildtype <bold>(A)</bold>, <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants <bold>(B)</bold> and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> apical region of stage 12 gynoecia <bold>(C)</bold>. <bold>(D&#x02013;G)</bold>
<italic>PID::PID:GFP</italic> expression in stage 9 wildtype <bold>(D)</bold> or <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> gynoecia and in the style/stigma region of stage 12 wildtype <bold>(F)</bold> or <italic>35S::NGA3</italic>
<bold>(G)</bold> pistils. <bold>(H&#x02013;M)</bold> Histochemical detection of GUS activity driven by the <italic>WAG2</italic> promoter in wildtype <bold>(H,K)</bold>, <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants <bold>(I,L)</bold> and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic>
<bold>(J,M)</bold> gynoecia at stage 9 <bold>(H&#x02013;J)</bold> and stage 11 <bold>(K&#x02013;M)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-05-00210-g0004"/></fig><p>The differences in <italic>PID</italic> and <italic>WAG</italic> expression caused by altered NGA activity suggested that PIN protein localization could also be affected. PIN1 protein localization has been described in developing fruits, but no detailed patterns of expression have been described for any of the PIN transporters throughout gynoecium development (Sorefan et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). We compared <italic>PIN1::PIN1:GFP</italic> in wildtype, <italic>nga</italic>, and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> backgrounds, but no clear differences could be observed (Suppl. Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">2</xref>). Likewise, the <italic>PIN7::PIN7:GFP</italic> reporter line available to us showed very low levels of GFP activity and we could not obtain conclusive results. Finally, we determined <italic>PIN3::PIN3:GFP</italic> expression in wildtype developing gynoecia. PIN3:GFP protein was localized in a narrow apical ring and two longitudinal stripes at epidermal medial positions in stage nine pistils (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A,B</xref>). Apical expression was maintained at stage 12, restricted to the stigma and the underlying layers in the style, and also in the replum domain, although at lower levels (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C,D</xref>). It was difficult to determine the subcellular orientation of PIN3 both in the apical ring and in the replum domain at early stages, and therefore the direction of the auxin flux was not easily deduced. At stage 12, however, PIN3:GFP protein was mostly localized in the basal side of cells in the style and the replum, suggesting that auxin flux would be directed toward the basal part of the ovary (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>). We failed to introduce the <italic>PIN3::PIN3:GFP</italic> reporter in the <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants background, but PIN3:GFP accumulation was studied in the <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> background. <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> pistils showed similar accumulation patterns of PIN3 at stage 9 (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E,F</xref>). However, from stage 11, PIN3 accumulation appeared to be increased both in the apical domain and the replum region, where it comprised a higher number of cell rows, suggesting that basipetal auxin flux could be facilitated in the <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> background (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5G,H</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of NGA altered activity on PIN3 protein localization</bold>. <italic>PIN3::PIN3:GFP</italic> expression was observed in wildtype <bold>(A&#x02013;D)</bold> and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic>
<bold>(E&#x02013;H)</bold> developing gynoecia at stage 10 <bold>(A,B,E,F)</bold> and stage 12 <bold>(C,D,G,H)</bold>. Close view of the apical ring in wildtype <bold>(B)</bold> or <italic>35S::NGA3</italic>
<bold>(F)</bold> stage 10 pistils did not show a clear PIN3 subcellular polarization, although in the longitudinal stripes of cells running along the ovary, PIN3 appears to be predominantly at the basal side of cells. <bold>(C)</bold> Stage 12 wildtype gynoecia showed strong GFP signal in stigmatic cells and in a domain in the style just below the stigma. <bold>(D)</bold> In wildtype stage 12 ovaries three rows of cells showed PIN3:GFP expression, where PIN3:GPF protein appeared to be localized at the basal side of cells. <bold>(G)</bold> In <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> stage 12 pistils, PIN3:GFP is detected in stigma and a broader domain of the style <bold>(H)</bold> In <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> stage 12 ovaries, PIN3:GFP expands to 4&#x02013;5 cell longitudinal rows, also apparently localized to the basal side of cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-05-00210-g0005"/></fig></sec><sec><title>NGA mutations affect in different ways the expression of auxin response factors (ARFs) throughout gynoecium development</title><p>Finally, we took advantage of the recently created collection of ARF reporters described by Rademacher et al. (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) to examine the effect of NGA altered activity on the protein expression patterns of several ARFs expressed in the apical domain of developing gynoecia, namely ARF1, ARF8, ARF11, and ARF18. We also included in our analyses ARF3/ETT, since it was also expressed in the developing pistil, but we did not observe significant changes in reporter activity in the <italic>nga</italic> or <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> backgrounds (Suppl Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">3</xref>).</p><p><italic>ARF8::ARF8:GUS</italic> reporter activity in wildtype gynoecium development has been already described (Goetz et al., <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). ARF8 protein appears strongly associated to transmitting tissues, specially stigma and transmitting tract, and, at lower levels, in the ovary walls and the ovules (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A,C</xref>). Loss of <italic>NGA</italic> function mainly affected the accumulation of ARF8:GUS in the apical end of the gynoecium, which appeared reduced at anthesis although maintaining foci of expression at the apical end of valve protrusions, while did not alter significantly ARF8:GUS levels in the ovary or the ovules (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B,D</xref>). Crosses between <italic>ARF8::ARF8:GUS</italic> and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> line failed and therefore we were not able to analyze the activity of the reporter in this background for this work.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of NGA altered activity on the expression of ARFs throughout gynoecium development. (A&#x02013;D)</bold> Histochemical detection of <italic>ARF8::ARF8:GUS</italic> activity in wildtype <bold>(A,C)</bold>, and <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants <bold>(B,D)</bold> gynoecia at stage 12 <bold>(A,B)</bold> and at anthesis <bold>(C,D)</bold>. While in stage 12 pistils ARF8 apical accumulation is clearly reduced <bold>(B)</bold>, at anthesis shows some expression at valve protrusions formed in the nga quadruple mutant <bold>(D)</bold>. <bold>(E&#x02013;M)</bold>
<italic>ARF1::ARF1:GFP</italic> expression in wildtype <bold>(E,H,K)</bold>, <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants <bold>(F,I,L)</bold> and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> gynoecia <bold>(G,J,M)</bold> at stage 10 <bold>(E&#x02013;G)</bold> and at anthesis <bold>(H&#x02013;M)</bold>. <bold>(H&#x02013;J)</bold> show close up views of the apical domain, and <bold>(K&#x02013;M)</bold> show close up views of valve margins in the ovary region of anthesis pistils. <bold>(N&#x02013;S)</bold>
<italic>ARF11::ARF11:GFP</italic> expression in wildtype <bold>(N,Q)</bold>, <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants <bold>(O,R)</bold> and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> gynoecia <bold>(P,S)</bold> at stage 10 <bold>(N&#x02013;P)</bold> and at stage 11 <bold>(Q&#x02013;S)</bold>. Note the strongly reduced GFP signal in the apical region of <italic>nga</italic> mutants <bold>(O,R)</bold> and the strong signal associated with valve margins of <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> developing gynoecia <bold>(P,S)</bold>. <bold>(T&#x02013;Y)</bold>
<italic>ARF18::ARF18:GFP</italic> expression in wildtype <bold>(T,W)</bold>, <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants <bold>(U,X)</bold> and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> gynoecia <bold>(V,Y)</bold> at stage 11 <bold>(T&#x02013;V)</bold> and at anthesis <bold>(W&#x02013;Y)</bold>. Note expanded GFP signal associated with valve margins of <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> pistils <bold>(V,Y)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-05-00210-g0006"/></fig><p><italic>ARF1::ARF1:GFP</italic> reporter showed activity in medial and epidermal tissues of stage 10 wildtype gynoecia, with higher levels of GFP signal at the apical end of the gynoecial tube (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6E</xref>). In anthesis wildtype pistils, signal was mainly associated with stigmatic cells and valve margins, with low but consistent accumulation of ARF1:GFP detected in the epidermal cells of style and valves (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6H,K</xref>). In <italic>nga</italic> mutants, ARF1:GFP patterns were very similar to wildtype in preanthesis and anthesis stages, although likely due to the lack of stigmatic cells, no strong signal was detected in apical cells of anthesis <italic>nga</italic> gynoecia (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6F,I,L</xref>). As for <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> lines, ARF1:GFP expression was found at similar domains, although it appeared to be increased in level (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6G,J</xref>). This stronger expression was more conspicuous at anthesis, where valves showed clearly enhanced fluorescent signal (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6M</xref>).</p><p><italic>ARF11::ARF11:GFP</italic> reporter activity was detected already at stage 9&#x02013;10 in the presumptive developing style and the valve margins (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6N</xref>), accumulating below the stigmatic cells until stage 12 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6Q</xref>), and becoming barely detected at anthesis and later stages. In <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants, ARF11:GFP protein could be only detected at very reduced levels in a small apical domain of stage 10 pistils (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6O,R</xref>), while in <italic>35S::NGA3</italic>, ARF11:GFP protein accumulated similarly to wildtype in the apical tissues although in an expanded domain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6P</xref>). Interestingly, and unlike from wildtype, ARF11:GFP accumulated in the valve margins of <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> gynoecia from early stages of development, where it could still be strongly detected prior and at anthesis (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6P,S</xref>).</p><p><italic>ARF18::ARF18:GFP</italic> reporter drove a strong GFP signal in the apical domain of stage 10 wildtype pistils (style and stigmatic cells) and at the valve margins (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6T</xref>). At later stages (stage 13 and postanthesis), ARF18:GFP could still be detected in the stigmatic cells and the differentiating dehiscence zones, restricted to a few cell rows (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6W</xref>). In <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants, ARF18:GFP accumulation was similar to that observed in wildtype, in spite of the absence of style and stigma, and signal was detected in the valve protrusions that developed apically. In stage 11 <italic>nga</italic> gynoecia, a strong GFP signal could be observed in the apical domain and weakly at the valve margins (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6U</xref>). Apical expression could still be weakly detected in anthesis <italic>nga</italic> pistils, to become restricted to the dehiscence zones in post-anthesis stages (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6X</xref>). <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> pistils also showed similar patterns of ARF18:GFP accumulation in apical domains and in the valve margins (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6V</xref>). In anthesis and post-anthesis stages, however, the accumulation of ARF18:GFP was found in a broader area at the valve margins, correlating with the lateral expansion of the dehiscence zones in <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> fruits (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6Y</xref>) (Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The study carried out in this work shows how alterations in NGA function have significant effects in auxin signaling throughout gynoecium development and that these interactions likely occur at multiple levels.</p><p>First, we have shown that the apical auxin maxima that forms in stage 8&#x02013;9 wildtype gynoecia cannot be detected in <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants. While it is not conclusively proven that this maxima is directly responsible for style and stigma differentiation, it is clearly temporally correlated with the development of these tissues. Moreover, the inability of <italic>nga</italic> mutants to form this maxima and to differentiate apical tissues that we show in this work, together with the <italic>nga</italic>-like phenotypes of lines where the <italic>NGA3</italic> promoter directed the expression of <italic>iaaL</italic>, an enzyme that inactivates the pool of active auxin (Jensen et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>), supports this direct causative link. On the other hand, the partial rescue of <italic>nga</italic> apical defects by local auxin application might suggest that the absence of auxin maxima is not the only cause of <italic>nga</italic> phenotypic defects. However, the method that we used for local auxin treatment is coarse and may not reproduce properly the spatial distribution or the timing of auxin accumulation dynamics, therefore providing a partial picture of the expected effects and limiting the validity of these conclusions. Interestingly, the generation of auxin maxima as revealed by <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> in developing gynoecia that constitutively express <italic>NGA3</italic> is not significantly different from that of wildtype. <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> pistils do not show a dramatic overproliferation of style and stigma, thus indirectly reinforcing the idea of the putative instructive role of auxin accumulation in these tissues to direct the development of apical tissues (Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>The likely failure to accumulate auxin in the apical domain of <italic>nga</italic> mutants can also explain the insensitivity of <italic>nga</italic> mutants to PAT inhibition (Alvarez et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>): since no auxin is present, it can be expected that no basipetal transport takes place and therefore, no phenotypic defects result from this inhibition. It has been shown that <italic>shi/sty</italic> mutants are hypersensitive to NPA treatment (St&#x000e5;ldal et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). This situation is opposite to that found in <italic>nga</italic> mutants, in spite of the almost identical phenotypes found in gynoecium development and the apparent convergent regulation of YUC-mediated auxin synthesis by both NGA and SHI/STY factors (Kuusk et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Sohlberg et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Eklund et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). This could reflect a different role of NGA and SHI/STY factors in the establishment of auxin maxima or in the regulation of downstream effectors in response to those. To understand these mechanistical differences, it would be useful to describe auxin accumulation throughout gynoecium development in <italic>shi/sty</italic> multiple mutants.</p><p>Local auxin synthesis appears to be strongly reduced in apical tissues of <italic>nga</italic> mutants. It already has been shown that <italic>NGA</italic> downregulation leads to the loss of <italic>YUC2</italic> and <italic>YUC4</italic> activation in the apical domain of developing gynoecia (Trigueros et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). We show here that <italic>YUC8</italic> expression is completely absent in <italic>nga</italic> mutant pistils, while slightly increased in <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> lines. It could be envisioned that the lack of apical auxin maxima in <italic>nga</italic> pistils could be due to the absence of YUC-mediated auxin synthesis in this domain. The phenotypes of <italic>yuc2 yuc4 yuc8</italic> triple mutants have not been described, so it is not possible to directly compare both scenarios. Even in the triple mutants, since <italic>YUC2</italic> and <italic>YUC4</italic> are normally expressed in <italic>nga</italic> mutants outside the apical gynoecium, loss of <italic>YUC2</italic> and <italic>YUC4</italic> function could have additional effects that might obscure the specific role of <italic>YUC2/4/8</italic> in style and stigma differentiation, so in addition to generating and characterizing the <italic>yuc2 yuc4 yuc8</italic> triple mutants, it might be necessary to inactivate specifically all three enzymes in the apical developing gynoecium. In addition to the effect of <italic>nga</italic> mutations on <italic>YUC</italic> gene expression, <italic>TAA1</italic> and <italic>AMI1</italic> also appear to be under NGA direct or indirect regulation. TAA1 has been recently placed in the same biosynthetic route as the YUC enzymes (Stepanova et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) and thus it would be possible that the moderate effects of NGA altered function in <italic>TAA1</italic> expression would not lead to dramatic differences in auxin synthesis rates through this TAA-YUC pathway. Unlike the <italic>YUC</italic> genes for which detailed expression patterns in carpels have been reported, <italic>TAA1</italic> is expressed in carpel margins of stage 12 and postanthesis wildtype pistils. Interestingly, this valve margin expression is reduced in <italic>nga</italic> mutants while increased in <italic>NGA3</italic> overexpressors. While the role of this putative local auxin synthesis at the valve margin is currently unknown, as well as the precise role of <italic>NGA</italic> in valve margin development, the possible altered auxin synthesis in valve margins in response to NGA differential activity could partly explain the changes in the expression levels of <italic>ARF1</italic>, <italic>ARF11</italic> or <italic>ARF18</italic> in the different <italic>NGA</italic> backgrounds revealed in this study. Finally, a third putative contributor to local auxin synthesis is the AMI1 enzyme, which catalyzes the transformation of IAM to IAA. It is still unclear whether AMI1 activity significantly contributes to auxin synthesis in inflorescence development (Mano et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Zhao, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), but the strong <italic>AMI1</italic> expression in developing gynoecia and, specially, in apical and transmitting tissues, suggests that it may have a role in auxin production in this domain. We show here that <italic>nga</italic> mutations significantly reduce <italic>AMI1</italic> accumulation in the apical pistil, while <italic>NGA3</italic> overexpression leads to increased and persistent levels of <italic>AMI1</italic> expression, thus indicating that NGA could also positively regulate AMI1 activity in these tissues and hence putative auxin synthesis through this pathway. It has been described that <italic>ami1</italic> mutants (aka <italic>attoc64-I</italic>) do not show phenotypic defects (Aronsson et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), which could be due to redundancy with other members of the family, and therefore is its premature to speculate at this point about the relevance of the NGA-AMI1 functional relationship. However, the convergent effect of <italic>NGA</italic> mutations on the regulation of <italic>TAA1</italic>, <italic>YUC,</italic> and <italic>AMI1</italic> strongly suggests that NGA factors may function as strong positive regulators of auxin synthesis in the apical gynoecium.</p><p>The strongly reduced or absent local auxin synthesis in the apical developing <italic>nga</italic> mutant gynoecia probably contributes to the reduced auxin accumulation observed in these tissues, although it is unlikely to be the only cause. It is generally accepted that auxin maxima are mainly produced by PAT (Grieneisen et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), and there are examples of these maxima directing auxin synthesis that could reinforce auxin accumulation patterns (Grieneisen et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). In this work, it has been shown how enzymes involved in auxin synthesis are still expressed in the apical gynoecium after the <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> reporter signal has faded or is very reduced, suggesting that additional mechanisms have also an impact in auxin distribution downstream auxin synthesis. Clearly more work would be needed to resolve the interplay between transport, synthesis and probably other components of the pathway. Such further work should include a detailed characterization of auxin flux as directed by auxin transporters such as several PIN-family members or other transporters. Unfortunately, our analyses on the effect of <italic>NGA</italic> loss or gain of function on PIN proteins have not produced clear conclusions. Still, our results indicate that auxin transport is likely altered in <italic>nga</italic> mutants or the <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> line, since the expression of <italic>PID</italic> and <italic>WAG2</italic>, major regulators of PIN polarization, as well as the expression domain of PIN3 are affected by <italic>NGA</italic> altered function. In this sense, the expanded domain of expression of PIN3 observed in <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> pistils could facilitate auxin depletion from the apical domain through increased basipetal auxin transport, thus providing a hint on the mechanisms that could explain the wildtype-like response of <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> observed in <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> developing gynoecia.</p><p>Finally, protein accumulation patterns for several ARFs expressed through gynoecium development have been described in wildtype, <italic>nga</italic> mutants and <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> lines. We have found that NGA factors appear to differentially regulate the accumulation of the different ARFs under study. Thus, the apical domain of accumulation found for ARF11 is completely lost in <italic>nga</italic> mutants, while apical expression of <italic>ARF8</italic> and <italic>ARF1</italic> (and only slightly that of <italic>ARF18</italic>) are reduced, but not absent, from <italic>nga</italic> mutant apical gynoecia. Interestingly, <italic>NGA3</italic> constitutive expression appears to induce the expanded expression at valve margins of <italic>ARF1</italic>, <italic>ARF11</italic>, and <italic>ARF18</italic>, similarly to what was observed for <italic>TAA1</italic> expression, suggesting that they might be responsive to local auxin synthesis putatively mediated by TAA1. It has been described that <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> fruits have enlarged dehiscence zones and thus, this expanded expression domains could be also due to an indirect effect of <italic>NGA3</italic> overexpression on fruit morphology. Because no function has been assigned yet to <italic>ARF1</italic>, <italic>ARF11</italic>, or <italic>ARF18</italic> in gynoecium development, it remains to be studied whether ARF regulation may mediate <italic>NGA</italic> functions in this process.</p><p>In summary, our work shows that NGA factors impact on auxin signaling pathways at multiple levels throughout pistil development. First, and more importantly, NGA factors appear to be essential, but not sufficient for auxin synthesis in the apical developing gynoecium, since several members of the <italic>YUC</italic> family, as well as <italic>TAA1</italic> and <italic>AMI1</italic> were not expressed in this domain in <italic>nga</italic> quadruple mutants, but only showed moderately increased expression in <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> lines. Accordingly, <italic>DR5rev::GFP</italic> showed no activity in <italic>nga</italic> mutants but no significant differences in <italic>35S::NGA3</italic> pistils when compared to wildtype. It is thus tempting to speculate that NGA could only direct auxin synthesis in the presence of other factors, for which SHI/STY family members are strong candidates. In addition, NGA altered activity affected the expression of <italic>PID</italic> and <italic>WAG2</italic>, regulators of PIN subcellular localization, and thus likely had an impact on auxin transport in parallel to the effect on auxin synthesis. Finally, protein accumulation in pistils of several ARFs was differentially affected by <italic>nga</italic> mutations or <italic>NGA</italic> overexpression, suggesting that these accumulation patterns depend not only on auxin distribution but could be also regulated by transcriptional networks involving NGA factors. Again, <italic>NGA3</italic> constitutive expression did not result in wide activation of ARF expression in the gynoecium, reinforcing the idea of NGA requiring additional factors to exert their regulatory functions.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Stephan Pollmann (CBGP, Spain), Lars Ostergaard (JIC, UK), and Eva Sundberg (U. Uppsala, Sweden) for providing seeds, and Marisol Gasc&#x000f3;n (IBMCP) for technical help and advice with confocal microscopy. This work was supported by the Spanish Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovacion (grant no. BIO2009&#x02013;09920 to Cristina Ferr&#x000e1;ndiz), the Fondazione Cariplo (grant &#x0201c;Fruitalia&#x0201d; to Lucia Colombo and Cristina Ferr&#x000e1;ndiz), and the European Union (grant no. FP7&#x02013;PEOPLE&#x02013;PIRSES<bold>&#x02013;</bold>2009&#x02013;247589 to Lucia Colombo, Cristina Ferr&#x000e1;ndiz, Antonio C. Oliveira).</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary material" id="s5"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.frontiersin.org/Journal/10.3389/fpls.2014.00210/abstract">http://www.frontiersin.org/Journal/10.3389/fpls.2014.00210/abstract</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="DataSheet1.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alabadi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blazquez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrandiz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Amador</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Instructive roles for hormones in plant development</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Dev. Biol</source>. <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>1597</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1608</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1387/ijdb.072423da</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19247940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19247940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldshmidt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Efroni</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The NGATHA distal organ development genes are essential for style specification in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1393</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.065482</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19435933?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19435933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aronsson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boij</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Topel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Toc64/OEP64 is not essential for the efficient import of proteins into chloroplasts in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03207.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17655652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17655652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balanz&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarrete</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trigueros</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferr&#x000e1;ndiz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Patterning the female side of Arabidopsis: the importance of hormones</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot</source>. <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>3457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3469</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erl188</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17023565?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17023565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benkov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michniewicz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teichmann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seifertov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000fc;rgens</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Local, efflux-dependent auxin gradients as a common module for plant organ formation</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>602</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00924-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14651850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14651850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bossinger</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Morphogenesis in pinoid mutants of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>505</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>520</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1995.8040505.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Auxin biosynthesis by the YUCCA flavin monooxygenases controls the formation of floral organs and vascular tissues in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1790</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1799</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1415106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16818609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16818609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>agriGO: a GO analysis toolkit for the agricultural community</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>W64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W70</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq310</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20435677?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20435677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eklund</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x000e5;ldal</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valsecchi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cierlik</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiratsu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> STYLISH1 protein acts as a transcriptional activator regulating auxin biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>363</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.108.064816</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20154152?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20154152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrandiz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fourquin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prunet</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scutt</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trehin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Carpel development</article-title>. <source>Adv. Bot. Res</source>. <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-380868-4.00001-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18315540?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18315540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fourquin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrandiz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The essential role of NGATHA genes in style and stigma specification is widely conserved across eudicots</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <volume>202</volume>, <fpage>1001</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1013</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.12703</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24483275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24483275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Auxin transport &#x02013; shaping the plant</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Plant Biol</source>. <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369526602000031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12495745?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12495745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Girin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paicu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;rner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>INDEHISCENT and SPATULA interact to specify carpel and valve margin tissue and thus promote seed dispersal in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>3641</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3653</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.090944</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21990939?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21990939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivian-Smith</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koltunow</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR8 is a negative regulator of fruit initiation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1873</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1886</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.037192</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16829592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16829592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grieneisen</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maree</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostergaard</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Juicy stories on female reproductive tissue development: coordinating the hormone flows</article-title>. <source>J. Integr. Plant Biol</source>. <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>847</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>863</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jipb.12092</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23869979?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23869979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grieneisen</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maree</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogeweg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheres</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Auxin transport is sufficient to generate a maximum and gradient guiding root growth</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>449</volume>, <fpage>1008</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1013</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06215</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17960234?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17960234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hentrich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Expression of AMIDASE1 (AMI1) is suppressed during the first two days after germination</article-title>. <source>Plant Signal. Behav</source>. <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>1642</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1644</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.5.12.13810</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21150258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21150258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hangarter</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estelle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Auxin transport is required for hypocotyl elongation in light-grown but not dark-grown Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>. <volume>116</volume>, <fpage>455</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>462</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.116.2.455</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9489005?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9489005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuusk</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohlberg</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridborg</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>STY1 and STY2 promote the formation of apical tissues during Arabidopsis gynoecium development</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>129</volume>, <fpage>4707</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4717</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 12361963?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12361963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuusk</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohlberg</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnus Eklund</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Functionally redundant SHI family genes regulate Arabidopsis gynoecium development in a dose-dependent manner</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>111</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02774.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16740146?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16740146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Auxin and the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> gynoecium</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot</source>. <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>2619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2627</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert099</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23585670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23585670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>PINOID positively regulates auxin efflux in Arabidopsis root hair cells and tobacco cells</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1616</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.035972</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16731587?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mano</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The pathway of auxin biosynthesis in plants</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot</source>. <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>2853</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2872</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ers091</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22447967?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22447967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mano</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muranaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The AMI1 gene family: indole-3-acetamide hydrolase functions in auxin biosynthesis in plants</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot</source>. <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erp292</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19887500?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19887500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marsch-Martinez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos-Cruz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Irepan Reyes-Olalde</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano-Sotomayor</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuniga-Mayo</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Folter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012a</year>). <article-title>The role of cytokinin during Arabidopsis gynoecia and fruit morphogenesis and patterning</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>222</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>234</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2012.05062.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22640521?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22640521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marsch-Martinez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes-Olalde</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos-Cruz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano-Sotomayor</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Z&#x000fa;&#x000f1;iga-Mayo</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Folter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012b</year>). <article-title>Hormones talking: does hormonal cross-talk shapes the Arabidopsis gynoecium?</article-title>
<source>Plant Signal. Behav</source>. <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1698</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1701</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.22422</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23072997?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23072997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michniewicz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zago</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abas</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weijers</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweighofer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meskiene</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Antagonistic regulation of PIN phosphorylation by PP2A and PINOID directs auxin flux</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>130</volume>, <fpage>1044</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1056</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2007.07.033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17889649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17889649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nemhauser</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zambryski</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Auxin and ETTIN in Arabidopsis gynoecium morphogenesis</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>127</volume>, <fpage>3877</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3888</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 10952886?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10952886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Komaki</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Requirement of the auxin polar transport system in early stages of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> floral bu formation</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>677</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>684</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.3.7.677</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12324609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12324609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rademacher</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000f6;ller</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lokerse</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Llavata-Peris</surname><given-names>C. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Berg</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weijers</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A cellular expression map of the Arabidopsis AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR gene family</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>597</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>606</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04710.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21831209?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21831209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rawat</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sairanen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>REVEILLE1, a Myb-like transcription factor, integrates the circadian clock and auxin pathways</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source>. <volume>106</volume>, <fpage>16883</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16888</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0813035106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19805390?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805390</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santner</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The WAG1 and WAG2 protein kinases negatively regulate root waving in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>752</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>764</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02641.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16460509?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16460509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Early flower development in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>755</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>767</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.2.8.755</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2152125?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2152125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohlberg</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myrenas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuusk</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagercrantz</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalczyk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandberg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>STY1 regulates auxin homeostasis and affects apical-basal patterning of the Arabidopsis gynoecium</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02775.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16740145?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16740145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorefan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Girin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liljegren</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galv&#x000e1;n-Ampudia</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A regulated auxin minimum is required for seed dispersal in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>459</volume>, <fpage>583</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>586</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07875</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19478783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19478783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>St&#x000e5;ldal</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohlberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eklund</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Auxin can act independently of CRC, LUG, SEU, SPT and STY1 in style development but not apical-basal patterning of the Arabidopsis gynoecium</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <volume>180</volume>, <fpage>798</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>808</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2008.02625.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18811619?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18811619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>St&#x000e5;ldal</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The role of auxin in style development and apical-basal patterning of the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> gynoecium</article-title>. <source>Plant Signal. Behav</source>. <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.4.2.7538</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19649177?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19649177</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson-Hoyt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benavente</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolezal</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>TAA1-mediated auxin biosynthesis is essential for hormone crosstalk and plant development</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>133</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.01.047</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18394997?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18394997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The Arabidopsis YUCCA1 flavin monooxygenase functions in the indole-3-pyruvic acid branch of auxin biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>3961</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3973</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.088047</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22108406?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22108406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferr&#x000e1;ndiz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Gynoecium patterning in Arabidopsis: a basic plan behind a complex structure</article-title>, in <source>Annual Plant Reviews Volume 38: Fruit Development and Seed Dispersal</source>, ed <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>&#x000d8;stergaard</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>), <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/9781444314557.ch2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trigueros</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarrete-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelaz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The NGATHA genes direct style development in the Arabidopsis gynoecium</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1394</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1409</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.065508</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19435937?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19435937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Auxin biosynthesis and its role in plant development</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol</source>. <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042809-112308</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20192736?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cashman</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>A role for flavin monooxygenase-like enzymes in auxin biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>291</volume>, <fpage>306</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>309</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.291.5502.306</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11209081?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11209081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>