<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">gbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4202334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25193308</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evu198</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evu198</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genome Diversity and Divergence in <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic>: Multiple Signatures of Faster X Evolution</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garrigan</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="evu198-COR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kingan</surname><given-names>Sarah B.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Geneva</surname><given-names>Anthony J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vedanayagam</surname><given-names>Jeffrey P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Presgraves</surname><given-names>Daven C.</given-names></name></contrib><aff>Department of Biology, University of Rochester</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="evu198-COR1">*Corresponding author: E-mail: <email>dgarriga@ur.rochester.edu</email>.</corresp><fn id="FN1"><p><bold>Associate editor</bold>: Soojin Yi</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>09</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2444</fpage><lpage>2458</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" license-type="creative-commons"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic> is an Indian Ocean island endemic species that diverged from its two sister species, <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> and <italic>Drosophila sechellia</italic>, approximately 240,000 years ago. Multiple forms of incomplete reproductive isolation have evolved among these species, including sexual, gametic, ecological, and intrinsic postzygotic barriers, with crosses among all three species conforming to Haldane&#x02019;s rule: F<sub>1</sub> hybrid males are sterile and F<sub>1</sub> hybrid females are fertile. Extensive genetic resources and the fertility of hybrid females have made <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>, in particular, an important model for speciation genetics. Analyses between <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> and both of its siblings have shown that the X chromosome makes a disproportionate contribution to hybrid male sterility. But why the X plays a special role in the evolution of hybrid sterility in these, and other, species remains an unsolved problem. To complement functional genetic analyses, we have investigated the population genomics of <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>, giving special attention to differences between the X and the autosomes. We present a de novo genome assembly of <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> annotated with RNAseq data and a whole-genome analysis of polymorphism and divergence from ten individuals. Our analyses show that, relative to the autosomes, the X chromosome has reduced nucleotide diversity but elevated nucleotide divergence; an excess of recurrent adaptive evolution at its protein-coding genes; an excess of recent, strong selective sweeps; and a large excess of satellite DNA. Interestingly, one of two centimorgan-scale selective sweeps on the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> X chromosome spans a region containing two <italic>sex-ratio</italic> meiotic drive elements and a high concentration of satellite DNA. Furthermore, genes with roles in reproduction and chromosome biology are enriched among genes that have histories of recurrent adaptive protein evolution. Together, these genome-wide analyses suggest that genetic conflict and frequent positive natural selection on the X chromosome have shaped the molecular evolutionary history of <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>, refining our understanding of the possible causes of the large X-effect in speciation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>adaptation</kwd><kwd><italic>Drosophila</italic></kwd><kwd>genome</kwd><kwd>satellite DNA</kwd><kwd>selective sweep</kwd><kwd>X chromosome</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>During the past 30 years, the three species of the <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> clade&#x02014;<italic>D</italic><italic>. simulans, </italic><italic>Drosophila sechellia</italic>, and <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic>&#x02014;have emerged as important models in evolutionary genetics, owing mostly to their phylogenetic proximity to <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>. The common ancestor of the <italic>D. simulans</italic> clade species originated on Madagascar approximately 3 Ma, splitting from that of <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>, and later gave rise to <italic>D. sechellia</italic> on the Seychelles archipelago and to <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> on Mauritius nearly simultaneously, approximately 240 ka (<xref rid="evu198-B58" ref-type="bibr">Lachaise et al. 1986</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B5" ref-type="bibr">Ballard 2000a</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B53" ref-type="bibr">Kliman et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B24" ref-type="bibr">Dean and Ballard 2004</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B54" ref-type="bibr">Kopp et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B71" ref-type="bibr">McDermott and Kliman 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B35" ref-type="bibr">Garrigan et al. 2012</xref>). <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic> is an island endemic species, and <italic>D. simulans</italic>, despite having a recently established cosmopolitan distribution, has never been collected on Mauritius (<xref rid="evu198-B23" ref-type="bibr">David et al. 1989</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B61" ref-type="bibr">Legrand et al. 2011</xref>). Nevertheless, although <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> and <italic>D. simulans</italic> have had largely allopatric histories, there is evidence for limited interisland migration and natural hybridization. Multiple mitochondrial haplotypes have introgressed from <italic>D. simulans</italic> into <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> (<xref rid="evu198-B6" ref-type="bibr">Ballard 2000b</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B85" ref-type="bibr">Nunes et al. 2010</xref>), and evidence for interspecific introgression, probably from <italic>D. simulans</italic> into <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>, is scattered over all three major chromosomes (<xref rid="evu198-B35" ref-type="bibr">Garrigan et al. 2012</xref>). However, genomic introgressions between the <italic>D. simulans</italic> and <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> are underrepresented on the X chromosome (<xref rid="evu198-B35" ref-type="bibr">Garrigan et al. 2012</xref>), suggesting that X-linked chromosomal segments are less exchangeable between species than those on the autosomes.</p><p>The paucity of interspecific introgressions on the X chromosome may be attributable to selection against hybrid incompatibilities that cause intrinsic postzygotic isolation. Crosses between <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> and its two sister species follow Haldane&#x02019;s rule: all crosses yield sterile F<sub>1</sub> hybrid (XY) males but fertile F<sub>1</sub> hybrid (XX) females. Genetic analyses involving <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> show that the X chromosome has a disproportionately large effect on hybrid male sterility (HMS; <xref rid="evu198-B16" ref-type="bibr">Coyne 1985</xref>, <xref rid="evu198-B17" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B18" ref-type="bibr">Coyne and Charlesworth 1989</xref>). This so-called large X-effect has two proximate causes: recessive HMS factors on the X chromosome are fully expressed in hemizygous hybrid males (<xref rid="evu198-B110" ref-type="bibr">Turelli and Orr 1995</xref>, <xref rid="evu198-B111" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>); and between <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> and its siblings species, the density of HMS factors on the X chromosome is 2&#x02013;4 times greater than on the autosomes (<xref rid="evu198-B108" ref-type="bibr">True, Weir, et al. 1996</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B102" ref-type="bibr">Tao et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B69" ref-type="bibr">Masly and Presgraves 2007</xref>). The large X-effect holds across a range of taxa, including other <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref rid="evu198-B78" ref-type="bibr">Moehring et al. 2006</xref>), mammals (<xref rid="evu198-B36" ref-type="bibr">Good et al. 2008</xref>), fish (<xref rid="evu198-B52" ref-type="bibr">Kitano et al. 2009</xref>), butterflies (<xref rid="evu198-B79" ref-type="bibr">Naisbit et al. 2002</xref>), and birds (<xref rid="evu198-B94" ref-type="bibr">Saetre et al. 2001</xref>). Determining the evolutionary cause(s) of the large X-effect is thus one of the major unsolved problems of speciation genetics (<xref rid="evu198-B13" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth et al. 1987</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B19" ref-type="bibr">Coyne and Orr 1989</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B17" ref-type="bibr">Coyne 1992</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B91" ref-type="bibr">Presgraves 2008b</xref>). There are three leading candidate explanations. First, X&#x02013;autosome differences in transcriptional regulation exist in the male germline that may be especially prone to disruption by hybrid incompatibilities (<xref rid="evu198-B64" ref-type="bibr">Lifschytz and Lindsley 1971</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B113" ref-type="bibr">Wu and Davis 1993</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B38" ref-type="bibr">Hense et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B74" ref-type="bibr">Meiklejohn et al. 2011</xref>). Second, the X chromosome is susceptible to the invasion and spread of selfish genetic elements that may, as incidental byproducts, contribute to sterility in species hybrids (<xref rid="evu198-B32" ref-type="bibr">Frank 1991</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B44" ref-type="bibr">Hurst and Pomiankowski 1991</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B104" ref-type="bibr">Tao et al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B90" ref-type="bibr">Presgraves 2008a</xref>, <xref rid="evu198-B91" ref-type="bibr">2008b</xref>). Third, the X chromosome may experience a faster rate of adaptive evolution than the autosomes which could, in turn, contribute to the evolution of more X-linked hybrid incompatibilities (<xref rid="evu198-B13" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth et al. 1987</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B19" ref-type="bibr">Coyne and Orr 1989</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B91" ref-type="bibr">Presgraves 2008b</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B45" ref-type="bibr">Hvilsom et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B65" ref-type="bibr">Llopart 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B76" ref-type="bibr">Meisel et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B75" ref-type="bibr">Meisel and Connallon 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B55" ref-type="bibr">Kousathanas et al. 2014</xref>). These explanations are not mutually exclusive and, while evidence for each exists (<xref rid="evu198-B88" ref-type="bibr">Phadnis and Orr 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B12" ref-type="bibr">Campbell et al. 2013</xref>), their relative importance is still unknown.</p><p>To complement functional genetic analyses of speciation and the large X-effect, we have performed population genomics analyses of polymorphism and divergence for ten genomes sampled from <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>. Our analyses show that the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> X chromosome bears more signatures of recent, strong, and recurrent positive natural selection than the autosomes. Genes and gene regions with signatures of positive selection are enriched for functions in gametogenesis, chromosome biology, and satellite DNA, implying that genetic conflict over transmission contributes to molecular evolution in <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Fly Inbred Lines, Library Preparation, and Sequencing</title><p>We sampled nine wild-type isofemale lines of <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> (collected in 2006 and kindly donated by Maria Ramos&#x02013;Womack) and the inbred laboratory strain, <italic>mau12</italic> (14021-0241.60). Wild-type lines were subjected to single-pair sibling mating for a minimum of nine generations. Genomic DNA extraction and library preparation were performed for pooled females as previously described (<xref rid="evu198-B35" ref-type="bibr">Garrigan et al. 2012</xref>). However, additional sequences for the <italic>mau12</italic> line were collected from a large-insert, paired-end Nextera library (&#x0223c;3,000 bp) and a TrueSeq paired-end RNA library (&#x0223c;260 bp). For the large-insert library, we pooled females and purified genomic DNA from whole flies using the DNeasy Blood and Tissue kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA). DNA concentration was determined with the Qubit Flourometer (Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY) and quality was assessed using the Agilent Bioanalyzer (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA). Mate pair libraries were generated using the Nextera Mate Pair protocol (Illumina, San Diego, CA). Briefly, 4 &#x003bc;g of genomic DNA was fragmented per manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol followed by strand displacement, agarose gel size selection of 5-kb target size, and circularization. The 5-kb fragments were sheared using a Covaris S2 (Covaris Inc., Woburn, MA) to 300- to 1,000-bp size fragments for end repair, A-tailing, and indexed adaptor ligation. The amplified libraries were purified by AMPure (Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA) purification and hybridized to an Illumina paired-end flow cell for cluster amplification using the cBot (Illumina) at a concentration of 8 pmol per lane.</p><p>For RNAseq, males and females were reared on standard cornmeal food at room temperature. 50% of males and 50% of females were allowed to freely mate for 3 days, the rest were maintained as virgins. Adults were aged 4&#x02013;5 days then flash frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;80 &#x000b0;C. Total RNA was isolated from whole tissue using the RNeasy Plus Kit (Qiagen) per manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations. RNA concentration was determined with the NanoDrop 1000 spectrophotometer (NanoDrop, Wilmington, DE) and RNA quality was assessed with the Agilent Bioanalyzer (Agilent). The TruSeq RNA Sample Preparation Kit V2 (Illumina) was used for next generation sequencing library construction per manufacturer&#x02019;s protocols. Briefly, polyA mRNA was purified from approximately 100 ng total RNA with oligo-dT magnetic beads and fragmented. First-strand cDNA synthesis was performed with random hexamer priming followed by second-strand cDNA synthesis. End repair and 3&#x02032; adenylation was performed on the double-stranded cDNA. Illumina-indexed adaptors were ligated to both ends of the cDNA, purified by gel electrophoresis, and amplified with polymerase chain reaction primers specific to the adaptor sequences to generate amplicons of approximately 200&#x02013;500 bp in size. The amplified libraries were purified by AMPure (Beckman Coulter) purification and hybridized to an Illumina paired end flow cell for cluster amplification using the cBot (Illumina) at a concentration of 8 pmol per lane.</p><p>Each of the three additional <italic>mau12</italic> libraries (large-insert, male RNAseq, and female RNAseq) were bar-coded and multiplexed on the equivalent of one-half of a single flow cell. Paired-end (2&#x000d7;100 bp) sequencing was performed per manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations. The raw data were demultiplexed using configurebcl2fastq.pl version 1.8.3. Low complexity reads and vector contamination were removed using sequence cleaner (seqclean) and the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) univec database, respectively. The FASTX toolkit (fastq_quality_trimmer) was applied to remove bases with Phred quality scores below <italic>Q</italic> = 13 from the end of each read.</p></sec><sec><title>De Novo Genome Assembly</title><p>Both the short- and long-insert libraries were used for de novo assembly of the <italic>mau12</italic> genome. Raw sequence reads were first filtered by discarding reads with 1) more than 25% of bases called as ambiguous, 2) more than 40% of bases masked as low sequence complexity, and 3) containing either vector or adapter sequences. The ABYSS genome assembler software was then used to assemble reads from both libraries simultaneously (<xref rid="evu198-B95" ref-type="bibr">Simpson et al. 2009</xref>) with a <italic>k</italic>-mer size of 64 bp. Statistics describing the <italic>mau12</italic> de novo genome assembly can be found in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online.</p><p>The resulting contigs were ordered first by identifying contigs containing the flanking sequence from the <italic>P</italic> [<italic>lac-w</italic><sup>+</sup>]-element insertion sites (<xref rid="evu198-B2" ref-type="bibr">Araripe et al. 2006</xref>). A total of 69 contigs could be ordered using the <italic>P</italic>-element insertion sites, which represents nearly 39 Mb of sequence. Additional contigs were ordered by assuming synteny with <italic>D. simulans</italic>. The NUCMER program (<xref rid="evu198-B57" ref-type="bibr">Kurtz et al. 2004</xref>) was used to align all <italic>mau12</italic> contigs to the reference sequence for the <italic>D. simulans w</italic><sup>501</sup> strain (<xref rid="evu198-B43" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al. 2013</xref>). Contigs were then ordered by placing uniquely mapping contigs in the same order as the <italic>w</italic><sup>501</sup> genomic sequence with the highest sequence identity. There was no resulting conflict between placing contigs in this manner with the order inferred from the <italic>P</italic>-element insertion sites (data not shown). Finally, syntenic pseudochromosomes were constructed by inferring regions of overlap between adjacent contigs and filling gaps with IUPAC ambiguity characters, such that the total chromosome length of the <italic>mau12</italic> draft is the same as the <italic>w</italic><sup>501</sup> chromosomes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Finally, unincorporated contigs were blasted to the NCBI database. Unincorporated contigs with bacterial or viral homology were excluded, whereas those with homology to insects or those with no known homology were retained for further analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Short Read Alignment</title><p>The BWA-MEM alignment algorithm (<xref rid="evu198-B62" ref-type="bibr">Li 2013</xref>) was used to map sequence reads from each of the ten lines of <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> and two lines of <italic>D. simulans</italic>, the MD063 strain from Madagascar (<xref rid="evu198-B35" ref-type="bibr">Garrigan et al. 2012</xref>) and the <italic>w</italic><sup>501</sup> strain (<xref rid="evu198-B43" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al. 2013</xref>). Additionally, short reads from the <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> reference strain <italic>y; cn bw; sp</italic> were aligned to the <italic>mau12</italic> de novo draft genome (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online, for SRA accession numbers). Reads that did not properly pair in mapping or that had a Phred-scaled mapping score less than 30 were discarded. Additionally, to increase the accuracy of variant calling, all duplicate sequences were removed and reads were realigned around flanking indels using the SAMTOOLS software (<xref rid="evu198-B63" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. 2009</xref>). The total number of reads mapping to the <italic>mau12</italic> reference genome per library, after quality filtering, is provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online. Finally, the proportion of the <italic>mau12</italic> reference genome covered by the short read assembly and the median read depth across the major chromosome arms are given in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S4</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online.</p></sec><sec><title>Transcriptome Assembly and Annotation of Genome Features</title><p>To characterize the transcriptome of <italic>mau12</italic>, we separately mapped reads from paired-end RNA libraries of males and females to the <italic>mau12</italic> syntenic pseudochromosomes using BOWTIE2 (<xref rid="evu198-B60" ref-type="bibr">Langmead and Salzberg 2012</xref>). Transcripts were assembled using CUFFLINKS and the male and female GTF files were merged using CUFFMERGE (<xref rid="evu198-B107" ref-type="bibr">Trapnell et al. 2010</xref>). The largest open reading frame (ORF) was determined for each transcript using a custom Perl script, assuming canonical start and stop codons. A genome annotation file in GFF3 format (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sequenceontology.org/gff3.shtml">http://www.sequenceontology.org/gff3.shtml</ext-link>, last accessed September 12, 2014) was generated for the following fields using the GTF and ORF data for each transcript: exon, intron, coding sequences (CDS), 5&#x02032;-UTR, and 3&#x02032;-UTR.</p></sec><sec><title>Genome Scans of Polymorphism and Divergence</title><p>Divergence of the <italic>mau12</italic> assembly with the reference sequences of both <italic>D. simulans w</italic><sup>501</sup> and <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> was measured as a Hamming distance in 10-kb sliding windows along whole-chromosome alignments created with the MAUVE software (<xref rid="evu198-B22" ref-type="bibr">Darling et al. 2010</xref>). Only windows with greater than 10% of the total number of sites being aligned were considered for analysis. Polymorphism among the ten lines of <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> was summarized by measuring unbiased nucleotide diversity (<italic>&#x003c0;</italic>). Estimates of <italic>&#x003c0;</italic> in each 10-kb window were corrected for unequal sample sizes by multiplying by a factor of <italic>n</italic>/(<italic>n</italic> &#x02212; 1) (<xref rid="evu198-B81" ref-type="bibr">Nei 1987</xref>). Similarly, in each window, Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic> statistic was calculated as a measure of the site frequency spectrum (SFS) (<xref rid="evu198-B100" ref-type="bibr">Tajima 1989</xref>). Because the ten lines of <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> were inbred for at least nine generations, we also measured linkage disequilibrium in 10-kb windows using the unweighted average pairwise <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> statistic <italic>Z<sub>nS</sub></italic> (<xref rid="evu198-B49" ref-type="bibr">Kelly 1997</xref>). Singleton polymorphic sites were excluded from the calculation of <italic>Z<sub>nS</sub></italic>. All analyses of polymorphism, the SFS, and linkage disequilibrium were performed using the POPBAM software with default quality filtering settings (<xref rid="evu198-B34" ref-type="bibr">Garrigan 2013</xref>). Finally, the calculation of <italic>&#x003c0;</italic>, Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic>, and <italic>Z<sub>nS</sub></italic> assumed haploid genotypes, thereby ignoring any residual heterozygosity that remains after inbreeding.</p></sec><sec><title>Polymorphism and Divergence Analysis of Sequence Classes</title><p>We analyzed polymorphism and divergence for the following sequence classes: CDS, 5&#x02032;-UTR, 3&#x02032;-UTR, intron, exon, bases 8&#x02013;30 of introns shorter than 70 bp (the median intron length in the <italic>mau12</italic> genome). We analyzed the longest transcript from each of the annotated genes, a total of 11,348 transcripts. From the BAM file described above we generated a VCF file (<xref rid="evu198-B21" ref-type="bibr">Danecek et al. 2011</xref>) using SAMTOOLS mpileup and BCFTOOLS view, removing reads with mapping quality less than 20 and without performing indel calling (<xref rid="evu198-B63" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. 2009</xref>). For estimates of <italic>&#x003c0;</italic>, we used VCFTOOLS (<xref rid="evu198-B21" ref-type="bibr">Danecek et al. 2011</xref>) to generate estimates of average pairwise distance using the &#x0201c;window-pi&#x0201d; function. The VCF file generated to calculate <italic>&#x003c0;</italic> contained only the ten <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> samples (the &#x0201c;-s&#x0201d; option in BCFTOOLS view). To calculate <italic>&#x003c0;</italic> for CDS and UTR sequences that spanned multiple fragments, we concatenated the VCF files and then renumbered the position field starting with position &#x0201c;1&#x0201d; through the total length of all concatenated fragments. To calculate all other summary statistics, we generated FASTA sequences from the VCF file using vcfutils.pl vcf2fq (part of the SAMTOOLS package) and the &#x0201c;seq&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;cutN&#x0201d; utilities of the &#x0201c;sequence tool kit&#x0201d; (SEQTK v1.0-r31, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/lh3/seqtk">https://github.com/lh3/seqtk</ext-link>, last accessed September 12, 2014). For CDS and UTR sequences that spanned multiple fragments, we concatenated FASTA sequences together into a single file and reverse complemented CDS as necessary. The average Jukes&#x02013;Cantor-corrected pairwise distance (<xref rid="evu198-B82" ref-type="bibr">Nei and Kumar 2000</xref>) between <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> and <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> was calculated from these FASTA alignments using a custom Perl script. In addition, we calculated average <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> (<xref rid="evu198-B115" ref-type="bibr">Yang and Nielsen 2000</xref>) and <italic>p</italic><sub>N</sub> and <italic>p</italic><sub>S</sub> using a custom Perl script calling CODEML (<xref rid="evu198-B114" ref-type="bibr">Yang 2007</xref>). Similar results were obtained using YN00, which is an approximate method for calculating <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> (<xref rid="evu198-B115" ref-type="bibr">Yang and Nielsen 2000</xref>).</p><p>McDonald&#x02013;Kreitman (MK) tests were used to test the neutral model of protein evolution (<xref rid="evu198-B72" ref-type="bibr">McDonald and Kreitman 1991</xref>) and estimate the proportion of adaptive amino acid substitutions (<xref rid="evu198-B99" ref-type="bibr">Smith and Eyre-Walker 2002</xref>). Two different variants of the MK test were performed: 1) A pooled, unpolarized MK test between <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> and <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>, and 2) a lineage-specific MK test to identify <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>-specific mutations where <italic>D. simulans w</italic><sup>501</sup> was used as the near-outgroup and <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> as a far-outgroup. Tests were performed with custom Perl scripts using the method of <xref rid="evu198-B9" ref-type="bibr">Begun et al. (2007)</xref>. The proportion of divergent sites driven by positive selection (&#x003b1;) was calculated from counts of polymorphic and fixed synonymous and nonsynonymous changes (<xref rid="evu198-B29" ref-type="bibr">Fay et al. 2002</xref>), after excluding singletons. A polarized and unpolarized statistic was estimated as described for MK tests. A separate measure, &#x003b1;*, was calculated using the short intron sequence class as our neutral standard. Again, we counted the total polymorphic sites and fixed differences, excluding singletons. Finally, 95% confidence intervals around &#x003b1; estimates were calculated by performing 1,000 bootstrap resampling replicates.</p></sec><sec><title>Tests for Recent Selective Sweeps</title><p>Recent selective sweeps are expected to generate aberrant SFS surrounding the targets of selection. We used the parametric test described by Nielsen and colleagues, implemented in the program SweepFinder (<xref rid="evu198-B83" ref-type="bibr">Nielsen et al. 2005</xref>), to suggest candidate regions experiencing recent selective sweeps by identifying genomic windows with an unusual SFS. We first used POPBAM to identify all variable sites in the alignment described above. We then focused our analyses on the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> lineage by filtering for sites where a derived state was present in at least one <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> sample, but absent in all samples from <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> and <italic>D. simulans</italic>. We calculated unfolded frequency spectra for 10-kb nonoverlapping windows and used those windows with at least 5,000 aligned sites as input for SweepFinder, which determines a maximum composite likelihood ratio for each window by contrasting the likelihood of a complete selective sweep at the location to the null hypothesis of no sweep using the observed SFS in a window and the chromosome-wide SFS. We calculated <italic>P</italic> values of the maximum composite likelihood ratios reported by SweepFinder using 9 degrees of freedom. Finally, contiguous tracts of windows were grouped into putative sweep regions using a simple hidden Markov model with two possible states, &#x0201c;sweep&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;nonsweep.&#x0201d; The emission probabilities are derived directly from the SweepFinder <italic>P</italic> values and the transition probabilities are derived from the product of the marginal frequencies of significant and nonsignificant SweepFinder windows.</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of Repetitive Sequence</title><p>The repeat content of each chromosome arm was analyzed with RepeatMasker (<xref rid="evu198-B98" ref-type="bibr">Smit et al. 2010</xref>). To analyze repeat-enriched regions of each chromosome, a dot plot was generated in Geneious (<xref rid="evu198-B47" ref-type="bibr">Kearse et al. 2012</xref>) and repeat blocks were identified by eye. Chromosome coordinates were estimated as the proportional distance along the dot plot axis. Our repeat analysis is based on the proportion of masked sequence, rather than the absolute length of masked sequence, and is robust to error in estimating these coordinates. In addition, we separately characterized the <italic>D. simulans</italic> 359-bp satellite, which was absent from the Repbase database used by RepeatMasker (<xref rid="evu198-B46" ref-type="bibr">Jurka et al. 2005</xref>). The 359-bp satellite sequences were ascertained by a BLAST search using the <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> canonical 359 satellite sequence (<xref rid="evu198-B42" ref-type="bibr">Hsieh and Brutlag 1979</xref>) against the <italic>D. simulans</italic> reference assembly (<xref rid="evu198-B43" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al. 2013</xref>); the sequence defined by coordinates X:1,218,055&#x02013;1,218,405 was used as the query in the BLAST against our <italic>mau12</italic> reference sequence.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>De Novo Genome Assembly and Annotation</title><p>Our de novo assembly of the reference <italic>D. mauritiana white</italic> (<italic>w</italic>; here after <italic>mau12</italic>) has a total length of more than 124 Mb. The longest of our 2,759 scaffolds is nearly 3 Mb (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). More than 50% of the assembly is contained in scaffolds &#x02265;542 kb. We assembled chromosome-level sequences for the five major arms, using between 59 and 151 scaffolds per arm. Each chromosome-level draft sequence is &#x02265;80% of the length of the corresponding <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> reference sequence. For the ten <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> lines, we obtained 72- to 130-fold sequence coverage spanning 98.8&#x02013;99.5% of the de novo <italic>mau12</italic> assembly (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S4</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). To annotate the de novo assembly, we generated more than 38 (28) million pairs of 100-bp RNAseq reads from the whole bodies of <italic>mau12</italic> females (males), after quality filtering. In total, 86% (80%) of reads from females (males) were mapped to the <italic>mau12</italic> pseudochromosome reference sequences using BOWTIE2. Despite the greater number of reads generated from females, CUFFLINKS predicts 15,890 transcripts (from 12,071 genes) in males, compared with 12,488 transcripts (from 9,762 genes) in females. Merging the transcript annotations of the sexes yields a total of 16,261 predicted transcripts from 11,356 genes. Note that the number of genes in the merged annotation is lower than the male annotation because overlapping or closely neighboring transcripts may be combined into a single gene model.</p></sec><sec><title>Genome Diversity and Divergence</title><p>We surveyed nucleotide polymorphism and divergence from <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> in 10-kb windows for ten <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> genomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F1">fig. 1</xref>). Compared with the autosomes, the X chromosome has significantly elevated divergence (<italic>d</italic><sub>X</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>A</sub> = 1.100), but reduced polymorphism (<italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>X</sub>/<italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>A</sub> = 0.649; <xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T1">table 1</xref>, Mann&#x02013;Whitney <italic>U</italic> tests, <italic>P</italic><sub>MWU</sub> &#x0003c; 2.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;16</sup>). These contrasting X/A ratios for polymorphism and divergence cannot be explained by a standard neutral model, assuming no selection, an equal breeding sex ratio, and constant effective population size (<italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub>), such that <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub>,<sub>X</sub>/<italic>N</italic><sub>e,A</sub> = &#x000be;. Furthermore, the observed <italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>X</sub>/<italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>A</sub> ratio of nucleotide diversity is difficult to reconcile with an extreme founder event (<xref rid="evu198-B89" ref-type="bibr">Pool and Nielsen 2008</xref>), for which there is no evidence in the recent history of <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>. The X/A ratios of polymorphism and divergence are however consistent with a model involving selection. First, under a model of nearly neutral evolution, slightly deleterious substitutions can accumulate faster on the X than on the autosomes. Assuming new mutations have scaled selection coefficients of <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>s</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="MM1"><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> &#x02212;3 (or weaker), and assuming <italic>N</italic><sub>e,X</sub>/<italic>N</italic><sub>e,A</sub>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="MM2"><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 0.65 (as observed), then the X chromosome is expected to experience a higher rate of substitution than the autosomes, regardless of dominance (<xref rid="evu198-B112" ref-type="bibr">Vicoso and Charlesworth 2009</xref>). Second, under a model of adaptive evolution, beneficial mutations can accumulate on the X more quickly than on the autosomes (<xref rid="evu198-B13" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth et al. 1987</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B112" ref-type="bibr">Vicoso and Charlesworth 2009</xref>). Assuming new beneficial mutations tend to be recessive, then the X/A ratios of polymorphism and divergence could be consistent with a model of recurrent hitchhiking in which selective sweeps on the X chromosome are more frequent, stronger, and/or more often involve new beneficial mutations rather than standing genetic variation (<xref rid="evu198-B10" ref-type="bibr">Begun and Whitley 2000</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B86" ref-type="bibr">Orr and Betancourt 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B11" ref-type="bibr">Betancourt et al. 2004</xref>).
<fig id="evu198-F1" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 1.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>Scans of population genetics statistics across the five major chromosomal arms of the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> genome. The four statistics were calculated in nonoverlapping 10-kb windows. Each column of plots represents scans from a single chromosome arm. The top row of plots (blue points) shows scans of nucleotide diversity (<italic>&#x003c0;</italic>). The second row of plots (red points) shows the distribution of a likelihood ratio test statistic that measures the deviation of the local allele frequency spectrum (LR). The third row of plots (grey points) shows the measure of linkage disequilibrium (<italic>Z<sub>nS</sub></italic>) across all arms. Finally, the bottom row of plots (green points) shows the scan of average sequence divergence between the ten <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> samples and a single <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> genome sequence.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evu198f1p"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="evu198-T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Nucleotide Diversity in <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic> (<italic>&#x003c0;</italic>), Divergence between <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> and <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (<italic>d</italic>, Jukes&#x02013;Cantor Corrected Average Pairwise Divergence), and Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic> (<italic>TD</italic>) for Different Functional Classes of Site</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence Class</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>X</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>A</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>X</sub>/<italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>A</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>d</italic><sub>X</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>d</italic><sub>A</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>d</italic><sub>X</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>A</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>TD</italic><sub>X</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>TD</italic><sub>A</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>TD</italic><sub>X</sub>/<italic>TD</italic><sub>A</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genome</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.649*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.100*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SI8-30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.567*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.979*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Synonymous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.757</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.065*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.040*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UTR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.603*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.026*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonsynonymous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.868*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.260*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="evu198-TF1"><p>N<sc>ote</sc>.&#x02014;The values given in the table are averages over all autosomal sites and all X-linked sites. The ratio of the X-linked value to that of the autosomal value is also provided. Asterisk indicates a significant departure from expectations based on selective neutrality and equal breeding sex ratio (Mann&#x02013;Whitney <italic>U</italic> test, <italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Heterogeneity in levels of polymorphism and divergence also exists within chromosome arms, in part due to local selective sweeps (see below), and in part due to the qualitatively different patterns of diversity and divergence in centromere- and telomere-proximal regions. Euchromatic regions that are centromere- and telomere-proximal have reduced rates of crossing over (<xref rid="evu198-B108" ref-type="bibr">True, Mercer, et al. 1996</xref>), reduced polymorphism, and elevated divergence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F1">fig. 1</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B9" ref-type="bibr">Begun et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B59" ref-type="bibr">Langley et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B67" ref-type="bibr">Mackay et al. 2012</xref>). These patterns imply that recurrent selective sweeps and/or background selection, and their consequent Hill&#x02013;Robertson effects, impact the genomic distribution of polymorphism and divergence in the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> genome, especially in regions with reduced rates of crossing over (<xref rid="evu198-B41" ref-type="bibr">Hill and Robertson 1966</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B30" ref-type="bibr">Felsenstein 1974</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B70" ref-type="bibr">Maynard-Smith and Haigh 1974</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B8" ref-type="bibr">Begun and Aquadro 1992</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B14" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth et al. 1993</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B40" ref-type="bibr">Hey and Kliman 2002</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B59" ref-type="bibr">Langley et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B67" ref-type="bibr">Mackay et al. 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Selective Constraint in the Genome</title><p>To characterize how natural selection has shaped sequence evolution in the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> genome, we compared divergence and polymorphism across five sequence classes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T1">table 1</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Synonymous sites show the highest divergence, followed by bases 8&#x02013;30 of short introns (i.e., introns shorter than the median intron length of 70 bp, hereafter SI8-30), suggesting that these are the two least constrained sequence classes. Within <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>, SI8&#x02013;30 sites have the highest per-site estimate of <italic>&#x003c0;</italic> and the least negative Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic>, a summary of the SFS (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T1">table 1</xref>). These findings suggest that SI8&#x02013;30 sites have experienced the least selective constraint within the recent history of the species (<xref rid="evu198-B87" ref-type="bibr">Parsch et al. 2010</xref>). Divergence, polymorphism, and Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic> at nonsynonymous sites are lower than those at synonymous and SI8&#x02013;30 sites (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T1">table 1</xref>), consistent with strong functional constraints on protein-coding changes. Divergence, polymorphism, and Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic> at introns and UTRs are intermediate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T1">table 1</xref>), consistent with weaker functional constraints at these sites (<xref rid="evu198-B1" ref-type="bibr">Andolfatto 2005</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B9" ref-type="bibr">Begun et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B59" ref-type="bibr">Langley et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B67" ref-type="bibr">Mackay et al. 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Different Patterns of Molecular Evolution on the X Chromosome and Autosomes</title><p>Sequence divergence between <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> and <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> is higher on the X chromosome than on the autosomes for all sequence classes (<italic>P</italic><sub>MWU</sub> &#x02264; 0.023) but one: SI8&#x02013;30 site divergence on the X is significantly lower than on the autosomes (<italic>P</italic><sub>MWU</sub> = 0.0035; <xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T1">table 1</xref>). Assuming SI8&#x02013;30 sites are the least constrained class, the slower X evolution observed at these sites suggests either that these positions are weakly constrained, with more effective purifying selection on the X, or that the rate of mutation is lower on the X chromosome. Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic> at SI8&#x02013;30 sites is comparable between the X and autosomes (&#x02212;0.51 and &#x02212;0.55, respectively, <italic>P</italic><sub>MWU</sub> = 0.0783), giving no indication of a chromosome-wide difference in the efficacy of purifying selection. Instead, these findings are consistent with a male germline mutation rate that is 1.14-fold higher than that in the female germline (CI<sub>95</sub> = 0.91-1.42) (<xref rid="evu198-B77" ref-type="bibr">Miyata et al. 1987</xref>), as seen in some previous population and experimental genetic analyses in other <italic>Drosophila</italic> species (<xref rid="evu198-B3" ref-type="bibr">Bachtrog 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B48" ref-type="bibr">Keightley et al. 2009</xref>).</p><p>Several lines of evidence indicate more frequent positive selection on the X chromosome relative to the autosomes. First, assuming that SI8&#x02013;30 sites are indeed the least constrained class (<xref rid="evu198-B87" ref-type="bibr">Parsch et al. 2010</xref>), then the faster X evolution observed for all other sequence classes implies more frequent positive selection at these X-linked sites. Second, for all noncoding sequence classes, polymorphism on the X chromosome is significantly reduced relative to the autosomes (<italic>P</italic><sub>MWU</sub> &#x0003c; 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;16</sup>), even after accounting for the chromosome difference in effective size (<italic>N</italic><sub>x</sub>/<italic>N</italic><sub>A</sub> = &#x000be;). As the SFS is comparable between X and autosomes for each sequence class (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T1">table 1</xref>; the same holds for preferred, unpreferred, and neutral synonymous polymorphisms; not shown), the reduced sequence polymorphism on the X is not readily attributable to more effective purifying selection. A strong alternative is that the reduced diversity on the X reflects more frequent hitchhiking events caused by the fixation of new beneficial mutations (<xref rid="evu198-B10" ref-type="bibr">Begun and Whitley 2000</xref>). Taken together, the data support a model in which the X has a slightly lower mutation rate but nevertheless experiences a higher substitution rate at most functional sequence classes owing to a greater efficacy of positive natural selection (<xref rid="evu198-B13" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth et al. 1987</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B51" ref-type="bibr">Kirkpatrick and Hall 2004</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Adaptive Evolution of Protein-Coding Genes</title><p>We used MK tests (<xref rid="evu198-B72" ref-type="bibr">McDonald and Kreitman 1991</xref>) to evaluate the neutral mutation&#x02013;drift null hypothesis for more than 11,000 protein-coding genes. We performed unpolarized MK tests, with <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> as the outgroup species, and polarized MK tests, to characterize lineage-specific evolution in <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>, with <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> as the far-outgroup and <italic>D. simulans</italic> as an additional near-outgroup. The polarized MK tests thus involve polymorphisms and fixed differences accumulated only in the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> lineage. At the <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 level, 91 (417) genes have excess nonsynonymous substitutions for the polarized (unpolarized) MK tests, consistent with recurrent positive selection, whereas 26 (267) genes have excess nonsynonymous polymorphisms, consistent with segregating deleterious alleles or some forms of balancing selection. At the <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 level, 23 (144) genes have excess nonsynonymous substitutions for the polarized (unpolarized) MK tests, and 5 (89) have excess nonsynonymous polymorphisms. For the unpolarized MK tests, the X chromosome has a significant 1.6-fold excess of positively selected genes relative to autosomes at the <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 level using Fisher&#x02019;s exact test (<italic>P</italic><sub>FET</sub> = 0.020), but not at the <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 level (<italic>P</italic><sub>FET</sub> = 0.536). For the polarized tests, the X shows a 5.1- and 2.2-fold excess of positively selected genes on the X chromosome at the <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 and 0.05 levels (<italic>P</italic><sub>FET</sub> &#x02264; 0.001; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S5</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). The X and autosomes do not differ in the frequency of genes with excess nonsynonymous polymorphism (<italic>P</italic><sub>FET</sub> &#x02265; 0.550). For the unpolarized MK data, the estimate of the proportion of amino acid substitutions fixed by positive selection (&#x003b1;) is calculated using synonymous mutations as a neutral reference class, following <xref rid="evu198-B29" ref-type="bibr">Fay et al. (2002)</xref> and excluding singletons. The mean value of &#x003b1; for X-linked genes (0.240, CI<sub>95</sub> = 0.199&#x02013;0.282) is less than that for autosomal genes (0.359, CI<sub>95</sub> = 0.344&#x02013;0.373; <xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T2">table 2</xref>; but see below). For the polarized MK data, the opposite appears true: &#x003b1; for X-linked genes (0.362, CI<sub>95</sub> = 0.305&#x02013;0.418) is significantly greater than that for autosomal genes (0.211, CI<sub>95</sub> = 0.181&#x02013;0.240; <xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T3">table 3</xref>). These analyses show that X-linked genes are more likely to have individually significant histories of recurrent positive selection relative to autosomal genes and, at least for the polarized data, a greater fraction of nonsynonymous substitutions is beneficial on the X.
<table-wrap id="evu198-T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Mean and 95% Confidence Intervals for the Estimated Proportion of Nonsynonymous Fixations on the X Chromosome (&#x003b1;<sub>X</sub>) and Autosomes (&#x003b1;<sub>A</sub>) That Are Driven by Positive Selection, Assuming Synonymous Sites Are Selectively Neutral</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic><sub>X</sub><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic><sub>A</sub><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI<sub>95</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI<sub>95</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polarized</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.362</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.305&#x02013;0.418</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.211</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181&#x02013;0.240</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unpolarized</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.240</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199&#x02013;0.282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.344&#x02013;0.373</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="evu198-T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Mean and 95% Confidence Intervals for the Estimated Proportion of Fixations on the X Chromosome (&#x003b1;*<sub>X</sub>) and Autosomes (&#x003b1;*<sub>A</sub>) Driven by Positive Selection for a Variety of Sequence Classes, Assuming Short Introns Are Selectively Neutral</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;*</italic><sub>X</sub><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;*</italic><sub>A</sub><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI<sub>95</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI<sub>95</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Synonymous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.372</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.319 to 0.418</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.277</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.258 to 0.295</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonsynonymous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.583</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.541 to 0.572</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.559</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.546 to 0.370</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intron</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.203 to &#x02212;0.063</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.080 to &#x02212;0.030</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UTR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.187 to 0.282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.241</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.221 to 0.259</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>We tested for Gene Ontology (GO) category enrichment among genes having histories of recurrent adaptive protein evolution (<xref rid="evu198-B27" ref-type="bibr">Eden et al. 2009</xref>). Over the long <italic>D. mauritiana</italic><italic>&#x02013;</italic><italic>D. melanogaster</italic> history of divergence (unpolarized MK data), the top genes function in reproduction, the nuclear pore complex (including the hybrid incompatibility gene, <italic>Nup160</italic>; <xref rid="evu198-B101" ref-type="bibr">Tang and Presgraves 2009</xref>), and the regulation of satellite DNA (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S6</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). While not detected by formal GO analyses, we noted that 6/14 genes with roles in kinetochore function show evidence of recurrent positive selection, consistent with models of genetic conflict over centromeric drive (<xref rid="evu198-B37" ref-type="bibr">Henikoff et al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B68" ref-type="bibr">Malik and Henikoff 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B92" ref-type="bibr">Przewloka et al. 2007</xref>). During the recent history of the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> lineage (polarized MK data), the top genes function in the female germline (e.g., female germ-line cyst formation), mRNA catabolism (e.g., nuclear-transcribed mRNA catabolic process, nonsense-mediated decay), chromosome biology, and the regulation of satellite DNAs (e.g., <italic>dodeca-satellite-binding protein</italic> and <italic>topoisomerase</italic> 2; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S7</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online).</p><p>We also estimated the proportion of substitutions attributable to positive selection using SI8&#x02013;30 sites as a putatively neutral reference class (hereafter, &#x003b1;*), instead of synonymous sites (&#x003b1;), for the unpolarized data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T3">table 3</xref>). On the X chromosome, nonsynonymous (0.583, CI<sub>95</sub> = 0.541&#x02013;0.619), synonymous (0.372, CI<sub>95</sub> = 0.319&#x02013;0.418), and UTR substitutions (0.236, CI<sub>95</sub> = 0.187&#x02013;0.282) all show evidence for substantial adaptive evolution, whereas intronic sequences do not (&#x02212;0.132, CI<sub>95</sub> = &#x02212;0.203 to &#x02212;0.063). Similarly, on the autosomes, nonsynonymous substitutions have the highest &#x003b1;* (0.559, CI<sub>95</sub> = 0.546&#x02013;0.572), followed by synonymous (0.277, CI<sub>95</sub> = 0.258&#x02013;0.295) and UTR (0.241, CI<sub>95</sub> = 0.221&#x02013;0.259) substitutions, whereas intronic substitutions show no evidence for adaptive evolution ( &#x02212; 0.055, CI<sub>95</sub> = &#x02212;0.080 to &#x02212;0.030). These analyses provide evidence for adaptive evolution at UTR sequences (<xref rid="evu198-B1" ref-type="bibr">Andolfatto 2005</xref>) and, surprisingly, at synonymous sites. The latter finding has three implications. First, if true, then &#x003b1; for unpolarized nonsynonymous substitutions (&#x003b1; = 0.240 and 0.359 for X and autosomes, respectively; see above) are likely to be underestimates (&#x003b1;* = 0.583 and 0.559 for X and autosomes, respectively). Second, the X and the autosomes show comparable &#x003b1;* estimates among all sequence classes except synonymous substitutions, for which &#x003b1;* is significantly higher on the X (0.372 vs. 0.277). This finding helps to explain why &#x003b1; for nonsynonymous substitutions on the X appeared lower than on the autosomes in the unpolarized MK data (see above). Third, the higher &#x003b1;* for synonymous sites on the X chromosome implies a greater efficacy of weak positive selection than on the autosomes. However, as X-linked UTRs do not show an elevated &#x003b1;* relative to autosomes, the elevated &#x003b1;* at X-linked synonymous sites would seem to be attributable to the biology of biased codon usage rather than a generally greater efficacy of selection on the X. Interestingly, X-linked genes maintain higher codon usage bias for preferred synonymous codons in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref rid="evu198-B96" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al. 2005</xref>, <xref rid="evu198-B97" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). The present results suggest that synonymous sites genome-wide may be adapting to new or shifting optimal codon preferences (<xref rid="evu198-B15" ref-type="bibr">Comeron and Kreitman 2002</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B26" ref-type="bibr">DuMont et al. 2004</xref>). We cannot, however, exclude the possibility that the signal of adaptive evolution (or, part of it) results from a historical change in effective population size or functional constraints (<xref rid="evu198-B28" ref-type="bibr">Eyre-Walker 2002</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Recent Selective Sweeps</title><p>The SweepFinder analyses of 10,576 ten-kilobase windows from ten <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> strains identify 152 windows (1.4%) with significantly aberrant SFS relative to their chromosomal background at the <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F1">fig. 1</xref>). Significant windows are overrepresented on the X chromosome (61) relative to the autosomes (91; &#x003c7;<sup>2 </sup>= 54.68, df = 1, <italic>P</italic> = 1.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;13</sup>). To characterize the distribution of polymorphism in these anomalous regions, we compared summaries of polymorphism (<italic>&#x003c0;</italic>), linkage disequilibrium (<italic>Z<sub>nS</sub></italic>), and the SFS (using Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic>) in the 152 aberrant windows with randomly selected windows using a simple randomization test. We performed 1,000 replicates randomly selecting 152 windows without replacement, divided among chromosome arms to match the distribution of aberrant windows. Anomalous windows have significantly lower <italic>&#x003c0;</italic> and significantly higher <italic>Z<sub>nS</sub></italic> (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Although Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic> is not different, the variance in Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic> is significantly larger among anomalous windows (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary tables S8&#x02013;S11</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). For inferred sweep regions that are &#x02265;20 kb, eight large sweeps have affected approximately 4.1% of the total map length of chromosome <italic>X</italic>; four large sweeps affect approximately 1.7% of the length of chromosome <italic>2L</italic>, four affect 0.8% of <italic>2R</italic>, five affect 0.4% of <italic>3L</italic>, and no sweeps &#x02265;20 kb are detected on chromosome <italic>3R</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T4">table 4</xref>). Finally, the presence of these putative sweeps alone cannot account for the reduced <italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>X</sub>/<italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>A</sub> ratio (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T1">table 1</xref>); when all putative sweep regions on the X are excluded, <italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>X</sub>/<italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>A</sub> = 0.655 for the remaining X-linked sites.
<table-wrap id="evu198-T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Recently Swept Regions of the <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic> Genome That Are Larger Than 20 kb</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coordinates</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length (kb)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">cM</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2L</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,445,000&#x02013;1,468,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2L</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,687,000&#x02013;20,943,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.405</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2L</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,406,000&#x02013;22,635,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">229</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.362</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2L</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,837,000&#x02013;23,030,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.305</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2R</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,390,000&#x02013;1,576,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.294</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2R</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,704,000&#x02013;1,760,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2R</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,064,000&#x02013;3,087,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2R</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,774,000&#x02013;8,798,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.119</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3L</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,000&#x02013;128,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.399</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3L</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,379,000&#x02013;22,493,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3L</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,687,000&#x02013;22,879,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3L</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,184,000&#x02013;23,313,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3L</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,562,000&#x02013;23,610,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3L</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,712,000&#x02013;23,751,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>X</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41,000&#x02013;120,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>X</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">436,000&#x02013;457,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>X</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,127,000&#x02013;7,160,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.220</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>X</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,500,000&#x02013;9,050,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">550</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.008</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>X</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,351,000&#x02013;9,375,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>X</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,629,000&#x02013;14,661,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>X</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,134,000&#x02013;16,274,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.108</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>X</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,996,000&#x02013;20,227,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.679</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="evu198-TF3"><p>N<sc>ote</sc>.&#x02014;The sweep coordinates given are from the <italic>mau12</italic> genome assembly. The estimated size of the putative sweep region is provided in physical distance (kb) and centimorgans (<xref rid="evu198-B108" ref-type="bibr">True, Mercer, et al. 1996</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>The majority of putative selective sweeps on the autosomes occur in low-recombination centromere-proximal regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F1">fig. 1</xref>). However, several of the putative selective sweeps on the X chromosome affect unusually large physical and recombination distances in the middle of the chromosome (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T4">table 4</xref>). The largest putative selective sweep occurs between positions X:8,500,000&#x02013;9,050,000 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F2">fig. 2</xref>). Interestingly, this 3-cM sweep region is enriched for satellite DNAs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F2">figs. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F4">4</xref> and see the following subsection) and spans the locations of the Winters <italic>sex-ratio</italic> genes, <italic>MDox</italic> and <italic>Dox</italic>, which have been shown to be part of a cryptic male meiotic drive system in <italic>D. simulans</italic> (<xref rid="evu198-B103" ref-type="bibr">Tao et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B50" ref-type="bibr">Kingan et al. 2010</xref>). To assess the potential contribution of the Winters <italic>sex-ratio</italic> genes to this selective sweep, we assayed the presence of both <italic>Dox</italic> and <italic>MDox</italic> in 26 <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> strains, including six strains used for whole-genome sequencing (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary methods,</ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). We find that <italic>Dox</italic> is present in only 23% (6/26) of these strains (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S2</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online) and therefore could not have caused the large selective sweep. (The reference strain, <italic>mau12</italic>, lacks the <italic>Dox</italic> gene.) <italic>MDox</italic>, however, appears fixed in <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> (26/26; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary fig. S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Thus, <italic>MDox</italic> remains a potential cause of the selective sweep.
<fig id="evu198-F2" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 2.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>Nucleotide diversity (<italic>&#x003c0;</italic>) across a large selective sweep on the X chromosome of <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>. The red rectangle in the inset above the graph delimits the region of reduced polymorphism on the X chromosome. Unfilled circles plot nucleotide diversity in 1-kb windows between positions X: 8,500,000&#x02013;9,050,000. The red bars below the physical position of 1-kb windows represent the scaffolds constituting this region in the de novo assembly. Below the scaffolds are blue triangles that depict the gene models for a representative group of genes in the putative sweep regions (the names are from the homologous annotations in the <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> genome). The yellow squares mark the positions of 359-like satellite DNAs. Below the gene models are orange-filled triangles that show the positions of the markers used by <xref rid="evu198-B108" ref-type="bibr">True, Mercer, et al. (1996)</xref> and the observed intervening recombination distances. Finally, the green triangles give the locations of the two Winters <italic>sex-ratio</italic> meiotic drive genes in the <italic>D. simulans</italic> genome.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evu198f2p"/></fig></p><p>A second large sweep in a high-recombination region occurs sweep between positions 16,134,000 and 16,274,000 on the X chromosome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F1">fig. 1</xref>). For this putative sweep, we estimate the population-scaled selection intensity (<italic>&#x003b3;</italic> = 2<italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub><italic>s</italic>). We assume that nucleotide diversity before the sweep was <italic>&#x003c0;</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.0082 (the average for the X chromosome) and that the local per-base crossing over rate is 7.91 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup> (<xref rid="evu198-B108" ref-type="bibr">True, Mercer, et al. 1996</xref>). We then predict nucleotide diversity at recombination distance <italic>c</italic>, using the equation
<disp-formula id="evu198-M1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="MM3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p>(<xref rid="evu198-B7" ref-type="bibr">Barton 2000</xref>). We fit the model to the data using a simple least-squares approach. The best-fitting model occurs when <italic>&#x003b3;</italic> = 7.05 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F3">fig. 3</xref>). In this candidate sweep region, there is a 20-kb stretch of near-complete homozygosity in <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>. From our RNAseq data, we have annotated four genes in this 20-kb region and identified their homologs in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>: <italic>wupA</italic>, <italic>CG32553</italic>, <italic>CG43133</italic>, and <italic>ari-1</italic>. Of these four genes, only <italic>CG32553</italic> and <italic>CG43133</italic> have nonsynonymous substitutions exclusively in the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> sample (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S12</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Neither <italic>CG32553</italic> nor <italic>CG43133</italic> has any known function or phenotype in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> and their products do not possess homology with any known proteins or conserved domains, although, in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>, <italic>CG32533</italic> is expressed exclusively in the eye and <italic>CG43133</italic> in the eye-antennal disc. <xref rid="evu198-B84" ref-type="bibr">Nolte et al. (2013)</xref> raised the possibility that the HMS locus <italic>Odysseus</italic> (<italic>OdsH</italic>) is located within this sweep region; however, in our assembly, <italic>OdsH</italic> maps to a distal region 200 kb away.
<fig id="evu198-F3" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 3.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>A canonical selective sweep on the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> X chromosome spans more than 140 kb. The red rectangle in the inset above the graph delimits the region of reduced polymorphism on the X chromosome. Unfilled circles plot nucleotide diversity (<italic>&#x003c0;</italic>) in 1-kb windows and the red line plots the expected <italic>&#x003c0;</italic> under a simple hard sweep model (see text). The red bars below the physical position of the 1-kb windows represent the scaffolds in the de novo assembly. Below the scaffolds are blue triangles showing the gene models. A 20-kb region of near-complete homozygosity contains four genes: <italic>wupA</italic>, <italic>CG32553</italic>, <italic>CG43133</italic>, and <italic>ari-1</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evu198f3p"/></fig></p><p>Finally, there is another large putative selective sweep on chromosome X:7,127,000&#x02013;7,160,000 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T4">table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F1">fig. 1</xref>). In this 33-kb region, there is again a 20-kb interval of nearly complete homozygosity among the ten <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> strains. The RNAseq data indicate that six transcripts map to this 20-kb interval (data not shown), each with a homolog in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>: <italic>Hira</italic>, <italic>NELF-B</italic>, <italic>CG12155</italic>, <italic>Pdp</italic>, <italic>Rab39</italic>, and <italic>Tom40</italic>. Interestingly, expression of the <italic>Hira</italic> gene is known to be associated with <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-induced cytoplasmic incompatibility in male <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> (<xref rid="evu198-B116" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al. 2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Genomic Distribution of Repetitive DNAs</title><p>We characterized the genomic distribution of five classes of repetitive DNA in the de novo assembly of the reference strain <italic>mau12</italic>: long terminal repeat (LTR) and non-LTR retrotransposons, DNA transposons, satellite DNAs, and microsatellites. These analyses disproportionately survey the euchromatic portions of the genome, because heterochromatic regions can be underrepresented in the assembly. We find that the densities of all classes of repetitive DNA are significantly heterogeneous among chromosome arms (&#x003c7;<sup>2 </sup>= 72.30, df = 3, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S13</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Curiously, DNA transposons and both classes of retroelements are underrepresented on chromosome arm <italic>3R</italic> and overrepresented on <italic>2R</italic>. The other classes of repetitive DNAs are all overrepresented exclusively on the X chromosome; Although significant heterogeneity does exist among autosomal arms, all four arms show a dearth of repetitive DNAs relative to the X. The X chromosome has an approximately 1.4-fold excess of microsatellites (0.035% of the sequence) and low complexity (0.005%) repeats relative to the autosomes (0.02% and 0.003%, respectively; see also <xref rid="evu198-B4" ref-type="bibr">Bachtrog et al. 1999</xref>). And, strikingly, the X chromosome has a 7.5-fold excess of satellite DNA (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>; 0.5%) relative to the autosomes (0.04%; see also <xref rid="evu198-B33" ref-type="bibr">Gallach 2014</xref>). Although satellite DNAs are typically organized as large blocks in pericentric heterochromatin, those detected here correspond to satellite DNA islands in the euchromatin (<xref rid="evu198-B56" ref-type="bibr">Kuhn et al. 2012</xref>). As satellite DNAs are repetitive and organized into arrays longer than can be spanned by short-read sequences, our analyses probably detect only the edges of satellite DNA islands and thus underestimate the total amount of satellite DNA.</p><p>Dot plots highlight the heterogeneity in repetitive DNA densities along chromosome arms, as well as the qualitative difference in repetitive DNA densities between the X and autosomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F4">fig. 4</xref>). On chromosome arm <italic>2R</italic>, the pericentromeric proximal region is enriched for LTR retroelements, non-LTR retroelements, and DNA transposons. On the X, there are large megabase-scale regions in the middle of the chromosome arm with high densities of satellite DNAs, microsatellites, and low complexity sequences. The two most conspicuous concentrations of repetitive DNAs occur between coordinates X:8,235,022&#x02013;9,591,378 (block X.1) and X:11625913&#x02013;12594739 (block X.2). The coordinates of the first region coincide with those of the distal large 550-kb sweep region on the X (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F2">fig. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T4">table 4</xref>). Slightly more than half of the satellite DNA occurring in this region have homology with the 359-bp satellite (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">supplementary table S14</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link> online). Although there is evidence that the <italic>sex-ratio</italic> meiotic drive genes are not involved in this large selective sweep, the possibility remains that selfish satellite DNAs may play a role in eliminating variation over this large genomic region.
<fig id="evu198-F4" position="float"><label>F<sc>ig</sc>. 4.&#x02014;</label><caption><p>Repeat content differs on the X and autosomes. In the top row, dot plots of the X chromosome and a representative autosomal arm (<italic>2R</italic>) show an enrichment of repetitive sequence on the X, which is organized into blocks of high repeat density. The bottom left panel shows the Percent repetitive sequence for the X chromosome compared with the average across the major autosomal arms. Finally, the bottom right panel shows the proportion of the different repeat classes in the highlighted repeat blocks on chromosomes <italic>X</italic> and <italic>2R</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evu198f4p"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our survey of diversity and divergence from ten high-quality <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> genomes shows that the X chromosome bears more signatures of recent and recurrent positive natural selection than do the autosomes. The observed low X/A ratio of diversity cannot be easily explained by a recent population bottleneck (cf. <xref rid="evu198-B89" ref-type="bibr">Pool and Nielsen 2008</xref>). Our genome-wide analyses confirm that <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> harbors a surprisingly high level of nucleotide diversity for an island endemic species. Furthermore, the genome-wide SFS shows a mild excess of low frequency polymorphisms, a pattern that is more consistent with weak population expansion and/or functional constraints. In our data, there is no clear evidence for a recent recovery from a severe population bottleneck (see also <xref rid="evu198-B53" ref-type="bibr">Kliman et al. 2000</xref>). Instead, despite having what must be a smaller census population size than, say, the cosmopolitan species <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>, <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> maintains more diversity overall and, hence, a relatively large effective population size. Finally, the low X/A ratio of diversity cannot be attributed to greater functional constraints on the X, because the SFS is comparable between the X and the autosomes for all sequence classes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T1">table 1</xref>), and the X shows higher divergence from <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> than do the autosomes. The disparity between X/A diversity versus divergence thus implies that positive natural selection acts more frequently on the X chromosome than the autosomes.</p><p>Our genome-wide scan for anomalous SFS confirms that the X chromosome of <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> has experienced more recent selective sweeps than have the autosomes. In general, these X chromosome sweeps are larger and produce more aberrant SFS than those on the autosomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evu198-F1">fig. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T4">table 4</xref>). The excess of recent sweeps on the X cannot be attributed to adaptation from standing genetic variation, which causes difficult-to-detect &#x0201c;soft&#x0201d; sweeps (<xref rid="evu198-B39" ref-type="bibr">Hermisson and Pennings 2005</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B105" ref-type="bibr">Teshima et al. 2006</xref>), and is expected to progress more slowly on the X chromosome than the autosomes (<xref rid="evu198-B86" ref-type="bibr">Orr and Betancourt 2001</xref>). Instead, these findings suggest that the X has experienced more classic &#x0201c;hard&#x0201d; selective sweeps resulting from new beneficial mutations. A higher rate of adaptive evolution on the X is expected when new beneficial mutations are, on average, at least partially recessive (<xref rid="evu198-B13" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth et al. 1987</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B112" ref-type="bibr">Vicoso and Charlesworth 2009</xref>). This faster X model of adaptive molecular evolution may explain some of the excess divergence (<xref rid="evu198-B13" ref-type="bibr">Charlesworth et al. 1987</xref>) and reduced diversity on the X chromosome (<xref rid="evu198-B11" ref-type="bibr">Betancourt et al. 2004</xref>).</p><p>The relative abundance of hitchhiking effects on the X chromosome may be attributable to selfish genetic elements. Sex chromosomes are susceptible to the invasion and spread of multilocus meiotic drive elements (<xref rid="evu198-B44" ref-type="bibr">Hurst and Pomiankowski 1991</xref>), and these can cause patterns indistinguishable from classic selective sweeps (e.g., <xref rid="evu198-B25" ref-type="bibr">Derome et al. 2008</xref>). The distal 3-cM sweep valley on the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> chromosome <italic>X</italic> spans the <italic>MDox</italic> locus, which may be the original distorter element of the Winters <italic>sex-ratio</italic> system (<xref rid="evu198-B103" ref-type="bibr">Tao et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B50" ref-type="bibr">Kingan et al. 2010</xref>). Although additional data clearly show that the <italic>Dox</italic> locus cannot be the target of selection in this case, the progenitor <italic>MDox</italic> locus remains a viable explanation for this sweep. However, this large distal sweep also spans a particularly high density of 359-like satellite DNAs, which may also spread by manipulating transmission (<xref rid="evu198-B31" ref-type="bibr">Ferree and Prasad 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B33" ref-type="bibr">Gallach 2014</xref>). In primates, selective sweep regions on the X chromosome are also enriched for ampliconic genes (<xref rid="evu198-B80" ref-type="bibr">Nam et al. 2014</xref>), which may similarly be involved in conflict over transmission. Finally, our genome-wide MK analyses show that genes with individually significant evidence for recurrent adaptive protein evolution are overrepresented on the X chromosome and, separately, tend to be enriched for functions in reproductive biology and/or chromosome biology, suggestive of frequent genetic conflict (e.g., satellite DNA-binding proteins, nuclear pore proteins, kinetochore proteins).</p><p>Ours is the second population genomics analysis of <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>. The first used a &#x0201c;Pool-seq&#x0201d; strategy, sequencing 107 isofemale lines pooled to approximately 110-fold depth overall (<xref rid="evu198-B84" ref-type="bibr">Nolte et al. 2013</xref>). This shallow coverage of a deep sample is complementary to our deep coverage of a phased, shallow sample. Indeed, we detect the same faster X divergence, the same prominent selective sweeps on the X chromosome, and comparable sets of genes as targets of past recurrent adaptation. There are however large differences in our estimates of basic summary statistics. Despite a smaller sample, our estimates of <italic>&#x003c0;</italic> are 36% and 44% higher for the X and the autosomes, respectively. Conversely, our estimates of Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic> are 3.7- and 5.2-fold smaller than those of <xref rid="evu198-B84" ref-type="bibr">Nolte et al. (2013)</xref> for the X and the autosomes, respectively (e.g., Tajima&#x02019;s <italic>D</italic> = &#x02212;1.79 vs. &#x02212;0.33 for the autosomes; <xref ref-type="table" rid="evu198-T1">table 1</xref>). As noted by Nolte et al., the Pool-seq approach is biased toward an excess of rare variants, as sequencing errors are not readily distinguishable. Similarly, <xref rid="evu198-B66" ref-type="bibr">Lynch et al. (2014)</xref> estimated that the sequencing depth for Pool-seq must be 5-10&#x000d7; the sample size to infer low frequency alleles accurately. These comparisons suggest that Pool-seq can be useful for estimating net divergence and characterizing gross patterns of polymorphism, but not for the high-quality single nucleotide polymorphism calling necessary for accurate parameter estimation (<xref rid="evu198-B20" ref-type="bibr">Cutler and Jensen 2010</xref>).</p><p>The availability of population genomic data in <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> has two impacts on speciation genetics. First, for the past decade, evidence for faster X evolution in <italic>Drosophila</italic> has been equivocal, making it a doubtful contributor to the large X-effect for HMS (<xref rid="evu198-B91" ref-type="bibr">Presgraves 2008b</xref>). However, the present analyses, and others (<xref rid="evu198-B9" ref-type="bibr">Begun et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B59" ref-type="bibr">Langley et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B65" ref-type="bibr">Llopart 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B67" ref-type="bibr">Mackay et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B76" ref-type="bibr">Meisel et al. 2012</xref>), firmly establish the fact of faster X evolution, although its biological basis remains to be determined (<xref rid="evu198-B75" ref-type="bibr">Meisel and Connallon 2013</xref>). Our analyses, and others&#x02019; (<xref rid="evu198-B9" ref-type="bibr">Begun et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B84" ref-type="bibr">Nolte et al. 2013</xref>), are also consistent with the notion that genetic conflict is a major driver of molecular evolution, especially on the X chromosome (<xref rid="evu198-B32" ref-type="bibr">Frank 1991</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B44" ref-type="bibr">Hurst and Pomiankowski 1991</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B73" ref-type="bibr">Meiklejohn and Tao 2010</xref>). Second, the discovery that the <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> allele of <italic>Odysseus</italic> causes male sterility in a <italic>D. simulans</italic> genetic background (<xref rid="evu198-B106" ref-type="bibr">Ting et al. 1998</xref>) was a major step toward understanding the molecular biology of HMS. But identifying a panel of X-linked HMS factors is necessary to draw broad conclusions about the molecular basis of the large X-effect. Population genomics resources in <italic>D. mauritiana</italic> and <italic>D. simulans</italic> (<xref rid="evu198-B9" ref-type="bibr">Begun et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evu198-B93" ref-type="bibr">Rogers et al. 2014</xref>) will empower genetic mapping efforts and accelerate identification of more genes involved in HMS and other species differences.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">Supplementary methods</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">figures S1&#x02013;S3</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbe.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/gbe/evu198/-/DC1">tables S1&#x02013;S16</ext-link> are available at <italic>Genome Biology and Evolution</italic> online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/">http://www.gbe.oxfordjournals.org/</ext-link>).</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Data</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_6_9_2444__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_evu198_Supplementary_Material.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank Amanda Larracuente for discussion and comments. This work was made possible by a <funding-source>National Institutes of Health grant</funding-source>
<award-id>R01-ODO1054801</award-id> to D.G. and D.C.P.</p></ack><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="evu198-B1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andolfatto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive evolution of non-coding DNA in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>437</volume><fpage>1149</fpage><lpage>1152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16237443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Araripe</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckstrand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flanking regions of <italic>P</italic>-elements inserted in the 3rd chromosome of <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic></article-title><source>Dros Inf Serv.</source><year>2006</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>54</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bachtrog</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for male-driven evolution in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>619</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18234707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bachtrog</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zangerl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Brem</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlotterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of dinucleotide microsatellites in the <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> genome</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>602</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10335653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics of mitochondrial DNA in members of the <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> subgroup</article-title><source>J Mol Evol.</source><year>2000a</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10903372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>When one is not enough: introgression of mitochondrial DNA in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2000b</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1126</fpage><lpage>1130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10889226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic hitchhiking</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci.</source><year>2000</year><volume>355</volume><fpage>1553</fpage><lpage>1562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11127900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Begun</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquadro</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Levels of naturally occurring DNA polymorphism correlate with recombination rates in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1992</year><volume>356</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1560824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Begun</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Population genomics: whole-genome analysis of polymorphism and divergence in <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e310</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17988176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Begun</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced X-linked nucleotide polymorphism in <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>5960</fpage><lpage>5965</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10823947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Betancourt</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A pseudohitchhiking model of X vs. autosomal diversity</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2004</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>2261</fpage><lpage>2269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15611190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Good</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nachman</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meiotic sex chromosome inactivation is disrupted in sterile hybrid male house mice</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2013</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23307891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relative rates of evolution of sex chromosomes and autosomes</article-title><source>Am Nat.</source><year>1987</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>146</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of deleterious mutations on neutral molecular evolution</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1993</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>1289</fpage><lpage>1303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8375663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Comeron</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreitman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population, evolutionary and genomic consequences of interference selection</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2002</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12019253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genetic basis of Haldane&#x02019;s rule</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1985</year><volume>314</volume><fpage>736</fpage><lpage>738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3921852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics and speciation</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1992</year><volume>355</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1741030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of X-linked sterility in hybrids between three sibling species of <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Heredity</source><year>1989</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2732092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B19"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two rules of speciation</article-title><source>Speciation and its consequences</source><year>1989</year><publisher-loc>Sunderland (MA)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sinauer Associates</publisher-name><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>207</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>To pool, or not to pool?</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2010</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20855575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danecek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The variant call format and VCFtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2156</fpage><lpage>2158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Perna</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>progressiveMauve: multiple genome alignment with gene gain, loss and rearrangement</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e11147</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20593022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>McEvey</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Solignac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsacas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Drosophila</italic> communities on Mauritius and the ecological niche of <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic> (Diptera, Drosophilidae)</article-title><source>Rev Zool Afr.</source><year>1989</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>116</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>JWO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Linking phylogenetics with population genetics to reconstruct the geographic origin of a species</article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>998</fpage><lpage>1009</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15288072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derome</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Baudry</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogereau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Veuille</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Montchamp-Moreau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective sweeps in a two-locus model for <italic>sex-ratio</italic> meiotic drive in <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18071199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DuMont</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Calabrese</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquadro</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA variability and divergence at the <italic>notch</italic> locus in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> and <italic>D. simulans</italic>: a case of accelerated synonymous site divergence</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2004</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15166145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Navon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinfeld</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakhini</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GOrilla: a tool for discovery and visualization of enriched GO terms in ranked gene lists</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>48</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19192299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eyre-Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changing effective population size and the McDonald-Kreitman test</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2002</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>2017</fpage><lpage>2024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12524367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyckoff</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Testing the neutral theory of molecular evolution with genomic data from <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>415</volume><fpage>1024</fpage><lpage>1026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11875569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary advantage of recombination</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1974</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4448362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferree</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How can satellite DNA divergence cause reproductive isolation? Let us count the chromosomal ways</article-title><source>Genet Res Int.</source><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><fpage>430136</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22567387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haldane&#x02019;s rule&#x02014;a defense of the meiotic drive theory</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1991</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1714</fpage><lpage>1717</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrent turnover of chromosome-specific satellites in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1279</fpage><lpage>1286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24846631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrigan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>POPBAM: tools for evolutionary analysis of short read sequence alignments</article-title><source>Evol Bioinform.</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>353</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrigan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome sequencing reveals complex speciation in the <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> clade</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2012</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1499</fpage><lpage>1511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22534282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Good</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nachman</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A complex genetic basis to X-linked hybrid male sterility between two species of house mice</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2008</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>2213</fpage><lpage>2228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18689897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henikoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The centromere paradox: stable inheritance with rapidly evolving DNA</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>293</volume><fpage>1098</fpage><lpage>1102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11498581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hense</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Baines</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>X chromosome inactivation during <italic>Drosophila</italic> spermatogenesis</article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e273</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17927450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hermisson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennings</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soft sweeps: molecular population genetics of adaptation from standing genetic variation</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2005</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>2335</fpage><lpage>2352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15716498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kliman</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions between natural selection, recombination and gene density in the genes of <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2002</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11861564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of linkage on limits to artificial selection</article-title><source>Genet Res.</source><year>1966</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5980116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brutlag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence and sequence variation within the 1.688 g/cm3 satellite DNA of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>J Mol Biol.</source><year>1979</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">231676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Andolfatto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A second-generation assembly of the <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> genome provides new insights into patterns of lineage-specific divergence</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22936249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomiankowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Causes of sex ratio bias may account for unisexual sterility in hybrids: a new explanation of Haldane&#x02019;s rule and related phenomena</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1991</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1916248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hvilsom</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extensive X-linked adaptive evolution in central chimpanzees</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>2054</fpage><lpage>2059</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22308321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jurka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Repbase Update, a database of eukaryotic repetitive elements</article-title><source>Cytogenet Genome Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16093699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kearse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geneious Basic: an integrated and extendable desktop software platform for the organization and analysis of sequence data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1647</fpage><lpage>1649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22543367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keightley</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the genome sequences of three <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> spontaneous mutation accumulation lines</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1195</fpage><lpage>1201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19439516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A test of neutrality based on interlocus associations</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1997</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>1197</fpage><lpage>1206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9215920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kingan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrigan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrent selection on the Winters <italic>sex-ratio</italic> genes in <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2010</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19897749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Male-biased mutation, sex linkage, and the rate of adaptive evolution</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>2004</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15068360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A role for a neo-sex chromosome in stickleback speciation</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>461</volume><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1083</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19783981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kliman</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The population genetics of the origin and divergence of the <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> complex species</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2000</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>1913</fpage><lpage>1931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11102384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Barmina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interspecific divergence, intrachromosomal recombination, and phylogenetic utility of Y-chromosomal genes in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>741</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16325432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kousathanas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Halligan</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Keightley</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Faster-X adaptive protein evolution in house mice</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2014</year><volume>196</volume><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24361937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuttler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira-Filho</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Heslop-Harrison</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The 1.688 repetitive DNA of <italic>Drosophila</italic>: concerted evolution at different genomic scales and association with genes</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21712468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Versatile and open software for comparing large genomes</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>R12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14759262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lachaise</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemeunier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsacas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The reproductive relationships of <italic>Drosophila sechellia</italic> with <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic>, <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> and <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> from the Afrotropical region</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1986</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>262</fpage><lpage>271</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic variation in natural populations of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2012</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22673804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title><source>Nat Methods.</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Legrand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chenel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Campagne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lachaise</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cariou</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inter-island divergence within <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic>, a species of the <italic>D. simulans</italic> complex: past history and/or speciation in progress?</article-title><source>Mol Ecol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2787</fpage><lpage>2804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21599771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aligning sequence reads, clone sequences and assembly contigs with BWA-MEM</article-title><year>2013</year><comment>ArXiv e-prints</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2078</fpage><lpage>2079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lifschytz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsley</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of X-chromosome inactivation during spermatogenesis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source><year>1971</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4621547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Llopart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rapid evolution of X-linked male-biased gene expression and the large-X effect in <italic>Drosophila yakuba</italic>, <italic>D. santomea</italic>, and their hybrids</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>3873</fpage><lpage>3886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22844069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bost</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population-genetic inference from pooled-sequencing data</article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1210</fpage><lpage>1218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24787620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>TFC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> genetic reference panel</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>482</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22318601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Henikoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive evolution of <italic>Cid</italic>, a centromere-specific histone in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2001</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>1293</fpage><lpage>1298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masly</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Presgraves</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-resolution genome-wide dissection of the two rules of speciation in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e243</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17850182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maynard-Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haigh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hitch-hiking effect of a favorable gene</article-title><source>Genet Res.</source><year>1974</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4407212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kliman</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of isolation times of the island species in the <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> complex from multilocus DNA sequence data</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2008</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e2442</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18560591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreitman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive protein evolution at the <italic>Adh</italic> locus in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1991</year><volume>351</volume><fpage>652</fpage><lpage>654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1904993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meiklejohn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic conflict and sex chromosome evolution</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19931208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meiklejohn</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Landeen</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingan</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Presgraves</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex chromosome-specific regulation in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> male germline but little evidence for chromosomal dosage compensation or meiotic inactivation</article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e1001126</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21857805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meisel</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Connallon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The faster-X effect: integrating theory and data</article-title><source>Trends Genet.</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23790324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meisel</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Faster-X evolution of gene expression in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Genet.</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e1003013</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23071459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuyasu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasunaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Male-driven molecular evolution: a model and nucleotide sequence analysis</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol.</source><year>1987</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>863</fpage><lpage>867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3454295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moehring</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Llopart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Elwyn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genetic basis of postzygotic reproductive isolation between <italic>Drosophila santomea</italic> and <italic>D. yakuba</italic> due to hybrid male sterility</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16510788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naisbit</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiggins</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Linares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salazar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hybrid sterility, Haldane&#x02019;s rule and speciation in <italic>Heliconius cydno</italic> and <italic>H. melpomene</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2002</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>1517</fpage><lpage>1526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12196397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strong selective sweeps associated with ampliconic regions in great ape X chromosomes</article-title><year>2014</year><comment>arXiv:1402.5790</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B81"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular evolutionary genetics</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B82"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular evolution and phylogenetics</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic scans for selective sweeps using SNP data</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1566</fpage><lpage>1575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16251466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kofler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlotterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide patterns of natural variation reveal strong selective sweeps and ongoing genomic conflict in <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic></article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23051690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>MDS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wengel</surname><given-names>POT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreissl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schl&#x000f6;tterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple hybridization events between <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> and <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic> are supported by mtDNA introgression</article-title><source>Mol Ecol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>4695</fpage><lpage>4707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20958812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Betancourt</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haldane&#x02019;s sieve and adaptation from the standing genetic variation</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2001</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parsch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Novozhilov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saminadin-Peter</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Andolfatto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the utility of short intron sequences as a reference for the detection of positive and negative selection in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1226</fpage><lpage>1234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20150340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phadnis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single gene causes both male sterility and segregation distortion in <italic>Drosophila</italic> hybrids</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>323</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19074311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B89"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pool</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of founder events on chromosomal variability in multiply mating species</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1728</fpage><lpage>1736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18511425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B90"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Presgraves</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Birkhead</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosken</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitnick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drive and sperm: evolution and genetics of male meiotic drive</article-title><source>Sperm biology: an evolutionary perspective</source><year>2008a</year><publisher-name>Elsevier Press</publisher-name><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>506</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B91"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Presgraves</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex chromosomes and speciation in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Trends Genet.</source><year>2008b</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18514967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B92"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Przewloka</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular analysis of core kinetochore composition and assembly in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e478</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17534428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B93"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Landscape of standing variation for tandem duplications in <italic>Drosophila yakuba</italic> and <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1750</fpage><lpage>1766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24710518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B94"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saetre</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Speciation, introgressive hybridization and nonlinear rate of molecular evolution in flycatchers</article-title><source>Mol Ecol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11298984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B95"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ABySS: a parallel assembler for short read sequence data</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>1123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19251739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B96"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Codon bias and noncoding GC content correlate negatively with recombination rate on the <italic>Drosophila</italic> X chromosome</article-title><source>J Mol Evol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16044248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B97"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Larracuente</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contrasting the efficacy of selection on the X and autosomes in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>454</fpage><lpage>467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18083702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B98"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>AFA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RepeatMasker Open-3.0</article-title><year>2010</year><comment>[cited 2014 Sep 12]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.repeatmasker.org">http://www.repeatmasker.org</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B99"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyre-Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive protein evolution in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>415</volume><fpage>1022</fpage><lpage>1024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11875568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B100"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statistical method for testing the neutral mutation hypothesis by DNA polymorphism</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1989</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2513255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B101"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Presgraves</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> nuclear pore complex results in multiple hybrid incompatibilities</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>323</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19197064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B102"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic dissection of hybrid incompatibilities between <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> and <italic>D. mauritiana</italic>. I. Differential accumulation of hybrid male sterility effects on the X and autosomes</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2003</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>1383</fpage><lpage>1397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12930747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B103"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A <italic>sex-ratio</italic> meiotic drive system in <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic>. II: an X-linked distorter</article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e293</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17988173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B104"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex-ratio segregation distortion associated with reproductive isolation in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>13183</fpage><lpage>13188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11687638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B105"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teshima</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coop</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Przeworski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How reliable are empirical genomic scans for selective sweeps?</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>702</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16687733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B106"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>C-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsaur</surname><given-names>S-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C-I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapidly evolving homeobox at the site of a hybrid sterility gene</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1998</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>1501</fpage><lpage>1504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9822383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B107"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B108"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>True</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in crossover frequency and distribution among three sibling species of <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1996</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8852849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B109"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>True</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genome-wide survey of hybrid incompatibility factors by the introgression of marked segments of <italic>Drosophila mauritiana</italic> chromosomes into <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1996</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>837</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8849890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B110"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dominance theory of Haldane&#x02019;s rule</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1995</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7635302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B111"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dominance, epistasis and the genetics of postzygotic isolation</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2000</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>1663</fpage><lpage>1679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B112"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vicoso</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effective population size and the faster-X effect: an extended model</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>2009</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>2413</fpage><lpage>2426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19473388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B113"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of postmating reproductive isolation: the composite nature of Haldane&#x02019;s rule and its genetic bases</article-title><source>Am Nat.</source><year>1993</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19425975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B114"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PAML 4: phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1586</fpage><lpage>1591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B115"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating synonymous and nonsynonymous substitution rates under realistic evolutionary models</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10666704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="evu198-B116"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>P-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y-F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Wolbachia</italic>-induced cytoplasmic incompatibility is associated with decreased <italic>Hira</italic> expression in male <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e19512</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21559343</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>