<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3966863</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-00919</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093009</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA stability</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Proteomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome Analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Transcriptome Analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome Expression Analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Regulation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Functional Genomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Physiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Sequencing Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome Sequencing</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Emerging Infectious Diseases</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Pathology and Laboratory Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathogenesis</subject><subj-group><subject>Host-Pathogen Interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Gene and Protein Expression in Response to Different Growth Temperatures and Oxygen Availability in <italic>Burkholderia thailandensis</italic></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Response to Environmental Cues in <italic>B. thailandensis</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peano</surname><given-names>Clelia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chiaramonte</surname><given-names>Fabrizio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Motta</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pietrelli</surname><given-names>Alessandro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jaillon</surname><given-names>Sebastien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>Elio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Consolandi</surname><given-names>Clarissa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Champion</surname><given-names>Olivia L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Michell</surname><given-names>Stephen L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Freddi</surname><given-names>Luca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Falciola</surname><given-names>Luigi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Basilico</surname><given-names>Fabrizio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garlanda</surname><given-names>Cecilia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mauri</surname><given-names>Pierluigi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De Bellis</surname><given-names>Gianluca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Landini</surname><given-names>Paolo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Institute of Biomedical Technologies, National Research Council, Segrate, Milan, Italy</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Biosciences, Universit&#x000e0; degli Studi di Milano, Milan, Italy</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Humanitas Clinical and Research Center Institute, Rozzano, Milan, Italy</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>College of Life and Environmental Sciences, University of Exeter, Exeter, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Department of Chemistry, Universit&#x000e0; degli Studi di Milano, Milan, Italy</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Morici</surname><given-names>Lisa A.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Tulane University School of Medicine, United States of America</addr-line></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>paolo.landini@unimi.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CP CG PM GDB PL. Performed the experiments: CP FC SM SJ CC OLC L. Freddi L. Falciola FB. Analyzed the data: CP AP ER SLM CG PM GDB PL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: OLC SLM L. Falciola SJ CG. Wrote the paper: PL.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e93009</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Peano et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic>Burkholderia thailandensis</italic>, although normally avirulent for mammals, can infect macrophages <italic>in vitro</italic> and has occasionally been reported to cause pneumonia in humans. It is therefore used as a model organism for the human pathogen <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>, to which it is closely related phylogenetically. We characterized the <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> clinical isolate CDC2721121 (BtCDC272) at the genome level and studied its response to environmental cues associated with human host colonization, namely, temperature and oxygen limitation. Effects of the different growth conditions on BtCDC272 were studied through whole genome transcription studies and analysis of proteins associated with the bacterial cell surface. We found that growth at 37&#x000b0;C, compared to 28&#x000b0;C, negatively affected cell motility and flagella production through a mechanism involving regulation of the flagellin-encoding <italic>fliC</italic> gene at the mRNA stability level. Growth in oxygen-limiting conditions, in contrast, stimulated various processes linked to virulence, such as lipopolysaccharide production and expression of genes encoding protein secretion systems. Consistent with these observations, BtCDC272 grown in oxygen limitation was more resistant to phagocytosis and strongly induced the production of inflammatory cytokines from murine macrophages. Our results suggest that, while temperature sensing is important for regulation of <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> cell motility, oxygen limitation has a deeper impact on its physiology and constitutes a crucial environmental signal for the production of virulence factors.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by Fondazione CARIPLO (Progetto Vaccini, contract number 2009&#x02013;3577) and by Ministero dell&#x02019;Istruzione, dell&#x02019;Universit&#x000e0; e della Ricerca (MIUR) (project FIRB RBLA039LSF). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="21"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The <italic>Burkholderia</italic> genus includes several environmental species and one obligate pathogen, <italic>B. mallei</italic><xref rid="pone.0093009-Coenye1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Several <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species are &#x0201c;environmental pathogens&#x0201d;, <italic>i.e.</italic>, facultative pathogenic bacteria commonly found in the environment. For instance, the <italic>Burkholderia cepacia</italic> complex, an association of around 17 <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species, is able to infect several plants and can be a highly problematic opportunistic pathogen in cystic fibrosis patients <xref rid="pone.0093009-Mahenthiralingam1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Another very important environmental pathogen, <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>, is commonly found in waters and wet soil in tropical regions. Upon entry into humans either through skin cuts or by inhalation, <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> can cause melioidosis, a disease with multiple symptoms and a complex outcome, including acute pneumonia and septic shock, often fatal for the patient <xref rid="pone.0093009-White1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> was initially thought to exist in two different biotypes, one able to cause melioidosis in humans, the second avirulent and distinguishable from the other by its ability to utilize arabinose as a carbon source <xref rid="pone.0093009-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. This avirulent biotype was later classified as a separate species, <italic>B. thailandensis</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Brett1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Although generally considered an environmental saprophyte, <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> has been reported to cause occasional pneumonia and melioidosis-like symptoms in humans, especially in victims of traumatic injuries <xref rid="pone.0093009-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Lertpatanasuwan1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Comparison between <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> and <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> genomes has highlighted several features that might be responsible for the strong difference in virulence between the two species, such as the presence, in <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>, of a <italic>Yersinia</italic>-like fimbrial cluster and of a specific capsular polysaccharide <xref rid="pone.0093009-Reckseidler1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0093009-Sim1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. However, it has recently been shown that some <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> strains, despite being able to produce a <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>-like (Bp-like) capsule, are avirulent in mouse infection models, suggesting that additional factors are responsible for the difference in virulence between the two species <xref rid="pone.0093009-Sim1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Wand1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. On the other hand, genomic studies have shown that, despite its poor pathogenicity in mammals, <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> shares a large set of putative virulence factors with <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Galyov1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Indeed, <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> can induce formation of multi-nucleated giant cells (MNGC) in macrophage infection models <italic>in vitro</italic>; in addition, it is highly virulent in experimental infection models utilizing either nematodes or insects <xref rid="pone.0093009-Wand1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-OQuinn1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0093009-Pilatova1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>.</p><p>Thus, <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> represents an intriguing example of a &#x0201c;transition state&#x0201d; between an environmental bacterium and a human pathogen, making it a suitable model for the study of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>. In this work, we studied the <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> strain CDC2721121, a clinical isolate identified as the etiologic agent of a pleural infection in a 76-year old male <xref rid="pone.0093009-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> and investigated its response to environmental signals through determination of global gene expression and cell surface-associated protein production. In particular, we studied the effects of oxygen availability and of different growth temperatures (28&#x000b0;C versus 37&#x000b0;C), <italic>i.e.</italic>, environmental conditions typical of the human host, but that can also be encountered by <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> in its natural niche (water and soil in tropical and subtropical regions). We found that changes in both temperature and oxygen availability trigger specific responses in global gene expression and in cell surface protein composition in <italic>B. thailandensis</italic>: in particular, growth at 37&#x000b0;C inhibits production of flagella and cell motility, while oxygen limitation promotes expression of factors involved in bacteria-host interactions.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Genome Sequence of <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> CDC2721121 (BtCDC272)</title><p><italic>B. thailandensis</italic> CDC2721121 (BtCDC272), unlike other <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> clinical isolates, does not produce the Bp-like capsule, but an exopolysaccharide more typical of strictly environmental <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> strains (Bt-EPS) <xref rid="pone.0093009-Sim1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, thus making this strain very interesting for the identification of additional virulence mechanisms. To gather more information about BtCDC272, we obtained its genomic sequence by performing Illumina paired-end deep sequencing. Through generation of more than 10 Million reads, we were able to map about 1 Gb of BtCDC272 genomic sequence to the corresponding sequences in the environmental isolate <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> E264 (BtE264), whose genome has been entirely sequenced and characterized <xref rid="pone.0093009-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> (GeneBank Accession number: <underline>CP000086</underline>, <underline>CP000085</underline>). Comparison to the BtE264 reference genome showed that 92.58% of Chromosome 1 was sequenced with a 124X-coverage and 94.63% of Chromosome 2 was sequenced with a depth of about 119X-coverage, thus obtaining a mean coverage of the whole BtE264 genome of 93.51% with a depth of coverage of about 122X (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). Mapping the BtCDC272 Illumina sequencing reads to the BtE264 genome revealed the presence of 193 regions greater than 100 bp showing 0X coverage, for a total of 428.7 Kbp. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g001">Figure 1B</xref> shows the median coverage of BtE264 chromosomes 1 and 2 using a 10 Kb moving window; the regions with a median 0X coverage which span the entire moving window are highlighted by red circles. 78 of these 0X coverage regions (40.4%) were located inside previously identified genomic islands (GI) and novel genomic islets (nGI) regions <xref rid="pone.0093009-Sim1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <italic>i.e.</italic>, chromosomal regions associated with horizontal gene transfer and exhibiting unusual sequence features, such as atypical codon bias or GC content, or the presence of multiple prophage and transposon-related genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s005">File S1</xref>; sheet &#x0201c;0X coverage regions in Gi-nGi&#x0201d;). Such regions are often composed of mobile DNA elements, leading to their frequent loss or acquisition in a strain-specific manner. 87 of the remaining 0X coverage regions overlap with 89 BtE264 CDS for at least 50% of their length, suggesting that these genes might be absent in BtCDC272 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s005">File S1</xref>; sheet &#x0201c;novel 0X coverage regions&#x0201d;). Interestingly, 43 of these 89 CDS encode for putative transposases and, although not part of any GI region, are also related to DNA mobile elements. The remaining sequences, encompassing 46 genes belonging to different functional categories, were often adjacent to genes encoding transposases. Interestingly, among BtE264 genes missing in BtCDC272 we found a gluconate transport system (BTH_II0352-0353, flanking a putative transposase-encoding gene, BTH_II0354) and two gene clusters encoding putative rhamnosyltransferases possibly involved in rhamnolipid biosynthesis: BTH_II1075-1081, flanking the transposase-encoding BTH_II1082 gene, and BTH_II1875-1880. It is noteworthy that rhamnolipid production is related to virulence in several opportunistic pathogens such as <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Jensen1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> and that different ability in sugar (arabinose) utilization is a distinctive feature of <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> vs. <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Finally, 28 0X coverage regions are BtCDC272 specific sequences not matching to the BtE264 genome (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s005">File S1</xref>; sheet &#x0201c;novel 0X coverage regions&#x0201d;).</p><fig id="pone-0093009-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093009.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Genome sequencing of <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> BtCDC272.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Reference genome coverage. BtCDC272 reads were aligned against the BtE264 reference. Y-axis: percentage nucleotide coverage of the BtE264 genome. X-axis: number of reads covering each nucleotide. The inset graph indicates range from 1 to 50X coverage; ca. 90% of the BtE264 genome was sequenced with a 50X read depth. (<bold>b</bold>) Sequence coverage gaps in BtE264 are associated with GIs and nGis. Shown are coverage maps of BtE264 chromosome 1 (left) and chromosome 2 (right). Graph: median fold-coverage of BtCDC272 sequence reads using a 10-kb moving window. Red circles evidence the regions with a median 0X coverage within the entire 10 Kb moving window. The x-axis shows the BtE264 genome co-ordinates (bp). (<bold>c</bold>) Functional enrichment of Bt genes with nonsynonymous SNPs (Nsy SNPs). COG functional categories are indicated on the y-axis, and the percentage of genes in each COG category is shown on the x-axis. Dark blue columns represent BtCDC272 genes with Nsy SNPs relative to BtE264, and red columns indicate all BtE264 genes with COG annotations. COG categories exhibiting a significant enrichment of genes with Nsy SNPs are highlighted by asterisks (*P&#x0003c;0.05 or **P&#x0003c;0.01, binomial test; after Bonferroni correction).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0093009.g001"/></fig><p>Altogether, <italic>de novo</italic> assembly of the BtCDC272 reads yielded 594 sequence contigs with median size (N50) of 41229 bases. The annotation of the 594 contigs generated 6141 CDS, 5212 of which, showing more than 30% of protein sequence identity over more than 80% of the protein length, were considered as matching genes present in the BtE264 genome. In contrast, 929 CDS appeared to be specific for BtCDC272 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s006">File S2</xref>). Similar to other <italic>Burkholderia</italic> genomes, we found frequent duplications of genes and operons (often found in one copy for each chromosome), such as for genes encoding flagellum biosynthetic proteins, ATP synthase, aspartate carbamoyltransferase, etc. A homology search for the 929 CDS specific for BtCDC272 was performed using a <italic>Burkholderia</italic> database containing 98044 protein sequences from 4 <italic>B. mallei</italic>, 9 <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> and 3 <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> strains; 331 BtCDC272-specific CDS showed very high similarity (match &#x0003e;80% protein length - Identity &#x0003e;30%) with CDS from other <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species, mainly with <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> CDC3015869 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s007">File S3</xref>), thus reiterating the close phylogenetic relation among <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> clinical isolates <xref rid="pone.0093009-Sim1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Of the 929 BtCDC272-specific CDS only 245 could tentatively be assigned to functional categories, the most represented being: Carbohydrate transport and metabolism (15 CDS), Transcription (24 CDS), Replication, recombination and repair (33 CDS), Cell wall/membrane/envelope biogenesis (17 CDS), and Secondary metabolites biosynthesis, transport and catabolism (14 CDS). Among the genes belonging to the &#x0201c;Replication, recombination and repair&#x0201d; category, the majority coded for integrases and transposases, once again underlining the correlation between strain-specific genes and mobile DNA elements. Finally, 19 genes, found on two different contigs, encode phage assembly proteins, suggesting the presence of at least one prophage on the BtCDC272 genome. Interestingly, similar phage-like gene clusters were found on the genome of the <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> CDC3015869 strain, suggesting that these two clinical isolates of <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> might carry the same prophage. In addition to genes homologous to other <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species, several genes possibly involved in Cell wall/membrane/envelope biogenesis were highly similar to other Gram-negative bacteria, like <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> and <italic>Caulobacter vibrioides,</italic> while genes involved in Secondary metabolites biosynthesis showed significant similarity to various <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> polyketide synthases. Thus, genome sequencing of BtCDC272 confirmed once again the elevated plasticity of the <italic>Burkholderia</italic> genomes.</p><p>Comparing regions conserved between BtE264 and BtCDC272 genomes, we identified 44,613 Single Nucleotide Variations (SNVs), approximately 77.5% of which (34595 SNVs) occurred within coding sequences. Non-synonymous SNVs amounted to 17,121, yielding an overall intragenic nucleotide diversity between BtE264 and BtCDC272 of approximately 5.9 SNV per kilobase. When mapped across various functional pathways (COG categories), the percentage of genes containing non-synonymous SNVs (SNVs predicted to alter protein sequence) were found to be significantly higher (q-value&#x0003c;0.05, Fisher Exact Test, after multiple hypothesis Bonferroni correction) in pathways related to signal transduction mechanisms, chromatin structure and dynamics, cell division, and amino acid transport and metabolism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). Interestingly, two BtCDC272 genes belonging to the Bt-EPS biosynthetic cluster, and homologous to the BtE264 genes BTH_I1343 and BTH_I1339, show a significantly higher mutation frequency (12.87 and 7.66 SNV/kbp, respectively) than the average. It remains to be understood whether such a high mutation frequency might result in altered enzymatic catalytic activity or substrate affinity, thus affecting composition and structure of the Bt-EPS in BtCDC272 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s008">File S4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Gene and Protein Expression Changes in BtCDC272 in Response to Different Temperatures and to Oxygen Limitation</title><p>In order to investigate the response of <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> to environmental signals, we compared BtCDC272 global gene expression in different growth conditions, namely, in LB growth medium with full aeration at either 28&#x000b0;C or 37&#x000b0;C, and at 37&#x000b0;C in oxygen limitation, <italic>i.e.</italic>, in liquid cultures incubated with no shaking at 37&#x000b0;C (abbreviated 37&#x000b0;C An, for &#x0201c;anoxic&#x0201d;, in figures and tables). In cultures grown at 37&#x000b0;C with no shaking, concentration of dissolved oxygen in liquid medium decreased rapidly from the initial value of around 5 mg/l, falling below detection limits in stationary phase cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s001">Figure S1B</xref>), as determined by direct oxygen measurement using a galvanic sensor for dissolved oxygen in liquids (see <italic>Methods</italic>). Lack of oxygen results in earlier growth arrest and in production of lower biomass (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s001">Figure S1A</xref>); indeed, LB medium is not able to support anaerobic respiration by BtCDC272, unless supplemented with additional nitrate (data not shown). In contrast, oxygen concentration remained constant at all times in cultures grown with vigorous shaking (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s001">Figure S1B</xref>). Fluctuations in temperature and oxygen availability similar to those analyzed in our study are typical of <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> environment, <italic>i.e.</italic>, in soil and water bodies of tropical and subtropical regions. For instance, in pond waters in Thailand, the average temperature is estimated at 31.6&#x000b0;C <xref rid="pone.0093009-Braaten1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> and oxygen concentrations can drop resulting in microaerophilic or even anoxic conditions. Upon entry to a human host, environmental bacteria experience a shift to 37&#x000b0;C, initially in an aerobic niche (<italic>e.g.</italic>, skin wounds, or nostrils upon inhalation) and then, progressing in the host tissues or bloodstream, into a microaerophilic/anoxic environment. Thus, the growth conditions chosen in this work aimed to compare BtCDC272 gene expression in conditions resembling human host colonization versus conditions more typical of the external environment. Samples for RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) were taken from stationary phase BtCDC272 cultures (grown 16 hours starting from an inoculum of OD600 nm&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.1; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s001">Figure S1</xref>); additional details are provided in <italic>Methods</italic>. The statistics regarding RNA-seq data generation are included in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s009">File S5</xref>. We chose to use bacteria in stationary phase, rather than actively growing cells, since their physiology is more similar to environmental conditions, typically oligotrophic and unable to support fast growth, and also to the situation encountered by bacteria in the host, in particular upon ingestion by macrophages <xref rid="pone.0093009-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Genes showing significantly differential expression (DEGs) (p-val&#x02264;0.01 and log2 fold change &#x02265;1 or log2 fold change &#x02264;&#x02212;1) are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s010">File S6</xref> (37&#x000b0;C versus 28&#x000b0;C; 416 genes) and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s011">File S7</xref> (37&#x000b0;C An versus 37&#x000b0;C; 618 genes). Analysis of functional classes affected by the different growth conditions showed that a significantly higher number of DEGs genes belonging to two functional classes, <italic>i.e.</italic>, &#x0201c;Cell motility and secretion&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Signal transduction mechanisms&#x0201d; were less expressed at 37&#x000b0;C than at 28&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s002">Figure S2A</xref>): most genes belonging to the second category are in fact signal transduction proteins involved in chemotaxis (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>), and thus also related to cell motility. In contrast, genes involved in primary metabolism (Functional classes &#x0201c;Energy production and conversion&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;Nucleotide transport and metabolism&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Translation, ribosomal structure and biogenesis&#x0201d;) were significantly more expressed in anoxic than in fully aerated conditions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s002">Figure S2B</xref>). This result was unexpected, since expression of primary metabolism genes, in particular of those encoding ribosomal proteins, usually correlates with growth rate (reviewed in <xref rid="pone.0093009-Condon1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>) and is therefore higher in optimal growth conditions. However, in our experiments, we used stationary phase cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s001">Figure S1A</xref>), in which growth-rate regulation should not come into play. A more detailed analysis of the effects of oxygen limitation on ribosomal gene expression is provided in &#x0201c;<italic>Validation of functional genomics experiments by Real-Time PCR</italic>&#x0201d; (see below). Differentially Expressed Genes (DEGs) and Outer membrane Proteins (DEPs) most relevant to specific cellular processes are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref> (37&#x000b0;C versus 28&#x000b0;C) and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref> (37&#x000b0;C An versus 37&#x000b0;C) and are discussed in the following subsections.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0093009-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093009.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Gene and protein regulation in response to different growth temperatures (28&#x000b0;C vs. 37&#x000b0;C).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0093009-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0093009.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene ID(name)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene product</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">RNAseq</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MudPIT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conservation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">d</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organization in operons and previously observed regulation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">e</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">GENES/PROTEINS DOWNREGULATED AT 37&#x000b0;C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FC<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">log<sub>2</sub>(FC)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAve<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref></td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Motility (12)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0200 (<italic>fliF</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar MS-ring protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0202 (<italic>fliS</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellin specific chaperone</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0237</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar biosynthesis chaperone</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0237&#x02192;<italic>flgM</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0238 (<italic>flgM</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti &#x003c3;<sup>28</sup> factor; regulator offlagellin synthesis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0237&#x02192;<italic>flgM</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0243 (<italic>flgE</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar hook protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;94.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0250 (<italic>flgK</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar hook associated protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>flgK</italic>&#x02192;<italic>flgL</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0251 (<italic>flgL</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagelin and related proteins</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>flgK</italic>&#x02192;<italic>flgL</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3184 (<italic>motB</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar motor protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>motA</italic>&#x02192;<italic>motB</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3185 (<italic>motA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar motor component</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>motA</italic>&#x02192;<italic>motB</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I3196 (<italic>fliC</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>flagellin</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>0.38</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&#x02212;1.4</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&#x02212;110.2</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3197 (<italic>fliD-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar capping protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1544 (<italic>fliD-2</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar capping protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Chemotaxis (12)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3175 (<italic>cheZ</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis protein histidine kinase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cheZ</italic>&#x02192;<italic>cheA</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3176 (<italic>cheY</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis regulatory protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cheZ</italic>&#x02192;<italic>cheA</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3177 (<italic>cheB</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis response regulator</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cheZ</italic>&#x02192;<italic>cheA</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3178 (<italic>cheD</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemoreceptor protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cheZ</italic>&#x02192;<italic>cheA</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3179 (<italic>cheR</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis methyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cheZ</italic>&#x02192;<italic>cheA</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3180</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">methyl-accepting chemotaxis protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cheZ</italic>&#x02192;<italic>cheA</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3181 (<italic>cheW</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis signal transduction protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cheZ</italic>&#x02192;<italic>cheA</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3182 (<italic>cheA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis protein histidine kinase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cheZ</italic>&#x02192;<italic>cheA</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3209</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tar, methyl-accepting chemotaxis protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1464</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tar, methyl-accepting chemotaxis protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1955</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tar, methyl-accepting chemotaxis protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II2364 (<italic>cheC</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis protein, MCP inhibitor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>ATP synthesis (6)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0419 (<italic>atpD-2</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>1</sub>-complex, beta subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpD</italic>-2&#x02192;<italic>atpG-2</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0420 (<italic>atpC-2</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>1</sub>-complex, epsilon subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpD</italic>-2&#x02192;<italic>atpG-2</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0423 (<italic>atpB-2</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>0</sub> complex, a subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpD</italic>-2&#x02192;<italic>atpG-2</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0424 (<italic>atpE-2</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>0</sub> complex, c subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpD</italic>-2&#x02192;<italic>atpG-2</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0425 (<italic>atpF-2</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>0</sub> complex, b subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpD</italic>-2&#x02192;<italic>atpG-2</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0427 (<italic>atpG-2</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>1</sub> complex gamma subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpD</italic>-2&#x02192;<italic>atpG-2</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Nitrogen metabolism (6)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1851 (<italic>narI</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nitrate reductase, gamma subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>narI</italic>&#x02192;BTH_I1856 <xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1852 (<italic>narJ</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nitrate reductase, delta subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>narI</italic>&#x02192;BTH_I1856 <xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1855 (<italic>narK</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nitrate transporter</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>narI</italic>&#x02192;BTH_I1856 <xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2321 (<italic>nosL</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lipoprotein involved in nitrous oxide reduction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2317&#x02192;<italic>nosD</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2324 (<italic>nosD</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">periplasmic copper binding protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2317&#x02192;<italic>nosD</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2325 (<italic>nosZ</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nitrous oxide reductase activity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Universal stress proteins (USP) (6)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1566</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1567</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1567&#x02192;II1568</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1568</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1567&#x02192;II1568</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1569</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1268</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp,Bc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0442</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp,Bc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>GENES/PROTEINS UPREGULATED AT 37&#x000b0;C</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Chaperones (3)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1308 (<italic>dnaK</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">molecular chaperone DnaK</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1309 (<italic>dnaJ</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">molecular caperone DnaJ</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1458 (<italic>groL</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chaperonin GroEL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Protein secretion systems/exoenzymes (6)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0028 (<italic>fliN</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar motor switch/type III secretory pathway protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0198 (<italic>fliH</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar biosynthesis protein/type III secretory pathway protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0191 (<italic>flgI</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar basal-body P-ring protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2671 (<italic>plcC</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">acid phosphatase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2962 (<italic>hcp</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hemolysin coregulated protein, T6SS component</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp,Bc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2963</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uncharacterized T6SS protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bc, Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p>FC&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;fold change in differential expression;</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>b</label><p>log<sub>2</sub>(FC)&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;logarithm<sub>2</sub> of fold change.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>c</label><p>DAve&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;Difference in Average (amount); calculated as in Experimental procedures.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>d</label><p>Conservation in <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species pathogenic for humans: Bc&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>B. cenocepacia</italic>; Bm&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>B. mallei</italic>; Bp&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>e</label><p>in the reference indicated, the gene or its orthologous has been found with the same trend of expression in growth conditions comparable with this work. Genes and corresponding proteins found to be differentially expressed both in transcriptomics and proteomics experiments are <underline>underlined</underline>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0093009-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093009.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Gene and protein regulation in response to oxygen-limiting conditions.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0093009-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0093009.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene ID (name)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene product</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">RNAseq</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MudPIT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conservation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">d</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organization in operons and previously observed regulation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">e</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">GENES/PROTEINS DOWNREGULATED IN OXYGEN LIMITATION</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FC<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">log<sub>2</sub>(FC)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">b</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAve<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">c</xref></td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Motility (1)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3196 (<italic>fliC</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flagellin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;98.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Extracellular proteins (6)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I0090 (<italic>cpxP</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>P pilus assembly/Cpx signaling pathway, periplasmic inhibitor</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>0.41</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&#x02212;1.3</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&#x02212;150</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0866 (<italic>fimC</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P pilus assembly protein, chaperone PapD</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2461 (<italic>cpaA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flp pilus assembly protein, protease CpaA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_II1990</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>putative outer membrane</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>0.38</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&#x02212;1.4</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&#x02212;150</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0447</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TolC-like outer membrane protein/RND efflux system component</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1638</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-type lectin domain containing protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;184.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Polyhydroxyalkanoates synthesis (3)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2255 (<italic>phaC</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">poly(3-hydroxyalkanoate) synthetase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2258 (<italic>phaR</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">polyhydroxyalkanoate synthesis repressor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;120.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0418 (<italic>phaC</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">poly(3-hydroxyalkanoate) synthetase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;113.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Universal stress proteins (USP) (6)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1566</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1567</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1567&#x02192;II1568</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1568</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1567&#x02192;II1568</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1569</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1268</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp,Bc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II2484</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">universal stress protein UspA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Sulfur assimilation (5)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0817 (<italic>cysD</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sulfate adenylyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2478 (<italic>cysW</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC-type sulfate transport system, permease component</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2500 (<italic>ssuC/tauC</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">alkanesulfonate transporter permease subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1370</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cystathionine beta-synthase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II2316 (<italic>sulP</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sulfate permease</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>GENES/PROTEINS UPREGULATED IN OXYGEN LIMITATION</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Chaperones (7)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0955 (<italic>htpG</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chaperone HSP90 family</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0977 (<italic>hslJ</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HslJ, heat shock protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1306 (<italic>grpE</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">molecular chaperone GrpE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1308 (<italic>dnaK</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">molecular chaperone DnaK</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I1457 (<italic>groS</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>co-chaperonin GroES</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>4.59</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.2</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>23.5</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>groS</italic>&#x02192;<italic>groL</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I1458 (<italic>groL</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>chaperonin GroEL</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.46</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.3</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>99</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>groS</italic>&#x02192;<italic>groL</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1878 (<italic>hscB</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">co-chaperone HscB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Ribosomal proteins and RNA polymerase (54)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I0473 (<italic>rplY</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>ribosomal protein L25</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>6.50</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.7</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>150</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0735 (<italic>rpsT</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0779 (<italic>rpmG</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rpmG</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rpmB</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I0780 (<italic>rpmB</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>L28</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>3.73</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.9</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>150</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rpmG</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rpmB</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1055 (<italic>rpsO</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S15P/S13E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1140 (<italic>rplU</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rplU</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rpmA</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1141 (<italic>rpmA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rplU</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rpmA</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1233 (<italic>rplM</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rplM</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rpsI</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I1234 (<italic>rpsI</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>S9</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>3.03</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.6</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>26.5</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rplM</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rpsI</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I1638 (<italic>rpsA</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>S1</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>4.29</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.1</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>142.8</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I1661 (<italic>rpsP</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>S16</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.83</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.5</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>83.5</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I1664 (<italic>rplS</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>L19</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>5.28</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.4</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>133.8</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1715 (<italic>rpmF</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I2027 (<italic>rpsB</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>S2</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>4.00</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>132.5</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2179 (<italic>rpsF</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rpsR</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rplI</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2181 (<italic>rpsR</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rpsR</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rplI</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2182 (<italic>rplI</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I2213 (<italic>rpmE</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>L31</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>4.92</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.3</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>150</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2592 (<italic>rplT</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rplT</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rpmI</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2593 (<italic>rpmI</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rplT</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rpmI</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3041 (<italic>rplQ</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I3043 (<italic>rpsD</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>S4</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>3.73</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.9</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>129.1</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I3049&#x02192;BTH_I3058 </underline>(<italic><underline>rplO</underline></italic><underline>&#x02192;<italic>rplN</italic></underline>;10 genes)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>L15, </underline>L30, <underline>S5</underline>,<underline>L18</underline>, <underline>L6</underline>, S8, S14, L5, <underline>L24</underline>, <underline>L14 </underline>(6 proteins)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>4&#x02192;15</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2&#x02192;3.9</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>83&#x02192;141</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rplO</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rplN</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I3059&#x02192;BTH_I3068 </underline>(<italic><underline>rpsQ</underline></italic><underline>&#x02192;<italic>rpsC</italic></underline>;10 genes)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S17,L29, L16, <underline>S3</underline>, L22, S19, <underline>L2</underline>, <underline>L23</underline>, <underline>L4</underline>, <underline>L3 </underline>(5 proteins)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>3&#x02192;14</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.6&#x02192;4</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>48&#x02192;139</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rpsQ</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rplC</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I3069 (<italic>rpsJ</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>S10</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>3.3</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>61.4</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3072 (<italic>rpsG</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3073 (<italic>rpsL</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I3077 (<italic>rplL</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>L7/L12</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>3.25</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.7</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>153.1</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I3078 (<italic>rpllJ</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>L10</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>7.46</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.9</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>100</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3079 (<italic>rplA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rplA</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rplK</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3080 (<italic>rplK</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rplA</italic>&#x02192;<italic>rplK</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3195 (<italic>rpsU-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0618 (<italic>rpsU-2</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Sass1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3042 (<italic>rpoA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA directed RNA polymerase alpha subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3075 (<italic>rpoC</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA directed RNA polymerase beta&#x02019; subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3077 (<italic>rpoB</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA directed RNA polymerase beta subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Motility (5)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0200 (<italic>fliF</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar biosynthesis lipoprotein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0241 (<italic>flgC</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar basal body rod protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Hamad1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0242 (<italic>flgD</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar hook capping protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>flgD</italic>&#x02192;<italic>flgE</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Hamad1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0243 (<italic>flgE</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar hook protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>flgD</italic>&#x02192;<italic>flgE</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Hamad1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1544 (<italic>fliD</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagellar capping protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>ATP-synthesis (8)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3307 (<italic>atpC-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>1</sub>-complex, epsilon subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I3308 (<italic>atpD-1</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>ATP synthase F<sub>1</sub>-complex, beta subunit</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>4.92</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.3</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>110.2</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpD-1</italic>&#x02192;<italic>atpA-1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3309 (<italic>atpG-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>1</sub>-complex, gamma subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpD-1</italic>&#x02192;<italic>atpA-1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I3310 (<italic>atpA-1</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>ATP synthase F<sub>1</sub>-complex, alpha subunit</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>4.00</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>100</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpD-1</italic>&#x02192;<italic>atpA-1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3311 (<italic>atpH</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>1</sub>-complex, delta subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpH</italic>&#x02192;<italic>atpF</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3312 (<italic>atpF</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>0</sub> complex, b subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>atpH</italic>&#x02192;<italic>atpF</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3313</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>0</sub> complex, c subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3314 (<italic>atpB-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase F<sub>0</sub> complex, a subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Protein secretion systems/secreted proteins (11)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2959 (<italic>tssG-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uncharacterized T6SS protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>clpV-1</italic>&#x02192;<italic>hcp-1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2960 (<italic>tssF-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uncharacterized T6SS protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>clpV-1</italic>&#x02192;<italic>hcp-1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I2962 (<italic>hcp-1</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>hemolysin coregulated protein</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.83</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.5</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>19.8</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bc, Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>clpV-1</italic>&#x02192;<italic>hcp-1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I2963 (<italic>tssC-1</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>uncharacterized T6SS protein</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.64</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.4</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>163.6</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bc, Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tssC-1</italic>&#x02192;<italic>tagM-1</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Sass1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2964 (<italic>tssB-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypothetical T6SS protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bc, Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tssC-1</italic>&#x02192;<italic>tagM-1</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Sass1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2965 (<italic>tagM-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uncharacterized T6SS protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bc, Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tssC-1</italic>&#x02192;<italic>tagM-1</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Sass1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2967 (<italic>tssK-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uncharacterized T6SS protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bc, Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3204</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipoprotein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3204&#x02192;<italic>csgG</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3205</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lipoprotein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3204&#x02192;<italic>csgG</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I3206 (<italic>csgG</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>lipoprotein, export of curli fibers</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>3.03</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.6</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>43.9</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3204&#x02192;<italic>csgG</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0816</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">zinc metalloprotease (elastase)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bc, Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Sass1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Nucleotide biosynthesis (19)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I0474 (<italic>prsA</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>phosphoribosylpyrophosphate synthetase</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>3.48</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.8</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>150</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0739 (<italic>adk</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adenylate kinase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0860 (<italic>dcd</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">deoxycytidine deaminase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1014 (<italic>purD</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I1056 (<italic>pnp</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>polyribonucleotide nucleotidyltransferase</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.14</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.1</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>79.8</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I1153 (<italic>nrdA</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>ribonucleotide reductase, alpha subunit</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.30</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.2</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>200</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1250 (<italic>purH</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AICAR transformylase/IMP cyclohydrolase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1317 (<italic>purM</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phosphoribosylaminoimidazole (AIR) synthetase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1465 (<italic>pyrB</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aspartate carbamoyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1612 (<italic>add</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adenosine deaminase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>BTH_I1892 (<italic>pyrG</italic>)</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>CTP synthase</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>2.14</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>1.1</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>150</underline></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2029 (<italic>pyrH</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uridylate kinase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2135 (<italic>purL</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phosphoribosylformylglycinamidine synthase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2231 (<italic>ndk</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nucleoside diphosphate kinase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2245 (<italic>purA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adenylosuccinate synthase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2414 (<italic>purN</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phosphoribosylglycinamide formyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2511 (<italic>pyrD</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dihydroorotate dehydrogenase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3111 (<italic>pyrE</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">orotate phosphoribosyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II0686 (<italic>purF</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glutamine phospho ribosylpyrophosphate amidotransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>EPS/LPS biosynthesis (16)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1125 (<italic>lpxC</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDP-3-O-acyl-N-acetylglucosamine deacetylase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1470 (<italic>rfbA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dTDP-glucose pyrophosphorylase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1469&#x02192;I1479</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1476 (<italic>galE-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDP-glucose-4-epimerase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1469&#x02192;I1479</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1477</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycosyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1469&#x02192;I1479</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1478 (<italic>wcaA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycosyltransferases</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bm, Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1469&#x02192;I1479</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1485 (<italic>galE-2</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDP-glucose-4-epimerase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1643 (<italic>rfaE</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADP-heptose synthase, bifunctional sugar kinase/adenylyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1757 (<italic>rfaG</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycosyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1982 (<italic>ydhO</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell wall hydrolase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2035</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">outer membrane protective antigen OMA87</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2035&#x02192;<italic>lpxD</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2036 (<italic>hlpA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">outer membrane protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2035&#x02192;<italic>lpxD</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2037 (<italic>lpxD</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDP-3-O-[3-hydroxymyristoyl] glucosamine N-acyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2035&#x02192;<italic>lpxD</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2038 (<italic>fabA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-hydroxymyristoyl dehydratase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>fabA</italic>&#x02192;BTH_I2042</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2039 (<italic>lpxA</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">acyl- UDP-N-acetylglucosamine O-acyltransferase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>fabA</italic>&#x02192;BTH_I2042</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2190 (<italic>wcaG</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nucleoside-diphosphate-sugar epimerase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I3150 (<italic>lptE</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lipoprotein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Isoprenoids and siderophores biosynthesis (5)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I0783 (<italic>ispH-1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-enyl diphosphate reductase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2418</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">siderophore related peptide synthetase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1233</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">putative siderophore non ribosomal peptide synthase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1236</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">putative non ribosomal peptide synthase/polyketide synthase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II2243 (<italic>ispH-2</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-enyl diphosphate reductase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Other outer membrane proteins (7)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1212</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rare lipoproptein B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I1907</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uncharacterized lipoprotein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2443</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multidrug efflux protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2443&#x02192;I2445 <xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2444</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">multidrug efflux protein (AcrB)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2443&#x02192;I2445 <xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2445</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">membrane fusion protein (AcrA)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_I2443&#x02192;I2445 <xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1520</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OmpC, outer membrane protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTH_II1720</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OmpC, outer membrane protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bp, Bc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt106"><label>a</label><p>FC&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;fold change in differential expression;</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label>b</label><p>log<sub>2</sub>(FC)&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;logarithm<sub>2</sub> of fold change.</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label>c</label><p>DAve&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;Difference in Average (amount); calculated as in Experimental procedures.</p></fn><fn id="nt109"><label>d</label><p>Conservation in <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species pathogenic for humans: Bc&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>B. cenocepacia</italic>; Bm&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>B. mallei</italic>; Bp&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;<italic>B. pseudomallei.</italic></p></fn><fn id="nt110"><label>e</label><p>in the reference indicated, the gene or its orthologous has been found with the same trend of expression in growth conditions comparable with this work. Genes and corresponding proteins found to be differentially expressed both in transcriptomics and proteomics experiments are <underline>underlined</underline>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Regulation of Gene/Protein Expression by Temperature</title><p>The most striking effect of growth at 37&#x000b0;C versus 28&#x000b0;C is the lower expression level of genes related to cellular motility and chemotaxis: altogether, 12 genes involved in flagellar motility and 12 genes encoding chemotactic receptors and signal transduction proteins were expressed at lower levels at 37&#x000b0;C. On the other hand, three flagellar genes (<italic>fliN</italic>, <italic>fliH</italic>, <italic>flgI</italic>) were upregulated at 37&#x000b0;C: however, the <italic>fliN</italic> and <italic>fliH</italic> genes encode components of a type 3 secretion systems (T3SS) involved not only in translocation of flagellar subunits, but also of the anti-&#x003c3;<sup>28</sup> factor FlgM. Thus, their increased expression can be understandable even in a context of flagellar downregulation, as part of the complex regulation typical of the flagellar apparatus <xref rid="pone.0093009-Chilcott1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Growth at 37&#x000b0;C also resulted in downregulation of 6 out of 9 genes in the Chromosome 2-located operon encoding one of the two ATP synthase complexes present in the <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> genome; of 3 genes belonging to an operon encoding nitrate reductase and of 3 genes encoding nitrous oxide reductase subunits. Finally, 6 genes whose products belong to the class of universal stress proteins also showed lower expression at 37&#x000b0;C. Very few genes were upregulated by growth at 37&#x000b0;C: in addition to the T3SS proteins involved in the flagellar system, only two chaperones (<italic>dnaJ</italic> and <italic>dnaK</italic>) and the extracellular enzyme acid phosphatase were found to be transcribed at higher levels at 37&#x000b0;C. Interestingly, conditions identical to the ones studied in this work (28&#x000b0;C vs. 37&#x000b0;C, stationary phase cells) were included in a recently published investigation of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> genome expression in response to a large variety of environmental signals <xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, which, in agreement with our results, showed that expression of chaperone-encoding genes was higher at 37&#x000b0;C, while most flagellar genes were downregulated at this temperature.</p><p>To confirm the results of the global gene expression experiments, and to investigate expression changes of cell surface-associated proteins, which, being in direct contact with the external environment, can play an important role in adaptation to the human host, we performed an enrichment procedure for outer membrane and cell surface-associated proteins (see <italic>Methods</italic>). Protein production in outer membrane protein-enriched preparations (OMPs) from BtCDC272 cultures grown at either 28&#x000b0;C or 37&#x000b0;C was analyzed by Mass Spectrometry, using <underline>Mu</underline>lti<underline>d</underline>imensional <underline>P</underline>rotein <underline>I</underline>dentification <underline>T</underline>echnology <xref rid="pone.0093009-Mauri1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. MudPIT analysis allowed us to verify the effective enrichment of known outer membrane proteins in the OMP fractions in all samples tested; Outer Membrane Proteins found to be differentially expressed (DEPs) are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s012">File S8</xref> (37&#x000b0;C versus 28&#x000b0;C; 54 DEPs) and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s013">File S9</xref> (37&#x000b0;C An versus 37&#x000b0;C; 127 DEPs). Among proteins showing differential production, MudPIT analysis detected lower amounts of flagellin (the main flagellar subunit) from BtCDC272 grown at 37&#x000b0;C, in agreement with decreased transcription levels of the <italic>fliC</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>). The amounts of FliF and FlgE, two proteins belonging respectively to the flagellar hook and to the MS (membrane and supramembrane) ring, were also decreased at 37&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>), further suggesting downregulation of flagellar production at this temperature. In OMPs from BtCDC272 grown at 37&#x000b0;C, we found higher amounts of two proteins (BTH_I2962 and BTH_I2963) belonging to a type 6 secretion system (T6SS) <xref rid="pone.0093009-Schwarz1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> and also the GroEL subunit of the GroEL-GroES chaperonin (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>). Enhanced GroEL protein production at 37&#x000b0;C, together with higher transcription levels of <italic>dnaJ</italic> and <italic>dnaK</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>), would suggest a general temperature-dependent increase of chaperone production, consistent with their role as heat-shock proteins.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Regulation of Gene/Protein Expression by Oxygen Limitation</title><p>Growing BtCDC272 at 37&#x000b0;C in oxygen-limiting conditions had a much larger impact on BtCDC272 physiology, inhibiting growth rate (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s001">Figure S1</xref>) and resulting in a larger number of DEGs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). In anoxic conditions, expression of 5 genes involved in sulfur assimilation and hydrogen sulfide production was reduced, likely in response to changes in the redox state of the cytoplasm due to lower oxygen levels. Likewise, transcription of the six genes encoding universal stress proteins, which already showed reduced expression at 37&#x000b0;C compared to 28&#x000b0;C, were further downregulated. In contrast with our observations, genes encoding universal stress proteins have been found to be upregulated in hypoxia in different <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species as well as in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-AlvarezOrtega1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0093009-Sass1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. A possible explanation for this discrepancy is that we compared cells in stationary phase rather than exponentially growing cells growing at different rates: indeed, it has been suggested that universal stress proteins respond to reduction in growth rate <xref rid="pone.0093009-Nachin1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. In addition, regulation mechanisms of Usp-encoding genes can vary in different bacteria; for instance, gene array experiments showed anaerobic downregulation of the <italic>uspA</italic> gene in <italic>E. coli</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Soini1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, consistent with its role in response to oxidative stress in this bacterium <xref rid="pone.0093009-Nachin1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>.</p><p>Genes whose products show homology to pilus assembly components and regulators were also expressed less in anoxic conditions. MudPIT protein content analysis of the OMP cell fraction confirmed reduced production of BTH_I0090 (a putative regulator of pilus assembly) and BTH_II1990 (a putative outer membrane protein), in agreement with reduced transcription levels of their corresponding genes. Finally, MudPIT analysis indicated reduced levels of flagellin, of another putative outer membrane protein (BTH_II1638) and of three polypeptides involved in polyhydroxyalkanoate (PHA) synthesis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>), whose presence in the OMP fraction is possibly due to their association to high molecular weight PHA granules.</p><p>Consistent with the lack of a nitrate source able to support BtCDC272 anaerobic growth in LB medium (data not shown), we did not observe any induction of genes involved in nitrate reduction and anaerobic respiration in oxygen-limiting conditions. Oxygen limitation induced two distinct protein secretion systems: one operon (BTH_I2959-BTH_I2965, with 6 out of 7 genes found to be differentially expressed in RNA-seq experiments) encodes a T6SS, whose outer membrane-associated components have also been found in higher amounts in BtCDC272 grown at 37&#x000b0;C compared to 28&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>). A second operon (BTH_I3204-BTH_I3206), encodes a protein export system showing high similarity to a system found in <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> and to the <italic>E. coli csg</italic> complex, responsible for secretion and assembly of thin aggregative fimbriae (curli) on the outer membrane <xref rid="pone.0093009-Loferer1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Interestingly, a large number of the genes showing increased transcription levels in oxygen-limiting conditions encodes proteins central to the cell&#x02019;s primary metabolism: all ribosomal proteins and RNA polymerase subunits, nucleotide biosynthesis enzymes, and several enzymes involved in the biosynthesis of lipopolysaccharide (LPS) and of EPS precursors. Consistent with upregulation of energy-requiring cellular processes, the ATP synthase-encoding operon located on Chromosome 1 was also induced in response to oxygen limitation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). Higher transcription of chaperone-encoding genes in oxygen limitation (5 genes, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>) would also correlate with increased protein synthesis rates. In contrast, no increased expression for genes involved in DNA replication and cell wall biosynthesis was detected, as expected for cells in stationary phase. Increased expression of genes involved in primary metabolism, although apparently surprising, might be related to different metabolic requirements in stationary phase cells grown in anoxic conditions, as further discussed in &#x0201c;<italic>Validation of functional genomics experiments by Real-Time PCR</italic>&#x0201d;.</p><p>Protein analysis of the OMP fraction, performed on a separate set of cultures, confirmed the trends highlighted by RNAseq experiments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). Among cell surface-associated proteins, MudPIT analysis suggested increased production, in oxygen-limiting conditions, of the products of the BTH_I2962, BTH_I2963 and of BTH_I3205 genes, <italic>i.e.</italic>, components of a T6SS and of the <italic>csg</italic>-like protein secretion systems, in agreement with RNA-seq data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). Three proteins belonging to the flagellar structure (FliF, FlgE and FliD) were also found in higher levels in OMPs from BtCDC272 grown in oxygen-limiting conditions, in contrast to the main flagellar subunit, FliC, which was present in lower amounts (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>), possibly suggesting that the flagellar structure might be reorganized in response to lack of oxygen. Many DEPs found in the OMP fraction in anoxic conditions are cytoplasmic, such as chaperones, ribosomal proteins, etc.: the presence of cytoplasmic proteins, especially when abundant and/or part of high molecular complexes likely to co-precipitate with cell membranes during fractionation, is normally observed in OMP fractions <xref rid="pone.0093009-Lacqua1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Schell1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. In addition to products of genes showing higher transcription levels, three cytoplasmic proteins belonging to non ribosomal peptide synthesis (NRPS) complexes were found in larger amounts in OMP fractions of BtCDC272 grown in oxygen-limiting conditions. NRPS activity can be aimed to production of antibiotics, signal molecules, and siderophores: indeed, BTH_I2418 shows high similarity to genes involved in siderophore biosynthesis such as ornibactin in <italic>B. cenocepacia</italic>, enterobactin in <italic>E. coli</italic> and pyoverdin in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, thus suggesting that a siderophore-producing NRPS might be activated in anoxic conditions in BtCDC272.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Validation of Functional Genomics Experiments by Real-Time PCR</title><p>In order to confirm the results shown in the previous section, we performed quantitative Real Time PCR (qRT-PCR) determination of transcript levels on genes showing differential expression in RNAseq experiments. qRT-PCR were performed on RNA samples taken from two independent overnight cultures. We selected 9 genes, representative of the major trends in differential expression, as observed in RNA-seq experiments, namely: flagellar motility and chemotaxis-related genes (<italic>fliC</italic>, <italic>flgK</italic> and <italic>cheB</italic> genes), showing temperature-dependent regulation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>); ribosomal operons, EPS-related genes and genes encoding protein secretion systems (<italic>rplR</italic>, <italic>rplW</italic>, <italic>galE</italic> and <italic>csgG</italic> genes), showing increased expression in oxygen-limiting conditions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). Finally, we tested two genes encoding cell surface-associated proteins (<italic>cpxP</italic> and BTH_II1990), whose downregulation in oxygen-limiting conditions was confirmed by reduced levels of their corresponding proteins in OMP (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). For the evaluation of qRT-PCR results, amount of transcripts in BtCDC272 grown at 37&#x000b0;C in aerobic conditions were arbitrarily considered as &#x0201c;standard expression levels&#x0201d;, to which the effects of growth either at 28&#x000b0;C or in oxygen limitation were compared (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g002">Figure 2</xref>). qRT-PCR experiments clearly confirmed that oxygen limitation stimulates expression of the <italic>rplR</italic>, <italic>rplW</italic>, <italic>galE</italic> and <italic>csgG</italic> genes, while downregulating <italic>cpxP</italic> and BTH_II1990, in agreement with RNA-seq experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). As expected, none of this set of genes showed any significant expression change in response to different growth temperatures, suggesting that their expression specifically responds to anoxic conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). In contrast, expression of flagellar and chemotaxis-related genes showed a more complex pattern: <italic>fliC</italic>, <italic>flgK</italic> and <italic>cheB</italic> transcript levels were significantly higher at 28&#x000b0;C than at 37&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g002">Figure 2A</xref>), thus confirming the downregulation of these genes at 37&#x000b0;C observed in RNA-seq data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>). However, a slight induction (2.35- to 3.10-fold) was also observed in anoxic conditions, although only the difference in <italic>fliC</italic> expression appears to be statistically significant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). This result is in apparent contrast with MudPIT observations that detected lower amounts of flagellin, the <italic>fliC</italic> gene product, in OMPs of BtCDC272 grown at 37&#x000b0;C An (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>): however, other flagellar genes show higher transcription levels in oxygen limiting conditions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>), thus suggesting complex regulation of the flagellar machinery in response to anoxia.</p><fig id="pone-0093009-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093009.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Validation of RNAseq results by qRT-PCR experiments.</title><p>Genes tested are indicated in the graph; &#x0201c;II1990&#x0201d; refers to the BTH_II1990 gene. &#x00394;Ct between the gene of interest and the 16S gene was arbitrarily set at 1 (dashed line) for expression levels in BtCDC272 grown at 37&#x000b0;C in aerobic conditions, to which expression levels at either 28&#x000b0;C (Panel A) or at 37&#x000b0;C in anoxic conditions (Panel B) were compared. The Relative expression values indicated in the graph are the average of at least four experiments (two repeats, each performed on duplicate samples, from two independent RNA extractions), and standard deviations are shown. The asterisks denote significant differences relative to BtCDC272 grown at 37&#x000b0;C in aerobic conditions (<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.05; Tukey multigroup analysis).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0093009.g002"/></fig><p>Results of qRT-PCR experiments confirmed increased expression of ribosomal protein-encoding genes in oxygen-limiting conditions in comparison to aerobic growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Since genes encoding ribosomal proteins are known to be more expressed in optimal growth conditions, induction in anoxic conditions was unexpected; in addition, this result might seem at odds with previous findings showing decreased expression of protein synthesis-related genes in response to hypoxia in different <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species <xref rid="pone.0093009-Hamad1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Sass1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. In these reports, however, experiments had been carried on using exponentially-growing bacteria. To address these discrepancies, we performed qRT-PCR experiments measuring <italic>rplR</italic> and <italic>rplW</italic> expression at different stages of growth at 37&#x000b0;C either in aerobic or anoxic conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Cells were inoculated to OD<sub>600nm</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.1 and RNA samples were taken at 2, 5, and 16 hours. At the 2 hour sample, expression of both <italic>rplR</italic> and <italic>rplW</italic> was higher (ca. 4- and 3-fold, respectively) in the faster-growing aerobic cultures than in oxygen-limiting conditions. However, in aerobic cultures, a 10-fold decrease already took place at 5 hours, in correspondence to a shift to slower growth (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s001">Figure S1A</xref> for comparison), followed by a further, albeit slighter, decrease at 16 hours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g003">Figure 3</xref>). In contrast, although a reduction in <italic>rplR</italic> and <italic>rplW</italic> expression, as cells progressed into stationary phase, could also be observed in anoxic conditions, the decrease was not as steep, leading to residual <italic>rplR</italic> and <italic>rplW</italic> expression higher than in aerobic conditions, in agreement with RNAseq, MudPIT analysis and qRT-PCR experiments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Thus, although maximal transcript levels for <italic>rplR</italic> and <italic>rplW</italic> were observed in exponential phase in aerobic conditions, as expected, their residual expression in stationary phase was higher under oxygen limitation, suggesting that a higher rate of protein and macromolecular synthesis might take place in these conditions.</p><fig id="pone-0093009-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093009.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Time-course expression of ribosomal protein-encoding genes in different growth conditions.</title><p>Samples were taken at 2, 5 and 16 hours from the initial inoculum at OD600&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.1 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s001">Figure S1A</xref> for comparison) and relative amounts of <italic>rplR</italic> (circles) and <italic>rplW</italic> (squares) transcripts were determined by qRT-PCR in cultures grown either aerobically (open symbols) and in oxygen limitation (closed symbols). Maximal gene expression corresponded to &#x00394;Ct values for <italic>rplR</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;6.8 and for <italic>rplW</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;5.5 and was set to 100%. qRT-PCR was repeated three times (with replicate samples for each experiment) on RNA obtained from a single extraction. Standard deviations are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0093009.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Temperature-dependent Regulation of Cell Motility</title><p>Our results clearly indicate lower expression of flagellar and chemotaxis genes, and reduced production of flagellar proteins, in BtCDC272 grown at 37&#x000b0;C in comparison to 28&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g002">Figure 2A</xref>), suggesting that flagellar motility would be subject to temperature-dependent regulation. To verify this hypothesis, we performed cell motility assays on soft agar plates, which, indeed, showed that BtCDC272 motility at 37&#x000b0;C was reduced by ca. 50% compared to 28&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g004">Figure 4A&#x02013;B</xref>). Direct TEM observation provided further confirmation of a reduced number of flagella at 37&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g004">Figure 4C</xref>); however, in agreement with the results of MudPIT analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>), TEM observations show that flagellar production is indeed downregulated, but not totally abolished, at 37&#x000b0;C. In order to better understand the contribution of flagella to cell motility in our assays, we tried to introduce mutations in the <italic>fliC</italic> gene of BtCDC272: however, despite various attempts, we did not succeed in creating any mutant (either in <italic>fliC</italic> or in other genes, data not shown), suggesting that the BtCDC272 is not readily amenable for genetic manipulations. Most flagellar genes in <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> are clustered in complex operons, present in two copies (one on each chromosome); temperature-dependent regulation seems to predominantly affect the flagellar operons located on Chromosome 1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>). The <italic>fliC</italic> gene (BTH_I3196), encoding flagellin, <italic>i.e.</italic>, the main flagellar subunit, is a direct target of temperature-dependent regulation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). We investigated whether downregulation of <italic>fliC</italic> expression at 37&#x000b0;C might be mediated by reduced transcription initiation or by decreased mRNA stability. RNA degradation kinetics experiments performed by qRT-PCR showed a 3-fold decrease of <italic>fliC</italic> mRNA half-life at 37&#x000b0;C: estimated half-life was 4 minutes versus 12 minutes at 28&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g004">Figure 4D</xref>), suggesting that control of mRNA stability may account for, or at least contribute to, temperature-dependent regulation of flagellar genes.</p><fig id="pone-0093009-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093009.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Temperature-dependence of cellular motility and <italic>fliC</italic> gene regulation.</title><p>Motility assays on LB soft 0.4% agar plates as from a typical experiment (<bold>A</bold>) and quantitative estimate from an average of six independent experiments (<bold>B</bold>). Statistical analysis (two-tailed Student&#x02019;s t test) of the results provided a p value&#x0003c;0.0001 (indicated by the three asterisks in the figure). <bold>C</bold>: TEM observation of cells from BtCDC272 overnight cultures grown either at 28&#x000b0;C or 37&#x000b0;C. The 1 &#x003bc;m scale bar is shown in the right bottom corner of each panel. <bold>D</bold>: RNA stability assays on the transcript of the <italic>fliC</italic> gene, as determined using qRT-PCR. The horizontal dashed line indicates 50% of residual amount of mRNA after rifampicin addition; the vertical dashed lines define the half-life values. Values are the average of four experiments (two repeats, each performed on duplicate samples, from two independent experiments) and standard deviations are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0093009.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Polyhydroxyalkanoate (PHA) Accumulation does not Occur in Oxygen-limiting Conditions</title><p>In response to nitrogen or phosphorous limitation, several bacterial species of the <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> and <italic>Burkholderia</italic> genera can store excess carbon as PHA. PHA accumulation results in the formation of large, light-reflecting granules easily detectable in the cytoplasm by electron microscopy (reviewed in <xref rid="pone.0093009-Zinn1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>). Our proteomics data indicate that expression of proteins involved in PHA synthesis is downregulated in oxygen-limiting conditions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). However, previous reports had suggested increased transcription levels of genes involved in PHA biosynthesis in response to lack of oxygen in other <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species <xref rid="pone.0093009-Hamad1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Sass1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Thus, to confirm the results of our proteomic analysis, we assessed formation of PHA granules in BtCDC272 grown in different conditions by TEM observations. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g005">Figure 5</xref>, BtCDC272 cells grown in full aeration, regardless of temperature, showed significant accumulation of PHA granules, which were totally absent in cells grown in oxygen-limiting conditions. This result would be consistent with the notion that PHA synthesis is triggered by exhaustion of an essential nutrient in the presence of excess carbon. In the case of growth in oxygen-rich conditions, cells reach a much higher biomass in stationary phase (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s001">Figure S1</xref>), likely resulting in complete depletion of some essential nutrient (possibly phosphorous in a nitrogen-rich medium such as LB) that, in contrast, would still be present in cultures grown in oxygen-limiting conditions, thus preventing induction of PHA biosynthesis.</p><fig id="pone-0093009-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093009.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>TEM observation of ultrathin sections of paraffin-embedded BtCDC272 grown in different conditions.</title><p>Arrows point to PHA granules. The 1 &#x003bc;m scale bar is shown in the left bottom corner of each panel.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0093009.g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Growth in Oxygen Limitation Stimulates EPS Production</title><p>RNA-seq experiments showed induction of several genes involved in LPS and/or EPS biosynthesis in response to oxygen limitation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). To confirm this result, we isolated cell surface-associated polysaccharides from BtCDC272 grown in different conditions by EDTA extraction, and quantified their amounts, using the phenol/sulfuric acid determination as described in <italic>Methods</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). Amounts of EPS were roughly similar in BtCDC272 cultures grown either at 28&#x000b0;C or at 37&#x000b0;C in aerobic conditions (1.4 ng/10<sup>6</sup> cfu versus 1.8 ng/10<sup>6</sup> cfu, respectively), while, in contrast, they were significantly higher (5.6 ng/10<sup>6</sup> cfu) at 37&#x000b0;C in oxygen-limiting conditions. We investigated whether the higher amount of cell surface-associated polysaccharides in BtCDC272 cultures grown in oxygen limitation could be ascribed to any specific cell structure. Indeed, SDS-tricine gels of cell-surface associated polysaccharides show a clear increase in production of LPS core (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g006">Figure 6B</xref>). Interestingly, increased LPS core production was only detected in the fraction obtained by EDTA treatment, while analysis of total cellular LPS did not show any significant difference in any growth condition tested (data not shown). Enhanced production of LPS core would be in agreement with RNA-seq data, which showed an anoxia-dependent increase in transcription levels for two LPS biosynthetic operons (BTH_I1470-1478 and BTH_I2035-2039, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0093009-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093009.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>EPS/LPS determination.</title><p><bold>A</bold>) Quantitative determination of cell surface-associated polysaccharides using the phenol/sulfuric acid method. Values are the average of six measurements (two repeats for three independent cultures) and standard deviations are shown. Statistical analysis (two-tailed Student&#x02019;s t test) of the results provided a p value&#x0003c;0.0001 (indicated by the three asterisks in the figure). <bold>B</bold>) PAGE analysis of cell surface-associated polysaccharides. The main band detected by silver staining, is indicated by the arrow. PAGE analysis of cell surface-associated polysaccharides from three independent BtCDC272 cultures gave very similar results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0093009.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2i"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> Interaction of BtCDC272 Grown in Different Conditions with Innate Myeloid Cells</title><p>Our results show that growth at 37&#x000b0;C and oxygen limitation, <italic>i.e.</italic>, environmental cues similar to those encountered upon contact to the human host, can affect a variety of cellular processes in BtCDC272. To investigate whether such changes in BtCDC272 cell physiology could impact its interaction with neutrophils, we measured <italic>in vitro</italic> uptake of BtCDC272 grown in different conditions by human neutrophils in whole blood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g007">Figure 7</xref>). We monitored BtCDC272 uptake at two Multiplicities of Infection (10 and 100 M.O.I.) and at two different incubation times (15 and 30 minutes); BtCDC272 grown at 37&#x000b0;C in aerobic conditions was used as reference condition in these experiments. Similar levels of phagocytosis were obtained at 15 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g007">Figure 7</xref>) and 30 minutes (data not shown), suggesting that bacterial uptake by neutrophils has already reached the plateau at 15 min. In comparison to cultures grown at 37&#x000b0;C, cells grown at 28&#x000b0;C, and thus characterized by increased flagellar production, were phagocytosed by human neutrophils with similar efficiency (MFI 34054&#x000b1;4325 <italic>vs</italic> 33789&#x000b1;4965 at 100 M.O.I, 15 min; Mean &#x000b1; SEM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g007">Figure 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s003">Figure S3</xref>). Only at 10 M.O.I. at 15 minutes did we detect a slight, although statistically significant, increase in BtCDC272 phagocytosis (24% increase, p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.02). In contrast, growing BtCDC272 in oxygen limitation significantly affected its phagocytosis by neutrophils at both incubation times and both M.O.I. tested (MFI 34054&#x000b1;4325 <italic>vs</italic> 21540&#x000b1;2837 at 100 M.O.I, 15 min; Mean &#x000b1; SEM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g007">Figure 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s003">Figure S3</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0093009-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093009.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><italic>In vitro</italic> phagocytosis of BtCDC272 grown in different conditions by neutrophils in whole blood.</title><p><italic>In vitro</italic> phagocytosis of BtCDC (10 and 100 M.O.I) by human neutrophils of two donors was determined by FACS analysis at 15 min. Data are expressed as the percentage of control MFI. The mean value &#x000b1; SEM is shown. *<italic>p</italic>&#x02264;0.05; **<italic>p</italic>&#x02264;0.01; ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02264;0.001; two-tailed Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test. 0. Results for each donor, expressed as MFI, are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s003">Figure S3</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0093009.g007"/></fig><p>To further evaluate possible effects of BtCDC272 on the inflammatory response, we monitored cytokine production in the culture supernatant of the mouse macrophage cell line RAW264.7 exposed to BtCDC272 grown in different conditions. Commercial preparation of <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS was used as positive control in macrophage activation experiments. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g008">Figure 8</xref>, exposure of macrophages to BtCDC272 grown in oxygen-limiting conditions resulted in a stronger secretion of tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-&#x003b1;, interleukin 6 (IL-6), and chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 2 (CXCL2), also known as macrophage inflammatory protein (MIP)-2. In particular, exposure to BtCDC272 grown in anoxic conditions triggered a dramatic increase in IL-6 production (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g008">Figure 8B</xref>). Macrophage viability was not significantly affected by exposure to BtCDC272, regardless of pre-growth conditions (data not shown), indicating that differences in cytokine production were indeed due to different levels of macrophage activation.</p><fig id="pone-0093009-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093009.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Cytokine production by mouse macrophage cell line RAW264.7 exposed to BtCDC272 grown in different conditions and at different M.O.I.</title><p>Confluent monolayers of cells were incubated with bacteria cultured at the indicated conditions. Bacteria were added at MOI of 0.005, 0.05, 0.5 or 5 for 4 hours to confluent monolayers of RAW264.7 cells. LPS (100 ng/ml from <italic>E. coli</italic> Serotype 055:B5; Sigma-Aldrich) was used as positive control of macrophage activation. Murine CXCL2, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-6 levels were measured in cell supernatants by ELISA Results are mean&#x000b1; SEM of two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0093009.g008"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this work, we have studied the <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> strain BtCDC272, a clinical isolate identified as the etiologic agent of a pleural infection in a 76-year old male <xref rid="pone.0093009-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Since <italic>B. thailandensis</italic>, unlike its closely related species <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>, is normally non-pathogenic for humans, the BtCDC272 strain represents an intriguing example of a &#x0201c;transition state&#x0201d; between an environmental bacterium and a human pathogen. Analysis of its genome sequence did not provide any clear hint to its pathogenic potential: results of the genomic analysis confirmed that BtCDC272 produces an EPS more typical of strictly environmental <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> strains, rather than the Bp-like capsule polysaccharide produced by other <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> clinical isolates <xref rid="pone.0093009-Sim1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, thus suggesting that, in <italic>B. thailandensis,</italic> capsule production is not essential for pathogenesis in humans. Interestingly, several BtCDC272 genomic elements not present in the environmental isolate BtE264 were conserved in another clinical isolate, CDC3015869, including a putative prophage genome; although none of the 19 prophage-like genes show any clear homology to known virulence genes, it could be interesting to further evaluate the possible role of prophage-like sequences, which often carry pathogenesis-related genes, in <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> virulence. We then focused our investigation on the effects of different growth temperatures and oxygen availability, environmental signals associated to colonization of the human host, on gene expression and production of cell surface-associated proteins in BtCDC272. Our results suggest that temperature sensing plays a major role in flagellar production and cellular motility (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g004">Figure 4</xref>), through a mechanism involving regulation of <italic>fliC</italic> gene expression at the mRNA stability level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g004">Figure 4D</xref>). Downregulation of flagellar expression at 37&#x000b0;C has been observed in human pathogens, like in <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Kamp1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, and it is considered a strategy to prevent recognition of the highly antigenic flagellar structure by the host immune system. In contrast, mutations affecting flagellar motility reduce virulence both in <italic>B. cepacia</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Tomich1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> and in <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0093009-Chua1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. In <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>, flagellar motility seems to be important for virulence when mice are infected via intranasal, but not intraperitoneal, route <xref rid="pone.0093009-Chua1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0093009-Chuaygud1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Interestingly, however, the only obligate pathogen in the <italic>Burkholderia</italic> genus, <italic>B. mallei</italic>, is non-motile, likely as a result of pathoadaptive mutations inactivating its flagellar genes <xref rid="pone.0093009-Galyov1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Thus, pathogenic <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species appear to have adopted very different strategies in terms of utilization of flagellar motility during host infection. Temperature-dependent downregulation of flagellar genes is also present in <italic>B. pseudomallei,</italic> as determined by recent gene expression studies <xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, although with little or no effect on cell motility (<xref rid="pone.0093009-DeShazer1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref> and our unpublished data). It could be speculated that modulation of flagella production at 37&#x000b0;C might somehow reduce the load of antigenic presentation to the host, without complete loss of cell motility, needed for host infection. In the BtCDC272 strain studied in our work, cellular motility appears to be the main cellular process affected by growth at 37&#x000b0;C versus growth at 28&#x000b0;C; indeed, apart from flagellar and chemotaxis genes, most of the genes showing reduced expression at 37&#x000b0;C belong to energy generation systems (<italic>e.g.</italic>, ATP synthase, nitrate and nitrous oxide reduction; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>), which might reflect an increased ATP requirement by the cell at 28&#x000b0;C due to higher flagellar activity. Interestingly, of the two operons encoding two distinct ATP synthase complexes present in the <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> genome, only the one located on Chromosome 2 was co-regulated with flagellar production and activity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>). In contrast, the ATP synthase operon located on Chromosome 1 showed co-regulation with genes involved in primary metabolism (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>), thus suggesting possible functional specialization of the two ATP synthase complexes.</p><p>Growth in oxygen-limiting conditions showed a broader impact on BtCDC272 cell physiology, in terms of overall number of differentially expressed genes as well as of cellular processes affected (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). Both RNA-seq and proteome analysis showed that protein secretion systems, an extracellular metalloprotease, and siderophore biosynthetic enzymes, are activated in response to anoxia (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>), suggesting that lack of oxygen might represent an important environmental signal for cellular processes linked to virulence. Interestingly, among the six T6SS present in the <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> genome, we found that only the one encoded by genes BTH_I2959-BTH_I2965 was activated by anoxia (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). However, extracellular protein components of this T6SS complex (BTH_I2962-2963) were also found in higher amounts in the OMPs of BtCDC272 grown at 37&#x000b0;C compared to 28&#x000b0;C, although no difference in transcription level of the corresponding genes was observed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t001">Table 1</xref>), suggesting that this T6SS might be subject to various forms of regulation in response to either temperature or oxygen limitation. This is in line with several observations suggesting that expression of T6SS-encoding genes in the <italic>Burkholderia</italic> genus is strongly dependent on environmental cues: for instance, a recent work has shown that expression of the cluster 1 T6SS in <italic>B. mallei</italic> (BMAA0730-0744) is activated by the two component regulatory system VirAG in response to lack of divalent metals such as iron and zinc <xref rid="pone.0093009-Burtnick1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>; in contrast, another study on <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> reports that genes encoding two distinct T6SS are not transcribed in any of the 66 different <italic>in vitro</italic> conditions tested, suggesting that they are only expressed <italic>in vivo</italic>, possibly during macrophage infection <xref rid="pone.0093009-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>.</p><p>Another important effect of oxygen limitation was the increase in expression of genes and proteins involved in primary metabolism, such as transcription and translation, ATP synthesis (operon located on Chromosome 1), and nucleotide biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). However, anoxia-dependent increase in transcription of primary metabolism genes, such as the ribosomal protein-encoding genes <italic>rplR</italic> and <italic>rplW</italic>, is restricted to their residual expression levels observed in stationary phase, as their maximal expression occurs, consistent with their functional role, during exponential growth in aerobic conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g004">Figure 4</xref>). In our work, we compared cells that have entered stationary phase due to exhaustion of different elements, <italic>i.e.</italic>, oxygen in case of anoxic conditions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s001">Figure S1B</xref>) and another nutrient, possibly phosphorous, in aerobic cells. This results in strong differences in stationary phase metabolism, such as PHA accumulation, exclusive of aerobically-grown cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g005">Figure 5</xref>), or higher residual levels of protein synthesis and primary metabolism, observed in oxygen limitation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g002">Figures 2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g003">3</xref>).</p><p>Anoxic conditions strongly increased expression of genes involved in LPS/EPS production and in the biosynthesis of their precursors (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093009-t002">Table 2</xref>). High expression level for LPS-related genes in response to oxygen limitation was confirmed by direct observation, on SDS-PAGE, of increased LPS core production (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g006">Figure 6</xref>). Interestingly, increase of LPS core production in response to anoxia was only detected in the cell surface fraction released upon mild EDTA treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g006">Figure 6B</xref>): this would suggest that excess LPS core is loosely attached to the cell membrane, possibly due to active shedding from the bacterium. It is noteworthy that, in <italic>B. cepacia</italic>, genes involved in EPS biosynthesis are also induced in response to oxygen limitation <xref rid="pone.0093009-Pessi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>; thus, induction of cell surface-associated polysaccharides in response to anoxia might be a conserved mechanism in different <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species. It would be tempting to speculate that increase in LPS production in BtCDC272 grown in oxygen limiting conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g006">Figure 6B</xref>) might be the main trigger for the strong production of inflammatory mediators observed in macrophages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g008">Figure 8</xref>). In addition to cytokine induction, neutrophil phagocytosis of BtCDC272 grown in oxygen limitation was also dampened (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g007">Figure 7</xref>), suggesting that growth in anaerobic conditions might increase virulence of BtCDC272. Our results about interaction between BtCDC272 and host innate cellular immunity also reiterate that, to fully evaluate interaction of bacteria with eukaryotic cells <italic>in vitro</italic>, it might be advisable to pre-grow them in conditions reflecting the host-bacterial interaction. We propose that oxygen limitation might take place upon ingestion of <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> by nematodes and other invertebrates, and it might therefore have evolved into an important environmental cue for active production of core LPS, which, through its endotoxin activity, might significantly contribute to virulence in these hosts.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Bacterial Growth Conditions and Motility Assays</title><p>For global gene and protein expression profiles analysis, BtCDC272 was grown in Luria Bertani (LB) broth in flasks filled for 1/5 of their volume and shaken at a rotation speed of 150 rpm, either at 28&#x000b0;C or 37&#x000b0;C. Oxygen-limiting conditions were obtained by growing BtCDC272 in the same conditions but with no shaking. The dissolved oxygen (DO) concentration was evaluated with a CellOx 325 membrane covered galvanic DO cell (WTW Scientific). The sensor was calibrated at the experimental temperature, which was controlled and monitored throughout the measurements. The DO values for LB medium prior to bacterial inoculums are in the range of the maximum DO for water (6.71 mg/l at 37&#x000b0;C).</p><p>Separate sets of cultures were used for each experiment performed in this study (RNAseq, proteomic analysis, qRT-PCR, electron microscopy observations, flagellar motility assays, EPS determination, interaction with blood cells). For each experiment, both &#x0201c;biological&#x0201d; (<italic>i.e.</italic>, different bacterial cultures) and &#x0201c;technical&#x0201d; replicates (<italic>i.e.</italic>, multiple measurements performed on the same biological sample) were obtained (see description of specific experiments for further details).</p><p>For motility test assays, 5 &#x003bc;l of BtCDC272 overnight cultures were inoculated on LB medium supplemented with 0.4% agar and incubated either at 28&#x000b0;C or 37&#x000b0;C for 16 hours. TEM analysis was performed as follows: 10 &#x003bc;l of an overnight culture of BtCDC272 grown either at 28&#x000b0;C or 37&#x000b0;C was absorbed on 300 mesh formvar/carbon copper grids; after 20 minutes the excess sample was dried with a filter paper and grids were negatively stained with 2% uranyl acetate. Sample observation was carried out at EFTEM Leo912 ab (Zeiss) transmission electron microscope operating at 80 kV and digital images were recorded by a Proscan 1 K CCD camera (Olympus).</p><p>For TEM observation of Epon resin-embedded samples, overnight cultures were centrifuged 30 minutes at 6000 <italic>g</italic>, resuspended in 2.5% gluteraldehyde in 0.1 M sodium cacodylate, incubated at ambient temperature for 15 minutes, centrifuged at 20000 <italic>g</italic> for 10 minutes. After an overnight incubation at 4&#x000b0;C, samples were treated with 1% OsO<sub>4</sub> in distilled water for 30 min on ice in darkness. Finally, cells were dehydrated in a graded ethanol series (70, 80, 90, 96, and 100% ethanol), gradually infiltrated with Epon resin, sectioned (80-nm sections) using a Reichert Ultracut E Microtome (Leica Microsystems, Vienna, Austria), and collected on carbon-Formvar-coated 100-mesh hexagonal copper grids.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Nucleic Acid Extractions</title><p>Genomic DNA from 1 ml of bacterial cultures was extracted with the GeneElute Bacterial Genomic DNA Kit (SIGMA), quantified using NanoDrop spectrophotometer (Nanodrop Technologies), and its integrity was evaluated by agarose gel electrophoresis. For RNA-seq experiments, total RNA was extracted and treated as previously described <xref rid="pone.0093009-Peano1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Total RNA extraction for qRT-PCR was performed using RNeasy minikit (QIAGEN) from 1 ml of BtCDC272 overnight cultures (ca. 16 hours growth, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s001">Figure S1</xref>). RNA samples were checked by agarose gel electrophoresis to assess the lack of degradation and then quantified with NanoDrop spectrophotometer. Genomic DNA degradation and reverse transcription were performed on 1 &#x003bc;g of total RNA using QuantiTect Reverse Transcription kit (QIAGEN).</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Genomic DNA Sequencing and Data Analysis</title><p>The library for genomic DNA sequencing was prepared according to the TruSeq DNA Sample preparation protocol (Illumina). Briefly, 1 &#x003bc;g of genomic DNA was sonicated to fragments with a medium length of 400 bp; after end repair, indexed adapters were ligated at DNA fragment ends, libraries were quantified using a quantification Real Time PCR (qPCR) by KAPA Library Quant Kits (KAPA Biosystems). After a short amplification step the library was sequenced on a Illumina Genome Analyzer IIx sequencer to generate 86 bp paired-end reads.</p><p>Paired-end reads were aligned against BtE264 genome (Ref Seq accession number: NC_007651 and NC_007650) using the aligner tool BWA <xref rid="pone.0093009-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref> allowing up to 5 mismatches. High-quality alignment files (HQ-BAM) were generated by removing duplicates reads and by filtering-out reads with mapping quality less than 15 with samtools v0.1.19 <xref rid="pone.0093009-Li2" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. HQ-BAM statistics on genome coverage and read depth were calculated using BEDTools <xref rid="pone.0093009-Quinlan1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> using annotation files provided by Burkholderia Genome database <xref rid="pone.0093009-Winsor1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Single nucleotide variations (SNVs) were called using samtools v0.1.19 <xref rid="pone.0093009-Li2" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> filtering out those variations with a depth less than 20 reads and variant annotation were carried out using annovar <xref rid="pone.0093009-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. <italic>De novo</italic> assembly of short reads was performed with AbySS <xref rid="pone.0093009-Simpson1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. In brief, the reads were assembled with different k-mers (from 41 to 64) and the assembly with k&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;45 were chosen as optimal assembly for our dataset. Afterward, the contigs were annotated using FgenesB (Softberry) with default parameters and all the CDS deriving from automatic annotation were compared with BtE264 CDSs using BLAST suite.</p><p>The genomic data are available in Sequence Reads Archive (SRA) accession number <underline>SRR988099</underline>.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>RNA Sequencing and Data Analysis</title><p>RNA was extracted from two separate sets of BtCDC272 overnight cultures grown at 28&#x000b0;C, 37&#x000b0;C and 37&#x000b0;C anoxic. RNA samples with RNA Integrity Number (RIN) higher than 8 were employed for the RNA-Seq experiment. mRNA was enriched by removing ribosomal RNA using MICROBExpress kit (Ambion, Austin, TX); 500 ng were used for the preparation of cDNA libraries using the Ovation Prokaryotic RNA-seq System, which uses random primers selectively designed to avoid rRNA amplification. Then, 200 ng of double stranded cDNA were used to prepare NGS library with NuGEN&#x02019;s Encore NGS Library System, according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Due to the small size of cDNA obtained, no fragmentation treatment was performed prior to library preparation, as suggested by NuGEN&#x02019;s instructions. Each sample was prepared as a replicate and sequenced. Sequencing was performed using the Illumina Genome Analyzer IIx platform to generate paired-end 48 bp reads <xref rid="pone.0093009-Peano1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s009">File S5</xref>).</p><p>Transcriptome reads were extracted using GERALD software and mapped on BtE264 genome by BWA applying the same parameters used for the genomic alignment. Read count for gene relative abundance, differential expression analysis and statistical analysis were performed as described <xref rid="pone.0093009-Peano1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Differential expression analysis was performed on a subset of 4658 CDSs (representing more than 80% of all the BtE264 CDSs) commonly above the Detection Threshold (7 reads) in all the growing conditions analyzed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s009">File S5</xref>). The transcriptomic data are available in Sequence Reads Archive (SRA) accession number <underline>SRR988099</underline>.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Multidimensional Protein Identification Technology (MudPIT) Analysis</title><p>The enrichment procedure for outer membrane proteins was basically carried out using the N-lauroylsarcosinate method as described <xref rid="pone.0093009-Gualdi1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Proteins were extracted from two separate cultures for each growth conditions, and analyzed separately. Outer membrane samples were first treated with RapiGest SF (Waters Corporation) at a final concentration of 0.2% (w/v). After incubation at 100&#x000b0;C for 5 min, the samples were cooled to room temperature and digested with trypsin (Sequencing Grade Modified Trypsin, Promega) as described previously <xref rid="pone.0093009-Comunian1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Trypsin-digested samples were divided in half and analyzed as technical replicates by two-dimensional micro-liquid chromatography coupled to ion trap mass spectrometry (2DC-MS/MS) using ProteomeX-2 configuration (Thermo Electron Corporation, San Jos&#x000e8;, CA, USA), according to <xref rid="pone.0093009-Palma1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. In particular, peptides were eluted using eight steps of increasing ammonium chloride concentration (0, 20, 40, 80, 120, 200, 400, 700 mM).</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Mass Spectrometry Data Handling for MudPIT Analysis</title><p>The experimental mass spectra produced by MudPIT analyses were correlated to tryptic peptide sequences by comparing with theoretical mass spectra, obtained by <italic>in silico</italic> digestion of BtCDC272 protein database. Data processing was performed using the 3.3.1. Bioworks version, based on SEQUEST algorithm (Thermo Finnigan Corp.), and parameters previously reported <xref rid="pone.0093009-Regonesi1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>.</p><p>The SEQUEST output were treated with an in-house software called MAProMa (Multidimensional Algorithm Protein Map) <xref rid="pone.0093009-Mauri2" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>: specific tools inserted in MAProMa permit the alignment of protein lists of replicate analyses, the evaluation of identification frequency and the subsequent comparison among the different conditions analyzed. Differentially expressed proteins are estimated by means of two algorithms of MAProMa, DAve (Differential Average), measuring changes in expression levels, and DCI (Differential Coefficient Index), measuring total protein amount in a given sample <xref rid="pone.0093009-Mauri1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. A DAve value either &#x0003e;0.1 or &#x0003c;&#x02212;0.1 is an indication of different relative expression level between two samples, while a DAve value either&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;200 or&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;&#x02212;200 indicates exclusive presence of a protein in only one sample. Only proteins showing significant DAve values and identical trends in at least 3 out of 4 analyses (two technical replicates of samples from two independent cultures) were considered as differentially expressed.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>qRT-PCR and mRNA Decay Experiments</title><p>qRT-PCR was performed as previously described <xref rid="pone.0093009-Gualdi1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. The primers used are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093009.s004">Table S1</xref>. All reactions were performed at least four times (duplicate repeats on RNA extractions from two independent cultures); RNA samples not treated with reverse transcriptase, used as negative controls, never showed significant threshold cycles. The relative amounts of the transcripts were determined using as reference genes 16S rRNA; for experiments shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g002">Figure 2</xref>, a different set of experiments using the the <italic>aceA</italic> mRNA as reference gene gave very similar results (data not shown). mRNA decay experiments on the <italic>fliC</italic> transcript were carried out using qRT-PCR as described <xref rid="pone.0093009-Wang2" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Briefly, RNA was extracted from bacterial cultures in exponential phase (OD600 nm&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.8); rifampicin at a 100 &#x003bc;g/ml final concentration was added at time 0, and additional samples (1 ml each from a 25 ml-culture grown in a 100 ml-flask) were taken at 2, 4, 7, 10, 15 and 20 minutes, and immediately processed as for standard qRT-PCR experiments. 16S rRNA was used as reference gene and, as expected, did not show any observable changes in threshold cycles following rifampicin treatment.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>Cell Surface-associated Polysaccharide Extraction and Extracellular Polysaccharide Analysis</title><p>Bacterial cultures grown in different conditions were normalized to OD600&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.5 and 100 ml of normalized cultures were centrifuged at 5000 rpm for 15 min at room temperature. Bacterial cells were resuspended in 2% EDTA (2 ml) and incubated for 4 h at 4&#x000b0;C under slight agitation. The suspension was centrifuged as above, and the supernatant was collected and filtered at 0.45 &#x003bc;m. Total sugar quantification was performed using the phenol-H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> method <xref rid="pone.0093009-Dubois1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. After sugar quantification, samples were dried under vacuum and the lyophilized material was suspended in polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) sample buffer. LPS was separated by Tricine-sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS)-PAGE and silver stained <xref rid="pone.0093009-Maskell1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. Both sugar quantification and PAGE analysis were performed on three separate cultures for each growth condition, always with identical results.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title><italic>B. thailandensis</italic> Phagocytosis Assay by Neutrophils in Fresh Human Blood</title><p>Phagocytosis assay of BtCDC272 by human neutrophils was performed as recently described <xref rid="pone.0093009-Moalli1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. Bacteria were pre-cultured in different growth conditions as described above and labeled with CFSE-mixed isomers (Invitrogen). 10<sup>8</sup> bacteria were incubated for 1 h at room temperature with 5 &#x003bc;l CFSE 5 mM in 100 &#x003bc;l HBSS, extensively washed and resuspended in PBS with Ca<sup>2+</sup>/Mg<sup>2+</sup>. Labelling was controlled by FACS analysis. A total of 10<sup>7</sup> (multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 10) or 10<sup>8</sup> (MOI 100) CFSE-labelled BtCDC272 were added to 200 &#x003bc;l of whole blood (collected with heparin) and incubated for either 15 min or 30 min at 37&#x000b0;C in an orbital shaker. Human blood (3 ml/donor) was collected from 3 healthy blood donors after verbal consent. Written consent was not considered necessary by the institutional review board due to the lack of risk and invasiveness of the procedures involved. Participant consent was documented in the laboratory records. This study and the consent procedure were approved by the ethics committee of the Istituto Clinico Humanitas, Rozzano, Italy (14-11-2012). Samples were immediately placed on ice to block phagocytosis, and red blood cells were lysed by adding cold ammonium chloride lysis solution (3 ml, pH 7.2). Cells were stained with PerCP&#x02013;anti-CD45 (BD Biosciences), fixed in 4% formaldehyde and CFSE mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) was analyzed in human neutrophils (CD45-positive cells, neutrophils defined as FSC-A<sup>high</sup>/SSC-A<sup>high</sup>) by FACS analysis <xref rid="pone.0093009-Moalli1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Murine Macrophages Activation and Cytokine Quantification by <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> Grown in Different Conditions</title><p>Mouse macrophage cell line RAW264.7 was cultured in RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 10% Fetal Calf Serum and 2 mM L-glutamine (all from Invitrogen). Confluent monolayers of cells were incubated with bacteria cultured at the indicated conditions. Bacteria were added at MOI of 0.005, 0.05, 0.5 or 5 for 4 hours. LPS (100 ng/ml from <italic>E. coli</italic> Serotype 055:B5; Sigma-Aldrich) was used as positive control of macrophage activation. Murine CXCL2, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-6 levels were measured in cell supernatants by ELISA (R&#x00026;D DuoSet ELISA Development System) according to manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Macrophage viability was determined as described previously <xref rid="pone.0093009-Moalli1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><bold>Growth curves and dissolved oxygen determination.</bold>
<bold>A</bold> Growth curves of BtCDC272 at 28&#x000b0;C (circles), 37&#x000b0;C (closed squares) and 37&#x000b0;C anoxic (open triangles). Data are from a typical experiment. Growth curves were repeated at least six times; standard deviations were less than 5%. <bold>B</bold>. Oxygen concentrations in liquid medium in cells grown at 37&#x000b0;C aerobically (squares) or in oxygen-limiting conditions (triangles). Dissolved oxygen values were determined as described in <italic>Methods</italic>.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><bold>Functional enrichment of Differentially Expressed Genes (DEGs).</bold> A) Functional categories enriched in 37&#x000b0;C vs 28&#x000b0;C DEGs list B) Functional categories enriched in 37&#x000b0;C An vs 37&#x000b0;C DEGs list. Dark blue columns represent BtCDC272 DEGs, and red columns indicate all BtE264 genes belonging to each functional category. (*P&#x0003c;0.05 or **P&#x0003c;0.01, binomial test; after Bonferroni correction).</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><bold><italic>In vitro</italic> phagocytosis of BtCDC (10 and 100 M.O.I) by human neutrophils measured in each of the two donors.</bold> Values are indicated in MFI. The average data, expressed as the percentage of control MFI, is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093009-g007">Figure 7</xref>.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s003.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s004"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><bold>Primers used for qRT-PCR experiments.</bold> Coordinates refer to the BtE264 genome.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s004.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s005"><label>File S1</label><caption><p><bold>0X coverage region statistics and overlapping with Gi and nGi previously published.</bold> i) sheet: &#x0201c;novel 0X coverage regions&#x0201d; contains the list of the regions with 0X coverage with respect to the BtE264 genome not including in the Gi-nGi dataset <xref rid="pone.0093009-Sim1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. ii) sheet: &#x0201c;0X coverage regions in Gi-nGi&#x0201d; contains the list of the regions with 0X coverage with respect to the BtE264 genome that are included in the Gi-nGi dataset <xref rid="pone.0093009-Sim1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s005.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s006"><label>File S2</label><caption><p><bold>List of the 929 CDS specific for BtCDC272 and relative annotation predicted by FGENESB.</bold></p><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s006.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s007"><label>File S3</label><caption><p><bold>List of the 331 BtCDC272-specific genes showing high similarity to CDS from a <italic>Burkholderia</italic> database containing 98044 protein sequences from 4 <italic>B. mallei</italic>, 9 <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> and 3 <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> strains other than BtE264.</bold></p><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s007.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s008"><label>File S4</label><caption><p><bold>Non-synonymous SNVs distribution inside all the CDSs belonging to the Bt-EPS cluster and relative mutation rate evaluation.</bold></p><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s008.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s009"><label>File S5</label><caption><p><bold>RNA-seq mapping statistics, rRNA removal efficiency and analysis of gene detection sensitivity.</bold></p><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s009.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s010"><label>File S6</label><caption><p><bold>List of all the 416 Differentially Expressed Genes (DEGs) (p-val&#x02264;0.01 and log<sub>2</sub> fold change &#x02265;1 or log<sub>2</sub> fold change &#x02264;&#x02212;1) in the of 37&#x000b0;C versus 28&#x000b0;C comparison.</bold></p><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s010.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s011"><label>File S7</label><caption><p><bold>List of all the 618 Differentially Expressed Genes (DEGs) (p-val&#x02264;0.01 and log<sub>2</sub> fold change &#x02265;1 or log<sub>2</sub> fold change &#x02264;&#x02212;1) in the 37&#x000b0;C An versus 37&#x000b0;C comparison.</bold></p><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s011.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s012"><label>File S8</label><caption><p><bold>List of all the 54 Outer Membrane-associated proteins found to be differentially expressed in the 37&#x000b0;C versus 28&#x000b0;C comparison.</bold> Significant differential expression was defined as described in <italic>Methods</italic> (Differential Average: DAve&#x0003e;0.2 and DAve&#x0003c;&#x02212;0.2; Differential Coefficient Index: DCI&#x0003e;200 and DCI&#x0003c;&#x02212;200).</p><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s012.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0093009.s013"><label>File S9</label><caption><p><bold>List of all the 127 Outer Membrane-associated proteins found to be differentially expressed in the 37&#x000b0;C Anoxic versus 37&#x000b0;C comparison.</bold> Significant differential expression was defined as described in <italic>Methods</italic> (Differential Average: DAve&#x0003e;0.2 and DAve&#x0003c;&#x02212;0.2; Differential Coefficient Index: DCI&#x0003e;200 and DCI&#x0003c;&#x02212;200).</p><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0093009.s013.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank Nadia Santo (Interdepartimental Center of Advanced Microscopy, Universit&#x000e0; degli Studi di Milano) for TEM analysis and Maria Vurchio (Institute of Biomedical Technologies, National Research Council, Milan) for technical and administrative support.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0093009-Coenye1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Coenye</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vandamme</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Diversity and significance of <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species occupying diverse ecological niches</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12919407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Mahenthiralingam1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mahenthiralingam</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The multifarious, multireplicon <italic>Burkholderia cepacia</italic> complex</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>144</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15643431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-White1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Melioidosis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><volume>361</volume>: <fpage>1715</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12767750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Smith1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Angus</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wuthiekanun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Arabinose assimilation defines a nonvirulent biotype of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>65</volume>: <fpage>4319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9317042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Brett1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeShazer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title><italic>Burkholderia thailandensis</italic> sp. nov., a <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic>-like species</article-title>. <source>Int J Syst Bacteriol 48 Pt</source><volume>1</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>320</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Glass1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steigerwalt</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cavuoti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Pneumonia and septicemia caused by <italic>Burkholderia thailandensis</italic> in the United States</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source><volume>44</volume>: <fpage>4601</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17050819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Lertpatanasuwan1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lertpatanasuwan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sermsri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petkaseam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trakulsomboon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thamlikitkul</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Arabinose-positive <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> infection in humans: case report</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>28</volume>: <fpage>927</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10825075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Reckseidler1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reckseidler</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeShazer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sokol</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Detection of bacterial virulence genes by subtractive hybridization: identification of capsular polysaccharide of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> as a major virulence determinant</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>69</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11119486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Yu1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Genomic patterns of pathogen evolution revealed by comparison of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic>, the causative agent of melioidosis, to avirulent <italic>Burkholderia thailandensis</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16725056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Sim1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chantratita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nandi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tewhey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genomic acquisition of a capsular polysaccharide virulence cluster by non-pathogenic <italic>Burkholderia</italic> isolates</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>R89</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20799932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Wand1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wand</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Titball</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michell</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Macrophage and <italic>Galleria mellonella</italic> infection models reflect the virulence of naturally occurring isolates of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>, <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> and <italic>B. oklahomensis</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21241461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Kim1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ulrich</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarria</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Bacterial genome adaptation to niches: divergence of the potential virulence genes in three <italic>Burkholderia</italic> species of different survival strategies</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>174</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16336651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Galyov1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Galyov</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeShazer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Molecular insights into <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>Burkholderia mallei</italic> pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><volume>64</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20528691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-OQuinn1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Quinn</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiegand</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jeddeloh</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title><italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> kills the nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> using an endotoxin-mediated paralysis</article-title>. <source>Cell Microbiol</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11422081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Fisher1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ribot</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Applefeld</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeShazer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Madagascar hissing cockroach as a novel surrogate host for <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic>, <italic>B. mallei</italic> and <italic>B. thailandensis</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol</source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22892068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Pilatova1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pilatova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dionne</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title><italic>Burkholderia thailandensis</italic> is virulent in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e49745</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23209596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Jensen1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bjarnsholt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phipps</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Rapid necrotic killing of polymorphonuclear leukocytes is caused by quorum-sensing-controlled production of rhamnolipid by <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source><volume>153</volume>: <fpage>1329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17464047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Braaten1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Braaten</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Hydrology of inland brackishwater shrimp ponds in Chachoengsao, Thailand</article-title>. <source>Aquacultural engineering</source><volume>23</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>313</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Condon1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Condon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Squires</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Squires</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Control of rRNA transcription in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiol Rev</source><volume>59</volume>: <fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8531889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Chilcott1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chilcott</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Coupling of flagellar gene expression to flagellar assembly in <italic>Salmonella enterica serovar typhimurium</italic> and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><volume>64</volume>: <fpage>694</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11104815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Ooi1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nandi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kreisberg</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The Condition-Dependent Transcriptional Landscape of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source><volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e1003795</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24068961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Mauri1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mauri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scarpa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nascimbeni</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benazzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parmagnani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Identification of proteins released by pancreatic cancer cells by multidimensional protein identification technology: a strategy for identification of novel cancer markers</article-title>. <source>Faseb J</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15985535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Schwarz1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>West</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carl</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title><italic>Burkholderia</italic> type VI secretion systems have distinct roles in eukaryotic and bacterial cell interactions</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1001068</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20865170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-AlvarezOrtega1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alvarez-Ortega</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Responses of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> to low oxygen indicate that growth in the cystic fibrosis lung is by aerobic respiration</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>65</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17581126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Hamad1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hamad</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vazquez-Torres</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Adaptation and antibiotic tolerance of anaerobic <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic></article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><volume>55</volume>: <fpage>3313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21537012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Sass1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sass</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmerk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Agnoli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Norville</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eberl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The unexpected discovery of a novel low-oxygen-activated locus for the anoxic persistence of <italic>Burkholderia cenocepacia</italic></article-title>. <source>Isme J</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1568</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23486248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Nachin1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nachin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nannmark</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nystrom</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Differential roles of the universal stress proteins of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in oxidative stress resistance, adhesion, and motility</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>187</volume>: <fpage>6265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16159758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Soini1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Soini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Falschlehner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liedert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bernhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vuoristo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Norvaline is accumulated after a down-shift of oxygen in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> W3110</article-title>. <source>Microb Cell Fact</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18940002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Loferer1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Loferer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hammar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Normark</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Availability of the fibre subunit CsgA and the nucleator protein CsgB during assembly of fibronectin-binding curli is limited by the intracellular concentration of the novel lipoprotein CsgG</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>26</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9383186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Lacqua1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lacqua</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colangelo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martinotti</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Landini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Emergence of biofilm-forming subpopulations upon exposure of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> to environmental bacteriophages</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>72</volume>: <fpage>956</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16391144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Schell1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Outer membrane proteome of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>Burkholderia mallei</italic> from diverse growth conditions</article-title>. <source>J Proteome Res</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>2417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21391724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Zinn1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zinn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Witholt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Egli</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Occurrence, synthesis and medical application of bacterial polyhydroxyalkanoate</article-title>. <source>Adv Drug Deliv Rev</source><volume>53</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11733115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Pessi1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pessi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Braunwalder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grunau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Omasits</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ahrens</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Response of <italic>Burkholderia cenocepacia</italic> H111 to Micro-Oxia</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e72939</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24023794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Kamp1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kamp</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A protein thermometer controls temperature-dependent transcription of flagellar motility genes in <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Tomich1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tomich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herfst</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Role of flagella in host cell invasion by <italic>Burkholderia cepacia</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>70</volume>: <fpage>1799</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11895941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Chua1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Flagella are virulence determinants of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source><volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1622</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12654773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Chuaygud1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chuaygud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tungpradabkul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sirisinha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Utaisincharoen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A role of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> flagella as a virulent factor</article-title>. <source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>102</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue>: <fpage>S140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19121676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-DeShazer1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>DeShazer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carlyon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Mutagenesis of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> with Tn5-OT182: isolation of motility mutants and molecular characterization of the flagellin structural gene</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>179</volume>: <fpage>2116</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9079894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Burtnick1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Burtnick</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title><italic>Burkholderia mallei</italic> and <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> Cluster 1 Type VI Secretion System Gene Expression Is Negatively Regulated by Iron and Zinc</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e76767</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24146925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Peano1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pietrelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Consolandi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petiti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>An efficient rRNA removal method for RNA sequencing in GC-rich bacteria</article-title>. <source>Microb Inform Exp</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23294941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Li1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Li2"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wysoker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2078</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Quinlan1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>26</volume>: <fpage>841</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Winsor1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Winsor</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Khaira</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Rossum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whiteside</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Burkholderia</italic> Genome Database: facilitating flexible queries and comparative analyses</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>2803</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18842600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Wang1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hakonarson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>ANNOVAR: functional annotation of genetic variants from high-throughput sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>e164</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20601685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Simpson1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jackman</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>ABySS: a parallel assembler for short read sequence data</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19251739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Gualdi1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gualdi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tagliabue</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Landini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Biofilm formation-gene expression relay system in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: modulation of sigmaS-dependent gene expression by the CsgD regulatory protein via sigmaS protein stabilization</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>189</volume>: <fpage>8034</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17873038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Comunian1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Comunian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rusconi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Palma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brunetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Catalucci</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A comparative MudPIT analysis identifies different expression profiles in heart compartments</article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>2320</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21598388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Palma1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Samori</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cecchini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Atomistic simulations of 2D bicomponent self-assembly: from molecular recognition to self-healing</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source><volume>132</volume>: <fpage>17880</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17885</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21114285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Regonesi1"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Regonesi</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Del Favero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Basilico</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Briani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benazzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Analysis of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> RNA degradosome composition by a proteomic approach</article-title>. <source>Biochimie</source><volume>88</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16139413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Mauri2"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mauri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deho</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A proteomic approach to the analysis of RNA degradosome composition in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source><volume>447</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19161840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Wang2"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Babitzke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>CsrA post-transcriptionally represses pgaABCD, responsible for synthesis of a biofilm polysaccharide adhesin of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1648</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15916613</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Dubois1"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rebers</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1956</year>) <article-title>Colorimetric Method for Determination of Sugars and Related Substances</article-title>. <source>Analytical Chemistry</source><volume>28</volume>: <fpage>350</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>356</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Maskell1"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maskell</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The resolution of bacteroides lipopolysaccharides by polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis</article-title>. <source>J Med Microbiol</source><volume>34</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2030500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0093009-Moalli1"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moalli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deban</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zelante</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zagarella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Role of complement and Fc{gamma} receptors in the protective activity of the long pentraxin PTX3 against <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></article-title>. <source>Blood</source><volume>116</volume>: <fpage>5170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20829368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>