<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">G3 (Bethesda)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>G3: Genes|Genomes|Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2160-1836</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Genetics Society of America</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4978903</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">GGG_028878</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.116.028878</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Investigations</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Whole Genome Sequencing Identifies a Novel Factor Required for Secretory Granule Maturation in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kontur</surname><given-names>Cassandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn2"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn3"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Santosh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn2"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn4"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>Xun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>&#x02021;</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn2"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>Jonathan K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>&#x02021;</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>&#x000a7;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>Aaron P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>*</label>Department of Molecular Genetics and Cell Biology, The University of Chicago, Illinois 60637</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02020;</label>Department of Genetics, Stanford University, California 94305</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>&#x02021;</label>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Stanford University, California 94305</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>&#x000a7;</label>Department of Biology, Stanford University, California 94305</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="afn2" fn-type="equal"><label>1</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn id="afn3" fn-type="present-address"><label>2</label><p>Present address: Department of Genetics, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT 06510.</p></fn><fn id="afn4" fn-type="present-address"><label>3</label><p>Present address: Department of Cell Biology, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT 06520.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>4</label>Corresponding author: Department of Molecular Genetics and Cell Biology, The University of Chicago, 920 E. 58th Street, IL 60637. E-mail: <email>apturkew@uchicago.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2505</fpage><lpage>2516</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Kontur <italic>et al.</italic></copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="2505.pdf"/><abstract><p>Unbiased genetic approaches have a unique ability to identify novel genes associated with specific biological pathways. Thanks to next generation sequencing, forward genetic strategies can be expanded to a wider range of model organisms. The formation of secretory granules, called mucocysts, in the ciliate <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> relies, in part, on ancestral lysosomal sorting machinery, but is also likely to involve novel factors. In prior work, multiple strains with defects in mucocyst biogenesis were generated by nitrosoguanidine mutagenesis, and characterized using genetic and cell biological approaches, but the genetic lesions themselves were unknown. Here, we show that analyzing one such mutant by whole genome sequencing reveals a novel factor in mucocyst formation. Strain UC620 has both morphological and biochemical defects in mucocyst maturation&#x02014;a process analogous to dense core granule maturation in animals. Illumina sequencing of a pool of UC620 F2 clones identified a missense mutation in a novel gene called <italic>MMA1</italic> (<italic>M</italic>ucocyst <italic>ma</italic>turation). The defects in UC620 were rescued by expression of a wild-type copy of <italic>MMA1</italic>, and disrupting <italic>MMA1</italic> in an otherwise wild-type strain phenocopies UC620. The product of <italic>MMA1</italic>, characterized as a CFP-tagged copy, encodes a large soluble cytosolic protein. A small fraction of Mma1p-CFP is pelletable, which may reflect association with endosomes. The gene has no identifiable homologs except in other <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> species, and therefore represents an evolutionarily recent innovation that is required for granule maturation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>evolutionary cell biology</kwd><kwd>endomembranes</kwd><kwd>secretion</kwd><kwd>dense core</kwd><kwd>regulated exocytosis</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="80"/><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>All eukaryotes possess a network of membrane-bound organelles that underlie wide-ranging cellular activities. While the basic features of this network are conserved, there is phylogenetic evidence that specific pathways have tended to experience high levels of innovation over evolutionary time, including pathways directly involved in protein secretion (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Kienle <italic>et al.</italic> 2009a</xref>, <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">2009b</xref>; <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Kloepper <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Dacks and Field 2007</xref>). From a cell biological perspective, such innovations are interesting because they may underlie specialized secretory responses. Dense core granules (DCGs) in animal cells are secretory organelles that are adapted for the storage of bioactive peptides (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Guest <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Kelly 1991</xref>). These peptides can subsequently be released in response to extracellular stimuli, a phenomenon called regulated exocytosis (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Burgoyne and Morgan 1993</xref>). Studies of DCG biogenesis, particularly in mammalian endocrine cells, have detailed a biosynthetic pathway in which newly formed DCGs undergo extensive maturation before they are competent for cargo exocytosis (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Morvan and Tooze 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Steiner 2011</xref>). Maturation involves pathway-specific machinery. For example, key proteases&#x02014;the prohormone convertases&#x02014;dedicated to generating bioactive peptides, were evolutionarily derived from a <italic>trans</italic>-Golgi network protease called KEX2/furin that is conserved within the Opisthokont lineage (including both fungi and animals) but not demonstrably present in other eukaryotic lineages (<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Steiner 2011</xref>, <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). More recently, genetic dissection of DCG biogenesis in invertebrates is uncovering numerous additional factors. Some of these are conserved within metazoa, without any clearly homologous genes in other lineages (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ailion <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Sumakovic <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Thus, mechanisms underlying the formation of DCGs in animals are likely to depend, in part, on lineage-restricted innovation.</p><p>Ciliates are a large clade of unicellular eukaryotes, many of which are striking in their behavioral and structural complexity. This complexity includes a remarkable array of secretory vesicles that contribute to functions including predation, predator deterrence, and encystation (<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Rosati and Modeo 2003</xref>). The ciliate vesicles show marked structural and functional similarities to metazoan DCGs (<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Turkewitz 2004</xref>). However, as members of the SAR (Stramenopile/Alveolate/Rhizaria) lineage, Ciliates are very distantly related to Opisthokonts (<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Parfrey <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). This immense evolutionary divergence raises the possibility that dense core granules in Ciliates could have arisen largely independently from those in animals (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Elde <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Lukes <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>).</p><p>Biochemical and other molecular data for ciliate granules are largely limited to two species belonging to the Oligohymenophorean branch: <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> and <italic>Paramecium tetraurelia</italic> (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Briguglio and Turkewitz 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Vayssie <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Lynn and Doerder 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Gentekaki <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). The ciliate granule cargo proteins, like many proteins in endocrine granules, are acidic, bind calcium with low affinity, and form large aggregates within the secretory pathway, suggesting that compartment-specific aggregation may be a widespread mechanism for sorting to secretory granules(<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Chanat <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Arvan and Castle 1992</xref>; <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Verbsky and Turkewitz 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Chilcoat <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Garreau de Loubresse 1993</xref>). Moreover, the ciliate proteins subsequently undergo proteolytic maturation via endo- and exoproteolytic processing, similar to cargo proteins in metazoan endocrine granules (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Madeddu <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Verbsky and Turkewitz 1998</xref>). However, neither the ciliate cargo proteins nor the processing enzymes are homologous to their functional counterparts in metazoans, suggesting that unrelated proteins evolved to produce similar functions within the secretory pathway (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Madeddu <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005b</xref>). That idea is also consistent with identification of a set of genes required in <italic>P. tetraurelia</italic> for granule exocytosis, which are lineage-restricted rather than conserved (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Bonnemain <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Gogendeau <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Froissard <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Skouri and Cohen 1997</xref>). Similarly, while <italic>T. thermophila</italic> and <italic>P. tetraurelia</italic> express large families of classical eukaryotic trafficking determinants such as Rab GTPases and SNAREs, they lack any clear homologs of some specific subtypes that are associated with secretory granules in metazoans (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Bright <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Schilde <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Bustos <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Taken together, the current data are consistent with the idea that similar functions in granule formation can be provided in ciliates and animals by paralogs that arose independently within the same gene families, or by unrelated genes.</p><p>One potentially powerful approach to expanding our catalog of genes involved in ciliate granulogenesis is forward genetics, which has provided a key tool in dissecting mechanisms of membrane trafficking in budding yeast and other organisms (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Novick and Schekman 1980</xref>; <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Horazdovsky <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>). Importantly, screens based on random mutagenesis are free of the bias inherent in candidate gene approaches. In <italic>T. thermophila</italic>, mutants with a variety of defects in secretory granule biogenesis have been generated using nitrosoguanidine, and characterized using genetic and cell biological approaches, but none of the underlying genetic lesions has been identified (<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Orias <italic>et al.</italic> 1983</xref>; <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Melia <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005a</xref>; <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Maihle and Satir 1985</xref>). However, advances in high throughput sequencing should make it possible to identify the causative mutations via whole genome comparisons, as has recently been demonstrated for a <italic>T. thermophila</italic> mutant in ciliary basal body orientation (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Galati <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).</p><p>The secretory granules in <italic>T. thermophila</italic>, called mucocysts, are filled primarily with proteins of the Grl (Granule lattice) family (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Cowan <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). The Grl proteins undergo proteolytic processing, which is required for morphological maturation of newly synthesized mucocysts (<xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Verbsky and Turkewitz 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Bradshaw <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Ding <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Collins and Wilhelm 1981</xref>). Mucocysts also contain a second family of abundant proteins(<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Haddad <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005b</xref>). The best-studied member is Grt1p (Granule tip), whose name derives from the polarized distribution of this protein in mature mucocysts (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005a</xref>). Both Grl proprotein processing, and Grt1p polarization, are largely blocked in an exocytosis-deficient mutant, generated by nitrosoguanidine mutagenesis, called UC620 (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005a</xref>). The UC620 mutation showed Mendelian inheritance expected for a recessive allele, and the mucocyst maturation defects were partially suppressed under starvation conditions (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005a</xref>). This suppression is potentially related to the notable upregulation of many genes involved in mucocyst biogenesis under starvation conditions, as judged by transcript abundance (Rahaman <italic>et al.</italic> 2009; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Briguglio <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). We have now used whole genome sequencing, applied to F2 progeny of UC620, to identify the genetic lesion in this mutant. Analysis of the gene, which we call <italic>MMA1</italic> for <italic>M</italic>ucocyst <italic>Ma</italic>turation 1, illustrates the power of forward genetics to uncover ciliate-restricted innovations required for secretory granule biogenesis.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2"><title>Cells and cell culture</title><p><italic>T. thermophila</italic> strains relevant to this work are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>. Unless otherwise stated, cells were cultured in SPP [2% proteose peptone, 0.2% dextrose, 0.1% yeast extract, 0.003% sequestrene (ferric ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid)] and starved in 10&#x000a0;mM Tris buffer, pH&#x000a0;7.4, both at 30&#x000b0; while shaking at 99&#x000a0;rpm. PP medium (2% proteose peptone, 0.003% sequestrene), for cells grown in 96-well plates, also included 250&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml penicillin G, 250&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml streptomycin sulfate, and 0.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml amphotericin B fungizone (Gibco). For most uses, cells were grown overnight to medium density (1.5&#x02013;3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml) in a volume of SPP equal to one-fifth of the nominal culture flask volume. Cell densities were determined using a Z1 Beckman Coulter Counter. Cells in 96-well or drop plates, including cells under drug selection, were grown for 3&#x000a0;d at 30&#x000b0; in moisture chambers. Scoring and screening of cells was done on an inverted microscope at 100&#x000d7; magnification.</p><table-wrap id="t1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Strains used in the work</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="12.14%" span="1"/><col width="38.36%" span="1"/><col width="17.15%" span="1"/><col width="10.32%" span="1"/><col width="22.03%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug Resistance [Micronuclear Genotype (Macronuclear Phenotype)]</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exocytosis Phenotype</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mating Type</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Notes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B2086</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mpr1-1/mpr1-1</italic> (mp-s)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exo<sup>+</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parental</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CU428</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mpr1-1/mpr1-1</italic> (mp-s)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exo<sup>+</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VII</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parental (mutagenized)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CU427</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>chx1-1/chx-1-1 (cy-s)</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exo<sup>+</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VI</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial outcross</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IA264</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>gal1-1/gal1-1 (dg-s)</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exo<sup>+</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcross, this paper</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">UC620</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>chx1-1/chx1-1;</italic></td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">exo<sup>-</sup></td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1"><italic>mpr1- 1/mpr1-1</italic> (cy-r, mp-r)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">F1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHX/chx1-1;MPR/mpr1-1; GAL/gal1-1,exo<sup>+</sup>/exo<sup>-</sup></td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">exo<sup>+</sup></td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">(cy-r, mp-r, dg-r)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="justify" scope="row" colspan="1">CU428 <italic>MMA1</italic>- CFP</td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1"><italic>mpr1-1/mpr1-1</italic> (mp-s); (cy-r)</td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">exo<sup>+</sup></td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">VII</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MMA1</italic>-CFP::rpL29 cy-R inducibly expressed in CU428</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">background</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="justify" scope="row" colspan="1">UC620 <italic>MMA1</italic>- CFP</td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1"><italic>chx1-1/chx1-1</italic>; <italic>mpr1- 1/mpr1-1</italic> (cy-r, mp-r); (cy- r)</td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">exo<sup>+</sup></td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MMA1</italic>-CFP::rpL29 cy-R inducibly expressed in UC620</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">background</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mpr1-1/mpr1-1</italic> (mp-s); (pmr-r)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exo<sup>-</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VII</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MMA1</italic> disruption by neo4, in CU428 background</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Genetic crosses</title><p>Cultures of strains to be mated were grown to 1.5&#x02013;3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml, washed twice, and resuspended in starvation medium, 10&#x000a0;mM Tris, pH&#x000a0;7.4, to a final density of 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml. Unless otherwise specified, cells were pelleted in 50&#x000a0;ml conical tubes at &#x0223c;600&#x02013;1000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic> for 1&#x000a0;min. Aliquots of 10&#x000a0;ml of cells were starved overnight (12&#x02013;18&#x000a0;hr) at 30&#x000b0; in 100&#x000a0;mm Petri dishes to initiate sexual reactivity. Equal volumes (5&#x000a0;ml) of cells to be mated were then gently mixed, within the 30&#x000b0; incubator, in a new Petri dish. Mating cells were incubated at 30&#x000b0; for 5&#x02013;8&#x000a0;hr in a moist chamber, and then refed with an equal volume of 2%&#x000a0;PP to generate karyonides (<xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Orias and Hamilton 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Orias <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Hamilton and Orias 2000</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Selecting progen</title><p>Beginning 1&#x000a0;hr after refeeding, single mating pairs were isolated by mouth pipetting into individual 30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l drops of SPP in a Petri dish containing 48 drops in an 8&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;6 grid array. To maximize the number and diversity of progeny established, exconjugants were also isolated by distributing 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l/well of mating pairs into a 96-well plate containing 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l/well SPP (<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Orias 2012</xref>). Cells were grown, then replicated into separate 96-well plates containing 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l/well 2%&#x000a0;PP supplemented with the appropriate drug to eliminate drug-sensitive parentals. Selection with cycloheximide (chx) and 6-methyl purine (6-mp) was on 15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml (both from 1000&#x000a0;&#x000d7; stock; chx stock in 100% methanol), paromomycin (pms) at 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml (from 1000&#x000a0;&#x000d7; stock), and 2-deoxygalactose (2-dgal) at 2.5 mg/ml (from 50&#x000a0;&#x000d7; stock)(<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Orias 2012</xref>). After 3&#x000a0;d growth, plates were scored for drug resistance to identify progeny. Cells selected with 2-dgal were scored after 7&#x000a0;d.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Obtaining drug-sensitive F1 assortants</title><p>In outcrosses where one parent contributed an allele conferring drug resistance (chx1-1), exconjugant progeny were initially heterozygous in both the MIC and MAC. Through phenotypic assortment, some subsequent vegetative progeny will lose all copies of the resistance allele in the MAC. We identified these progeny by serial passaging combined with drug sensitivity tests, as described in (Orias 2000).</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Mating type testing</title><p>Bacterized medium was prepared by adding <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> to a 25-ml flask of SPP, and growing overnight at 30&#x000b0; with shaking at 225&#x000a0;rpm. This culture was diluted 50-fold in sterile water to constitute 2% bacterized peptone (BP). Clones to be tested were replicated into a 96-well plate with 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l/well 2% BP and grown for 3&#x000a0;d. A 100-&#x003bc;l inoculum of each tester strain (MT II, III, IV, V, VI, or VII), taken from an overnight culture, was added to 10&#x000a0;ml 2% BP in Petri dishes and grown for 3&#x000a0;d. Tester strains were obtained from the Tetrahymena Stock Center (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://tetrahymena.vet.cornell.edu/">https://tetrahymena.vet.cornell.edu/</ext-link>). At that time, 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l/well of the tester strains were added separately to each unknown, and plates were incubated at 30&#x000b0;. A control matrix of each tester separately mated to each of the others and itself was also included. Between 4 and 8&#x000a0;hr after mixing, cells were scored for pairing. The mating type was defined for clones that paired with five of the six mating type testers, as equivalent to that of the sole tester strain with which it failed to pair.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Testing assortants for exocytosis competence using Alcian Blue</title><p>Cells were grown in SPP, replicated into a 96-well plate with 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l/well 2% BP, and grown for 3&#x000a0;d. Capsule formation was induced by adding 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l/well 0.02% Alcian blue in 0.5&#x000a0;mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> solution to each well, followed by the immediate addition of 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of 2% PP. Wells were scored for the presence of Alcian blue-stained capsules. Clones showing no capsule formation whatsoever were then retested in bulk culture, before being selected for genomic DNA extraction. For this, cells were grown to 3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml in 25&#x000a0;ml SPP, washed twice and resuspended in 10&#x000a0;mM Tris, pH&#x000a0;7.4, then starved overnight (12&#x02013;18&#x000a0;hr) at 30&#x000b0;. Cells were concentrated to 3&#x000a0;ml, and transferred to a new 125-ml flask, stimulated by rapid addition via syringe of 1&#x000a0;ml 0.1% Alcian blue, then diluted after 15&#x000a0;sec with 45&#x000a0;ml 0.25% PP&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;0.5&#x000a0;mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. Cells were washed once in 50&#x000a0;ml Tris, concentrated to 2&#x000a0;ml, and resuspended in 25&#x000a0;ml Tris for screening by microscopy.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Genomic DNA extraction</title><p>Cells were grown to 3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml in 25&#x000a0;ml SPP, and starved for 18&#x02013;24&#x000a0;hr in 10&#x000a0;mM Tris-HCl, pH&#x000a0;7.5; 1.5&#x000a0;ml of cells was then placed in an Eppendorf tube and concentrated by pelleting to 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l. Urea buffer (700&#x003bc;l; 42% w/v urea, 0.35&#x000a0;M NaCl, 0.01&#x000a0;M Tris pH&#x000a0;7.4, 0.01&#x000a0;M EDTA, 1% SDS) was added, followed by gentle shaking and subsequent addition of 0.1&#x000a0;mg/ml Proteinase K for a 5-min incubation at 50&#x000b0;. A 750-&#x003bc;l aliquot of phenol:chloroform:isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1) was then added, the tube contents mixed by inversion, and then spun for 15&#x000a0;min at 3500&#x000a0;rpm. The top, aqueous, layers were transferred to new tubes using pipette tips with cut-off ends, and the extraction repeated. The top layers were then extracted with an equal volume of chloroform:isoamyl alcohol (24:1), and mixed with a one-third volume of 5&#x000a0;M NaCl. DNA was precipitated with an equal volume of isopropyl alcohol, gently spooled onto a hooked glass pipette and transferred to a new nonstick Eppendorf tube (Eppendorf LoBind Microcentrifuge tube). DNA was washed and pelleted twice with 1&#x000a0;ml 70% ethanol, and the final pellet left to air dry for 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;min. DNA was resuspended in 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7; TE, pH&#x000a0;8.0, treated with 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l RNAse A (10&#x000a0;mg/ml, Fermentas) overnight at 55&#x000b0;, and stored at &#x02013;20&#x000b0;.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Disruption of MMA1 to generate &#x00394;mma1 strains</title><p><italic>MMA1</italic> (TTHERM_00566910) was replaced in the Macronucleus with the neo4 drug resistance cassette, generously provided by K. Mochizuki (IMPA, Vienna, Austria) via homologous recombination with the linearized vector pUC620MACKO-neo4 (Supplemental Material, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028878/-/DC1/FigureS1.jpg">Figure S1</ext-link>). We amplified &#x0223c;600&#x000a0;bp of the upstream and downstream flanks of <italic>MMA1</italic> using the primer pairs 034 and 035, and 036 and 037, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028878/-/DC1/FigureS2.pptx">Figure S2</ext-link>), and cloned them into the <italic>Sac</italic>I and <italic>Xho</italic>I sites, respectively, of the neo4 cassette using an In-Fusion cloning kit (Clontech, Mountain View, CA). CU428 cells were then biolistically transformed with the final construct pUC620MACKO-neo4, linearized with <italic>Not</italic>I and <italic>Sal</italic>I (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Chilcoat <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Transformants were selected on the basis of paromomycin resistance, then serially transferred for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;wk in increasing drug concentrations to drive fixation of the null allele.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>RT-PCR confirmation of MMA1 disruption</title><p>Cultures were grown to 1.5&#x02013;3.0&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml, washed, and starved for 2&#x000a0;hr in 10&#x000a0;mM Tris pH&#x000a0;7.4. Total RNA was isolated as per manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions using RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA). The presence of <italic>MMA1</italic> transcripts was assayed with the OneStep RT-PCR kit (Qiagen) using primers (083 and 073, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028878/-/DC1/FigureS2.pptx">Figure S2</ext-link>) to amplify &#x0223c;650&#x000a0;bp of the <italic>MMA1</italic> gene. Gene knockout was confirmed by the continued absence of the corresponding transcripts after &#x0223c;2&#x000a0;wk of growth in the absence of drug selection (four to five serial transfers/wk). To confirm that equal amounts of cDNA were being amplified, control RT-PCR with primers specific for the &#x003b1;-tubulin gene were run in parallel.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Vector construction and expression of the MMA1-CFP gene fusion</title><p>The <italic>MMA1</italic> gene was cloned into the pBSICC Gateway vector (a gift from D. Chalker, Washington University, St. Louis, MO), using the primers listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028878/-/DC1/FigureS2.pptx">Figure S2</ext-link>. Briefly, <italic>MMA1</italic>, minus the stop codon, was PCR-amplified using primers 091 and 092, and recombined into a destination vector (pIBCC) containing an <italic>MTT1</italic>-inducible CFP tagged expression cassette cloned upstream of a cycloheximide-resistant rpl29 allele. For transformation, the construct was linearized with BaeI and <italic>Spe</italic>I, and biolistically transformed into the wild type CU428 or mutant UC620 cell line (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Biolistic transformation</title><p><italic>Tetrahymena</italic> were transformed by biolistic transformation as previously described (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Chilcoat <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>). Afterward, filters were transferred to a flask with 50&#x000a0;ml prewarmed (30&#x000b0;) SPP without drug, and incubated at 30&#x000b0; with shaking for 4&#x000a0;hr. Transformants were then selected by adding paromomycin (120&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml with 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml CdCl<sub>2</sub>), or cycloheximide (12&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml). Cells were scored for drug resistance after 3&#x000a0;d (paromomycin) or 5&#x000a0;d (cycloheximide). Transformants were serially transferred 5&#x000a0;d a week in decreasing concentrations of CdCl<sub>2</sub> and increasing concentrations of drug. In all cases, selection was for at least 2&#x000a0;wk before further testing (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Chalker 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p>To visualize mucocysts, cells were fixed, permeabilized with detergent, immunolabeled with mAb 5E9 (10%) or mAb 4D11 (20%) hybridoma supernatant, and analyzed as described previously (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bowman and Turkewitz 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). After a 2-hr induction by 2&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml CdCl<sub>2</sub>, Mma1p-CFP fusion protein was visualized using Rabbit anti GFP (Invitrogen) (1:400), followed by Alexa 488-conjugated anti-Rabbit antibody (1:250). For simultaneous imaging of Mma1p-CFP and Grl3p, cells were costained using the mAb 5E9 as previously described, and with the polyclonal anti-GFP antibody (Life Technologies) diluted 1:400 in 1%&#x000a0;BSA. Cells were then coincubated with the 2&#x000b0; antibodies Texas red-coupled goat anti-mouse IgG diluted 1:99, and 488-coupled donkey anti-rabbit IgG diluted 1:250 in 1%&#x000a0;BSA. Cells were imaged using a Leica SP5 II Confocal Microscope, and image data were analyzed as previously described (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Images were captured with the LAS_AF confocal software (Leica) for Windows&#x000a0;7. Image data were colored and adjusted for brightness/contrast using ImageJ.</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Dibucaine stimulation</title><p>Dibucaine stimulation of exocytosis was performed as described previously (Rahaman <italic>et al.</italic> 2009).</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Subcellular fractionation</title><p>Cells were grown to 3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup>/ml, and then transferred into 10&#x000a0;mM Tris, pH&#x000a0;7.4. Transgene expression was induced using 0.25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml CdCl<sub>2</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hr at 30&#x000b0;. Cells were chilled and centrifuged (1000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic>) in a clinical centrifuge for 1&#x000a0;min. All subsequent steps were at 4&#x000b0;. Cells were resuspended and washed once in Buffer A (20&#x000a0;mM HEPES-KOH pH&#x000a0;7.0, 38&#x000a0;mM KCl, 2&#x000a0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 2&#x000a0;mM EGTA) and the pellet volume measured. The pellet was resuspended in three volumes of Buffer B (20&#x000a0;mM HEPES-KOH pH&#x000a0;7.0, 38&#x000a0;mM KCl, 2&#x000a0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2&#x000a0;mM EGTA, and 0.3&#x000a0;M sucrose) containing protease inhibitor cocktail tablet (Roche). Cells were passed through a ball-bearing cell cracker with nominal clearance of 0.0004&#x000a0;inches. The homogenate was centrifuged for 30&#x000a0;min at 10,000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic>. To separate cytosolic and membrane fractions, that supernatant was further centrifuged for 1&#x000a0;hr at 100,000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic>. After centrifugation, supernatant (cytosolic) and pellet (membrane) fractions were dissolved in SDS-PAGE buffer and incubated for 15 min at 90&#x000b0;.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Tricholoracetic acid precipitation of whole cell lysates</title><p>Cells (&#x0223c;3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup>)cells were pelleted, washed twice with 10&#x000a0;mM Tris pH&#x000a0;7.4, and precipitated with 10% trichloroacetic acid (TCA). Precipitates were incubated on ice for 30&#x000a0;min, centrifuged (18,000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic>, 10&#x000a0;min, 4&#x000b0;), washed with ice-cold acetone, repelleted (18,000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic>, 5&#x000a0;min, 4&#x000b0;) and then dissolved in 2.5&#x000d7; SDS-PAGE sample buffer.</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Immunoprecipitation</title><p>CFP-tagged fusion protein was immunoprecipitated (for western blot) from detergent lysates using polyclonal rabbit anti-GFP antiserum as described previously (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Briguglio <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Western blotting</title><p>Samples were resolved by SDS-PAGE and transferred to 0.45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m PVDF membranes (Thermo Scientific, Rockford, IL). Blots were blocked and probed as previously described (<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Turkewitz <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>). The rabbit anti-Grl1p, rabbit anti-Grl3p, rabbit anti polyG (<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Xie <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), and mouse monoclonal anti-GFP (Covance, Princeton, NJ) 1&#x000b0; antibodies were diluted 1:2000, 1:800, 1:10,000, and 1:5000, respectively. Protein was visualized with either ECL Horseradish Peroxidase-linked anti-rabbit (NA934), or anti-mouse (NA931) (Amersham Biosciences, Buckinghamshire, England) 2&#x000b0; antibody diluted 1:20,000, and SuperSignal West Femto Maximum Sensitivity Substrate (Thermo Scientific, Rockford, IL).</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Gene expression profiles</title><p>Expression profiles were derived from the <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> Functional Genomics Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tfgd.ihb.ac.cn/">http://tfgd.ihb.ac.cn/</ext-link>), with each profile normalized to that gene&#x02019;s maximum expression level (<xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Xiong <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Miao <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>In silico analyses</title><p>Alignment of protein sequences was performed using CLUSTALX (1.8) with default parameters.</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Library construction</title><p>DNA was sonicated to produce a 300&#x02013;400&#x000a0;bp distribution, and then end-repaired and A-tailed enzymatically using Illumina&#x02019;s standard TruSeq DNA library preparation. These products were ligated to Illumina Truseq adapters. Libraries, following indexing via PCR, were size selected to remove adapter and PCR dimers, pooled, and cosequenced on two lanes of the Illumina HiSequation 2500 using a 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;100 base pair format. The unique sequences incorporated during library construction were subsequently used to identify the source of each read, using postsequencing bioinformatics.</p></sec><sec id="s22"><title>Whole genome sequencing</title><p>Sequencing of the macronuclear DNA library was performed on an Illumina HiSequation 2500 by the University of Chicago Genomics Facility at the Knapp Center for Biomedical Discovery (KCBD). The sequencing process followed the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions, and the sequence files (fastq) were produced using the Illumina demultiplexing software CASAVA (v1.8). A total number of 269&#x000a0;million paired-end reads (2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;101 bp) were generated. The F2 lines with the mutation of interest were sequenced to &#x0223c;70-fold genome coverage. The parental strain, <italic>i.e.</italic>, the wildtype background upon which the mutations were initially induced, was sequenced to &#x0223c;256-fold genome coverage. The two strains that were used in outcrossses to generate the F2 lines were sequenced to &#x0223c;65- and &#x0223c;73-fold genome coverage, respectively. Genome sequencing of <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> primarily reflects the Macronuclear genome, in which genes are generally present at &#x0223c;45 copies compared to the two copies in the Micronucleus. Because the Micronucleus represents the germline nucleus, only Micronuclear alleles are transmitted to progeny (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Karrer 2000</xref>). However, because all parental lines are wild type regarding exocytosis except for UC620 itself, we made the simplifying assumption that bulk DNA sequencing of mutant <italic>vs.</italic> parental lines would permit us to identify the causative mutation in UC620.</p></sec><sec id="s23"><title>Sequence alignment</title><p>Reads from total genomic DNA sequencing were mapped to the <italic>T. thermophila</italic> Macronuclear genome sequence released by Broad institute using the Burrows-Wheeler Aligner software (BWA) version 0.5.9 (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Eisen <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Coyne <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Li and Durbin 2009</xref>). Default parameters were used when running bwa aln except the following: 1) &#x0201c;Maximum edit distance&#x0201d; was set to &#x0201c;2&#x0201d;; 2) &#x0201c;Maximum number of gap opens&#x0201d; was set to &#x0201c;0&#x0201d;; 3) &#x0201c;Number of threads&#x0201d; was set to &#x0201c;8&#x0201d;; and 4) &#x0201c;Iterative search&#x0201d; was disabled. The output files were converted to bam files using the &#x0201c;sampe&#x0201d; utility of the BWA software with default parameters, and the SAMtools software version 0.1.18 (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). SAMtools was then used to sort the bam files and remove PCR duplicates. Picard Tools version 1.92 was used to add group names to the bam files with parameter &#x0201c;VALIDATION_STRINGENCY&#x0201d; set to &#x0201c;LENIENT&#x0201d; (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://picard.sourceforge.net">http://picard.sourceforge.net</ext-link>). The resulting bam files were indexed by SAMtools.</p></sec><sec id="s24"><title>Variants discovery</title><p>The Genome Analysis Toolkit (GATK) version 2.5-2 was applied to identify variants with total genomic DNA sequencing data of the five samples (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">McKenna <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). The following steps were taken in this procedure. 1) Realignment of reads using RealignerTargetCreator and IndelRealigner tool of the GATK package to correct the misalignment caused by site mutations, insertions and deletions; and 2) variants were called using the HaplotypeCaller tool of the GATK package with the &#x0201c;out_mode&#x0201d; set to &#x0201c;EMIT_ALL_CONFIDENT_SITES&#x0201d; that produces calls at variant sites and confident reference sites; &#x0201c;stand_call_conf&#x0201d; set to &#x0201c;50.0&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;stand_emit_conf&#x0201d; set to &#x0201c;30.0&#x0201d;. Full documentation of parameters can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/guide/tooldocs/org_broadinstitute_gatk_tools_walkers_haplotypecaller_HaplotypeCaller.php#-output_mode">https://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/guide/tooldocs/org_broadinstitute_gatk_tools_walkers_haplotypecaller_HaplotypeCaller.php#-output_mode</ext-link>. A total number of 67,256 variants was called with this procedure. Among these, 23,493 were single-nucleotide variants (SNVs), which resulted in a SNV density of &#x0223c;0.23&#x000a0;kbp<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> for a genome of a mappable size of 103,014,375&#x000a0;bp (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Coyne <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s25"><title>Candidate screening</title><p>The candidate causal variants of the cell exocytosis dysfunction phenotype were selected with the following steps. 1) Variants with missing values for the genotypes were filtered, <italic>i.e.</italic>, a variant will be filtered out if GATK is unsure of the genotype of the variant in any of the samples. 2) Candidate sites had to be homozygous in all strains, and the mutant F2 strain genotype must be different from the genotype of the parental strain and wild-type strains. A total number of 28 such candidate sites was found. Among these 28 variants, 10 were on chromosome&#x000a0;1, seven were on chromosome&#x000a0;2, four were on chromosome&#x000a0;3, one was on chromosome&#x000a0;4, four were on chromosome&#x000a0;5, and two were undefined.</p></sec><sec id="s26"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data and reagents from this work will be made freely available upon request for noncommercial purposes.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s27"><title>Results</title><sec id="s28"><title>Generation of F2 clones for sequencing</title><p>The concentration of nitrosoguanidine used for mutagenesis to generate UC620 is expected to produce a large number of mutations in each cell (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005a</xref>). For that reason, we could not usefully compare the genomes of UC620 to that of the unmutagenized parent strain, as this would be confounded by the large background of SNVs unrelated to the mutation of interest. To partially overcome this problem, we outcrossed UC620 with strains bearing useful drug resistance markers, and used drug resistance to select progeny that would be heterozygous in the germline Micronuclei for the UC620 mutation. We then mated several progeny clones with one another, and derived the F2 progeny from isolated mating pairs. Since the UC620 mutation is recessive, 1/4 of the progeny, namely those homozygous for the mutant alleles, should display the UC620 phenotype. We therefore focused on matings producing the expected 1:3 ratio of mutant:wildtype exocytosis phenotypes among the progeny. A flowchart of the overall genetic strategy is shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028878/-/DC1/FigureS3.pptx">Figure S3</ext-link>.</p><p>Identifying the homozygous mutant F2 progeny was complicated by the phenomenon of phenotypic assortment, which derives from the amitotic division of the Macronucleus during cytokinesis (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Karrer 2000</xref>). In particular, even within clones of cells heterozygous for the UC620 mutation, some cells will lose most, or all, wildtype alleles in the Macronucleus, due to the random assortment of Macronuclear alleles at each cell division (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Doerder <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>). For this reason, we judged the homozygous mutant clones to be those showing no wild-type phenotypes whatsoever, in tests performed initially in 96-well plates, and confirmed in bulk cultures. We obtained 25 such clones, derived from two matings.</p><p>DNA was prepared from the individual clones, and then pooled for sequencing. In parallel, we prepared and sequenced DNA from the strains used during the initial mutagenesis to create UC620, as well as from the strains used for the outcrosses described above.</p></sec><sec id="s29"><title>A tetrahymenid-restricted gene on chromosome&#x000a0;1 represents a candidate for the mutated gene in UC620</title><p>A total of 28 SNVs was identified that were homozygous in the mutant pool but not present in the parental strains. The criteria used in SNV discovery are detailed in <italic>Materials and Methods</italic>. Of the 28, 10 fell on chromosome&#x000a0;1, to which the UC620 mutation had previously been mapped (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005a</xref>). Four of these chromosome&#x000a0;1 candidates fell within previously annotated genes. Among these, we focused on TTHERM 00566910 based on its expression profile. An online database of <italic>T. thermophila</italic> gene expression allows one to visualize the expression profiles of all genes in this organism, over a range of culture conditions (<xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Xiong <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Using this database, we previously discerned that a large number of genes associated with mucocyst biogenesis had nearly identical expression profiles (Rahaman <italic>et al.</italic> 2009; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). TTHERM 00566910, which we have called <italic>MMA1</italic> for <italic>M</italic>ucocyst <italic>ma</italic>turation, is expressed at under twice the corrected background for the whole genome dataset (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Miao <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). However, the shape of the expression profile was strikingly similar to that of known mucocyst-associated genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). This profile was not shared by other genes harboring SNVs on chromosome&#x000a0;1 (unpublished data). On this basis, <italic>MMA1</italic> emerged as the prime candidate for the gene underlying the defect in UC620.</p><fig id="fig1" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Expression profiling and genomic knockout of <italic>MMA1</italic>. (A) The expression profile of <italic>MMA1</italic> (red trace) is highly similar to that of <italic>SOR4</italic> (blue trace), which encodes a receptor required for mucocyst biogenesis. The profiles of transcript abundance under a variety of culture conditions, derived via hybridization of stage-specific cDNAs to whole genome microarrays, are from the Tetrahymena Functional Genomics Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tfgd.ihb.ac.cn/">http://tfgd.ihb.ac.cn/</ext-link>). In the plots shown, each trace was normalized to that gene&#x02019;s maximum expression level. The culture conditions sampled at successive time points represent growing (L-l, L-m, and L-h), starved (S-0, S-3, S-6, S-9, S-12, S-15, and S-24), and conjugating (C-0, C-2, C-4, C-6, C-8, C-10, C-12, C-14, C-16, and C-18) cultures. For details on the sampling conditions, see <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Miao <italic>et al.</italic> (2009</xref>). (B) Schematic of <italic>MMA1</italic> Macronuclear gene knockout construct. Replacement of the Macronuclear <italic>MMA1</italic> gene by the Neo4 drug resistance cassette was targeted by homologous recombination. (C) Confirmation of <italic>MMA1</italic> Macronuclear knockout by RT-PCR. RNA was extracted from wild type, UC620, and &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic>, converted to cDNA, and PCR amplified using <italic>MMA1</italic>-specific primers listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028878/-/DC1/TableS1.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>. A 1% ethidium bromide-stained agarose gel is shown. The <italic>MMA1</italic> product (indicated by arrow), which was confirmed by sequencing, was present in wild type and UC620 samples but absent in &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic>. The larger amplicon present in all lanes corresponds to <italic>MMA1</italic> with the intron still present, as determined by sequencing, and thus likely reflects amplification of a genomic (Micronuclear) DNA contaminant. Parallel amplification of the &#x003b1;&#x02212;tubulin gene from all samples was used to control for sample loading.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="2505f1"/></fig><p><italic>MMA1</italic> has clear homologs in several recently sequenced Tetrahymena species (<italic>T. malaccensis</italic>, <italic>T. ellioti</italic>, and <italic>T. borealis</italic>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028878/-/DC1/FigureS4.jpg">Figure S4</ext-link>). Alignment of these genes, together with extensive RNAseq data from <italic>T. thermophila</italic>, facilitated confident assignment of exon&#x02013;intron boundaries, as well as start and stop codons, for this previously undescribed gene. Based on this annotation, the SNV identified in UC620 changed the <italic>MMA1</italic> stop codon (TGA) to TGT, which encodes cysteine. The mutation therefore potentially results in an aberrant polypeptide product containing an additional 180 amino acids. Except for the homologs in these other Tetrahymenids, we could not identify <italic>MMA1</italic> homologs in any other species.</p></sec><sec id="s30"><title>Disruption of MMA1 blocks synthesis of docked mucocysts</title><p>To ask whether a defect in <italic>MMA1</italic> might account for the mutant phenotype in UC620, we disrupted <italic>MMA1</italic> in wildtype cells by homologous recombination with a drug resistance cassette (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). The resulting &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> cells had no detectible <italic>MMA1</italic> transcript (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). They grew at wild-type rates, indicating that the gene is not essential for normal growth under laboratory conditions.</p><p>Strikingly, the &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> cells demonstrated a strong defect in mucocyst exocytosis. The complete failure to release mucocyst contents upon cell stimulation was identical to that of UC620, when tested with the secretagogues Alcian blue (not shown) or dibucaine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). This defect was due to the failure of &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> cells to synthesize mature docked mucocysts, as revealed by indirect immunofluorescence using antibodies against two mucocyst cargo proteins, Grl3p and Grt1p. The &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> cells in growing cultures did not accumulate Grl3p in docked mucocysts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). Instead, as in UC620, the Grl3p localized to relatively homogeneous cytoplasmic vesicles.</p><fig id="fig2" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><italic>MMA1</italic> knockout produces a phenocopy of the UC620 mutation. (A) Equal numbers of CU428 wildtype, UC620 and &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> cells were stimulated with dibucaine, which promotes global mucocyst exocytosis, and then centrifuged. In wildtype cells, this results in a pellet of cells with an overlying flocculent consisting of the released mucocyst contents. For clarity, the flocculent layer is delineated with a dashed line at the upper border, and an unbroken line at the lower border. In contrast, neither UC620 nor &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> produces detectible flocculent. The pellet in wildtype (layer beneath solid line) is smaller than in the mutants because many wild-type cells are trapped in the flocculent. (B and C) Wild-type, UC620, and &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> were fixed, permeabilized, and stained with antibodies against two mucocyst core proteins, Grl3p (left panels, 5E9 antibody), and Grt1p (right panels, 4D11 antibody). Shown are optical sections of individual cells, at the cell surface, and a cross section. Wildtype CU428 accumulate docked mucocysts, visible as elongated vesicles that are highly concentrated at the cell periphery. UC620 and &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic>, in contrast, do not form elongated vesicles, and Grl3p and Grt1p are found in vesicles throughout the cells. The Grt1p signals in both UC620 and &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> often appear localized to the vesicle perimeter, while in wildtype cells the signal is localized to the docked mucocyst tips. The scale bars represent 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. (D and E) Whole cell lysates of growing (D), or 6-hr starved (E) cells were resolved by 4&#x02013;20% SDS-PAGE, and transfers were immunoblotted with antibodies against Grl1p or Grl3p. The unprocessed (pro-Grl) and processed forms of the Grl proteins are indicated by arrows and arrowheads, respectively. In CU428, Grl proteins accumulate primarily in the fully processed form. In contrast, the pro-Grl forms predominate in growing cultures of UC620 and &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic>. For both UC620 and &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic>, the defect in processing proGrl proteins is partially rescued under starvation conditions (E). To demonstrate equivalent loading, all samples were immunoblotted in parallel with anti-tubulin antibody (D and E). Each lane in (D) and &#x020ac; represents 10<sup>3</sup> cell equivalents.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="2505f2"/></fig><p>Similarly, a 2nd mucocyst protein, Grt1p, was mislocalized in both UC620 and &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> cells. In wildtype cells, Grt1p resides in docked mucocysts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>). In both UC620 and &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic>, Grt1p instead localizes in cytoplasmic vesicles, frequently appearing as a ring around the vesicle periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s31"><title>&#x00394;mma1 cells are defective in proteolytic maturation of mucocyst contents</title><p>In UC620, the mislocalization of Grl3p and other Grl-family proteins is accompanied by their aberrant biochemical maturation: the Grl pro-protein precursors largely fail to undergo the proteolytic processing that occurs during mucocyst maturation in wild-type cells (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005a</xref>). The &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> cells showed the same defect in pro-Grl processing, as shown for two different Grl proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>). Moreover, the processing defect in &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> was partially suppressed when cells were transferred to starvation conditions, as we had previously reported for UC620 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2E</xref>) (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005a</xref>). These results are consistent with the idea that <italic>MMA1</italic> represents the affected gene in the UC620 mutant.</p></sec><sec id="s32"><title>Mma1p appears to be cytosolic and partially membrane-associated</title><p>A hydropathy plot based on the primary sequence of Mma1p did not reveal either a signal sequence, as would be expected for a protein translocated into the secretory pathway, nor any hydrophobic stretches that could function as transmembrane helices (not shown). Thus the protein is likely to be cytosolic. We expressed a CFP-tagged copy of <italic>MMA1</italic> under the control of the strong and inducible <italic>MTT1</italic> (metallothionein 1) promoter (<xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Shang <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). We resorted to this overexpression strategy because the very low level expression of wildtype <italic>MMA1</italic> made it impossible to detect the expression of 3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;GFP-tagged <italic>MMA1</italic> expressed at the endogenous locus (unpublished data). Mma1p-CFP, immunoprecipitated from whole cell lysates, appeared by Western blotting as a band of the expected size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). We fractionated cells expressing Mma1p-CFP by cracking them with a ball bearing homogenizer, and then subjecting the cleared lysate to high-speed (100,000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic>) centrifugation. The protein was found primarily in the soluble fraction, but roughly 10% was found in the high-speed pellet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). Visualization of the CFP in these cells by indirect immunofluorescence showed a large number of small puncta present throughout the cell, but no significant colocalization with mature docked mucocysts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that Mma1p-CFP is a cytosolic protein that is partially associated with small vesicles.</p><fig id="fig3" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Expression and characterization of Mma1p-CFP. (A) Expression of <italic>MMA1</italic>-CFP. Mma1-CFP fusion protein was immunoprecipitated from detergent cell lysates using anti-GFP antiserum, with wildtype CU428 cells processed in parallel. Immunoprecipitates were subjected to 4&#x02013;20% SDS-PAGE, and PVDF transfers blotted with anti-GFP mAb. An immunoreactive band (arrowhead) of the size expected for the Mma1p-CFP fusion is seen only in cells expressing this construct. (B) Cells expressing Mma1p-CFP were grown to 3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup>/ml, and then fractionated into soluble (cytosolic) and pelletable (membrane) fractions, as described in <italic>Materials and Methods</italic>. Samples were separated by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted with anti-GFP mAb. Three different loadings are shown for each sample, corresponding to 0.2&#x02013;0.8% of the entire cytosolic fraction, and 2&#x02013;8% (<italic>i.e.</italic>, 10&#x000a0;&#x000d7; higher cell equivalents) of the membrane fraction; &#x0223c;10% of the Mma1p-CFP is found in the membrane fraction. (C) After induction as in (A), cells were fixed, permeabilized, and immunolabeled with rabbit anti-GFP and mAb 5E9, followed by 2&#x000b0; fluorophore-coupled Abs. The scale bars represent 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. Mma1p-CFP (green) appears in small puncta through the cytoplasm, with no significant overlap with docked mucocysts (red). Wildtype cells processed in parallel showed no significant labeling in the green channel (not shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="2505f3"/></fig></sec><sec id="s33"><title>Expression of Mma1p-CFP rescues the UC620 mutant</title><p>To ask whether the CFP-tagged copy of Mma1p was active, we introduced the identical construct into UC620 cells. Since the mutation in UC620 behaves as a recessive allele, the defects in these cells should be rescued by expression of a wild-type copy of the affected gene. A polypeptide of the expected size for the fusion protein was detected by Western blotting, and was localized to a large number of small cytoplasmic puncta (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4, A and B</xref>). Importantly, UC620 cells expressing <italic>MMA1</italic>-CFP were indistinguishable from wild type in both mucocyst accumulation, and in pro-Grl processing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4, C, D, and E</xref>). The full rescue of UC620 cells by expression of <italic>MMA1</italic> provides confirmatory evidence that whole genome sequencing has allowed us to identify the genetic lesion in UC620, and that <italic>MMA1</italic> represents a novel factor required for mucocyst maturation.</p><fig id="fig4" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic>MMA1</italic>-CFP rescues the UC620 mutant. (A) Detergent lysates of UC620, or UC620 expressing <italic>MMA1</italic>-CFP, were immunoprecipitated with anti-GFP Ab, and the precipitates separated by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted with anti-GFP mAb. Cells expressing <italic>MMA1</italic>-CFP show a band of the expected size for the fusion protein (arrow). (B and C) After induction of <italic>MMA1</italic>-CFP with CdCl<sub>2</sub>, cells were fixed, permeabilized, and immunolabeled with rabbit anti-GFP (B) or mAb 5E9 (C), followed by 2&#x000b0; fluorophore-coupled Abs. The scale bars represent 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. (B) Mma1p-CFP localizes to multiple cytoplasmic puncta. (C) The expression of the fusion protein in UC620 cells restores the wild-type pattern of docked mucocysts. (D and E) <italic>MMA1</italic>-CFP expression was induced for 2&#x000a0;hr in growing cell cultures, and wild type and UC620 cultures were in parallel treated with CdCl<sub>2</sub>. Whole cell lysates were resolved by 4&#x02013;20% SDS-PAGE, and transfers were immunoblotted with antibodies against Grl1p (D) or Grl3p (E). The expression of <italic>MMA1</italic>-CFP in UC620 rescues the processing defect seen for both Grl proteins in UC620. Each lane represents 10<sup>3</sup> cell equivalents.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="2505f4"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s34"><title>Discussion</title><p><italic>T. thermophila</italic> possesses many characteristics that make it an attractive model organism for investigating cell biological questions (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Collins and Gorovsky 2005</xref>). One particularly promising approach to dissect a variety of pathways has been forward genetics following chemical mutagenesis. The cells are diploid, but can be rapidly brought to homozygosity via a specialized mating, thereby facilitating screening for recessive mutations (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Cole and Bruns 1992</xref>). More generally, starved cultures of compatible mating types will undergo highly synchronous mating, and the cells are large enough to be readily isolated as individual pairs, which facilitates classical genetic analysis (Orias 2000).</p><p>Using these and related tools, &#x0003e;&#x000a0;20 secretion mutants were previously generated by nitrosoguanidine mutagenesis, and analyzed to various degrees (<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Orias <italic>et al.</italic> 1983</xref>; <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Melia <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005a</xref>). All of them fail to release mucocyst contents upon stimulation, and the underlying cell biological defects range from a block in mucocyst synthesis to defects in exocytosis <italic>per se</italic>. However, none of the genetic lesions has ever been identified, thus limiting the insights gained from this collection. Similarly, the literature contains detailed analysis of <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> mutants with defects in features such as cortical pattern formation, cell size, lysosomal enzyme release, cell surface antigen expression, food vacuole formation, motility, and rDNA maturation (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Frankel 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Hunseler <italic>et al.</italic> 1987</xref>; <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Basmussen and Orias 1975</xref>; <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Pennock <italic>et al.</italic> 1988</xref>; <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Kapler <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Doerder <italic>et al.</italic> 1985</xref>), but in only a single recent case has the gene responsible been identified (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Galati <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). That work, by Pearson and colleagues, used a whole genome sequencing approach similar to that which we independently pursued and report in this paper. Our results therefore suggest that mutagenesis linked with whole genome sequencing should be considered a highly accessible approach to link defined pathways with their underlying genes in this organism. This is relevant both for revisiting previously characterized mutants, as well as for developing new genetic screens. Recently, next generation sequencing applied to the ciliate <italic>P. tetraurelia</italic> has illuminated a set of mutants first characterized many decades ago (<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Singh <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).</p><p>Our sequencing strategy involved first outcrossing UC620 to generate heterozygous F1 clones, and then using an F1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;F1 cross to regenerate homozygous mutant progeny. In principle, the second step could have been simplified by crossing the F1 lines with a so-called star (*) strain, employing a strategy called uniparental cytogamy (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Cole and Bruns 1992</xref>). Conjugation in <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> involves the reciprocal exchange of haploid meiotic products between the pairing cells. A cell that conjugates with a * cell fails to receive a viable haploid pronucleus, and this promotes the endoreduplication of its own haploid genome. As a result, such * crosses can produce whole-cell homozygotes, which would be ideal for screening and sequencing (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Cole and Bruns 1992</xref>). Star crosses are also known to produce additional, poorly characterized, outcomes at low frequency, but this has not detracted from their usefulness for many applications. However, in early experiments we found that a significant fraction of the progeny of the uniparental cytogamy crosses, isolated as individual pairs, showed drug-resistance phenotypes inconsistent with simple endoreduplication, and we therefore employed the somewhat more laborious F1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;F1 strategy.</p><p>One key element in quickly identifying the causative SNV in UC620 was our prior physical mapping. Such mapping is relatively straightforward in <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> due to the availability of a panel of so-called &#x02018;nullisomic&#x02019; strains, each bearing a homozygous deletion of an entire micronuclear chromosome, and available from the Tetrahymena Stock Center (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Bruns and Brussard 1981</xref>). By crossing a strain bearing a recessive mutation with the panel of nullisomics, one can quickly identify the micronuclear chromosome on which the mutation resides. By this approach, the UC620 mutation was mapped to chromosome 1 (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 2005a</xref>). By using an additional panel of available strains with partial chromosomal deletions, this approach may be extended to map mutations to chromosome arms. However, we failed to obtain viable progeny using some of the partial deletion strains on chromosome 1. In future, it might be very valuable to generate a larger panel of partial chromosomal deletions to cover the <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> genome. If a fine scale panel were available, the mapping of a mutation might be sufficient to then directly identify a small number of candidate genes by sequencing. This approach would bypass the multiple crosses, mating type testing, and progeny screening that we employed to identify <italic>MMA1</italic>.</p><p>The mutation identified in the UC620 strain was predicted to change the <italic>MMA1</italic> stop codon, thereby potentially producing a longer polypeptide product. We found unambiguous <italic>MMA1</italic> homologs in the recently sequenced genomes of three other Tetrahymena species, and these alignments helped to confirm the stop codon assignment. The stop codon mutation may result in production of a short-lived mRNA or polypeptide, since we found that the UC620 mutation was phenocopied by complete deletion of the <italic>MMA1</italic> gene. &#x02206;<italic>mma1</italic> cells, like UC620, showed defects in biochemical and morphological maturation of mucocysts, which were conditional with respect to growth conditions. Moreover, the defects in UC620 were fully rescued by expression of a wild-type copy of <italic>MMA1</italic> tagged with CFP.</p><p>Judging by transcript abundance, <italic>MMA1</italic> is expressed at a very low level. Consistent with this, we could not detect Mma1p tagged with 3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;GFP, when expressed under its endogenous promoter, and had to induce overexpression to visualize the protein in live cells. Analysis of those cells suggested that Mma1p is a cytosolic protein that partially associates with membranes, which may be small vesicles. This assignment as a cytosolic protein is also consistent with <italic>in silico</italic> predictions, namely the apparent absence of an endoplasmic reticulum translocation signal sequence or of any likely transmembrane domains. The precise role of Mma1p is unknown. Mucocyst biogenesis depends in part on endolysosomal trafficking, as judged by the requirement for a receptor in the VPS10 family, and several other proteins associated with trafficking to lysosome-related organelles (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Briguglio <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; and our unpublished data). The small, relatively homogeneous, Mma1p-GFP-labeled puncta may therefore represent endosomes involved in mucocyst formation.</p><p>We have previously noted that the genes encoding all known luminal proteins in mucocysts were coexpressed together with a receptor responsible for their delivery and the processing enzymes responsible for their maturation (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Briguglio <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Kumar <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Since the expression profile of <italic>MMA1</italic> closely matches that of the <italic>SOR4</italic> receptor, it appears that the phenomenon of coregulation extends to genes encoding cytosolic machinery in this pathway.</p><p>Although a mechanistic understanding of Mma1p action during mucocyst maturation is not yet in hand, our results demonstrate the power of forward genetics in <italic>T. thermophila</italic> to identify lineage-restricted genes that play essential roles in this pathway. It is particularly interesting that <italic>MMA1</italic> has no identifiable homolog in <italic>P. tetraurelia</italic>, another Oligohymenophorean ciliate that makes secretory granules called trichocysts. Trichocysts, like mucocysts, undergo biochemical and morphological maturation. Significantly, for virtually all known components of <italic>Paramecium</italic> trichocysts and <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> mucocysts, one can readily identify homologous (and likely orthologous) genes in the other organism. This is true for genes encoding the luminal cargo, processing enzymes, and membrane proteins involved in docking. Thus, the absence of an <italic>MMA1</italic> homolog in <italic>Paramecium</italic> is exceptional, and suggests the recent emergence of a novel mechanism in a largely conserved pathway within Oligohymenophorean ciliates.</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplemental Material</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_6_8_2505__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028878_FigureS1.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application"
mime-subtype="vnd.ms-powerpoint"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028878_FigureS2.pptx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application"
mime-subtype="vnd.ms-powerpoint"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028878_FigureS3.pptx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"
xlink:href="supp_g3.116.028878_FigureS4.jpg"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We gratefully acknowledge valuable advice from Eric Cole (St. Olaf College, MN) on the interpretation of uniparental cytogamy crosses, and help from Eileen Hamilton and Ed Orias (UC Santa Barbara, California) on genetic crosses and on mapping Macronuclear sequences to Micronuclear chromosomes. Wei Miao (Chinese Academy of Sciences, Wuhan, China), and Shelby Bidwell and Robert Coyne (J. Craig Venter Institute, Rockville, MD), provided valuable help in annotating <italic>MMA1</italic> and homologous genes in <italic>T. thermophila</italic> and other Tetrahymenids; Doug Chalker (Washington Univ., St. Louis) shared tagging vectors, Jacek Gaertig (Univ. Georgia, Athens) shared anti-tubulin antibodies, Marlo Nelsen and Joseph Frankel (U. Iowa, Iowa City) shared mAbs 4D11 and 5E9, and Kazufumi Mochizuki (IMBA, Vienna, Austria) shared the NEO4 gene disruption construct. Vytas Binokas and Christine Labno (Univ. Chicago Light Microscopy Core Facility) provided expert help, and members of A.P.T.&#x02019;s laboratory benefited from discussion with Joseph Briguglio, Harsimran Kaur, and Daniela Sparvoli. Work in A.P.T.&#x02019;s laboratory was supported by National Institutes of Health (NIH) 1R03MH094953, and by National Science Foundation (NSF) MCB-1051985; work in J.K.P.&#x02019;s laboratory was supported by the Howard Hughes Medical Foundation and NIH 1RO1ES025009.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p>Supplemental material is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028878/-/DC1">www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.116.028878/-/DC1</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn2"><p>Communicating editor: B. J. Andrews</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ailion</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Two Rab2 interactors regulate dense-core vesicle maturation.</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>82</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>180</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24698274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arvan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1992</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Protein sorting and secretion granule formation in regulated secretory cells.</article-title>
<source>Trends Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>331</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14731510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basmussen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orias</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1975</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>Tetrahymena</italic>: growth without phagocytosis.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>190</volume>(<issue>4213</issue>): <fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>465</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1166313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonnemain</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulik-Krzywicki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandchamp</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1992</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Interactions between genes involved in exocytotic membrane fusion in <italic>Paramecium</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>130</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>470</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1551571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2001</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Analysis of a mutant exhibiting conditional sorting to dense core secretory granules in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>159</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1616</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11779800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elde</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2005</year><comment>a</comment>&#x02003;<article-title>Core formation and the acquisition of fusion competence are linked during secretory granule maturation in <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Traffic</source>
<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>323</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15752136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael Siu</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearlman</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2005</year><comment>b</comment>&#x02003;<article-title>Genomic and proteomic evidence for a second family of dense core granule cargo proteins in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>.</article-title>
<source>J. Eukaryot. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>52</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16014006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>N. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chilcoat</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbsky</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2003</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Proprotein processing within secretory dense core granules of <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>.</article-title>
<source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>278</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>4087</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4095</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12435750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kambesis</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Comprehensive analysis reveals dynamic and evolutionary plasticity of Rab GTPases and membrane traffic in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Genet.</source>
<volume>6</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>e1001155</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20976245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briguglio</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>: a divergent perspective on membrane traffic.</article-title>
<source>J. Exp. Zoolog. B Mol. Dev. Evol.</source>
<volume>322</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>500</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>516</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briguglio</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Lysosomal sorting receptors are essential for secretory granule biogenesis in <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>.</article-title>
<source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>203</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>537</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>550</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24189272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruns</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brussard</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1981</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Nullisomic <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>: eliminating germinal chromosomes.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>213</volume>(<issue>4507</issue>): <fpage>549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>551</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17794842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burgoyne</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1993</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Regulated exocytosis.</article-title>
<source>Biochem. J.</source>
<volume>293</volume>: <fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>316</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8343109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bustos</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucchesi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruete</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayorga</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomes</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Rab27 and Rab3 sequentially regulate human sperm dense-core granule exocytosis.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>109</volume>(<issue>30</issue>): <fpage>E2057</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E2066</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22753498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chalker</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transformation and strain engineering of <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Methods Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22444150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chanat</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimplikar</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinchcombe</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huttner</surname><given-names>W.B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1991</year>&#x02003;What the granins tell us about the formation of secretory granules in neuroendocrine cells. <italic>Cell Biophys</italic> 19: 85&#x02013;91.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chilcoat</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melia</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1996</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Granule lattice protein 1 (Grl1p), an acidic, calcium-binding protein in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> dense-core secretory granules, influences granule size, shape, content organization, and release but not protein sorting or condensation.</article-title>
<source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>135</volume>(<issue>6 Pt 2</issue>): <fpage>1775</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1787</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8991090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruns</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1992</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Uniparental cytogamy: a novel, efficient method for bringing mutations of <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> into homozygous expression with precocious sexual maturity.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>132</volume>: <fpage>1017</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1031</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1459424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorovsky</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2005</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>R317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>R318</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15886083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1981</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Post-translational cleavage of mucocyst precursors in <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>.</article-title>
<source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>256</volume>: <fpage>10475</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10484</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6793582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2005</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genetic, genomic, and functional analysis of the granule lattice proteins in <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> secretory granules.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source>
<volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>4046</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4060</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15958493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiagarajan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wortman</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tallon</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Refined annotation and assembly of the <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> genome sequence through EST analysis, comparative genomic hybridization, and targeted gap closure.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>562</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19036158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dacks</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Evolution of the eukaryotic membrane-trafficking system: origin, tempo and mode.</article-title>
<source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>120</volume>(<issue>Pt 17</issue>): <fpage>2977</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2985</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17715154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Satir</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1991</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A potential mucus precursor in <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> wild type and mutant cells.</article-title>
<source>J. Protozool.</source>
<volume>38</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>623</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1818207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doerder</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkowitz</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skalican-Crowe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1985</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Isolation and genetic analysis of mutations at the SerH immobilization antigen locus of <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>111</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>286</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4054606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doerder</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deak</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lief</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1992</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Rate of phenotypic assortment in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Dev. Genet.</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>132</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1499154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiagarajan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Macronuclear genome sequence of the ciliate <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>, a model eukaryote.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Biol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>e286</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16933976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elde</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A role for convergent evolution in the secretory life of cells.</article-title>
<source>Trends Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>164</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17329106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>What do genic mutations tell us about the structural patterning of a complex single-celled organism?</article-title>
<source>Eukaryot. Cell</source>
<volume>7</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1617</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1639</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18658256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Froissard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2001</year>&#x02003;<article-title>ND9P, a novel protein with armadillo-like repeats involved in exocytosis: physiological studies using allelic mutants in <italic>Paramecium</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>157</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>620</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11156983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galati</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonney</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronenberg</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarissa</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yandell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>DisAp-dependent striated fiber elongation is required to organize ciliary arrays.</article-title>
<source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>207</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>705</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>715</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25533842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Garreau de Loubresse, N., 1993&#x02003;Early steps of the secretory pathway in <italic>Paramecium</italic>: ultrastructural, immunocytochemical, and genetic analysis of trichocyst biogenesis, pp.&#x000a0;27&#x02013;60 in <italic>Membrane Traffic in Protozoa</italic>, edited by H. Plattner. JAI Press, Greenwich, CT.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gentekaki</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolisko</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boscaro</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Large-scale phylogenomic analysis reveals the phylogenetic position of the problematic taxon Protocruzia and unravels the deep phylogenetic affinities of the ciliate lineages.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Phylogenet. Evol.</source>
<volume>78</volume>: <fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24814356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gogendeau</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koll</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2005</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Nd6p, a novel protein with RCC1-like domains involved in exocytosis in <italic>Paramecium tetraurelia</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Eukaryot. Cell</source>
<volume>4</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>2129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2139</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16339730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guest</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailyes</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>N. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1991</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Insulin secretory granule biogenesis.</article-title>
<source>Biochem. J.</source>
<volume>274</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2001253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A new class of cargo protein in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> dense core secretory granules.</article-title>
<source>Eukaryot. Cell</source>
<volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>583</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>593</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12456006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orias</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2000</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genetic crosses: setting up crosses, testing progeny, and isolating phenotypic assortants.</article-title>
<source>Methods Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>228</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10503193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horazdovsky</surname><given-names>B. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeWald</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emr</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1995</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Protein transport to the yeast vacuole.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>544</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>551</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7495575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunseler</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheidgen</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiedtke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1987</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Isolation and characterization of a mutant of <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> blocked in secretion of lysosomal enzymes.</article-title>
<source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3443604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapler</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orias</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackburn</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1994</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> mutants defective in the developmentally programmed maturation and maintenance of the rDNA minichromosome.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>137</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>455</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>466</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8070657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karrer</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2000</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>Tetrahymena</italic> genetics: two nuclei are better than one.</article-title>
<source>Methods Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>186</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10503190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1991</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Secretory granule and synaptic vesicle formation.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>654</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>660</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1663373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kienle</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloepper</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fasshauer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year><comment>a</comment>&#x02003;<article-title>Differences in the SNARE evolution of fungi and metazoa.</article-title>
<source>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</source>
<volume>37</volume>(<issue>Pt 4</issue>): <fpage>787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>791</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19614595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kienle</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloepper</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fasshauer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year><comment>b</comment>&#x02003;<article-title>Phylogeny of the SNARE vesicle fusion machinery yields insights into the conservation of the secretory pathway in fungi.</article-title>
<source>BMC Evol. Biol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19166604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kloepper</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kienle</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fasshauer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>An elaborate classification of SNARE proteins sheds light on the conservation of the eukaryotic endomembrane system.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source>
<volume>18</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>3463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3471</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17596510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Briguglio</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;An aspartyl cathepsin, CTH3, is essential for proprotein processing during secretory granule maturation in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>. Mol. Biol. Cell 25(16): 2444&#x02013;2460.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Briguglio</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Secretion of polypeptide crystals from <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> secretory organelles (mucocysts) depends on processing by a cysteine cathepsin, Cth4p.</article-title>
<source>Eukaryot. Cell</source>
<volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>817</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>833</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26092918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler Transform.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1760</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wysoker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>25</volume>(<issue>16</issue>): <fpage>2078</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2079</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leander</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Cascades of convergent evolution: the corresponding evolutionary histories of euglenozoans and dinoflagellates.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>106</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>): <fpage>9963</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9970</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19528647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doerder</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The life and times of <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Methods Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22444141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madeddu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Caer</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garreau de Loubresse</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1994</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Protein processing and morphogenesis of secretory granules in <italic>Paramecium</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Biochimie</source>
<volume>76</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7819344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madeddu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vayssi&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1995</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A large multigenic family codes for the polypeptides of the crystalline trichocyst matrix in <italic>Paramecium</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>649</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>659</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7579685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maihle</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Satir</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1985</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Protein secretion in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>: characterization of the secretory mutant strain SB281.</article-title>
<source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>78</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3912402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivachenko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cibulskis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The Genome Analysis Toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data.</article-title>
<source>Genome Res.</source>
<volume>20</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20644199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melia</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1998</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Mutational analysis of regulated exocytosis in Tetrahymena.</article-title>
<source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>111</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9394019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Microarray analyses of gene expression during the <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> life cycle.</article-title>
<source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>e4429</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19204800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morvan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tooze</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Discovery and progress in our understanding of the regulated secretory pathway in neuroendocrine cells.</article-title>
<source>Histochem. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>129</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>252</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18197413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schekman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1980</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Secretion and cell-surface growth are blocked in a temperature-sensitive mutant of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>76</volume>: 1858&#x02013;1862.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orias</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> genetics: concepts and applications.</article-title>
<source>Methods Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>301</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>325</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22444149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orias</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2000</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genetically sorting a collection of <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> mutants.</article-title>
<source>Methods Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>263</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10503196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orias</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flacks</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Satir</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1983</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Isolation and ultrastructural characterization of secretory mutants of <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>.</article-title>
<source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>64</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6662863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orias</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orias</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2000</year>&#x02003;<article-title><italic>Tetrahymena</italic> as a laboratory organism: useful strains, cell culture, and cell line maintenance.</article-title>
<source>Methods Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>211</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10503191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parfrey</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbero</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasser</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunthorn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Evaluating support for the current classification of eukaryotic diversity.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Genet.</source>
<volume>2</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>e220</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17194223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pennock</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thatcher</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruns</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorovsky</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1988</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A conditional mutant having paralyzed cilia and a block in cytokinesis is rescued by cytoplasmic exchange in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>120</volume>: <fpage>697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>705</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3224807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahaman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year><comment>b</comment>&#x02003;<article-title>Independent transport and sorting of functionally distinct protein families in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic> dense core secretory granules.</article-title>
<source>Eukaryot. Cell</source>
<volume>8</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1575</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1583</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19684282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosati</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Modeo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2003</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Extrusomes in ciliates: diversification, distribution, and phylogenetic implications.</article-title>
<source>J. Eukaryot. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>50</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>402</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14733430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schilde</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schonemann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehring</surname><given-names>I. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plattner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Distinct subcellular localization of a group of synaptobrevin-like SNAREs in <italic>Paramecium tetraurelia</italic> and effects of silencing SNARE-specific chaperone NSF.</article-title>
<source>Eukaryot. Cell</source>
<volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>288</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20023070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corstanje</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2002</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A robust inducible-repressible promoter greatly facilitates gene knockouts, conditional expression, and overexpression of homologous and heterologous genes in <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>99</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>3734</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3739</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11891286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saudemont</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guglielmi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnaiz</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gout</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genome-defence small RNAs exapted for epigenetic mating-type inheritance.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>509</volume>(<issue>7501</issue>): <fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>452</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24805235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skouri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1997</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genetic approach to regulated exocytosis using functional complementation in <italic>Paramecium</italic>: identification of the ND7 gene required for membrane fusion.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1063</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1071</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9201716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1998</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The proprotein convertases.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9667917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>On the discovery of precursor processing.</article-title>
<source>Methods Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>768</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21805235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sumakovic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegermann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Husson</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarze</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>UNC-108/RAB-2 and its effector RIC-19 are involved in dense core vesicle maturation in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</article-title>
<source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>186</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>897</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>914</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19797081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2004</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Out with a bang! <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> as a model system to study secretory granule biogenesis.</article-title>
<source>Traffic</source>
<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14690495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madeddu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1991</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Maturation of dense core granules in wild type and mutant <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>.</article-title>
<source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>10</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1979</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1987</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2065648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vayssie</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skouri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2000</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Molecular genetics of regulated secretion in <italic>Paramecium</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Biochimie</source>
<volume>82</volume>(<issue>420324923</issue>): <fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10865117</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verbsky</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkewitz</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1998</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Proteolytic processing and Ca2+-binding activity of dense-core vesicle polypeptides in <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>511</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9450970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorovsky</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Endoplasmic reticulum retention signal-dependent glycylation of the Hsp70/Grp170-related Pgp1p in <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Eukaryot. Cell</source>
<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17189490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xiong, J., Y. Lu, J. Feng, D. Yuan, M. Tian <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013&#x02003;<italic>Tetrahymena</italic> functional genomics database (TetraFGD): an integrated resource for <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> functional genomics. Database (Oxford) 2013:bat008.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>