<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><?origin nihpa?><?iso-abbr Nature?><?submitter-system nihms?><?submitter-canonical-name Nature Publishing Group?><?submitter-canonical-id NATURE-STRUCTUR?><?submitter-userid 8068858?><?submitter-authority myNCBI?><?submitter-login nature-structure?><?submitter-name Nature Publishing Group?><?domain nihpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0410462</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">6011</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nature</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nature</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0028-0836</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1476-4687</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4909121</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26982719</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature17184</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">nihpa755501</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>PGC1&#x003b1;-dependent NAD biosynthesis links oxidative metabolism to renal protection</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>Mei T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zsengeller</surname><given-names>Zsuzsanna K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>Anders H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khankin</surname><given-names>Eliyahu V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhasin</surname><given-names>Manoj K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Wondong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clish</surname><given-names>Clary B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>Isaac E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karumanchi</surname><given-names>S. Ananth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>Eugene P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>Samir M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Division of Nephrology and Department of Medicine, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA 02215</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Center for Vascular Biology Research, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA 02215</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Division of Clinical Chemistry, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA 02215</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Pathology, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA 02215</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Bioinformatics and Systems Biology Core, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA 02215</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Renal and Endocrine Units, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, 02114</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard, Cambridge, MA, 02139</aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Chevy Chase, MD 20815</aff><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>2</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>531</volume><issue>7595</issue><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1038/nature17184--><permissions><license><license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</uri></license-p></license><license license-type="permissions-link"><license-p>Reprints and permissions information is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.nature.com/reprints">www.nature.com/reprints</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">The energetic burden of continuously concentrating solutes against gradients along the tubule may render the kidney especially vulnerable to ischemia. Indeed, acute kidney injury (AKI) affects 3% of all hospitalized patients.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Here we show that the mitochondrial biogenesis regulator, PGC1&#x003b1;,<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> is a pivotal determinant of renal recovery from injury by regulating NAD biosynthesis. Following renal ischemia, PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice developed local deficiency of the NAD precursor niacinamide (Nam), marked fat accumulation, and failure to re-establish normal function. Remarkably, exogenous Nam improved local NAD levels, fat accumulation, and renal function in post-ischemic PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. Inducible tubular transgenic mice (iNephPGC1&#x003b1;) recapitulated the effects of Nam supplementation, including more local NAD and less fat accumulation with better renal function after ischemia. PGC1&#x003b1; coordinately upregulated the enzymes that synthesize NAD <italic>de novo</italic> from amino acids whereas PGC1&#x003b1; deficiency or AKI attenuated the <italic>de novo</italic> pathway. Nam enhanced NAD via the enzyme NAMPT and augmented production of the fat breakdown product beta-hydroxybutyrate (&#x003b2;-OHB), leading to increased prostaglandin PGE<sub>2</sub>, a secreted autocoid that maintains renal function.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Nam treatment reversed established ischemic AKI and also prevented AKI in an unrelated toxic model. Inhibition of &#x003b2;-OHB signaling or prostaglandins similarly abolished PGC1&#x003b1;-dependent renoprotection. Given the importance of mitochondrial health in aging and the function of metabolically active organs, the results implicate Nam and NAD as key effectors for achieving PGC1&#x003b1;-dependent stress resistance.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="P2">The mature renal tubule returns ~140L/day of filtered plasma water back to the circulation by establishing energy-intensive electrochemical gradients between the filtrate and vasculature. The kidney is only second to the heart in mitochondrial abundance.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> We hypothesized that PGC1&#x003b1; (peroxisome proliferator activated receptor gamma co-activator-1-alpha), enriched in renal tubules and important for stress resistance in the brain, heart and other metabolically active organs,<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> regulates oxidative metabolism in the epithelium to affect overall kidney health.</p><p id="P3">Hans Krebs identified acylglycerols as a major renal fuel.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Following transient local ischemia, renal function worsened, PGC1&#x003b1; expression declined, tubular mitochondria swelled, and a pronounced accumulation of acylglycerols developed in tubules (p &#x0003c; 0.0001, <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1a&#x02013;e</xref>, <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 1a&#x02013;c</xref>). The fidelity of serum creatinine was confirmed by comparison to cystatin C and inulin clearance (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 1d&#x02013;f</xref>). PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice experienced worse renal function, greater fat accumulation, and more tubular injury following ischemia (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1f</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 2a&#x02013;g</xref>). To define pathways specific to PGC1&#x003b1; altered by ischemia, we examined metabolite profiles. Comparing sham vs. post-ischemic kidneys yielded six differentially abundant metabolites; comparing uninjured PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> vs. wildtype littermate kidneys yielded 11. Four were shared between settings, with all four lower in PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and post-ischemic kidneys (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1g,h</xref>, <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 3a,b</xref>).</p><p id="P4">Of these, carnitine deficiency in PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and post-ischemic kidneys supported mitochondrial involvement in both situations. Deficiency of betaine and choline, two osmolytes essential for cell volume maintenance in the uniquely hypertonic renal environment, was not unanticipated. We therefore focused on niacinamide (Nam), the predominant mammalian precursor to synthesize the energy carrier NAD needed for fatty acid oxidation (FAO).<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> After confirming the metabolomics results (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 3c&#x02013;e</xref>), we tested the effect of Nam supplementation. Exogenous Nam increased renal Nam (p &#x0003c; 0.001), normalized post-ischemic fat accumulation, and completely prevented post-ischemic AKI in PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1i</xref>, <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 3f&#x02013;h</xref>), implicating this metabolite as an unexpected effector of PGC1&#x003b1;.</p><p id="P5">To probe the robustness of PGC1&#x003b1;&#x02019;s relation to Nam, fat accumulation, and renal function, we developed an inducible tubular epithelial transgenic model using the well-validated Pax8 promoter (iNephPGC1&#x003b1;).<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Heterologous PGC1&#x003b1; was tightly controlled without leaky gene expression; organ size and mass were indistinguishable; and mitochondrial abundance increased&#x02014;as assessed by comparing mitochondrial to nuclear DNA and mitochondrial gene products to cytosolic gene products&#x02014;without altering ultrastructural morphology or the anatomical distribution favoring cortex and outer stripe of the outer medulla (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2a&#x02013;c</xref>, <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 4a&#x02013;i</xref>). iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice tolerated renal ischemia more successfully, achieving better survival (p = 0.0039), more preserved function (p &#x0003c; 0.0001), better kidney perfusion, and less tubular injury (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2d&#x02013;k</xref>, <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 4j,k</xref>). Sham-operated mice experienced no significant change in creatinine or reduced survival. Renal Nam was higher in post-ischemic iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice, and post-ischemic fat accumulation was markedly reduced compared to controls (p &#x0003c; 0.0001, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2l&#x02013;q</xref>). Renal protection in iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice was shared across distinct models as post-inflammatory renal injury was also attenuated (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 5a</xref>). PGC1&#x003b1;&#x02019;s effect appeared to be cell-type specific as endothelial over-expression conferred no renoprotection (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 5b</xref>).</p><p id="P6">RNA sequencing identified 1160 transcripts associated with PGC1&#x003b1;-dependent renoprotection (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3a</xref>, <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Information Table 1</xref>). The pathways most over-represented related to intermediary metabolism (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3b</xref>). Closer examination revealed that <italic>de novo</italic> NAD biosynthetic enzymes were coordinately regulated, induced in uninjured iNephPGC1&#x003b1; kidneys and suppressed in post-ischemic or uninjured PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> kidneys (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3c&#x02013;f</xref>). PGC1&#x003b1;&#x02019;s effect on the <italic>de novo</italic> pathway was cell- autonomous as knockdown in isolated renal tubular cells was sufficient to suppress the pathway (p = 0.0001, <xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 6a</xref>).</p><p id="P7">As epithelial PGC1&#x003b1; defended renal function and resolved post-ischemic fat accumulation, we hypothesized that protection from AKI may relate to Nam, NAD, and fatty acid utilization. Indeed, exogenous Nam dose-dependently increased renal NAD and drove local accumulation of the fatty acid breakdown product &#x003b2;-OHB to ~ten-fold higher than normal circulating concentrations (p &#x0003c; 0.0001, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3g</xref> and <xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 6b,c</xref>). &#x003b2;-OHB activates HCAR2, a G-protein coupled receptor that induces the renoprotective prostaglandin PGE<sub>2</sub>.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Silencing or chemical inhibition of HCAR2 markedly reduced both basal and ligand-dependent PGE<sub>2</sub> secretion (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3h</xref>, <xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 6d,e</xref>). Nam augmented PGE<sub>2</sub> secretion, requiring conversion to NAD via the enzyme NAMPT to do so (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3i</xref>, <xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 6f,g</xref>).<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Silencing of PGC1&#x003b1; reduced each intermediate, lowering the cellular NAD and secreted &#x003b2;-OHB and PGE<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3j&#x02013;l</xref>). In PGC1&#x003b1;-silenced cells, excess &#x003b2;-OHB was still able to induce PGE<sub>2</sub> secretion (p &#x0003c; 0.0001, <xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 6h</xref>). Finally, renal levels of each component mirrored the cellular results, with opposing effects of PGC1&#x003b1; deficiency and excess on NAD, &#x003b2;-OHB, and PGE<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3m&#x02013;o</xref>, <xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 7a&#x02013;c</xref>). Together, these results implicated PGC1&#x003b1;-dependent NAD production as an important determinant of cellular metabolism that induces renoprotective molecules (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3p</xref>).</p><p id="P8">To test this further, we inhibited &#x003b2;-OHB signaling with mepenzolate bromide or prostaglandin synthesis with indomethacin in iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice subjected to ischemia. Renal protection was similarly abolished in either setting, confirming their roles as PGC1&#x003b1; effectors (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4a,b</xref>, <xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 7d,e</xref>). Since Nam prevented ischemic AKI in PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, we then asked whether Nam has a broader therapeutic role. Nam administered after established AKI significantly improved renal function (p = 0.0011, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4c</xref>). We also observed that renal Nam declined following cisplatin, a chemotherapy whose use is limited by nephrotoxicity and whose injurious mechanism involves mitochondria but is considered distinct from ischemia (<xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 7f,g</xref>). Nam supplementation prevented cisplatin-induced AKI (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4d,e</xref>). Finally, we found that PGC1&#x003b1; expression in human AKI was strongly suppressed, even in histologically normal regions of renal tissue (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4f&#x02013;h</xref>, <xref rid="F12" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 8a&#x02013;f</xref>), mirroring the AKI-induced suppression of PGC1&#x003b1; observed in experimental models (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 1c</xref> and <sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>). These results show that PGC1&#x003b1; is a negatively regulated target in AKI.</p><p id="P9">The present results identify PGC1&#x003b1; as a pivotal mediator of renal resistance to acute stressors. By linking oxidative metabolism in the epithelium to overall organ function, the proposed pathway provides new insight into a longstanding observation, namely the exquisite sensitivity of the kidney to ischemia and other insults. More fundamentally, the results implicate NAD biosynthesis as a coordinately regulated target of PGC1&#x003b1;.</p><p id="P10">NAD has long been recognized for its central role in energy metabolism, with recent work demonstrating that NAD is rate-limiting for mitochondrial function.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> NAD augmentation appears to restore youthful mitochondrial function and reverse age-related declines in health.<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> In contrast, NAD depletion has been described as a feature of diabetes.<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Since diabetes and aging are two of the most prevalent predispositions for AKI, the present results motivate interest in whether local NAD concentration may provide a setpoint for resistance to acute renal stressors. NAD may also be important for the gradual decline of kidney function with normal aging.</p><p id="P11">That an even larger set of known AKI risk factors&#x02014;including diabetes, but also chronic kidney disease (<xref rid="F12" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 8g,h</xref>), sepsis, and warm ischemia&#x02014;is associated with reduction of PGC1&#x003b1;,<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> further attests to the potential relevance of the results to human disease. Experiments targeting mitochondrial biogenesis through a drug-screening approach offer additional promise for this avenue in AKI.<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Since AKI has been associated with death in critically ill patients,<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> that excess renal PGC1&#x003b1; improves survival after AKI highlights the importance of the kidney to overall health. Downstream of PGC1&#x003b1;, Nam may not only be an effective preventative agent, but also a potential therapy for established AKI, a set of diseases for which no drug has yet been identified.</p><p id="P12">PGC1&#x003b1; in skeletal muscle has been shown to exert extracellular effects, whether through the myokine irisin, metabolites such as kynurenine, or the angiogenic factor VEGF.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> By comparison, the present results show that renal tubular PGC1&#x003b1; communicates with neighboring cells at least through PGE<sub>2</sub>. Therapeutic manipulation of renal &#x003b2;-OHB may constitute one means of increasing PGE<sub>2</sub>. PGE<sub>2</sub> is a well-recognized vasodilator in the kidney, but may also be exerting cytoprotective effects in AKI (reviewed in <sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>), actions that have been demonstrated in multiple animal models and even humans.<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup></p><p id="P13">We observed enhanced renal function, vascular relaxation, and increased perfusion at baseline as a result of excess PGC1&#x003b1; in the epithelial compartment of the kidney in the iNephPGC1&#x003b1; model (<xref rid="F13" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 9a&#x02013;j</xref>), physiological features that would be consistent with functional responses of the local vasculature to the excess renal PGE<sub>2</sub> present in this model. However, we also asked whether VEGF was regulated by renal PGC1&#x003b1; as such features could also arise from increased vascularization (<xref rid="F13" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 9k&#x02013;m</xref>). PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice showed no decrement in renal VEGF and iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice displayed only modest induction vs. their respective controls. This strongly contrasts with VEGF induction by skeletal muscle PGC1&#x003b1;,<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> suggesting the presence of cell-specific modulators of PGC1&#x003b1; function such as ERR&#x003b1;, which is notably more abundant in skeletal muscle than kidney (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.biogps.org">www.biogps.org</ext-link>).</p><p id="P14">Our results suggest several avenues for future investigation. First, the coordinated regulation of NAD biosynthesis by PGC1&#x003b1; may occur in other cells and organs, particularly under stress conditions. Of the major biosynthetic routes to NAD&#x02014;<italic>de novo</italic> from amino acids, the Preiss-Handler pathway from niacin, and salvage from Nam via NAMPT&#x02014;PGC1&#x003b1;&#x02019;s action on each will require careful dissection as this may vary depending on cell type and condition. The transcription factor(s) with which PGC1&#x003b1; interacts to induce the <italic>de novo</italic> pathway are of substantial interest. Since ischemia did not reduce renal NAMPT (<xref rid="F14" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 10</xref>), the salvage pathway may be a viable therapeutic route. Second, the rapid reduction of NAD during AKI may also relate to its already short half-life<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> as well as the action of NAD-consuming enzymes such as PARPs, nucleotidases, and sirtuins, all of which have been implicated in this condition.<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Third, NAD&#x02019;s emerging role as a guardian against age-related decline in health and mitochondrial function<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> suggests that therapeutic manipulation of Nam and NAD may have implications beyond AKI. For example, NAMPT agonism protects against experimental neuronal injury.<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> And inhibition of urinary Nam disposal (by blocking N-methylation) prevents experimental obesity.<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> Finally, the link from mitochondrial metabolism to renoprotective prostaglandins unites two major avenues of mechanistic investigation in AKI, but other mediators and downstream effectors for renal PGC1&#x003b1; may also exist.</p><p id="P15">In summary, the present work applies complementary discovery approaches to identify a new pathway by which parenchymal PGC1&#x003b1; affects NAD to protect against renal injury. The results may have mechanistic, diagnostic, and therapeutic implications in the kidney and beyond.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="S1" specific-use="web-only"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="S2"><title>Mouse studies</title><p id="P16">All studies with mice were reviewed and approved by the Institutional Animal Use and Care Committee of Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center (BIDMC). PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> (stock # 008597), Pax8-rtTA (# 007176) and TRE-PGC1&#x003b1; (# 012387) mice were all obtained from Jackson Laboratories and bred at BIDMC. The parental strains were generated on a mixed C57 background with further backcrossing into C57BL/6J as described by the manufacturer, except for the TRE-PGC1&#x003b1; mouse, which was generated on and is maintained on FVB. Primers for genotyping have been described elsewhere.<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> All experiments were performed with littermate controls.</p><p id="P17">Ischemia-reperfusion injury (IRI) was performed on 8&#x02013;12 week-old males through two small paramedial dorsal incisions by applying a microvascular clamp to each renal pedicle for 20 minutes. Mice were anesthetized with isoflurane for the duration of surgery and warmed to 37&#x000b0;C using a servo-controlled heating pad. Incisions were closed in two layers and mice were revived with 1 ml warm saline injected intraperitoneally.</p><p id="P18">All chemicals were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich unless otherwise noted. Niacinamide was given by intraperitoneal injection of 400 mg/kg/day &#x000d7; 4 days in saline, with the final dose an hour prior to IRI surgery. In rescue experiments, the same dose was administered once 18 hours after reperfusion. Indomethacin was given by intraperitoneal injection of 10 mg/kg in 0.1 M sodium carbonate/saline an hour prior to IRI. The HCAR2 inhibitor, mepenzolate bromide, was given by intraperitoneal injection of 10 mg/kg in saline an hour prior to IRI.<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> LPS (<italic>E.coli</italic> serotype O111:B4) was given by intraperitoneal injection of 25 mg/kg in saline. Cisplatin was given by intraperitoneal injection of 25 mg/kg as previously described.<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> Unless otherwise stated, blood and kidneys were collected 24 h after the AKI model.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Mass spectrometry measurements</title><p id="P19">All measurements were performed in a blinded fashion by an independent facility. Creatinine was analyzed by LC/MS-MS at the University of Alabama Birmingham O&#x02019;Brien Core Center for Acute Kidney Injury Research (NIH P30-DK079337). This method adds the accuracy of MS to the LC method of creatinine measurement endorsed by a renal investigative consortium (diacomp.org). The coefficient of variation was 6% indicating high assay precision.</p><p id="P20">For metabolomics measurements, snap frozen kidneys were cut to equal weights (20 mg/specimen) and mechanically homogenized into 4 volumes of ice-cold water. Metabolites were assayed as previously described.<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> In brief, amino acids, amines, acylcarnitines, nucleotides, and other cationic polar metabolites were measured in 10 &#x003bc;l of kidney homogenate using hydrophilic interaction liquid chromatography coupled with nontargeted, positive ion mode MS analysis on an Exactive Plus Orbitrap MS (Thermo Scientific). Polar and non-polar lipids were measured in 10 &#x003bc;l of kidney homogenate using C8 chromatography and nontargeted, positive ion mode MS analysis on a Q Exactive MS (Thermo Scientific). Identification of known metabolites was achieved by matching retention times and mass-to-charge ratio (m/z) to synthetic mixtures of reference compounds and characterized pooled plasma reference samples. Results were analyzed in MetaboAnalyst (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.metaboanalyst.ca">www.metaboanalyst.ca</ext-link>).</p><p id="P21">LC-MS assays were developed for multiplex quantification of Nam, NAD, and &#x003b2;-hydroxybutyrate (&#x003b2;-OHB) from cellular experiments. NAD measurements reflect total NAD<sup>+</sup> plus NADH. Briefly, conditioned medium was extracted with methanol (80% methanol final concentration) spiked with isotopic standards for Nam and &#x003b2;-OHB (CDN Isotopes, Inc.). Precipitated proteins were removed by centrifugation, and supernatants were analyzed directly. For analysis of cell lysates, cells were washed with ice-cold PBS, scraped and lysed on dry ice into methanol containing isotopic standards. After extraction, cell and media supernatants were analyzed by LC-MS/MS using reverse-phase chromatography (NAM and NAD/NADH) or hydrophilic interaction chromatography (&#x003b2;-OHB) coupled to tandem mass spectrometry using an API 5000 triple quadruple mass spectrometer. Analytes were quantified by multiple reaction monitoring using the following m/z transitions: &#x003b2;-OHB 103.1&#x0003e;59, &#x003b2;-OHB IS 105.1&#x0003e;60, NAM 123.3&#x0003e;80.2, NAM IS 127.3&#x0003e;84.2, NAD/NADH 664.2&#x0003e;542.0. Eluting peaks were quantified by area under the curve (AUC).</p><p id="P22">Raw AUC values were divided by the mean value of the control group for each experiment, thus the results are presented as relative concentrations to the control group. All assays were performed in triplicate and replicate measurements demonstrated a CV &#x0003c; 5%.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>RNASEQ sequencing and identification of differentially expressed transcripts</title><p id="P23">PolyA-enriched RNA was isolated from whole kidneys and checked for quality by denaturing agarose gel as well as Aglient Bioanalyzer. Sequencing libraries were generated from the double-stranded cDNA using the Illumina TruSeq kit according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Library quality control was checked using the Agilent DNA High Sensitivity Chip and qRT-PCR. High quality libraries were sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq 2000. To achieve comprehensive coverage for each sample, we generated ~25&#x02013;30 million single end reads. Raw results were passed through quality controls steps and aligned to the mouse genome. Gene expression measurement was performed from aligned reads by counting the unique reads. The read count based gene expression data was normalized on the basis of library complexity and gene variation. The normalized count data was compared among groups using a negative binomial model to identify differentially expressed genes. The differentially expressed genes were identified on the basis of raw P value and fold change. Genes were considered significantly differentially expressed if the multiple test corrected p-value was &#x0003c; 0.05 and absolute fold change &#x0003e; 2.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Functional enrichment analysis</title><p id="P24">Ingenuity Pathway Analysis (IPA 8.0, Qiagen) was used to identify the functions that are significantly affected by significantly differentially expressed genes from different comparisons. The knowledge base of this software consists of functions, pathways, and network models derived by systematically exploring the peer reviewed scientific literature. A detailed description of IPA analysis is available at the Ingenuity Systems&#x02019; web site (http//<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ingenuity.com">www.ingenuity.com</ext-link>). A p-value is calculated for each function according to the fit of the users&#x02019; data to the IPA database using one-tailed Fisher exact test. The functions with multiple test corrected p-values &#x0003c; 0.01 were considered significantly affected.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Western analysis</title><p id="P25">Kidney lysate preparation, gel electrophoresis, transfer, immunoblotting, detection, and image acquisition were performed as previously described.<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> Antibodies against PGC1&#x003b1; (Cayman Chemical), cytochrome c oxidase subunit IV (Cell Signaling Technology), and Transcription Factor A Mitochondrial, TFAM (Abcam) were used as previously described. <sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Quantitative PCR</title><p id="P26">Total RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis were performed as previously described.<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> PCR reactions were performed in duplicate using the ABI 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR and TaqMan gene expression assays (Applied Biosystems). The following TaqMan gene probes were used: <italic>Ppargc1a, Ndufs1, Cycs, Atp5o, Nrf1, Tfam, Vegfa, Nos1, Nos3, Hcar2.</italic> Of the four known <italic>Ppargc1a</italic> transcripts (1&#x02013;4), <italic>Ppargc1a1</italic> (Taqman Mm00447183_m1) was studied in all gene expression analyses.<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> Mouse <italic>Ido2, Afmid, Kynu, Kmo, Haao, Qprt, Naprt,</italic> and <italic>Nmnat1</italic> for SYBR Green PCR have been described elsewhere.<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> Mouse <italic>Nampt</italic> SYBR primers were designed using PrimerQuest Tool (Integrated DNA Technologies). Relative expression levels were determined using the comparative threshold method.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Mitochondrial DNA copy number analysis</title><p id="P27">Total DNA was extracted from mouse kidneys using the DNeasy Blood and Tissue Kit (Qiagen) with on-column RNase digestion per manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Gene expression of mitochondrial-encoded NADH dehydrogenase 1 (<italic>mt-Nd1</italic>) relative to nuclear 18S rRNA was used to determine mitochondrial DNA copy number as previously described.<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Histopathology</title><p id="P28">Formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded blocks were sectioned and stained with H &#x00026; E, PAS, and Masson trichrome. Ten random high-power fields in the cortex and ten random high-power fields in the outer stripe of the outer medulla were viewed and graded for tubular necrosis&#x02014;defined as the loss of the proximal tubular brush border, blebbing of apical membranes, tubular necrosis/apoptosis and epithelial cell detachment from _the basement membrane or intraluminal aggregation of necrotic debris. Each high-power field was separately scored on a scale (0 = no necrosis, 1= rare single necrotic cells, 2= frequent single necrotic cells, 3 = groups of necrotic cells, and 4 = confluent tubular necrosis) and the average score was compiled for each specimen and then used for between-group comparisons. All scoring was performed by a single operator blinded to genotype and experimental model (IES).</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>In situ COX enzyme chemistry</title><p id="P29">Enzyme histochemistry to detect cytochrome c oxidase (COX) activity was performed on 6 &#x003bc;m snap-frozen sagittal sections as previously described.<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> Functional electron microscopy used in the cisplatin kidney injury model was described earlier.<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Electron microscopy</title><p id="P30">The complete method is previously described.<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> Briefly, kidneys were fixed with 1.25% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M cacodylate buffer (pH 7.4) and cut in 1 &#x003bc;m section in both sagittal and transverse planes for image analysis. After drying the sections, slides were stained at 65&#x000b0;C for 20 minutes in 0.1% Toluidine blue in 1% sodium borate, cooled to room temperature, washed in distilled water, cleaned in xylene, and mounted in Permount sections for light microscopy. Subsequent ultrathin sections (0.5 &#x003bc;m) were examined by transmission electron microscopy (JEOL 1011, JEOL Corp.) with Orca-HR Digital Camera (Hamamatsu Corp.), and Advanced Microscopy Technique Corporation image capture system.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Oil-Red-O staining</title><p id="P31">Oil-Red-O solution was prepared by dissolving 0.5 g Oil-Red-O (Poly Scientific) in 100 ml isopropanol. Frozen sections were cut to 5 &#x003bc;m and natively stained in Oil-Red-O solution for 20 minutes at room temperature, then rinsed in running tap water for 2 min. Hematoxylin counter-staining was performed without differentiation in HCl-ethanol and sections were rinsed with water, then mounted with VectaMount AQ Aqueous Mounting medium (Vector Labs).</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Human biopsy series</title><p id="P32">All studies were approved by the Institutional Review Board at BIDMC. Control specimens came from normal tissue sections of nephrectomies. CKD diagnoses included focal segmental glomerulosclerosis, chronic allograft nephropathy, chronic interstitial nephritis, and chronic IgA nephropathy. AKI diagnoses included acute ischemic injury, post-transplant delayed graft function attributable to ischemia-reperfusion injury, and acute interstitial nephritis. PGC1&#x003b1; antibody (Abcam ab54481) was used at a dilution of 1:100 and developed with horseradish peroxidase (ImmPRESS polymer staining kit, Vector Labs). The peptide immunogen SKYDSLDFDSLLKEAQRSLRR (synthesized by the Biopolymers Lab, Koch Institute at MIT) was pre-incubated in 100-fold excess of the PGC1&#x003b1; antibody to confirm antibody specificity in human IHC studies. Ten randomly selected high-powered fields were viewed per specimen, with each field scored on a 4-point scale (1 = weakest, 4 = strongest) based on the intensity of staining, specifically in non-necrotic areas and unscarred areas and avoiding obvious collecting ducts. The average score of each specimen was then used for between-group comparisons. All scoring was performed by a single operator blinded to the underlying diagnosis (IES).</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Microultrasound</title><p id="P33">The full method is previously described.<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> Briefly, mice were lightly anesthetized, secured to a heat-controlled stage, and continuously monitored for respiration, ECG, and core temperature. A high frequency, high resolution digital imaging platform with linear array technology and equipped with a high-frequency linear array probe MS550D (22&#x02013;55 MHz) was used throughout the study (Vevo 2100 Visual Sonics). The flow volume was modeled as a circular cylinder of length equal to the average velocity time integral and diameter measured empirically (n = 3 cardiac cycles), then multiplied by the heart rate (bpm), then converted from mm<sup>3</sup>/min to ml/min. All measurements and analyses were performed by a single blinded operator (EVK).</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Cellular studies</title><p id="P34">Mouse intermedullary collecting duct (IMCD3) cells were obtained from ATCC. Please refer to their website for validation and mycoplasma testing. Cells were transfected with siRNA targeting mouse PGC1&#x003b1;, HCAR2 or a negative control siRNA (Qiagen) for 24 h. Niacin, mepenzolate bromide, &#x003b2;-hydroxybutyrate, the NAMPT inhibitor FK866,<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> and niacinamide were diluted to the indicated concentrations in serum- free cell culture medium. Prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub> (PGE<sub>2</sub>) was measured in the conditioned media 24&#x02013;72 hours after treatment.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Cystatin C</title><p id="P35">Cystatin C in mouse serum (1:200 dilution) was measured by ELISA (R&#x00026;D Systems).</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>FITC-inulin clearance</title><p id="P36">The full method is described elsewhere.<sup><xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> Briefly, male C57BL/6J mice (Jackson Laboratories) were given a single bolus injection of 5%-FITC- inulin (3.74 &#x003bc;l/g body weight). Clearance kinetics of FITC-inulin post-injection was measured by serial blood collection at specified time points from 3 through 70 minutes post-injection. Blood samples were centrifuged and resulting plasma was buffered to pH 7.4 with 500 mM HEPES. Fluorescence in the buffered plasma samples was determined with 485 nm excitation, 538 nm emission. Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) was calculated from the two phase exponential decay model outlined previously.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Tissue PGE<sub>2</sub> &#x003b2;-OHB, and NAD measurements</title><p id="P37">PGE<sub>2</sub> was measured in mouse kidney tissue by ELISA (Cayman Chemical). &#x003b2;-OHB (Cayman Chemical) and total NAD (BioVision) was measured in mouse kidney tissue by colorimetric assays. These assays were performed on kidneys used for metabolomics and lipidomics in order to compare coordinated changes in metabolism and downstream signaling. NAD measurements reflect total NAD<sup>+</sup> plus NADH.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="P38">Comparisons between continuous characteristics of subject groups were analyzed with Mann-Whitney U tests or Student&#x02019;s t test. Survival was analyzed by log-rank test. For comparisons among more than two groups, ANOVA with Bonferroni correction was used where indicated. Associations between microultrasound measurements and other functional parameters were analyzed with Spearman&#x02019;s rank correlation coefficients. Sample size determination was guided by power calculations and prior experience. The following sample calculation was used to guide creatinine studies in mice: serum creatinine of 1.6 (&#x000b1; 0.3 SD) mg/dl vs. 1.0 (&#x000b1; 0.2 SD) requires n = 5 mice per condition to achieve an &#x003b1;-error &#x0003c; 5% and power 96%. Mice were randomized to experimental intervention vs. control. Two-tailed p-values &#x0003c; 0.05 were considered significant. Results are presented as mean &#x000b1; SEM and were prepared in GraphPad Prism.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Extended Data</title><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 1</label><caption><title>Regulation of PGC1&#x003b1; and other features of post-ischemic kidneys</title><p id="P39">a, Serum creatinine 24 h after sham or IRI (n=5 vs. 14 mice), ***p&#x0003c; 0.001. <bold>b,</bold> Absence of classwide changes in intrarenal phospholipids 24 h after IRI vs. sham operation (n=6/group, NS=non-significant). Each bar represents one lipid species. P-value by two-way ANOVA. <bold>c,</bold> Renal PGC1&#x003b1; expression 24 h after sham or IRI (n = 5 animals per group), **p&#x0003c;0.01. <bold>d,</bold> Correlation of LC-MS method for serum creatinine and serum cystatin C (measured by ELISA). <bold>e,</bold> Glomerular filtration rate in controls or 24 h after IRI was determined by two-phase exponential decay curves of fluorescently-labeled inulin as described in methods (n=5/group), *p&#x0003c;0.05. <bold>f,</bold> Correlation of LC-MS method for serum creatinine with clearance of FITC-inulin. Curve fit according to formula sCr=<bold>&#x003ba;</bold>/GFR where <bold>&#x003ba;</bold> is a constant. Error bars SEM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f5"/></fig><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 2</label><caption><title>Exacerbation of fat accumulation and tubular injury in post-ischemic PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> kidneys</title><p id="P40"><bold>a&#x02013;d,</bold> Low (<bold>a,b</bold>) and high-power (<bold>c,d</bold>) photomicrographs 24 h after IRI in WT vs. PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> (KO) mice. Scale bars 100 and 50 &#x003bc;m. <bold>e,f,</bold> Blinded scoring of tubular injury in cortex and outer stripe of outer medulla (OSOM) on 4-point injury scale as described in Methods (n=8 WT vs.12 KO mice), *p&#x0003c;0.05. <bold>g,</bold> Di-/tri-acylglycerols (DAGs, TAGs) in renal homogenates of KO mice at baseline and 24 h after injury (n=6/group). Each bar represents one lipid species. P-value by two-way ANOVA. Error bars SEM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f6"/></fig><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 3</label><caption><title>Niacinamide (Nam) reduction from IRI and PGC1&#x003b1; deficiency</title><p id="P41"><bold>a,</bold> Heatmaps (red=higher, green=lower) of Bonferroni-corrected significantly different metabolites in sham vs. IRI kidneys and WT vs. KO kidneys. Metabolites listed in purple are shared between settings. <bold>b,</bold> Total ion chromatogram of polar, positive ion mode method for representative WT-IRI sample, with niacinamide (Nam) peak at retention time = 3.88 minutes. Inset shows representative niacinamide peaks for kidney extracts from WT control (Ctrl) and WT-IRI (IRI) mice. <bold>c&#x02013;e,</bold> Relative renal Nam abundance in kidneys of KO mice vs. WT littermates; WT littermates at baseline and 24 h after IRI; and KO mice at baseline and 24 h after IRI (n=6/group). <bold>f,</bold> Relative renal Nam concentrations in kidneys of mice following vehicle (Veh) vs. Nam treatment (400 mg/kg IP &#x000d7; 4d) with and without IRI 24 h prior to tissue collection (n=6/group). P-values by two-way ANOVA. <bold>g,h,</bold> Oil Red O stain (pink) for fat accumulation 24 h after IRI with or without Nam pretreatment (400 mg/kg IP &#x000d7; 4 d), scale bar 20 &#x003bc;m. Error bars SEM, *p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01, ***p&#x0003c;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f7"/></fig><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 4</label><caption><title>Increased mitochondrial abundance and post-ischemic protection in renal tubular epithelial transgenic mice (iNephPGC1&#x003b1;)</title><p id="P42"><bold>a</bold>, Schematic for generating iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice. <bold>b</bold>, Relative renal PGC1&#x003b1; expression in controls vs. iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice with and without 4 weeks of doxycycline in drinking water (n = 5/group, **p&#x0003c;0.01 vs. all other groups). <bold>c,</bold> Ratio of kidney weight to total body weight (note body weights statistically indistinguishable as well, n=4/group). <bold>d,</bold> Example gross images with 1 cm scale of control vs. iNephPGC1&#x003b1; kidney. <bold>e,</bold> Renal mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) copy number as described in Methods. <bold>f</bold>, Relative renal gene expression of PGC1&#x003b1; targets (Ndufs1, Cycs, Atp5o), partnering transcription factors (Nrf1), and the mitochondrial transcription factor, TFAM. Results analyzed by two-way ANOVA with p-value for genotype as noted. N=8/group. *p&#x0003c;0.05 vs. control after Bonferroni correction. <bold>g,</bold> Western analysis of kidney lysates for Transcription Factor A, Mitochondrial (TFAM)<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> and loading control. <bold>h,i,</bold> Transmission EM of mitochondria sectioned perpendicular and parallel to long axis demonstrating normal morphology in iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice (representative of n=4/group), scale bar 500 nm. <bold>j,k</bold>, Blinded scoring of tubular injury in cortex and outer stripe of outer medulla (n=8 control; 12 iNephPGC1&#x003b1;). Error bars SEM, *p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f8"/></fig><fig id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 5</label><caption><title>Renal protection in systemic inflammation conferred by renal tubular epithelial, but not endothelial, PGC1&#x003b1;</title><p id="P43"><bold>a,</bold> Serum creatinine 24 h after bacterial endotoxin injection (LPS O111:B4), n=9/group. <bold>b,</bold> Serum creatinine 24 h after bacterial endotoxin (LPS O111:B4) in endothelial-specific (VEC=VE-cadherin) PGC1&#x003b1; transgenic mice (VEC-tTA x TRE-PGC1&#x003b1;), n=5/group. Error bars SEM, *p &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f9"/></fig><fig id="F10" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 6</label><caption><title>PGC1&#x003b1;-dependent <italic>de novo</italic> NAD biosynthesis and NAD-dependent accumulation of &#x003b2;-OHB and PGE<sub>2</sub></title><p id="P44"><bold>a,</bold> Gene expression for <italic>de novo</italic> NAD biosynthetic pathway in renal tubular cells 48 h after control vs. PGC1&#x003b1; knockdown (n=3/group). The gene expression set corresponds to the eight transcripts whose abundance was measured in kidney homogenates in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. P=0.0001 by two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni-corrected comparisons as indicated. <bold>b,</bold> Correlation of renal Nam vs. renal NAD in mice treated with vehicle or different doses of Nam (100&#x02013;400 mg/kg IP &#x000d7; 1). Arbitrary units on X- and Y-axes. <bold>c,</bold> Renal &#x003b2;-OHB concentrations in kidneys of mice following vehicle (Veh) vs. Nam treatment (400 mg/kg IP &#x000d7; 4 d) with and without IRI 24 h prior to tissue collection (n=5/group). P-value by two-way ANOVA. Dashed line indicates normal circulating concentration of &#x003b2;-OHB. <bold>d</bold>, Dosing for siRNA against HCAR2 in renal tubular cells. <bold>e,</bold> Dose-inhibition curve in renal tubular cells for PGE<sub>2</sub> release following 24 h of mepenzolate bromide at the indicated concentrations (n=3 replicates per concentration).<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>
<bold>f,g</bold> Intracellular Nam and secreted &#x003b2;-OHB for renal tubular cells following treatment with Nam (1 &#x003bc;M for 24 h) with or without pre-treatment with the NAMPT inhibitor FK866 (10 nM, n=6/group). <bold>h,</bold> PGE<sub>2</sub> in conditioned media of renal tubular cells after control vs. PGC1&#x003b1; knockdown and with and without exogenous &#x003b2;-OHB application (+, 5 mM, n=6/group, p values vs. control group). Error bars SEM, *p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01, ***p&#x0003c;0.001, and ****p&#x0003c;0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f10"/></fig><fig id="F11" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 7</label><caption><title>Effects of PGC1&#x003b1; on renal metabolites and features of cisplatin nephrotoxicity</title><p id="P45"><bold>a&#x02013;c</bold>, Relative renal NAD, &#x003b2;-OHB, and PGE<sub>2</sub> concentrations in WT littermates vs. PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> (KO) mice (n=6/group). <bold>d,</bold> Serum creatinine in genetic control mice for iNephPGC1&#x003b1; 24 h after IRI with vehicle vs. mepenzolate (MPN, 10 mg/kg IP) treatment (n=5/group). <bold>e,</bold> Serum creatinine in genetic control mice for iNephPGC1&#x003b1; 24 h after IRI with vehicle vs. indomethacin (INDO, 10 mg/kg IP) treatment (n=6/group). <bold>f,</bold> Transmission EM with cytochrome c oxidase enzyme histochemistry of proximal tubular cell 24 h following cisplatin exposure (25 mg/kg IP) demonstrating mitochondrial injury. Scale bar 500 nm. <bold>g</bold>, Relative renal Nam concentrations following cisplatin as in <bold>f</bold>. Error bars SEM, *p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01, ***p&#x0003c;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f11"/></fig><fig id="F12" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 8</label><caption><title>Renal immunostaining for PGC1&#x003b1; declines in human chronic kidney disease</title><p id="P46"><bold>a&#x02013;d,</bold> Low (<bold>a,b</bold>) and high-power (<bold>c,d</bold>) photomicrographs of PGC1&#x003b1; immunoreactivity (brown) in wildtype littermates (WT) and PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> (KO) kidneys. Scale bars 100 and 50 &#x003bc;m. <bold>e,f</bold> Representative results of peptide competition attenuating PGC1&#x003b1; immunoreactivity against human kidney (n=4) as described in Methods. <bold>g</bold>, Representative immunostaining (brown) for PGC1&#x003b1; in a renal biopsy with chronic kidney disease (CKD). Scale bar 50 &#x003bc;m. <bold>h,</bold> Results of scoring PGC1&#x003b1; immunostaining intensity (1=weakest, 4=strongest) in specimens with CKD by blinded operator. Each dot represents a unique specimen. Analyzed by Mann-Whitney.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f12"/></fig><fig id="F13" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 9</label><caption><title>Evidence for renal-tubular-epithelial-PGC1&#x003b1;-dependent reversible vascular relaxation</title><p id="P47"><bold>a,</bold> Serum creatinine in uninduced (&#x02212;Dox) vs. induced (+Dox) iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice (n = 8&#x02013;10 mice per group). <bold>b,</bold> Comparison of serum creatinine with degree of renal PGC1&#x003b1; expression, p&#x0003c;0.05. <bold>c,d</bold> Serial serum creatinines in iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice vs. controls before PGC1&#x003b1; induction (OFF), after 4 weeks of PGC1&#x003b1; induction (ON), and after 4 weeks of washout (OFF), *p&#x0003c;0.05 by repeated measures ANOVA. <bold>e&#x02013;g,</bold> Comparison of serum creatinine at different time points with renal artery flow in iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice from <bold>d</bold>, p&#x0003c;0.05 when correlation coefficient r = &#x02212;0.65. <bold>h&#x02013;j</bold>, Comparison of resistive index with renal artery flow volume in iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice from <bold>d</bold>, p&#x0003c;0.05 when correlation coefficient r = &#x02212;0.80. <bold>k</bold>, Relative renal expression of VEGF and nitric oxide synthases 1 and 3 (n=6/group). Analyzed by two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni corrections. <bold>l</bold>, Circulating thyroxine levels in iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice with and without gene induction (n=5/group) to rule out Pax8-related thyrotoxicosis driving perfusion differences as previously described.<sup><xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>
<bold>m</bold>, Relative renal expression for VEGF in PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (KO) vs. WT littermates (n=6/group). Error bars SEM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f13"/></fig><fig id="F14" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 10</label><caption><p id="P48">Relative renal expression for NAMPT in wildtype mice before and 24 h after IRI (n=6/group). Error bars SEM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f14"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S21"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>supp_source2c</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS755501-supplement-supp_source2c.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1155" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>supp_source4g</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS755501-supplement-supp_source4g.jpg" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1159" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>supp_tables</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS755501-supplement-supp_tables.pdf" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1163" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S22"><p>The authors thank Mark Zeidel (Harvard Medical School BIDMC) for advice; Zolt Arany (University of Pennsylvania) for the VE-cadherin-tTA x TRE-PGC1&#x003b1; mice; Anupam Agarwal (University of Alabama NIH P30-DK079337) for LC-MS measurements of serum creatinine; Anthony Hollenberg (Harvard Medical School, BIDMC) for thyroxine measurements; and Pal Pacher (NIH) for cisplatin-treated kidneys for microscopy. This work was supported by R01-DK095072 and philanthropic funds to SMP; K08-DK090142 and a grant from Satellite Healthcare to EPR; and K08-DK101560 to EVK.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><p><xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Information</xref> is linked to the online version of the paper at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.nature.com/nature">www.nature.com/nature</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p><bold>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</bold></p><p>MTT designed experiments, performed the breeding, genotyping, renal injury models, cellular studies, analyzed data, and wrote the manuscript. ZKZ and IES performed and analyzed histopathology, enzyme histochemistry, electron microscopy, and the human biopsy immunohistochemistry studies. AHB created LC-MS assays, measured metabolites for cellular experiments, and analyzed metabolic results. EVK and SAK performed microultrasounds and analyzed flow results. MKB analyzed raw RNA sequencing data. WK, CBC, and EPR performed metabolomics, follow-up metabolite measurements, and in vivo experiments with cisplatin and Nam. SMP designed the experiments, analyzed results, and wrote the manuscript with input from all authors.</p></fn><fn id="FN3" fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thadhani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonventre</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute renal failure</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1996</year><volume>334</volume><fpage>1448</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8618585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewington</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Raising awareness of acute kidney injury: a global perspective of a silent killer</article-title><source>Kidney Int</source><year>2013</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23636171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puigserver</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A cold- inducible coactivator of nuclear receptors linked to adaptive thermogenesis</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>829</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9529258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruas</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A PGC-1alpha isoform induced by resistance training regulates skeletal muscle hypertrophy</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>1319</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23217713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gille</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwykiel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nicotinic acid- and monomethyl fumarate- induced flushing involves GPR109A expressed by keratinocytes and COX-2-dependent prostanoid formation in mice</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2010</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>2910</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20664170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagliarini</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A mitochondrial protein compendium elucidates complex I disease biology</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18614015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weidemann</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fuel of respiration of rat kidney cortex</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>1969</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5805283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaykin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The management of nicotinamide and nicotinic acid in the mouse</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1972</year><volume>247</volume><fpage>778</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4333514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traykova-Brauch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schonig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Greiner</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An efficient and versatile system for acute and chronic modulation of renal tubular function in transgenic mice</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18724376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Revollo</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The NAD biosynthesis pathway mediated by nicotinamide phosphoribosyltransferase regulates Sir2 activity in mammalian cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>50754</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15381699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PGC-1alpha promotes recovery after acute kidney injury during systemic inflammation in mice</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2011</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>4003</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21881206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Canto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Oudart</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PARP-1 inhibition increases mitochondrial metabolism through SIRT1 activation</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><year>2011</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21459330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Declining NAD(+) induces a pseudohypoxic state disrupting nuclear-mitochondrial communication during aging</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2013</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>1624</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24360282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia Soriano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Virag</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagtap</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diabetic endothelial dysfunction: the role of poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase activation</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11135624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vafai</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mootha</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial disorders as windows into an ancient organelle</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>491</volume><fpage>374</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23151580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jesinkey</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stallons</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Formoterol restores mitochondrial and renal function after ischemia-reperfusion injury</article-title><source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source><year>2014</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1157</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24511124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arany</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Foo</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HIF-independent regulation of VEGF and angiogenesis by the transcriptional coactivator PGC-1alpha</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>451</volume><fpage>1008</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18288196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bostrom</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jedrychowski</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A PGC1-alpha-dependent myokine that drives brown-fat-like development of white fat and thermogenesis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>481</volume><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22237023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agudelo</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Femenia</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Orhan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Skeletal muscle PGC-1alpha1 modulates kynurenine metabolism and mediates resilience to stress-induced depression</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25259918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breyer</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Breyer</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional and molecular aspects of renal prostaglandin receptors</article-title><source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source><year>1996</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8808104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papanicolaou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Callard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bariety</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Milliez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of indomethacin and prostaglandin (PGE2) on renal failure due to glycerol in saline-loaded rats</article-title><source>Clinical science and molecular medicine</source><year>1975</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1192709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mauk</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Patak</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadem</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lifschitz</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of prostaglandin E administration in a nephrotoxic and a vasoconstrictor model of acute renal failure</article-title><source>Kidney Int</source><year>1977</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">916501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sketch</surname><given-names>MH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Whelton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schollmayer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevention of contrast media-induced renal dysfunction with prostaglandin E1: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study</article-title><source>American journal of therapeutics</source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11344383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feldkamp</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kribben</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roeser</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preservation of complex I function during hypoxia-reoxygenation-induced mitochondrial injury in proximal tubules</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Renal Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>F749</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14665431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morigi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Perico</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rota</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sirtuin 3-dependent mitochondrial dynamic improvements protect against acute kidney injury</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2015</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25607838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebrahimkhani</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Daneshmand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazumder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aag-initiated base excision repair promotes ischemia reperfusion injury in liver, brain, and kidney</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>E4878</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25349415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajakumar</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Crikis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deficiency or inhibition of CD73 protects in mild kidney ischemia-reperfusion injury</article-title><source>Transplantation</source><year>2010</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>1260</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21063242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nijhawan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>P7C3 neuroprotective chemicals function by activating the rate-limiting enzyme in NAD salvage</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>1324</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25215490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nicotinamide N-methyltransferase knockdown protects against diet-induced obesity</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2014</year><volume>508</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24717514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PGC-1alpha promotes recovery after acute kidney injury during systemic inflammation in mice</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>4003</fpage><lpage>4014</lpage><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21881206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traykova-Brauch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An efficient and versatile system for acute and chronic modulation of renal tubular function in transgenic mice</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>984</lpage><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18724376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rask-Andersen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Almen</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schioth</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in the exploitation of novel drug targets</article-title><source>Nature reviews Drug discovery</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21804595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mycobacterium tuberculosis-driven targeted recalibration of macrophage lipid homeostasis promotes the foamy phenotype</article-title><source>Cell host &#x00026; microbe</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23159056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feingold</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigenaga</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunfeld</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammation stimulates niacin receptor (GPR109A/HCA2) expression in adipose tissue and macrophages</article-title><source>J Lipid Res</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>2501</fpage><lpage>2508</lpage><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25320346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zsengeller</surname><given-names>ZK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cisplatin nephrotoxicity involves mitochondrial injury with impaired tubular mitochondrial enzyme activity</article-title><source>J Histochem Cytochem</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22511597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A genome-wide association study of the human metabolome in a community-based cohort</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23823483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Muscle immobilization and remobilization downregulates PGC-1alpha signaling and the mitochondrial biogenesis pathway</article-title><source>J Appl Physiol (1985)</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>1618</fpage><lpage>1625</lpage><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23970536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruas</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A PGC-1alpha isoform induced by resistance training regulates skeletal muscle hypertrophy</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>151</volume><fpage>1319</fpage><lpage>1331</lpage><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23217713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakahata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Astarita</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaluzova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassone-Corsi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian control of the NAD+ salvage pathway by CLOCK-SIRT1</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>324</volume><fpage>654</fpage><lpage>657</lpage><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19286518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agudelo</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Skeletal muscle PGC-1alpha1 modulates kynurenine metabolism and mediates resilience to stress-induced depression</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>159</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25259918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nutrient sensing by the mitochondrial transcription machinery dictates oxidative phosphorylation</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>768</fpage><lpage>784</lpage><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24430182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schemainda</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FK866, a highly specific noncompetitive inhibitor of nicotinamide phosphoribosyltransferase, represents a novel mechanism for induction of tumor cell apoptosis</article-title><source>Cancer research</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>7436</fpage><lpage>7442</lpage><year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14612543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serial determination of glomerular filtration rate in conscious mice using FITC-inulin clearance</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Renal Physiol</source><volume>286</volume><fpage>F590</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14600035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antonica</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Generation of functional thyroid from embryonic stem cells</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>491</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23051751</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Niacinamide (Nam) supplementation restores normal post-ischemic response in PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice</title><p><bold>a,</bold> Pre-ischemic normal morphology and <bold>b,</bold> swollen mitochondria inside tubular cell 24h after ischemia-reperfusion injury (IRI). Scale bar 200nm. <bold>c,</bold> Renal di-/tri-acylglycerols (DAGs, TAGs) 24h following sham or IRI (n=6/group). P-value by ANOVA. <bold>d,e,</bold> Oil Red O (pink) for fat in normal and post-ischemic kidneys, scale bar 20&#x003bc;m. <bold>f,</bold> serum creatinine wildtype (WT) vs PGC1&#x003b1;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> (KO) mice (basal, n=7/group; post-ischemia, n=18/group). <bold>g,h,</bold> Volcano plots of kidney metabolites from KO vs. WT or IRI vs. sham (univariate p&#x0003c;0.05 for colored dots, n=6/group). <bold>i,</bold> Serum creatinine in post-ischemic WT vs. KO mice treated with vehicle (Veh, n=5) vs. Nam (n=9). Error bars SEM, *p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f1"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Metabolic protection in post-ischemic iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice</title><p><bold>a,b,</bold> Renal cytochrome c oxidase activity (brown), scale bar 500&#x003bc;m. <bold>c,</bold> Renal PGC1&#x003b1; and cytochrome c oxidase subunit IV. <bold>d,</bold> Survival curve following IRI (n=14 control; 24 iNephPGC1&#x003b1;). Dashed line for sham-operated mice (n=10). <bold>e,</bold> Serial serum creatinines from mice in <bold>d</bold> analyzed by ANOVA. <bold>f,g,</bold> Renal artery pulse wave and color Doppler 24h after IRI representative of 6/group. <bold>h&#x02013;k,</bold> Tubular injury in cortex and outer stripe of outer medulla (OSOM) 24h after IRI representative of 8/group. Scale bar 100&#x003bc;m. <bold>l&#x02013;o,</bold> Oil red O (pink) for fat in iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice and controls 24h after IRI representative of 8/group. Scale bars 200&#x003bc;m (upper) and 50&#x003bc;m (lower)<bold>. p,</bold> Renal Di-/tri-acylglycerols (DAGs, TAGs) in post-ischemic iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice vs. controls (n=6/group). <bold>q,</bold> Relative renal Nam 24h after IRI (n=6/group). Error bars SEM, *p&#x0003c;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f2"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Nam induces &#x003b2;-OHB downstream of PGC1&#x003b1; to augment PGE<sub>2</sub></title><p><bold>a,</bold> Renal RNA sequencing 24h after IRI or sham operation in controls vs. iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice with enumerated transcripts. <bold>b,</bold> Pathway analysis of 1160 transcripts unique to post-ischemic iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice graphed by &#x02212;log<sub>10</sub>[Benjamini-Hochberg-corrected p-value]. Dashed line at p&#x0003c;0.05. <bold>c,</bold>
<italic>de novo</italic> NAD biosynthetic pathway adapted from KEGG (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.genome.jp/kegg">www.genome.jp/kegg</ext-link>). Trp=tryptophan, Kyn=kynurenine, Am=amino, Na=nicotinate. <bold>d&#x02013;f,</bold> Heatmaps (red=lower, blue=higher) of intrarenal expression for <italic>de novo</italic> pathway from KO vs. WT; 24h after sham vs. IRI; and iNephPGC1&#x003b1; vs. controls (n=6/group). P-values by ANOVA. <bold>g,</bold> Relative renal Nam and NAD 4h after indicated Nam dose. P-value by ANOVA. <bold>h,</bold> Conditioned-media<bold>-</bold>PGE<sub>2</sub> of renal tubular cells after HCAR2 knockdown with and without HCAR2 stimulation (+,niacin 10mM, n=6/group). <bold>i</bold>, PGE<sub>2</sub> from renal cells following Nam (1&#x003bc;M for 24h) with and without NAMPT inhibitor FK866 (10nM, n=6/group). <bold>j&#x02013;l,</bold> Intracellular NAD, conditioned-media beta-hydroxybutyrate (&#x003b2;-OHB), and conditioned-media PGE<sub>2</sub> in PGC1&#x003b1; knockdown cells (n=6/group). <bold>m&#x02013;o</bold>, Relative renal NAD, &#x003b2;-OHB, and PGE<sub>2</sub> in control vs. iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice (n=6/group). *p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01, ***p&#x0003c;0.001. <bold>p,</bold> Renal epithelial PGC1&#x003b1; coordinately upregulates <italic>de novo</italic> NAD biosynthesis, in the absence of which Nam is utilized through the NAMPT-salvage pathway to generate NAD. Consequently, &#x003b2;-OHB accumulates, which signals HCAR2 to induce PGE<sub>2</sub>. Error bars SEM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f3"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>PGC1&#x003b1; effectors, Nam as therapy, and PGC1&#x003b1; in human AKI</title><p><bold>a,</bold> Serum creatinine in iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice 24h after IRI with vehicle vs. mepenzolate (MPN, 10mg/kg IP) treatment (n=6/group). <bold>b,</bold> Serum creatinine in iNephPGC1&#x003b1; mice 24h after IRI with vehicle vs. indomethacin (INDO, 10mg/kg IP) treatment (n=6/group). <bold>c,</bold> Serial serum creatinines in mice receiving a single dose of Nam (400 mg/kg IP) 18h after the onset of reperfusion, i.e., with established AKI. Analyzed by ANOVA (n=5/group). <bold>d</bold>, Serial serum creatinines after cisplatin (25mg/kg IP administered on day 0) with or without Nam (400mg/kg IP on day &#x02212;1 and day 0). Analyzed with Bonferroni-corrected ANOVA (n=5/group). <bold>e,</bold> Relative renal Nam from <bold>d. f,g,</bold> Representative immunostaining (brown) for PGC1&#x003b1; from control human kidney and a renal biopsy for AKI. Scale bars 50&#x003bc;m. <bold>h,</bold> PGC1&#x003b1; immunostaining intensity (1=weakest, 4=strongest). Each dot represents a unique specimen. Analyzed by Mann-Whitney. Error bars SEM, *p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01, ****p&#x0003c;0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms755501f4"/></fig></floats-group></article>