<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">AMB Express</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">AMB Express</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>AMB Express</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2191-0855</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4755957</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">182</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13568-016-0182-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Deep RNA-Seq profile reveals biodiversity, plant&#x02013;microbe interactions and a large family of NBS-LRR resistance genes in walnut (<italic>Juglans regia</italic>) tissues</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>Sandeep</given-names></name><address><email>sanchak@ucdavis.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>Monica</given-names></name><address><email>mtbritton@ucdavis.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><address><email>pjmartinezgarcia@ucdavis.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Dandekar</surname><given-names>Abhaya M.</given-names></name><address><email>amdandekar@ucdavis.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Plant Sciences Department, University of California, Davis, CA 95616 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>UC Davis Genome Center Bioinformatics Core Facility, Davis, CA 95616 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>12</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Chakraborty et al. 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p>Deep RNA-Seq profiling, a revolutionary method used for quantifying transcriptional levels, often includes non-specific transcripts from other co-existing organisms in spite of stringent protocols. Using the recently published walnut genome sequence as a filter, we present a broad analysis of the RNA-Seq derived transcriptome profiles obtained from twenty different tissues to extract the biodiversity and possible plant&#x02013;microbe interactions in the walnut ecosystem in California. Since the residual nature of the transcripts being analyzed does not provide sufficient information to identify the exact strain, inferences made are constrained to the genus level. The presence of the pathogenic oomycete <italic>Phytophthora</italic> was detected in the root through the presence of a glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase. <italic>Cryptococcus</italic>, the causal agent of cryptococcosis, was found in the catkins and vegetative buds, corroborating previous work indicating that the plant surface supported the sexual cycle of this human pathogen. The RNA-Seq profile revealed several species of the endophytic nitrogen fixing <italic>Actinobacteria</italic>. Another bacterial species implicated in aerobic biodegradation of methyl tert-butyl ether (<italic>Methylibium petroleiphilum</italic>) is also found in the root. RNA encoding proteins from the pea aphid were found in the leaves and vegetative buds, while a serine protease from mosquito with significant homology to a female reproductive tract protease from <italic>Drosophila mojavensis</italic> in the vegetative bud suggests egg-laying activities. The comprehensive analysis of RNA-seq data present also unraveled detailed, tissue-specific information of ~400 transcripts encoded by the largest family of resistance (R) genes (NBS-LRR), which possibly rationalizes the resistance of the specific walnut plant to the pathogens detected. Thus, we elucidate the biodiversity and possible plant&#x02013;microbe interactions in several walnut (<italic>Juglans regia</italic>) tissues in California using deep RNA-Seq profiling.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>RNA-Seq</kwd><kwd><italic>Cryptococcus</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Phytophthora</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Juglans regia</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>California Walnut Board</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Rapid detection of pathogens in plants is becoming increasingly necessary to prevent loss of productivity and quality (Dandekar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2010</xref>; Fletcher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2006</xref>). The wide variety of diseases and pathogens necessitates a broad detection system (Asiatic citrus canker: <italic>Xanthomonas axonopodis</italic>, sudden oak death: <italic>Phytophthora ramorum</italic>, Pierce's disease of grapevine: <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic>, etc.). Traditionally, real-time PCR has been used extensively for plant disease diagnostics (Schaad and Frederick <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2002</xref>). However, these diagnostic tools are biased, and can only detect pathogens with a known nucleic acid template. RNA-Seq, a high-throughput DNA sequencing method, has revolutionized the field of gene discovery (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2009</xref>; Flintoft <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2008</xref>). RNA-Seq can detect transcripts with very low expression levels, in contrast to other traditional methods like RNA:DNA hybridization (Clark et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2002</xref>) and short sequence-based approaches (Kodzius et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2006</xref>). The RNA-Seq derived transcriptome with a selection protocol for polyadenylated mRNA from an organism with known genome enables detection of mRNA from extraneous eukaryotes like fungi and pests. Certain RNA-Seq protocols ensure that only polyadenylated mRNA is being analyzed, yet some bacterial mRNA does leak through in the analysis. Thus, this presents an unbiased method of diagnosing the presence of wide range of prokaryotic and eukaryotic organisms (Moretti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2007</xref>; Janse <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2010</xref>). Such a study can also guide downstream PCR diagnostics to determine the exact species/strain of a pathogen. We have recently used a RNA-Seq methodology to derive the transcriptome of walnut (<italic>Juglans regia</italic>) from twenty different tissues types with selection for polyadenylated mRNA in the course of obtaining the walnut genome sequence (WGS) (manuscript submitted). Firstly, we excluded transcripts that aligned to WGS and the <italic>E. coli</italic> genome. Expression counts enabled the determination of the localization, although the residual nature of the transcripts being analyzed did not provide sufficient information to identify the exact species/strain. Thus, inferences made were constrained to the genus. These counts were not normalized, since there were no comparisons of absolute or relative expression levels. Some non-polyadenylated bacterial mRNA leaked through the RNA-Seq analysis. We detected several well-known pathogens, fungi, endophytic bacteria, and pests. The detection of these pathogenic agents in an otherwise healthy plant can be ascribed to the presence and activity of resistance (R) genes that specifically recognize pathogens, which contain complementary avirulence genes (Staskawicz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2001</xref>).</p><p>The oomycete <italic>Phytophthora</italic>, a pathogen responsible for destructive diseases in a wide variety of crop plants, was found localized in the root (Fletcher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2006</xref>; Belisario et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2012</xref>; Nowicki et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2012</xref>). Although sequence homology indicated the presence of several species of <italic>Phytophthora</italic> (<italic>nicotianae, infestans, parasitica</italic>), the similarity among these strains did not allow for an exact enumeration of the individual species. For example, a glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase with 97&#x000a0;% identity to a GAPDH from <italic>P. parasitica</italic> and <italic>P. infestans</italic> is an enzyme detected from this pathogen. Cryptococcosis in human and animals is caused by <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> and <italic>C. gattii</italic>, which has been exacerbated in recent times in immuno-compromised individuals (Mitchell and Perfect <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">1995</xref>). The plant surface is a conducive environment for the sexual cycle of <italic>Cryptococcus</italic> (Xue et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2007</xref>). Here, we detect prolyl-isomerases and ADP/ATP translocases from <italic>Cryptococcus</italic> present in catkins and in vegetative buds, corroborating these findings. Endophytic <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> are present extensively in the inner tissues of living plants, and are a source of important secondary metabolites related to the defense response, growth and environmental stress (Ventura et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2007</xref>). Based on the top BLAST score, we detected several species in the <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> phyla spread out across all tissues. <italic>Methylibium petroleiphilum</italic>, which is capable of using methyl tert-butyl ether as a sole source of carbon, was also found in the root (Nakatsu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2006</xref>). The ribosomal L37 protein from the pest pea aphid was found in the leaves and vegetative buds. Interestingly, a serine protease from the mosquito (Kelleher and Markow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2009</xref>) with significant homology to a female reproductive tract protease from <italic>Drosophila mojavensis</italic> (Isoe et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2009</xref>) in the vegetative bud suggested egg-laying activities by these pests.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>RNA-Seq</title><p>Fifteen samples of walnut tissue (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) were gathered from Chandler trees in the UC Davis field facilities located in Davis, California. Three additional samples were taken from Chandler plant material maintained in tissue culture. The root sample was taken from potted Chandler trees in the greenhouse/lath house. Several grams of leaf and root tissue from each plant were frozen in liquid nitrogen immediately after harvest and then transferred to a &#x02212;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C freezer. RNA was isolated from each sample using the hot borate method (Wilkins and Smart <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">1996</xref>) followed by purification and DNAse treatment using an RNA/DNA Mini Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA) per the manufacturer's protocol. High quality RNA was confirmed by running an aliquot of each sample on an Experion Automated Electrophoresis System (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA). The cDNA libraries were constructed following the Illumina mRNA-sequencing sample preparation protocol (Illumina Inc., San Diego, CA). Final elution was performed with 16&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L RNase-free water. The quality of each library was determined using a BioRad Experion (BioRad, Hercules, CA). Each library was run as an independent lane on a Genome Analyzer II (Illumina, San Diego, CA) to generate paired-end sequences of 85&#x000a0;bp in length from each cDNA library. In total, over a billion reads were obtained. Prior to assembly, all reads underwent quality control for paired-end reads and trimming using Sickle (Joshi and Fass <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>). The minimum read length was 45&#x000a0;bp with a minimum Sanger quality score of 35. The quality controlled reads were de novo assembled with Trinity v2.0.6 (Grabherr et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2011</xref>). Standard parameters were used and the minimum contig length was 300&#x000a0;bp. Individual assemblies for each library and a combined assembly of all tissues were performed (Chakraborty et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2015</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Walnut tissue sources used for RNAseq analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Code</th><th align="left">Tissue source</th><th align="left">Sequence read archive</th><th align="left">Walnut genotype</th><th align="left">Developmental stage</th><th align="left">Source</th><th align="left">No of reads x10<sup>6</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">VB</td><td align="left">Vegetative bud</td><td align="left">SRS523592</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Vegetative</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">39.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">LY</td><td align="left">Leaf&#x02014;young</td><td align="left">SRS523594</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Vegetative</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">63.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RT</td><td align="left">Root</td><td align="left">SRS523799</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Vegetative</td><td align="left">Greenhouse</td><td char="." align="char">38.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CI</td><td align="left">Callus interior</td><td align="left">SRS523805</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Vegetative</td><td align="left">In Vitro</td><td char="." align="char">59.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CE</td><td align="left">Callus exterior</td><td align="left">SRS523808</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Vegetative</td><td align="left">In Vitro</td><td char="." align="char">29.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FL</td><td align="left">Pistillate flower</td><td align="left">SRS523810</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Vegetative</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">69.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CK</td><td align="left">Catkins</td><td align="left">SRS523917</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Immature</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">56.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SE</td><td align="left">Somatic embryo</td><td align="left">SRS523919</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Immature</td><td align="left">In Vitro</td><td char="." align="char">27.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">LM</td><td align="left">Leaf&#x02014;mature</td><td align="left">SRS523921</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Vegetative</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">50.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">LE</td><td align="left">Leaves</td><td align="left">SRS523922</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Vegetative</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">60.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IF</td><td align="left">Fruit immature</td><td align="left">SRS523923</td><td align="left">Mixed</td><td align="left">Immature</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">57.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HL</td><td align="left">Hull immature</td><td align="left">SRS523924</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Immature</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">115.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PT</td><td align="left">Packing tissue</td><td align="left">SRS523925</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Immature</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">62.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HP</td><td align="left">Hull peel</td><td align="left">SRS523926</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Mature</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">43.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HC</td><td align="left">Hull cortex</td><td align="left">SRS523927</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Mature</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">62.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PK</td><td align="left">Packing tissue</td><td align="left">SRS523928</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Mature</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">56.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PL</td><td align="left">Pellicle</td><td align="left">SRS523929</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Mature</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">42.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EM</td><td align="left">Embryo</td><td align="left">SRS523930</td><td align="left">Mixed</td><td align="left">Mature</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">35.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HU</td><td align="left">Hull&#x02014;dehiscing</td><td align="left">SRS523931</td><td align="left">Chandler</td><td align="left">Senescent</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">59.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TZ</td><td align="left">Transition wood</td><td align="left">SRS523933</td><td align="left">
<italic>J.nigra</italic>
</td><td align="left">Transition zone</td><td align="left">Orchard</td><td char="." align="char">48.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left" colspan="2">Total number of reads:</td><td char="." align="char">1080.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>In silico analysis</title><p>The NCBI database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy</ext-link>) provides several resources for the &#x02018;curated classification and nomenclature of all of organisms in the public sequence databases. This currently represents about 10&#x000a0;% of the described species of life on the planet.&#x02019; There were ~111&#x000a0;k transcripts. ~5&#x000a0;k did not align to the walnut genome, and were removed (Chakraborty et al. 2015). Of these, ~4&#x000a0;k transcripts had significant homology to <italic>E. coli</italic> genomes. The remaining ~1&#x000a0;k transcripts were the subject of analysis in the current manuscript, under the assumption that they were derived from extraneous organisms, pathogens or commensal, inhabiting the twenty different tissues. The species names were derived from the best BLAST match to the &#x02018;nt&#x02019; database. A bitscore (BLASTSCORE) cutoff of 150 was used (~E-value&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1E&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;33). The numerical identifier was obtained from the species name using the site <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/TaxIdentifier/tax">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/TaxIdentifier/tax</ext-link> identifier.cgi. For example, <italic>Arthrobacter</italic> has the tax ID 1663. These numerical IDs were then used to obtain the complete lineage. The first classification of all organisms was into Eukaryota or Bacteria. We used the second classification field to cluster the organisms discussed here. The expression counts are not normalized since we do not make any inferences on the absolute or relative abundance of the transcripts.</p><p>The iterative gene finding method described in YeATS (Chakraborty et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2015</xref>) was used to identify the homologous set of nucleotide-binding site (NBS)-leucine-rich repeat (LRR) class of genes. A BLAST bitscore of 100 (E value&#x000a0;~1E&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;20), with an increment of 20 for each iteration, was used as the homology threshold. The increment in each of the iterations ensures that the resultant proteins do not diverge far from the initially chosen protein. We have used 600 as a lower threshold for the length of NBS-LRR proteins. Additionally, we exclude transcripts with &#x000a0;% of leucine less than the 10&#x000a0;% frequency of leucine residues seen in plant proteomes. These transcripts are probably fragments which have not been assembled by Trinity (Chakraborty et al. 2015).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Results</title><p>As a result of the analysis of ~1&#x000a0;k transcripts obtained from 20 different tissues of walnut, different extraneous organisms, pathogens or commensal, were detected (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Several transcripts (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;260) were associated with <italic>Phytophthora</italic>, mostly localized in the root (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). A sample of transcripts, and the putative proteins they encode, identified C43181_G1_I1 encoding a 293 nt long ORF with a predicted protein (molecular weight&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;30&#x000a0;kDa) homologous to glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>a). This GAPDH has 97&#x000a0;% identity to a GAPDH from <italic>P. parasitica</italic> and <italic>P. infestans</italic>, and a 96&#x000a0;% identity to the GAPDH from <italic>P. sojae</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). The 3D structure of PhyGAPDH1 was modeled using SWISSMODEL (Arnold et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2006</xref>). The structural superimposition of the PhyGAPDH1 to the structure of the human placental GAPDH (PDBid:1U8F, chain O) reveals the structural conservation of this gene across different species (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). In this study, the presence of <italic>Cryptococcus</italic> was also confirmed in the catkins and the vegetative buds (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>b). We identified a cyclophilin A (peptidyl-prolyl cis&#x02013;trans isomerase) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>a) associated with <italic>Cryptococcus</italic>. In addition, we detected several transcripts associated with the endophytic <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> (EndAct) in several tissues of walnut (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). Most putative proteins from these transcripts have significant homologs in the BLAST&#x02019;nr&#x02019; database, although most of them are uncharacterized. Other interesting results are the presence of <italic>Methylibium petroleiphilum</italic> in the roots (3442 cumulative counts, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c), <italic>Acyrthosiphon pisum</italic> (or the pea aphid) with 1256 cumulative counts in the leaves (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d) and <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (yellow fewer mosquito) in the vegetative bud of walnut, with a total of 428 cumulative counts of transcripts (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>e).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Diseases, pests and pathogens affecting walnut: Images obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki">https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki</ext-link> and used under the Creative Commons Attribution 2.5 Generic license</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13568_2016_182_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Localization of transcripts. These shows the cumulative counts (not normalized) of transcripts assigned to each genus. <bold>a</bold>
<italic>Phytophthora</italic>&#x02014;localized in the root. <bold>b</bold>
<italic>Actinobacteria</italic>&#x02014;present in all tissues <bold>c</bold>
<italic>Methylibium</italic>&#x02014;localized in the root. <bold>d</bold>
<italic>Acyrthosiphon</italic>&#x02014;localized in early leaves and the vegetative bud. <bold>e</bold>
<italic>Aedes</italic>
<italic>aegypti</italic>&#x02014;localized in the vegetative bud</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13568_2016_182_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Proteins from <italic>Phytophthora</italic>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Transcript</th><th align="left">Description</th><th align="left">E-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">C43181_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_ 008893048.1 <italic>P. parasitica</italic> INRA-310 glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C30378_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_ 008895058.1 <italic>P. parasitica</italic> INRA-310 guanine nucleotide-binding protein</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C7548_G1_I1</td><td align="left">DQ057354.1 <italic>P. nicotianae</italic> manganese superoxide dismutase (MnSOD1a)</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C26754_G1_I1</td><td align="left">FJ493002.1 <italic>P. cinnamomi</italic> clone PC02 Ric1 protein mRNA, complete</td><td char="." align="char">1.00E&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;78</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C49955_G2_I1</td><td align="left">XM_ 002997461.1 <italic>P. infestans</italic> T30-4 14-3-3 protein epsilon (PITG 19017)</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C62634_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_ 002903199.1 <italic>P. infestans</italic> T30-4 transcription factor BTF3-like protein</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Transcripts from the pathogenic oomycete <italic>Phytophthora</italic> with ORFs that have significant matches in the BLAST &#x02018;nr&#x02019; database. There are several strains of <italic>P</italic>. (<italic>nicotianae</italic>, <italic>cinnamomi</italic>, <italic>infestans</italic>) that have the best matches to these transcripts. It is difficult to ascertain the exact species from these transcripts since some of these proteins have high conservation across many species</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Expression counts of selected transcripts</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2">Transcript</th><th align="left">CE</th><th align="left">CI</th><th align="left">CK</th><th align="left">EM</th><th align="left">FL</th><th align="left">HC</th><th align="left">HL</th><th align="left">HP</th><th align="left">HU</th><th align="left">IF</th><th align="left">LE</th><th align="left">LM</th><th align="left">LY</th><th align="left">PK</th><th align="left">PL</th><th align="left">PT</th><th align="left">RT</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">TZ</th><th align="left">VB</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="22">a</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C30378 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">104</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C7548 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">497</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">2</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C26754 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">28</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C43181 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">326</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C49955_G2_I1</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td align="left">1</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="left">2</td><td char="." align="left">1</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">185</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C62634 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">123</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C442 G2 I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C03 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C28542 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">18</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="22">b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C9244 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C87 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C61284 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">12</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C498 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C6553 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C35196 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">2</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">14</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C50331 G1 I4</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="left">11</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C34393 _G1_I1</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left">4</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td char="." align="left">4</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="left">45</td><td char="." align="left">12</td><td char="." align="char">68</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">21</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="left">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="22">c</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C50331_G1_I5</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">13</td><td char="." align="char">14</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">8</td><td char="." align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="left">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C58663 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C29801 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">4</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C30295 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">8</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C16207 _G1_I1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">54</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C50331 G1 I2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">1</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">4</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="left">14</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>These are raw counts, and are not normalized</p><p>
<italic>a</italic>
<italic>Phytophthora</italic> is the pathogen responsible for potato blight, which caused the Great Irish Famine (1845&#x02013;1849). C30378_G1_I1 encodes a glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase, an enzyme involved in glycolysis. Most transcripts from this oomycete are found localized in the root (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). <italic>b</italic>
<italic>Cryptococcus</italic> is the causal agent of cryptococcosis, affecting immuno-compromised individuals. These fungi are mostly localized in the catkins and the vegetative buds. It was previously shown that the plant surface provides a conducive environment for the sexual cycle of these pathogens. <italic>c</italic>
<italic>Pyrenophora</italic>: These fungi, responsible for the `tan spot&#x02019; disease in barley, are spread out throughout different tissues. <italic>d</italic>
<italic>Acyrthosiphon</italic>: The pea aphid pest. C58762_G1_I1 encodes a 91 long ORF that has a 99&#x000a0;% identity match to the ribosomal protein L37 (Accession:&#x000a0;NP 001129424.1). The low counts of this transcript are testimony to the ability of the RNAseq technology to accurately determine the sequence and localization of transcripts</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) from <italic>Phytophthora</italic>: C43181_G1_I1 encodes a 293&#x000a0;bp long ORF with a predicted molecular weight of 30&#x000a0;kDa and has 97&#x000a0;% identity GAPDH from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>parasitica</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>infestans</italic>, and a 96&#x000a0;% identity to the GAPDH from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>sojae</italic>. Thus, although the presence of a pathogen from the <italic>Phytophthora</italic> genus is almost certain, it is not possible to determine the exact strain of this pathogen. The <italic>Phytophthora</italic> GAPDH also shares a 70&#x000a0;% identity with the GAPDH in human placenta. <bold>a</bold> Multiple sequence alignment of the GAPDHs obtained using ENDscript 2.x (Robert and Gouet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2014</xref>). <bold>b</bold> Structural superimposition of the C43181_G1_I1 GAPDH to the structure of the human placental GAPDH (PDBid:1U8F, chain O). The structure of C43181_G1_I1 GAPDH was modelled using SWISSMODEL</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13568_2016_182_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Transcripts from fungi</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2">Transcript</th><th align="left">Description</th><th align="left">E-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">a</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C44240_G2_I1</td><td align="left">KGB78973.1 ADP/ATP translocase [<italic>Cryptococcus gattii</italic> R265]</td><td char="." align="char">3e-91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C8003_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_571019.1 <italic>C. neoformans</italic> var<italic>. neoformans</italic> JEC21 60&#x000a0;s ribosomal protein</td><td char="." align="char">3e-98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C28542_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XP 003191240.1 40&#x000a0;s ribosomal protein s3ae-a (s1-a) [<italic>Cryptococcus gattii</italic> WM276]</td><td char="." align="char">3e-91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C9244_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_569612.1 <italic>C. neoformans</italic> var<italic>. neoformans</italic> JEC21 40S ribosomal protein</td><td char="." align="char">3e-119</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C8207_G1_I1</td><td align="left">KGB74187.1 cyclophilin A, peptidyl-prolyl isomerase [<italic>Cryptococcus gattii</italic> R265]</td><td char="." align="char">5e-82</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C61284_G1_I1</td><td align="left">KGB74302.1 60S ribosomal protein L10 [<italic>Cryptococcus gattii</italic> R265]</td><td char="." align="char">1e-76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C60498_G1_I1</td><td align="left">AFR92589.1 glutamine synthetase [<italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> var<italic>. grubii</italic> H99]</td><td char="." align="char">9e-51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C6553_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_001932117.1 <italic>P. tritici</italic>-<italic>repentis</italic> Pt-1C-BFP subtilase-type proteinase</td><td char="." align="char">6e-130</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C35196_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_001932926.1 <italic>P. tritici</italic>-<italic>repentis</italic> Pt-1C-BFP 60S ribosomal protein</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C50331_G1_I4</td><td align="left">XM_001930633.1 <italic>P. tritici</italic>-<italic>repentis</italic> Pt-1C-BFP hypothetical protein</td><td char="." align="char">9e-125</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C34393 _G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_003296940.1 <italic>P. teres f. teres</italic> 0-1 ubiquitin-40S ribosomal protein</td><td char="." align="char">1e-101</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C50331_G1_I5</td><td align="left">XM_001930633.1 <italic>P. tritici</italic>-<italic>repentis</italic> Pt-1C-BFP hypothetical protein</td><td char="." align="char">1e-133</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C58663_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_001937272.1 <italic>P. tritici</italic>-<italic>repentis</italic> Pt-1C-BFP opsin-1, mRNA</td><td char="." align="char">3e-69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C29801_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_001936103.1 <italic>P. tritici</italic>-<italic>repentis</italic> Pt-1C-BFP conserved hypothetical</td><td char="." align="char">1e-57</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C30295_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_003306030.1 <italic>P. teres f. teres</italic> 0-1 hypothetical protein, mRNA</td><td char="." align="char">2e-70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C16207_G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_001935967.1 <italic>P. tritici</italic>-<italic>repentis</italic> Pt-1C-BFP conserved hypothetical</td><td char="." align="char">7e-97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x000a0;C50331_G1_I2</td><td align="left">XM_001930633.1 <italic>P. tritici</italic>-<italic>repentis</italic> Pt-1C-BFP hypothetical protein</td><td char="." align="char">1e-122</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>a</italic>
<italic>Cryptococcus</italic> is the causal agent of the human/animal respiratory disease cryptococcosis. These fungi are mostly localized in the catkins and the vegetative bud in walnut, corroborating previous results indicating that the plant surface provides a conducive environment for their sexual cycle. Here, we see two different species: <italic>C</italic>. <italic>neoformans</italic> var. <italic>neoformans</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>gattii</italic>. <italic>b</italic> The &#x02018;tan spot&#x02019; causing pathogenic fungi <italic>Pyrenophora</italic> had two different strains&#x000a0;present: <italic>P</italic>. <italic>tritici</italic>-<italic>repentis</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>teres</italic> f. <italic>teres</italic>
</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Species from <italic>Actinobacteria</italic>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Taxonomy name</th><th align="left">ID</th><th align="left">Lineage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Arthrobacter</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">1663</td><td align="left">Bacteria; Actinobacteria; Actinobacteria<italic>; Micrococcales; Micrococcaceae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Modestobacter</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">88138</td><td align="left">Bacteria; Actinobacteria; Actinobacteria<italic>; Geodermatophilales; Geodermatophilaceae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Microlunatus</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">29404</td><td align="left">Bacteria; Actinobacteria; Actinobacteria<italic>; Propionibacteriales; Propionibacteriaceae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Actinoplanes</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">1865</td><td align="left">Bacteria; Actinobacteria; Actinobacteria<italic>; Micromonosporales; Micromonosporaceae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Nakamurella</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">53460</td><td align="left">Bacteria; Actinobacteria; Actinobacteria<italic>; Nakamurellales; Nakamurellaceae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Streptomyces</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">1883</td><td align="left">Bacteria; Actinobacteria; Actinobacteria<italic>; Streptomycetales; Streptomycetaceae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Propionibacterium</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">1743</td><td align="left">Bacteria; Actinobacteria; Actinobacteria<italic>; Propionibacteriales; Propionibacteriaceae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Corynebacterium</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">1716</td><td align="left">Bacteria; Actinobacteria; Actinobacteria<italic>; Corynebacteriales; Corynebacteriaceae</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Micrococcus</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">1269</td><td align="left">Bacteria; Actinobacteria; Actinobacteria<italic>; Micrococcales; Micrococcaceae</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>We obtain the taxonomy ID from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/TaxIdentier/tax_identifer.cgi">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/TaxIdentier/tax_identifer.cgi</ext-link> using the taxonomy name, which is then used to get the lineage. The taxonomy names were obtained from best entry in a BLAST search to the &#x02018;nt&#x02019; database</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Discussion</title><p>High-throughput mRNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) has revolutionized the view of the profile of the transcriptome, enhancing gene discovery. Although some protocols are designed to view exclusively polyadenylated eukaryotic mRNA, prokaryotic mRNA can be surreptitiously included in the analysis, especially highly abundant transcripts like ribosomal proteins. This presents an opportunity to identify extraneous transcripts residing in various tissues, provided the genome of the organism is known. Expression counts are low due to the residual nature of the analysis. Yet, as we observed for pea aphid, very low counts were able to accurately identify the L37 ribosomal protein, which shares 88&#x000a0;% identity with the L37 protein from <italic>Drosophila</italic><italic>Melanogaster</italic> (Anger et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2013</xref>).</p><sec id="Sec7"><title><italic>Phytophthora</italic>: causal agent of potato blight</title><p>The oomycete <italic>Phytophthora</italic> is a pathogen responsible for destructive diseases in a wide variety of crop plants, including tomato, potato (Nowicki et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2012</xref>) and walnut (Belisario et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2012</xref>) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Although the presence of a pathogen from the <italic>Phytophtho</italic>ra genus is almost certain, it is not possible to determine the exact strain of this pathogen. GAPDH is involved in gycolysis, and other non-metabolic processes (Tarze et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2007</xref>), and is a well-known housekeeping gene (Eisenberg and Levanon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2013</xref>). The <italic>Phytophthora</italic> GAPDH also shares a 70&#x000a0;% identity with the GAPDH in human placenta (Jenkins and Tanner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2006</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Fungi</title><sec id="Sec9"><title><italic>Cryptococcus</italic>: Causal agent of cryptococcosis in human</title><p>These fungi are mostly localized in the catkins and the vegetative bud in walnut, corroborating previous results about their sexual cycle (Xue et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2007</xref>). Cryptococcosis is a disease of the respiratory system in human and animals, caused by <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> and <italic>C. gattii</italic>, and exacerbated in patients infected with the AIDS virus (Mitchell and Perfect <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">1995</xref>). Plants are known to host a large number of commensal fungi (Schmit and Mueller <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2007</xref>). An interesting ecological experiment demonstrated that the plant surface is a conducive environment, stimulating the sexual cycle of <italic>Cryptococcus</italic> (Xue et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2007</xref>). Myo-inositol and the plant growth hormone IAA synergistically were proved as &#x02018;strong aphrodisiacs&#x02019; (Xue et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2007</xref>). Two homologous cyclophilin A genes (KGB74193 and KGB74187) have been shown to influence cell growth, mating and virulence (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2001</xref>). A peptidyl-prolyl cis&#x02013;trans isomerase from <italic>Cryptococcus</italic> (Ess1), non-homologous to the above two genes, is required only for virulence (Ren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2005</xref>). Another pathogenic fungus, <italic>Pyrenophora</italic> (<italic>teres</italic>/<italic>triticirepentis</italic>), and the causal agent of the disease &#x02018;tan spot&#x02019; (Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2011</xref>) have been identified in several tissues (Tables <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>c, <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>b).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Actinobacteria: nitrogen fixing bacterial diazotrophs</title><p>Bacterial mRNA is non-polyadenylated, and most should be excluded by the RNA-Seq library preparation method, but some mRNA invariably leaks through. EndAct are present extensively in the inner tissues of living plants, and are a source of important secondary metabolites related to the defense response, growth and environmental stress (Qin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2011</xref>; Palaniyandi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2013</xref>). The significant homology of the putative proteins from these transcripts after BLAST results highlights the ability of the current methodology to detect a genus with fair precision. A clear example is the transcript C54818_G4_I1 that encodes a 68&#x000a0;bp long ORF, and matches to a &#x02018;MULTISPECIES: hypothetical protein&#x02019; from <italic>Streptomyces</italic> with 82&#x000a0;% identity. The nitrogen fixing diazotroph, <italic>Paenibacillus</italic><italic>polymyxa</italic> P2b-2R, was found to enhance the growth of the important oilseed crop canola (Puri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2016</xref>). EndAct obtained from healthy wheat tissue was shown to &#x02018;prime&#x02019; the systemic acquired resistance (SAR) and the jasmonate/ethylene (JA/ET) pathways in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>thaliana</italic> JA/ET pathways when infected with bacterial pathogen <italic>Erwinia</italic><italic>carotovora</italic> subsp. <italic>carotovora</italic> or the fungal pathogen <italic>Fusarium</italic><italic>oxysporum</italic>, respectively (Conn et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2008</xref>). The importance of EndAct in biodiversity was established in a tropical rainforest native plant, which identified a total of 312 <italic>Actinobacteria</italic> associated with the order <italic>Actinomycetales</italic> (Qin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2012</xref>). Recently, the genome sequence of <italic>Arthrobacter</italic><italic>koreensis</italic> 5J12A, a desiccation-tolerant strain, was obtained (Manzanera et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2015</xref>). Teicoplanin, an antibiotic working against Gram positive bacteria like methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus</italic><italic>aureus</italic> and <italic>Enterococcus</italic><italic>faecalis,</italic> was obtained from the fermentation broth of a strain of <italic>Actinoplanes</italic><italic>teichomyceticus</italic> (Jung et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2008</xref>). Another EndAct (<italic>Streptomyces</italic>) was shown to produce lipase, &#x003b2;-1-3-glucanase and chitinase (defence related enzymes), and aid plant growth (Gopalakrishnan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>). <italic>Micrococcus</italic> sp NII-0909 isolated from the Western ghat forest soil in India had demonstrable ability to enhance soil fertility and promote plant growth (Dastager et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2010</xref>). EndAct, for example <italic>Corynebacteria</italic>, can be associated with plant pathogenicity (Vidaver <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1982</xref>). Also, juglone has been found to have inhibitory effects on some of these nitrogen fixing bacteria (Dawson et al. Dawson and Seymour <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1983</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><italic>Methylibium</italic><italic>petroleiphilum</italic>: involved in aerobic biodegradation of methyl tert-butyl ether</title><p><italic>Methylibium petroleiphilum</italic> is capable of using methyl tert-butyl ether as a sole source of carbon in the root (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c) (Nakatsu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2006</xref>). Unlike <italic>Phytophthora</italic>, there are only two transcripts for <italic>Methylibium</italic>. One transcript is 461 nt long&#x000a0;and has a 92&#x000a0;% identity to the <italic>M.</italic><italic>petroleiphilum</italic> PM1 genome (Accession: CP000555.1). The ORF from this transcript has a 79&#x000a0;% identity to part of a protein (Accession: ABM53545.1) from uncultured beta proteobacterium CBNPD1 BAC clone 578, which was obtained in a metagenomic analysis of a freshwater toxic cyanobacteria bloom (Pope and Patel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2008</xref>). Although&#x000a0;the PCR-generated 75-clone, 16S rRNA gene library had confirmed the presence of <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>, data here associates this protein with <italic>M.</italic><italic>petroleiphilum</italic>. Interestingly, this transcript or ORF has no match in the new draft sequence of the <italic>Methylibium</italic> sp. strain T29, a fuel oxygenate-degrading bacterial isolate from Hungary (Szab&#x000f3; et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2015</xref>). This is explained by the differences observed: &#x02018;unlike M. <italic>petroleiphilum</italic> PM1 our isolate does not harbor the mega plasmid which carries the genes for MTBE-degradation&#x02019; (Szab&#x000f3; et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><italic>Acyrthosiphon pisum:</italic> the pea aphid pest</title><p>While both <italic>Methylibium</italic> and <italic>Phytophthora</italic> are mostly localized in the root, thepeaaphid <italic>A. pisum</italic>, which is a pest of importance in agriculture (Van Emden and Harrington <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2007</xref>), was found in the leaves (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d). One transcript of <italic>Acyrthosiphon</italic> (C58762 _G1_I1) encodes a 91 amino acid long ORF having a 99&#x000a0;% match to the ribosomal L37 protein (Accession: NP 001129424.1). The low count of this transcript demonstrates the accuracy of the RNA-Seq technology (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>d).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>: yellow fever mosquito</title><p>The presence of yellow fever mosquito in the vegetative bud was not expected (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>e) and was not previously reported in Northern California. The proteins found there include proteases (both serine and metallo), ribosomal RNA and an elongation factor (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). Among the serine proteases, C40984_G1_I1 encodes a trypsin that has a significant similarity to a female reproductive tract protease from <italic>Drosophila mojavensis</italic> (Uniprot id: C5IB51) (Kelleher and Markow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2009</xref>), suggesting that the mosquito had been using the vegetative buds for reproductive purposes. The importance of the serine proteases in egg-formation abilities of mosquitoes were established using a RNAi knockdown method (Isoe et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2009</xref>). Another interesting development has been the recent monitoring of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> by the California Department of Public Health.<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Transcripts from <italic>Aedes</italic>
<italic>aegypti</italic>, the yellow fever mosquito</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Transcript</th><th align="left">Description</th><th align="left">E-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">C40984 _G1_I1</td><td align="left">XM_ 001652893.1 <italic>Aedes</italic>
<italic>aegypti</italic> trypsin partial mRNA</td><td align="left">0.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C56263 _G1_I1</td><td align="left">AY432478.1 <italic>Aedes</italic>
<italic>aegypti</italic> ASAP ID: 35053 metalloendopeptidase mRNA sequence</td><td align="left">3e-152</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C58453 _G1_I1</td><td align="left">AY432463.1 <italic>Aedes</italic>
<italic>aegypti</italic> ASAP ID: 35049 serine protease mRNA sequence</td><td align="left">0.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C62133 _G1_I1</td><td align="left">U65375.1 AAU65375 <italic>Aedes</italic>
<italic>aegypti</italic> 18S ribosomal RNA gene</td><td align="left">0.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C24216 _G1_I1</td><td align="left">U65375.1 AAU65375 <italic>Aedes</italic>
<italic>aegypti</italic> 18S ribosomal RNA gene</td><td align="left">8e-148</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C5389 _G1_I1</td><td align="left">L22060.1 <italic>Aedes</italic>
<italic>albopictus</italic> 8S, 5.8S, and 28S ribosomal RNA genes</td><td align="left">0.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C58751 _G1_I1</td><td align="left">AY433205.1 <italic>Aedes</italic>
<italic>aegypti</italic> solate A20 28S ribosomal RNA gene</td><td align="left">9e-163</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C59860 _G1_I1</td><td align="left">AY736001.1 <italic>Aedes</italic>
<italic>aegypti</italic> elongation factor 1 alpha mRNA, partial cds</td><td align="left">4e-152</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>These match with high significance to the yellow fever mosquito BLAST &#x02018;nt&#x02019; database, and are mostly found in the vegetative bud (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>e). C40984_G1_I1 encodes an ORF with a 99&#x000a0;% identity to the <italic>Aedes</italic>
<italic>aegypti</italic> trypsin. Interestingly, this protein also has a significant similarity to a female reproductive tract protease from <italic>Drosophila</italic>
<italic>mojavensis</italic>, suggesting that the walnut vegetative bud has been used for egg-laying purposes by the female mosquito</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Their detection sites are updated regularly. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdph.ca.gov/HEALTHINFO/DISCOND/Pages/Aedes-albopictus-and-Aedes-aegypti-Mosquitoes.aspx">https://www.cdph.ca.gov/HEALTHINFO/DISCOND/Pages/Aedes-albopictus-and-Aedes-aegypti-Mosquitoes.aspx</ext-link>). However, their detection method is not known to us.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Nucleotide-binding site (NBS) and leucine-rich repeats (LRR) in walnut</title><p>The detection of several well-characterized plant pathogens in the current study raises the question of what innate resistance mechanism in walnut could provide resistance to these virulent agents. While it is possible that these strains of these pathogens are non-virulent, it is equally likely that this plant encodes and transcribes the desired resistance genes and transcripts needed to combat a virulent response from any one of these pathogens. Plants possess two distinct kinds of defence mechanisms&#x02014;the pathogen-associated molecular patterns (PAMP) mediated immunity (PTI) and effector-triggered immunity encoded by resistance (R) genes (ETI). PTI is analogous to the first line of defense (innate immunity) in vertebrates, which is bypassed or disrupted by pathogen effector molecules that are used to downregulate PTI, making the cell vulnerable to pathogen attack (Nicaise et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2009</xref>). R genes have evolved in this ensuing &#x0201c;evolutionary warfare&#x0201d; in plants, akin to the mammalian adaptive immunity, to recognize pathogens which contain complementary avirulence genes (DeYoung and Innes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2006</xref>). However, unlike the mammalian adaptive immune system which is enforced through specialized cells, R genes are active in all plant cells. The majority of R genes encode proteins comprise of a nucleotide-binding site (NBS) and leucine-rich repeats (LRRs). NBS-LRR proteins recognize and neutralize specialized pathogen avirulence (Avr) proteins, leading to the upregulation of PTI, thus, providing plants with resistance to the attack (Hayashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2010</xref>; Ernst et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2002</xref>; Borhan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2004</xref>; Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2010</xref>). It has been hypothesized that the distribution and diversity of NBS-LRR sequences is a direct consequence of extensive duplication and random rearrangements, endowing plants with the ability to recognize diverse molecules arising from dynamically changing biotic challenges (Meyers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2003</xref>). Here, we briefly describe the transcripts and expression levels of the NBS-LRRs genes in walnut. Two specific examples of such NBS-LRRs genes conferring resistance to plants are the blast-resistance gene Pb1 NBS-LRR from rice (Uniprot: E3WF10) (Hayashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2010</xref>) and the cyst nematode resistance gene from tomato (Uniprot: Q8GT46) (Ernst et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2002</xref>). In addition to being leucine rich, these two proteins are also abundant with the negatively charged glutamic acid (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). Although these specific NBS-LRRs are ~1300 amino acid long, the typical length of NBS-LRR varies from a few hundred to &#x0003c;2&#x000a0;K (McHale et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2006</xref>). Using these proteins as initial search entities, we have identified ~400 NBS-LRR transcripts (excluding splice variants denoted by transcripts having the same prefix) in walnut through the &#x02018;findgene&#x02019; algorithm described earlier by us (Chakraborty et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2015</xref>) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). This is in excellent agreement with the 374 NBS-LRR genes that were identified in a genome wide study of Chinese chestnut (<italic>Castanea mollissima</italic>) resistant to Chestnut Blight Disease (Zhong et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2015</xref>). The tissue-specific expression pattern allows the discrimination of the truly critical genes in this large family (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>). The tissue-specific nature of certain genes is exemplified by C54426_G7_I1, which has significantly higher expression in the catkins and hull, and shares 78&#x000a0;% identity with a Strubbelig-receptor family (SRF) from <italic>Malus domestica</italic>. SRFs are receptor-like kinases (Ey&#x000fc;boglu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2007</xref>), and are involved in tissue morphogenesis (Vaddepalli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2011</xref>) and immune response (Alc&#x000e1;zar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2010</xref>). As corroboration, we chose one NBS-LRR protein from each of the two major domains of NBS-LRR (McHale et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2006</xref>)&#x02014;TIR-NBS-LRR (Uniprot:Q6QX58 (Borhan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2004</xref>)) and CC-NBS-LRR Uniprot:Q56YM8 (Meyers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2003</xref>), and obtained the same number of transcripts encoded by NBS-LRR genes. Thus, we demonstrate that transcriptomic data that has revealed the biodiversity in different tissues of walnut simultaneously provides insights into the ability of the plant to negate the threat posed by some of these potentially destructive pathogens.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Nucleotide-binding site (<italic>NBS</italic>) and leucine-rich repeats (<italic>LRR</italic>) in walnut. <bold>a</bold> Amino acid frequency for two NBS-LRRs. The blast-resistance gene Pb1 NBS-LRR from rice (Uniprot: E3WF10) is in <italic>red</italic>, while the cyst nematode resistance gene from tomato (Uniprot: Q8GT46) is in <italic>green</italic>. While, expectedly, both these proteins are leucine rich, we also observe a large proportion of negatively charged glumatic acid. <bold>b</bold> Phylogenetic tree for the ~400 identified NBS-LRR genes in walnut obtained by Neighbor Joining/UPGMA phylogeny implemented in MAFFT (Katoh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2002</xref>) and drawn with FigTree v1.4.2</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13568_2016_182_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Expression counts of ten highly expressed transcripts from the NBS-LRR family</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Transcript</th><th align="left">CE</th><th align="left">CI</th><th align="left">CK</th><th align="left">EM</th><th align="left">FL</th><th align="left">HC</th><th align="left">HL</th><th align="left">HP</th><th align="left">HU</th><th align="left">IF</th><th align="left">LE</th><th align="left">LM</th><th align="left">LY</th><th align="left">PK</th><th align="left">PL</th><th align="left">PT</th><th align="left">RT</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">TZ</th><th align="left">VB</th><th align="left">L</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">C54426_G7_I1</td><td align="left">9.9</td><td char="." align="char">19.7</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">2.8</td><td char="." align="char">26.2</td><td char="." align="char">3.5</td><td char="." align="char">23</td><td char="." align="char">0.2</td><td char="." align="char">1.2</td><td char="." align="char">0.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.7</td><td char="." align="char">3.2</td><td char="." align="char">2.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.5</td><td char="." align="char">1.4</td><td char="." align="char">4.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.2</td><td char="." align="char">1.2</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">745</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C50016_G1_I3</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td char="." align="char">2.2</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">2.3</td><td char="." align="char">18.9</td><td char="." align="char">1.5</td><td char="." align="char">1.5</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td char="." align="char">8.1</td><td char="." align="char">0.4</td><td char="." align="char">7.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.7</td><td char="." align="char">8.6</td><td char="." align="char">2.4</td><td char="." align="char">1.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.2</td><td char="." align="char">3.3</td><td char="." align="char">1026</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C52820_G1_I1</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td char="." align="char">4.6</td><td align="left">3.8</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td char="." align="char">14.3</td><td char="." align="char">2.5</td><td char="." align="char">1 0</td><td char="." align="char">2.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.6</td><td char="." align="char">7.9</td><td char="." align="char">2.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.4</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td><td char="." align="char">2.4</td><td char="." align="char">1.4</td><td char="." align="char">12.3</td><td char="." align="char">1.4</td><td char="." align="char">4.5</td><td char="." align="char">1.1</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td><td char="." align="char">1010</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C8180_G1_I1</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td char="." align="char">2.8</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td char="." align="char">8.1</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">25.2</td><td char="." align="char">1.5</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td char="." align="char">13.9</td><td char="." align="char">2.4</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">3.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.1</td><td char="." align="char">0.3</td><td char="." align="char">17.2</td><td char="." align="char">1.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.5</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">668</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C55004_G7_I2</td><td align="left">2</td><td char="." align="char">4.4</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td char="." align="char">9.2</td><td char="." align="char">3.9</td><td char="." align="char">11.9</td><td char="." align="char">3.3</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td><td char="." align="char">5.6</td><td char="." align="char">7.3</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td><td char="." align="char">8.3</td><td char="." align="char">3.2</td><td char="." align="char">1.5</td><td char="." align="char">6.2</td><td char="." align="char">3.6</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">1.7</td><td char="." align="char">3.9</td><td char="." align="char">767</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C49942_G2_I1</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td char="." align="char">6.7</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">3</td><td char="." align="char">1.3</td><td char="." align="char">14.8</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td char="." align="char">4.8</td><td char="." align="char">7.4</td><td char="." align="char">2.9</td><td char="." align="char">1.3</td><td char="." align="char">2.7</td><td char="." align="char">1.3</td><td char="." align="char">6.5</td><td char="." align="char">5.1</td><td char="." align="char">4.2</td><td char="." align="char">3.2</td><td char="." align="char">2.8</td><td char="." align="char">5.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.8</td><td char="." align="char">669</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C47067_G1_I2</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td char="." align="char">2.6</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td char="." align="char">8.2</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">7.5</td><td char="." align="char">1.3</td><td char="." align="char">1.4</td><td char="." align="char">5.9</td><td char="." align="char">6.4</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td char="." align="char">4.4</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td char="." align="char">11.2</td><td char="." align="char">2.4</td><td char="." align="char">1.3</td><td char="." align="char">1.4</td><td char="." align="char">3.6</td><td char="." align="char">677</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C44186_G1_I3</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td char="." align="char">2.5</td><td align="left">4.5</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td char="." align="char">5.7</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">15.2</td><td char="." align="char">1.2</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">6.4</td><td char="." align="char">7.9</td><td char="." align="char">2.1</td><td char="." align="char">7.2</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0.7</td><td char="." align="char">9.3</td><td char="." align="char">5.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.1</td><td char="." align="char">4.3</td><td char="." align="char">1034</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C44186_G1_I1</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td char="." align="char">2.6</td><td align="left">4.6</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td char="." align="char">5.4</td><td char="." align="char">2.1</td><td char="." align="char">14.8</td><td char="." align="char">1.5</td><td char="." align="char">6.8</td><td char="." align="char">6.6</td><td char="." align="char">8.1</td><td char="." align="char">2.2</td><td char="." align="char">7.3</td><td char="." align="char">1.2</td><td char="." align="char">0.8</td><td char="." align="char">9.1</td><td char="." align="char">5.4</td><td char="." align="char">0.9</td><td char="." align="char">0.1</td><td char="." align="char">4.1</td><td char="." align="char">659</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C51189_G5_I1</td><td align="left">5</td><td char="." align="char">10.3</td><td align="left">4.1</td><td align="left">3.5</td><td char="." align="char">16.5</td><td char="." align="char">3.6</td><td char="." align="char">19.1</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">21.3</td><td char="." align="char">10.6</td><td char="." align="char">9.5</td><td char="." align="char">1.5</td><td char="." align="char">10.8</td><td char="." align="char">6.5</td><td char="." align="char">2.7</td><td char="." align="char">14.9</td><td char="." align="char">5.9</td><td char="." align="char">6.5</td><td char="." align="char">2.7</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">1017</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>These are raw counts in K (10<sup>3</sup>), and are not normalized. Some NBS-LRR&#x02019;s (like C54426_G7 _I1, a Strubbelig receptor kinase) are significantly overexpressed in specific tissues</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>In summary, high conservation of some proteins within a genus does not allow the proper characterization of the species. Thus, although we can state with a great degree of certainty the presence of the genus <italic>Phytophthora</italic>, it is not possible to identify the exact species/strain. No viruses have been detected using the current methodology. Also, since the root samples were derived from a sterile sample, we did not detect root lesion nematodes (<italic>Pratylenchus</italic><italic>vulnus</italic>), a major source of concern for the California walnut industry (Walawage et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2013</xref>). The detection of specific proteins from pathogens can serve as a target for therapeutics. The methodology described here presents an unbiased rapid tool to extract the metagenome from an RNA-Seq profile that can be used to develop diagnostics. In this study, the profile represented twenty different tissues from walnut, and the extracted metagenome from all of these tissue types presents a vivid picture of the biodiversity in its surroundings in California.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>Dandekar and Britton were involved in the design of the RNAseq, Dandekar and Chakraborty designed the metagenome extraction, Chakraborty did the in silico analysis that revealed the metagenome, Mart&#x000ed;nez-Garc&#x000ed;a was involved in the validation with the walnut genome sequence. Chakraborty wrote the first draft and the rest of the authors were involved in subsequent modifications.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Grant information: The authors wish to acknowledge support from the California Walnut Board and UC Discovery program.</p><p>Accesion number: Sequence data from this article can be found in the NCBI Sequence Read Archive under BioProject PRJNA232394.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alc&#x000e1;zar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronholm</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>de Meaux</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Natural variation at strubbelig receptor kinase 3 drives immune-triggered incompatibilities between <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> accessions</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1135</fpage><lpage>1139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.704</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21037570?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21037570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Armache</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Berninghausen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Habeck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Subklewe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structures of the human and <italic>Drosophila</italic> 80S ribosome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2013</year><volume>497</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23636399?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23636399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwede</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The SWISS-MODEL workspace: a web-based environment for protein structure homology modelling</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti770</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16301204?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16301204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belisario</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Luongo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Galli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First report of <italic>phytophthora</italic><italic>megasperma</italic> associated with decline and death of common walnut trees in Italy</article-title><source>Plant Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>1695</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS-05-12-0470-PDN</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borhan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Holub</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Beynon</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozwadowski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimmer</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> TIR-NB-LRR gene RAC1 confers resistance to <italic>Albugo candida</italic> (white rust) and is dependent on EDS1 but not PAD4</article-title><source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><year>2004</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI.2004.17.7.711</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15242165?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15242165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chakraborty S, Britton M, Wegrzyn J, Butterfield T, Mart&#x000ed;nez-Garc&#x000ed;a PJ, Rao BJ, Leslie CA, Aradhaya M, Neale D, Woeste K, Dandekar AM. YeATS&#x02014;a tool suite for analyzing RNA-seq derived transcriptome identifies a highly transcribed putative extensin in heartwood/sapwood transition zone in black walnut [version 2; referees: 1 approved]] F1000Research 2015, 2015;4:155. doi:10.12688/f1000research.6617.1.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugnet</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomewide analysis of mRNA processing in yeast using splicing-specific microarrays</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>296</volume><fpage>907</fpage><lpage>910</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1069415</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11988574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11988574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conn</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endophytic actino bacteria induce defense pathways in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>thaliana</italic></article-title><source>MPMI</source><year>2008</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI-21-2-0208</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18184065?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18184065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dandekar</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhushan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiehn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Skogerson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wohlgemuth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Souza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reagan</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cary</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardington</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of early host responses for asymptomatic disease detection and management of specialty crops</article-title><source>Crit Rev Immunol</source><year>2010</year><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1615/CritRevImmunol.v30.i3.50</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20370635?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20370635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dastager</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Deepa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of novel plant growth promoting <italic>Micrococcus</italic> sp NII-0909 and its interaction with cowpea</article-title><source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source><year>2010</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>987</fpage><lpage>992</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2010.09.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20951599?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20951599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of juglone concentration on growth in vitro of Frankia ArI3 and <italic>Rhizobium</italic><italic>japonicum</italic> strain 71</article-title><source>J Chem Ecol</source><year>1983</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1175</fpage><lpage>1183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00982220</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24407809?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24407809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeYoung</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Innes</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant NBS-LRR proteins in pathogen sensing and host defense</article-title><source>Nature Immunol</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1243</fpage><lpage>1249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni1410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17110940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Levanon</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human housekeeping genes, revisited</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tig.2013.05.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23810203?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23810203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriseleit</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloos</surname><given-names>DU</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The broad-spectrum potato cystnematode resistance gene (<italic>Hero</italic>) from tomato is the only member of a large gene family of NBS-LRR genes with an unusual amino acid repeat in the LRR region</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2002</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2002.01341.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12121443?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12121443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ey&#x000fc;boglu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Haberer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterisation of the STRUBBELIG-RECEPTOR FAMILY of genes encoding putative leucine-rich repeat receptor-like kinases in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-7-16</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17397538?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17397538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Budowle</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishimaru</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Luster</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Melcher</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Murch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scherm</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Seem</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobral</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant pathogen forensics: capabilities, needs, and recommendations</article-title><source>MMBR</source><year>2006</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.00022-05</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16760310?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16760310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flintoft</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomics: digging deep with RNA-Seq</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>568</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gopalakrishnan S, Srinivas V, Vidya MS, Rathore A. Plant growth-promoting activities of <italic>Streptomyces</italic> spp. in sorghum and rice. SpringerPlus 2013;2:574. doi:10.1186/2193-1801-2-574.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amit</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Adiconis</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Raychowdhury</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauceli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hacohen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnirke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhind</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>di Palma</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Birren</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusbaum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindblad-Toh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Regev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1883</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21572440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Funao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Durable panicle blast-resistance gene Pb1 encodes an atypical CC-NBR-LRR protein and was generated by acquiring a promoter through local genome duplication</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2010</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04348.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20807214?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20807214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isoe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasc&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Miesfeld</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular genetic analysis of midgut serine proteases in <italic>Aedes</italic><italic>aegypti</italic> mosquitoes</article-title><source>Insect Biochem Molec Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibmb.2009.10.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19883761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic methods for phytopathogenic bacteria of stone fruits and nuts in COST 873</article-title><source>EPPO Bulletin</source><year>2010</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2338.2009.02356.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-resolution structure of human d-glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr Sect D Biol Crystallogr</source><year>2006</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444905042289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16510976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Joshi N, Fass J. Sickle. A sliding-window, adaptive, quality-based trimming tool for fastq files. 2011. (version 1.33)[software].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization of culture conditions and scale-up to plant scales for teicoplanin production by <italic>Actinoplanes</italic><italic>teichomyceticus</italic></article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2008</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-008-1530-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18542948?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18542948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Misawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MAFFT: a novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transform</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>3059</fpage><lpage>3066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkf436</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12136088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12136088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Markow</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Duplication, selection and gene conversion in a <italic>Drosophila</italic><italic>mojavensis</italic> female reproductive protein family</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2009</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.108.099044</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19204376?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19204376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kodzius</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiyori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tagami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Harbers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashizaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Carninci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CAGE: cap analysis of gene expression</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2006</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth0306-211</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16489339?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16489339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellwood</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Friesen</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pyrenophora teres: profile of an increasingly damaging barley pathogen</article-title><source>Mol Plant Pathol</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2010.00649.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21118345?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21118345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manzanera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Narv&#x000e1;ez-Reinaldo</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Fontana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000ed;lchez</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome sequence of <italic>Arthrobacter</italic><italic>koreensis</italic> 5J12A, a plant growth-promoting and desiccation-tolerant strain</article-title><source>Genome Announc</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e00648</fpage><?supplied-pmid 26067978?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26067978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McHale</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Koehl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Michelmore</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant NBS-LRR proteins: adaptable guards</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>212</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2006-7-4-212</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16677430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16677430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Griego</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Michelmore</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of NBS-LRR-encoding genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>834</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.009308</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12671079?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12671079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Perfect</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cryptococcosis in the era of aids&#x02013;100&#x000a0;years after the discovery of <italic>cryptococcus</italic><italic>neoformans</italic></article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><year>1995</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><?supplied-pmid 8665468?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8665468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvestri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Natalini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Buonaurio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A protocol for rapid identification of <italic>brenneria nigrifluens</italic> among bacteria isolated from bark cankers in persian walnut plants</article-title><source>J Plant Pathol</source><year>2007</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>218</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakatsu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hristova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Scow</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamagata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Methylibium</italic><italic>petroleiphilum</italic> gen. nov., sp. nov., a novel methyl <italic>tert</italic>-butyl ether-degrading methylotroph of the <italic>Betaproteobacteria</italic></article-title><source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.63524-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16627642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16627642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicaise</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in PAMP-triggered immunity against bacteria: pattern recognition receptors watch over and raise the alarm</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>1638</fpage><lpage>1647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.139709</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19561123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19561123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nowicki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Foolad</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowakowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozik</surname><given-names>EU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potato and tomato late blight caused by <italic>phytophthora</italic><italic>infestans</italic>: an overview of pathology and resistance breeding</article-title><source>Plant Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PDIS-05-11-0458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palaniyandi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of actinobacteria on plant disease suppression and growth promotion</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2013</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>9621</fpage><lpage>9636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-013-5206-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24092003?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24092003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metagenomic analysis of a freshwater toxic cyanobacteria bloom</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source><year>2008</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6941.2008.00448.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18328084?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18328084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Padda</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanway</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence of nitrogen fixation and growth promotion in canola (<italic>Brassica napus L.</italic>) by an endophytic diazotroph <italic>Paenibacillus polymyxa</italic> P2b&#x02013;2R</article-title><source>Biol Fertil Soils.</source><year>2016</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00374-015-1051-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>GZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abundant and diverse endophytic actinobacteria associated with medicinal plant <italic>Maytenus</italic><italic>austroyunnanensis</italic> in Xishuangbanna tropical rainforest revealed by culture-dependent and culture-independent methods</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol Rep</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>522</fpage><lpage>531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1758-2229.2012.00357.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23760897?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23760897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity, bioactive natural products and biotechnological potential of plant-associated endophytic actinobacteria</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2011</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-010-2923-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20941490?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20941490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossettini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanes</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ess1 prolyl isomerase is dispensable for growth but required for virulence in <italic>cryptococcus</italic><italic>neoformans</italic></article-title><source>Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>1593</fpage><lpage>1605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.27786-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deciphering key features in protein structures with the new ENDscript server</article-title><source>Nucl Acids Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><issue>W1</issue><fpage>W320</fpage><lpage>W324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku316</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24753421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24753421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaad</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Frederick</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-time PCR and its application for rapid plant disease diagnostics</article-title><source>Can J Plant Pathol</source><year>2002</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07060660209507006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmit</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An estimate of the lower limit of global fungal diversity</article-title><source>Biodivers Conserv</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10531-006-9129-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staskawicz</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of plant-pathogen interactions specifying plant disease resistance</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.125.1.73</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11154300?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11154300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szab&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gyula</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Robotka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bat&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000e1;lik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pach</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pekker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bihari</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Draft genome sequence of <italic>Methylibium</italic> sp. strain T29, a novel fuel oxygenate-degrading bacterial isolate from Hungary</article-title><source>Stand Genomic Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40793-015-0023-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25678942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tarze</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Deniaud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Bras</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maillier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Molle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Larochette</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamzami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroemer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gapdh, a novel regulator of the pro-apoptotic mitochondrial membrane permeabilization</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2606</fpage><lpage>2620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1210074</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17072346?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17072346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaddepalli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Batoux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneitz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure-function analysis of STRUBBELIG, an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> atypical receptor-like kinase involved in tissue morphogenesis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e19730</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019730</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21603601?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21603601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Van Emden HF, Harrington R. Aphids as crop pests. CABI. 2007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Canchaya</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tauch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chater</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>van Sinderen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomics of actinobacteria: tracing the evolutionary history of an ancient phylum</article-title><source>MMBR</source><year>2007</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.00005-07</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17804669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17804669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vidaver</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The plant pathogenic corynebacteria</article-title><source>Ann Rev Microbiol</source><year>1982</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.mi.36.100182.002431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6756296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walawage</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Uratsu</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dandekar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stacking resistance to crown gall and nematodes in walnut rootstocks</article-title><source>BMC Genom</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>668</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-14-668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardenas</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perfect</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two cyclophilin a homologs with shared and distinct functions important for growth and virulence of cryptococcus neoformans</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/embo-reports/kve109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11415984?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11415984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA-Seq: a revolutionary tool for transcriptomics</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2484</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19015660?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smart</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Krieg</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of RNA from Plant Tissue</article-title><source>A laboratory guide to RNA: isolation, analysis, and synthesis</source><year>1996</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley-Liss Inc</publisher-name><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>41</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The human fungal pathogen cryptococcus can complete its sexual cycle during a pathogenic association with plants</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><year>2007</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2007.05.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18005707?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18005707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Laluk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Receptor-like cytoplasmic kinases integrate signaling from multiple plant immune receptors and are targeted by a <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> effector</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2010.03.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20413097?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20413097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhong Y, Li Y, Huang K, Cheng ZM. Species-specific duplications of NBS-encoding genes in chinese chestnut (<italic>Castanea mollissima</italic>). Scientific reports 5. 2015.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>