<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4585334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.00821</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. ferrous and ferric iron assimilation pathways</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>Elisa Fl&#x000e1;via L. C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/239718/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>Patr&#x000ed;cia de Sousa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/239698/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>Mirelle G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/199918/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>Alexandre M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/186605/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>Gabriel da Rocha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/32213/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kosman</surname><given-names>Daniel J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/122888/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>C&#x000e9;lia Maria de Almeida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/20636/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Biologia Molecular, Instituto de Ci&#x000ea;ncias Biol&#x000f3;gicas, Universidade Federal de Goi&#x000e1;s</institution><country>Goi&#x000e2;nia, Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Bioinform&#x000e1;tica, Universidade Cat&#x000f3;lica de Bras&#x000ed;lia</institution><country>Bras&#x000ed;lia, Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Biochemistry, School of Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, State University of New York at Buffalo</institution><country>Buffalo, NY, USA</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Helio K. Takahashi, Universidade Federal de S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Brazil</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Marcelo Tolmasky, California State University Fullerton, USA; Marcos Sergio Toledo, Universidade Federal de S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Brazil</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: C&#x000e9;lia Maria de Almeida Soares, Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Biologia Molecular, Instituto de Ci&#x000ea;ncias Biol&#x000f3;gicas II, Universidade Federal de Goi&#x000e1;s, Pr&#x000e9;dio ICB II, Sala 206, C&#x000e2;mpus Samambaia, 74690-900 Goi&#x000e2;nia, Brazil <email xlink:type="simple">cmasoares@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Fungi and Their Interactions, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="fn003"><p>&#x02020;Present Address: Elisa Fl&#x000e1;via L. C. Bail&#x000e3;o, Universidade Estadual de Goi&#x000e1;s, An&#x000e1;polis, Brazil; Mirelle G. Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o, Universidade Federal de Goi&#x000e1;s, Unidade Acad&#x000ea;mica Ci&#x000ea;ncias da Sa&#x000fa;de, Jata&#x000ed;, Brazil; Gabriel da Rocha Fernandes, Centro de Pesquisas Rene Rachou - Fiocruz, Grupo de Gen&#x000f4;mica e Biologia Computacional, Belo Horizonte, Brazil</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>821</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2015 Bail&#x000e3;o, Lima, Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o, Bail&#x000e3;o, Fernandes, Kosman and Soares.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bail&#x000e3;o, Lima, Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o, Bail&#x000e3;o, Fernandes, Kosman and Soares</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Iron is an essential micronutrient for almost all organisms, including fungi. Usually, fungi can uptake iron through receptor-mediated internalization of a siderophore or heme, and/or reductive iron assimilation (RIA). Traditionally, the RIA pathway consists of ferric reductases (Fres), ferroxidase (Fet3) and a high-affinity iron permease (Ftr1). <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. genomes do not present an Ftr1 homolog. However, this fungus expresses zinc regulated transporter homologs (Zrts), members of the ZIP family of membrane transporters that are able in some organisms to transport zinc and iron. A 2,3,5-triphenyltetrazolium chloride (TTC)-overlay assay indicates that both <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 express a ferric reductase activity; however, <sup>59</sup>Fe uptake assays indicate that only in <italic>Pb</italic>18 is this activity coupled to a reductase-dependent iron uptake pathway. In addition, Zrts are up-regulated in iron deprivation, as indicated by RNAseq and qRT-PCR using <italic>Pb</italic>01 transcripts. RNAseq strategy also demonstrated that transcripts related to siderophore uptake and biosynthesis are up-regulated in iron-deprived condition. The data suggest that the fungus could use both a non-classical RIA, comprising ferric reductases and Fe/Zn permeases (Zrts), and siderophore uptake pathways under iron-limited conditions. The study of iron metabolism reveals novel surface molecules that could function as accessible targets for drugs to block iron uptake and, consequently, inhibit pathogen's proliferation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>iron reduction</kwd><kwd>iron uptake</kwd><kwd>ferric reductase</kwd><kwd>zinc-regulated transporter</kwd><kwd>multicopper oxidases</kwd><kwd>paracoccidioidomycosis</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="9"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="50"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="8198"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Iron is the most common cofactor in biology. This fact could be explained by the high abundance of the element in nature and by its chemical properties, mainly by its redox ability. Since iron participates in several metabolic pathways, either aerobes or anaerobes must obtain ferrous iron (Fe<sup>2+</sup>), since ferric iron (Fe<sup>3+</sup>) is insoluble. Typically, fungi accumulate iron through two different strategies: (1) receptor-mediated internalization of ferric-siderophore complexes and/or heme group; and (2) reductive iron assimilation (RIA), involving iron reduction, followed by a ferroxidase-permeation step (Kosman, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The first strategy has been recently described in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. It has been shown that this fungus is able to utilize siderophores and hemoglobin as iron sources through receptor-mediated pathways (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). However, the RIA in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. remains elusive.</p><p>Ferric reductases have a central role in both strategies of iron capture (Baek et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). These enzymes, along with ferroxidases and permeases, promote high-affinity iron uptake (Kosman, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Moreover, ferric reductases are important in removing iron from siderophores (Yun et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>) or from host iron sources, such as transferrin and hemin (Knight et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Saikia et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In addition to the essential role in iron uptake, ferric reductases are also important for melanin production, resistance to azole drugs, virulence (Saikia et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and host adaptation (Hu et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) in <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>. In <italic>C. albicans</italic>, the ferric reductases also participate in the oxidative stress response, filamentous development and virulence (Xu et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Besides the transmembrane ferric reductase enzymes, a secreted &#x003b3;-glutamyltransferase (Ggt1) activity has been described in <italic>Histoplasma capsulatum, Blastomyces dermatitidis, Paracoccidioides</italic> sp. and <italic>Sporothrix schenckii</italic> (Zarnowski and Woods, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>).</p><p>Multicopper oxidases (MCOs) consist of four enzyme superfamilies: laccases, ascorbate oxidases, ferroxidases, and ceruloplasmin, that catalyze the four-electron reduction of molecular oxygen to two molecules of water (Sirim et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). In fungal ferroxidases, as noted for <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> Fet3, the specificity for Fe<sup>2+</sup> as an electron donor derives from the presence of two carboxyl groups, E185 and D409, which are in H-bond contact with the T1 Cu ligands H489 and H413, respectively (Kosman, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). In most fungi, the Fe<sup>3+</sup> product derived from a ferroxidase reaction is channeled to a high-affinity iron permease, Ftr1, which is associated to the ferroxidase in the fungal plasma membrane (Kwok et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Ziegler et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p><p>The <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> genus comprises thermodimorphic fungal pathogens causing paracoccidioidomycosis (PCM), which is a deep systemic mycosis with a high prevalence in Brazil, Colombia, Venezuela, and Argentina (San-Blas et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Since the notification of PCM cases is not obligatory, prevalence of this fungal disease is likely significantly under-reported (Martinez, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The treatment available for PCM is long and may include several side effects and pathogen resistance. Thus, there is a great demand for the development of safer alternative therapies that are able to overcome resistance (Bocca et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In this context, blocking iron acquisition is a good strategy to prevent or treat fungal diseases since iron is an essential nutrient for pathogen proliferation in vertebrate hosts (Kronstad et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In this way, the knowledge about <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. iron acquisition mechanisms can contribute to reveal new targets to antifungal therapy.</p><p>The iron uptake mechanisms in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. have been investigated in part (Parente et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Silva et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). It has been demonstrated by our group that <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. presents multiple ferric reductases and MCOs and a <italic>ggt1</italic> homolog, but no <italic>ftr1</italic> homolog (Silva et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Moreover, it was observed that ferric reductase transcripts (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>), zinc regulated transporters (Zrts) homologs (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), hemoglobin receptor homologs and transcripts related to siderophore synthesis and uptake (Parente et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) are induced during <italic>in vitro</italic> iron deprivation or when <italic>in vivo</italic> models of infection were used. Siderophore production and acquisition and host iron sources have been investigated in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. In iron-depleted condition, siderophore secretion by this fungus increases. Moreover, <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. are able to use siderophores as iron source, increasing the fungus ability to survive inside macrophages, a poor-iron environment (Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). We also demonstrated that hemoglobin is the preferential host iron source for <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. To acquire hemoglobin, the fungus presents hemolytic activity and the ability to internalize the entire molecule instead of promoting the iron release extracellularly. A GPI-anchored hemoglobin receptor, Rbt5, is a virulence factor (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Since <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. do not express an Ftr1 homolog, Fre homologs could reduce the iron, which could be imported by iron/zinc permeases (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Silva et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), but this hypothesis remains elusive.</p><p>In this work, the RIA pathway was investigated. We have demonstrated that <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. is able to reduce iron, and in the case of <italic>Pb</italic>18, this reductase activity is linked to ferric iron uptake. In contrast, this reductase activity in <italic>Pb</italic>01 does not appear to be up-stream from this uptake. After reduction, the data suggest that Fe<sup>2+</sup> is probably internalized through a Fe/Zn permease (Zrt). This suggestion is because <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. genomes do not present an <italic>ftr1</italic> homolog and the <italic>zrt1</italic> and <italic>zrt2</italic> transcripts are up-regulated during iron deprivation. In addition, transcripts related to siderophore uptake and biosynthesis are up-regulated upon iron deprivation. The data suggest that the fungus could use both a non-classical RIA, comprising ferric reductases and Fe/Zn permeases, and siderophore uptake pathways under iron-limited conditions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Strains and growth conditions</title><p><italic>Paracoccidioides Pb</italic>01 (ATCC MYA-826; <italic>Paracoccidioides lutzii</italic>) (Teixeira et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and <italic>Pb</italic>18 (ATCC 32069; <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic>, phylogenetic species S1) (Carrero et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) were used in this work. The fungus was maintained in brain heart infusion (BHI) medium supplemented with 4% (w/v) glucose at 36&#x000b0;C to cultivate the yeast form. Before each experiment, the cells were grown in liquid BHI supplemented with 4% (w/v) glucose for 72 h at 36&#x000b0;C under rotation.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In silico</italic> sequences analysis</title><p><italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 putative ferric reductase and ferroxidase amino acid sequences were obtained in the <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> genome database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/paracoccidioides_brasiliensis/MultiHome.html">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/paracoccidioides_brasiliensis/MultiHome.html</ext-link>). The <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. sequences were compared using the ClustalX2 program (Larkin et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Comparisons were performed with amino acid sequences from other fungi, as following: <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aspergillusgenome.org">http://www.aspergillusgenome.org</ext-link>), <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/fungi/aspergillus_nidulans_old">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/fungi/aspergillus_nidulans_old</ext-link>), <italic>H. capsulatum</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/histoplasma_capsulatum/MultiHome.html">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/histoplasma_capsulatum/MultiHome.html</ext-link>). <italic>Coccidioides immitis, Coccidioides posadasii</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/coccidioides_group/MultiHome.html">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/coccidioides_group/MultiHome.html</ext-link>), <italic>B. dermatitidis</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/blastomyces_dermatitidis/MultiHome.html">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/blastomyces_dermatitidis/MultiHome.html</ext-link>), <italic>Ustilago maydis</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/ustilago_maydis/Home.html">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/ustilago_maydis/Home.html</ext-link>), <italic>C. neoformans</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/cryptococcus_neoformans/MultiHome.html">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/cryptococcus_neoformans/MultiHome.html</ext-link>), <italic>S. pombe</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pombase.org">http://www.pombase.org</ext-link>), <italic>C. albicans</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.candidagenome.org/">http://www.candidagenome.org/</ext-link>), and <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.yeastgenome.org">http://www.yeastgenome.org</ext-link>). ClustalX2 program (Larkin et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) and TreeView v.1.6.6 program (Page, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>) were used for phylogenetic analysis and visualization, respectively, applying the neighbor-joining method and the tree architecture was inferred from 1000 bootstraps. Domains in amino acid sequences were localized using SMART online tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/">http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/</ext-link>).</p><p>A structural model of the putative ferroxidase, <italic>Pb</italic>01 PAAG_06004 was obtained using the Modeler program (Sali et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>) at the Max-Planck Institute for Developmental Biology website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://toolkit.tuebingen.mpg.de/modeller#">http://toolkit.tuebingen.mpg.de/modeller#</ext-link>). The input for the model used the structure of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Fet3 as template (PDB 1ZPU). InsightII was used subsequently to further energy minimize the model using the cvff forcefield with 5000 iterations and a CG convergence of 1.0.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA extraction and quantitative real time PCR (qRT-PCR)</title><p><italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 yeast cells were incubated in Synthetic Complete medium (SC medium: 6.67 g/l yeast nitrogen base without amino acids, 2% glucose plus amino acids mixture) with no supplementation or with addition of 200 &#x003bc;M of bathophenanthroline disulfonic acid (BPS) or 10 &#x003bc;M FeCl<sub>3</sub> at 36&#x000b0;C under rotation. After 2 h, the cells were harvested and total RNA was extracted using TRIzol (TRI Reagent, Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) and mechanical cell rupture (Mini-Beadbeater&#x02014;Biospec Products Inc., Bartlesville, OK). The total RNA was treated with DNAse I (Promega Corporation, Madison, WI, USA) and used as template in <italic>in vitro</italic> reverse transcription (SuperScript III First-Strand Synthesis SuperMix; Invitrogen, Life Technologies). Then, the cDNAs were submitted to a qRT-PCR reaction, which was performed using SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) in a StepOnePlus Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems Inc.). The expression values were calculated using the transcript that encoded alpha tubulin (XM_002796593) as the endogenous control as previously reported (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2012b</xref>). The annealing temperature for all primers was 62&#x000b0;C. The qRT-PCR reaction was performed in biological triplicate for each cDNA sample, and a melting curve analysis was performed to confirm single PCR products. The relative standard curve was generated using a pool of cDNAs from all the conditions that were used, which was serially diluted 1:5&#x02013;1:625. Relative expression levels of transcripts of interest were calculated using the standard curve method for relative quantification (Bookout et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Student's <italic>t</italic>-test was applied in the statistical analyses. For confirmation of Zrts induction in iron-deprived condition by qRT-PCR, all steps were performed as described, except for <italic>Pb</italic>01 incubation in chemically defined MMcM medium (Restrepo and Jim&#x000e9;nez, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">1980</xref>) supplemented with 3.5 &#x003bc;M inorganic iron [Fe(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>] or with 50 &#x003bc;M of the iron chelator bathophenanthroline disulfonic acid (BPS: Sigma-Aldrich, Germany) for 3 or 24 h before cell harvesting.</p></sec><sec><title>TTC indicator plates</title><p>To detect <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 surface reductase activity, a plate assay was used as described previously (Ogur et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">1957</xref>), except that the 2,3,5-triphenyltetrazolium chloride (TTC)-containing overlay was poured on fresh colonies grown on SC plates, supplemented or not with 50 &#x003bc;M BPS (no iron condition), 30 &#x003bc;M inorganic iron [Fe(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>], 30 &#x003bc;M hemoglobin, 120 &#x003bc;M hemin, 30 &#x003bc;g/ml ferritin, or 30 &#x003bc;M transferrin, independently. All host iron sources were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA.</p></sec><sec><title><sup>59</sup>Fe uptake assays</title><p>After 24 h of <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 incubation in SC medium with no supplementation or with addition of 200 &#x003bc;M BPS or 10 &#x003bc;M FeCl<sub>3</sub> at 36&#x000b0;C under rotation, the cells were harvested and washed with 1 mM EDTA in citrate uptake buffer (2% analar glucose, 0.1 MES buffer, and 20 mM Na-citrate, pH 6.0). After, the cells were washed twice with citrate uptake buffer and incubated for 15 min at 36&#x000b0;C under rotation. At this time, an aliquot of cells was collected and counted in a hemocytometer. Then, 20 mM of ascorbic acid was added (reductive-independent <sup>59</sup>Fe uptake assay) or not (reductive-dependent <sup>59</sup>Fe uptake assay); Cl<sub>4</sub>K<sub>2</sub>Pt (PtII compound) was added or not; and 0.2 &#x003bc;M <sup>59</sup>Fe solution (Perkin-Elmer, Waltham, MA) was added independent of the condition. A triplicate of point 0 and 60 min were collected in a filter membrane (type A/C 25 mm glass fiber filter, Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) and the cells were washed with ice-cold 1X Quench buffer (37.5 mM succinic acid, 62.5 mM Tris, and 12.8 mM EDTA, pH 6.0). Then filters containing the cells were placed on the bottom of the test tubes and internalized <sup>59</sup>Fe was measured using a Wallac &#x003b3; counter (LKB Wallac CompuGamma). <sup>59</sup>Fe values were normalized with the number of cells.</p></sec><sec><title>High-throughput mRNA sequencing (RNA-seq)</title><p><italic>Pb</italic>01 yeast cells were incubated in chemically defined MMcM medium supplemented with 3.5 &#x003bc;M Fe(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub> or with 50 &#x003bc;M BPS (Sigma-Aldrich, Germany) for 24 h at 36&#x000b0;C on a rotary shaker at 150 rpm. After that, the cells for both conditions, in biological triplicates, were treated with TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) to obtain RNA molecules. The cDNAs libraries were prepared from poly(A)-fragment selected mRNA and processed on the Illumina HiSeq2000 Sequencing System (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.illumina.com/">http://www.illumina.com/</ext-link>). As a result, approximately 40 million of reads of 100 bp paired-end sequencing were obtained for each sample. The sequencing reads were mapped to reference the <italic>Pb</italic>01 genome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/paracoccidioides_brasiliensis/MultiHome.html">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/paracoccidioides_brasiliensis/ MultiHome.html</ext-link>) using the Bowtie 2 tool (Langmead et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Briefly, each read was allowed to alignment in just one site of the genome and the reads were counted. The default parameters were used to perform the alignment. The number of mismatches allowed in seed alignment (&#x02212;N) is 0, and the length of each seed (&#x02212;L) is 20. Reads mapped to a gene region were counted to infer expression measurement. Differentially expressed genes were identified using Fisher Exact test in DEGseq package (Wang et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). A <italic>p</italic>-value lower than 0.001 and minimum fold change of 1.5 were used to filter the most relevant candidates. Meaning that transcripts with log2 (fold change) higher than 0.58 or less than &#x02212;0.58 were selected and classified as up- and down-regulated transcripts, respectively. Transcript's identifications and annotations were determined from the <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> genome database. The biological processes were obtained using the Pedant on MIPS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pedant.helmholtzmuenchen.de/pedant3htmlview/pedant3view?Method=analysis&#x00026;Db=p3_r48325_Par_brasi_Pb01">http://pedant.helmholtzmuenchen.de/pedant3htmlview/pedant3view?Method=analysis&#x00026;Db=p3_r48325_Par_brasi_Pb01</ext-link>) which provides a tool to browse and search the Functional Categories (FunCat) of proteins.</p><p>The predicted proteins encoded by the transcripts identified through RNAseq strategy were also classified as copper&#x02212;, iron&#x02212;, and zinc-binding proteins from <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> genome as previously described (Trist&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Briefly, metalloproteins were identified by using the RDGB tool (Andreini et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) with default options. In the RDGB strategy, the protein domains defined in the Pfam library are used to identify putative homologs in any desired genome or list of genomes. Copper&#x02212;, iron&#x02212;, and zinc-binding Pfam domains were initially identified in the sequence of copper&#x02212;, iron&#x02212;, and zinc-binding proteins of known 3D structures, which are available from the Protein Data Bank (PDB). When a particular metal is present within the 3D structure of the protein, this information can be readily extracted from the PDB database along with the pattern of amino acids that are involved in the interaction of the protein with the metal. In addition, other specific domains were also identified to predicted encoded transcripts using the <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> genome database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/paracoccidioides_brasiliensis/MultiHome.html">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/paracoccidioides_brasiliensis/MultiHome.html</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Characterization of <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. ferric reductases</title><p>The <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. Genome Database searching for proteins possessing all the three domains: FRD (PF01794), FAD-binding domain (PF08022), and ferric reductase NAD-binding domain (PF08030) resulted in seven <italic>Pb</italic>01 and seven <italic>Pb</italic>18 putative ferric reductases. Moreover, amino acid sequences of <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. Ggt1 homologs were collected in the same database. These sequences were used to construct a phylogenetic tree comprising ferric reductase sequences of different fungi: <italic>A. nidulans, A. fumigatus, H. capsulatum, C. immitis, C. posadasii, B. dermatitidis, U. maydis, C. neoformans, S. pombe, S. cerevisiae</italic>, and <italic>C. albicans</italic> (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">1</xref>). It could be observed that all the <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. sequences are grouped with <italic>H. capsulatum, C. immitis, C. posadasii</italic>, and <italic>B. dermatitidis</italic> sequences. Moreover, BLAST analyses revealed the presence of three groups of proteins in this phylogenetic three: (1) transmembrane ferric reductases; (2) NADPH oxidases; and (3) &#x003b3;-glutamyltransferases. The sequences identified as NADPH oxidases were excluded from posterior analyses, since they are out of the manuscript's scope.</p><p>All the <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 sequences classified as transmembrane ferric reductases contained characteristic features of ferric reductases, such as the FRD, NAD, and FAD-binding domains, a bis-heme motif and at least five transmembrane domains (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The sequences classified as &#x003b3;-glutamyltransferases were aligned and presented similarity, mainly in some regions of &#x003b3;-glutamyltranspeptidase domain (PF01019) (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">2</xref>), indicating that other fungi, such as <italic>A. fumigatus, A. nidulans, C. albicans, C. neoformans, S. cerevisiae, S. pombe, U. maydis, C. immitis</italic>, and <italic>C. posadasii</italic>, not tested yet for extracellular glutathione-dependent ferric reductase (GSH-FeR) activity could utilize this alternative iron reduction route.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold><italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. ferric reductases present typical domains</bold>. Domains identified in <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 transmembrane ferric reductases were: ferric reductase domain (blue box), FAD-binding domain (green box), and NAD-binding domain (yellow box). Asterisks indicate the bis-hememotif comprising conserved histidine residues. Black boxes above each sequence indicate the lengh and position of transmembrane domains. The number of amino acids (aa) of each protein is indicated adjacent to the sequences.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-06-00821-g0001"/></fig></sec><sec><title><italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. ferric reductase regulation and iron uptake</title><p>In order to evaluate the <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 putative ferric reductase transcripts, the yeast cells were cultivated in presence of 10 &#x003bc;M inorganic iron or 200 &#x003bc;M BPS. After 2 h, it was observed no relevant regulation of all <italic>Pb</italic>01 transcripts analyzed in response to iron availability. <italic>Pb</italic>18 <italic>fre3, fre7</italic>, and <italic>ggt1</italic> transcripts presented a slight regulation in response to iron availability. Under iron supplementation, <italic>Pb</italic>18 <italic>fre3</italic> transcript level increased, whereas <italic>Pb</italic>18 <italic>fre7</italic> and <italic>ggt1</italic> transcripts level reduced, comparing to the SC medium without any supplementation. Under iron deprivation (presence of BPS), <italic>Pb</italic>18 <italic>fre7</italic> transcript level reduced, whereas <italic>Pb</italic>18 <italic>ggt1</italic> transcript level increased, comparing to the SC medium without any supplementation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Overall, there was no indication of a pattern of iron regulation of ferric reductase transcripts abundance in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Expression profile of transcripts putatively encoding <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. ferric reductases</bold>. <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 yeast cells were recovered from SC medium, which was supplemented or not with 200 &#x003bc;M BPS or 10 &#x003bc;M FeCl<sub>3</sub>, after 2 h incubation. After RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis, <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 transcript levels were quantified using qRT-PCR. The expression values were calculated using alpha tubulin as the endogenous control. The data are expressed as the mean &#x000b1; SD from triplicates. <sup>*</sup>Statistically significant data as determined by Student's <italic>t</italic>-test (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-06-00821-g0002"/></fig><p>To investigate if the RIA pathway could be functional when <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. grow in presence of different iron sources, inorganic iron, hemoglobin, hemin, ferritin, or transferrin were used. SC medium not supplemented with iron or chelated with BPS (no iron) were also used as controls. The <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 yeast cells growing in all conditions presented cell surface reductase activity, as evidenced by the red colony color in the presence of TTC (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). In addition, <sup>59</sup>Fe uptake was quantified in presence or absence of the reducing agent ascorbic acid using <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 yeast cells grown in presence or absence of iron. The results showed that cells cultivated under iron deprivation (200 &#x003bc;M BPS) presented an increased <sup>59</sup>Fe uptake rate, when compared to cells cultivated in the presence of 10 &#x003bc;M FeCl3 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). When ascorbic acid was omitted, <sup>59</sup>Fe uptake should be dependent on ferric reduction; only <italic>Pb</italic>18 cells cultivated under iron deprivation were able to internalize <sup>59</sup>Fe added as ferric iron indicating that the reductase activity in this strain was coupled to iron uptake.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Activation of ferric reductase activity in presence of different iron sources by <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp</bold>. <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 cell cultures were collected after 24 h in presence of 200 &#x003bc;M BPS, washed and 10<sup>4</sup> cells were spotted on SC medium plates, which were supplemented or not with 50 &#x003bc;M BPS, 30 &#x003bc;M inorganic iron, 30 &#x003bc;M hemoglobin, 120 &#x003bc;M hemin, 30 mg/ml ferritin, or 30 &#x003bc;M transferrin, independently. After 10 days of growth, TTC-containing agar solution was poured on the plates containing the colonies. The red colonies after TTC addition indicate a reduction of the colorless electron acceptor TTC to a red formazan precipitate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-06-00821-g0003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>The iron uptake rate in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. is dependent on the culture conditions and on the oxidation state of available iron</bold>. <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 yeast cells were cultivated on SC medium, which was supplemented or not with 200 &#x003bc;M BPS or 10 &#x003bc;M FeCl<sub>3</sub>, for 24 h. Then, the cells were collected, washed and incubated in presence of <sup>59</sup>Fe with addition (+) or not (&#x02212;) of ascorbic acid for 60 min. After this, the cells were collected and washed again and submitted to a &#x003b3; counter for iron uptake rate establishment. The data is present as the mean &#x000b1; SD from triplicates or quadruplicates. <sup>*</sup>Statistically significant data, as determined by Student's <italic>t</italic>-test (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), relative to yeast cells cultivated on SC medium.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-06-00821-g0004"/></fig><p>Since the ferric reductase activity can be subject to inhibition by Pt(II) (Eide et al., <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>), the <italic>Pb</italic>18 ferric reductase sensitivity to this element was tested using as an indicator the sensitivity of <sup>59</sup>Fe uptake to this transition metal. <italic>Pb</italic>18 cells cultivated under iron deprivation exhibited a modest decrease in reductase-dependent <sup>59</sup>Fe uptake in the presence of Pt(II) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>); the limited uptake by <italic>Pb</italic>01 of <sup>59</sup>Fe added as ferric iron was not strongly affected by this addition (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of a platinum compound addition on the iron uptake rate of <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp</bold>. <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 yeast cells were cultivated on SC medium supplemented or not with 200 &#x003bc;M BPS for 24 h. Then, the cells were collected, washed and incubated in presence of <sup>59</sup>Fe with addition (+) or not (&#x02212;) of ascorbic acid and/or a platinum compound (PtII) for 60 min. After this, the cells were collected and washed again and submitted to a &#x003b3; counter for iron uptake rate establishment in <italic>Pb</italic>18 <bold>(A)</bold> and <italic>Pb</italic>01 <bold>(B)</bold>. The data is present as the mean &#x000b1; SD from triplicates or quadruplicates. <sup>*</sup>Statistically significant data, as determined by Student's <italic>t</italic>-test (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), relative to yeast cells cultivated on abscence of a PtII compound.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-06-00821-g0005"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The multicopper oxidases in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp.</title><p>To start an investigation about <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. ferroxidases, a searching for MCOs in Laccase Engineering Database (LccED: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lcced.uni-stuttgart.de">http://www.lcced.uni-stuttgart.de</ext-link>) was developed. It resulted in no <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. sequences classified in family E, corresponding to fungal ferroxidases. <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. MCOs are classified as basidiomycete laccases (family A), ascomycete laccases (family B), and fungal pigment MCOs (family D) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lcced.uni-stuttgart.de/cgi-bin/LccED1.2/index.pl?page=org&#x00026;id=35">http://www.lcced.uni-stuttgart.de/cgi-bin/LccED1.2/index.pl?page=org&#x00026;id=35</ext-link>). However, the sequences of all the <italic>Pb</italic>01 and <italic>Pb</italic>18 MCOs deposited in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> Genome Database were collected and aligned with <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Fet3 (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">3</xref>) to identify both potential Cu-binding residues and the carboxylate side chains that support ferrous oxidase activity in fungal ferroxidases (Kosman, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). This examination indicated that only PAAG_00163 do not clearly displayed all four Cu-binding motifs and therefore cannot support the ferroxidase activity typical in the RIA pathway.</p><p>The ferroxidase activity in fungal MCOs is due to two acidic residues; in Fet3 these are E185 and D407. The global alignments (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">3</xref>) provide insight into the presence of homologous residues in two <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. proteins, PAAG_06004 and PADG_05994, which are likely ferroxidases. A clear difference between Fet3 and <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. proteins is that the former presents a C-terminal transmembrane domain, whereas PAAG_06004 and PADG_05994 present N-terminal transmembrane domain (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">3</xref>). Due to high similarity in ferroxidase motifs and in residues involved in Fe<sup>2+</sup> binding between the PAAG_06004 and PADG_05994, a structural model of PAAG_06004 was constructed based on the structure of Fet3 (PBD 1ZPU). Despite the fact that the two proteins have only 22% identity, a satisfactory model was generated that did, however, contain a relatively large (unfavorable) Z-score for torsion angle energy. However, the model faithfully reproduced the conformation of the protein's four predicted Cu-coordination sites and indicated that in PAAG_06004 E280 and D536 could be part of a ferroxidase site in this protein (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Isolation and characterization of this protein is necessary to test this possible ferroxidase activity.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Model of the putative Cu-coordination sites in <italic>Pb</italic>01 PAAG_06004</bold>. The ribbon diagram illustrates the protein folds that contain the 11 side chains that make up the coordination sites for the 4 Cu-atoms found in fungal MCOs. The six His side chains in the lower left quadrant are ligands to the T2 and T3 Cu atoms that make up the trinuclear cluster to which O<sub>2</sub> binds and is reduced to 2H<sub>2</sub>O. The grouping of H540, C616, H621, and M626 are ligands to the T1 Cu that is the electron acceptor from the reducing substrate. Ferroxidases contain two acidic side chains outer-sphere to this ligand grouping that are in H-bond contact with each of the His side chains. The unbiased computer model of PAAG_06004 has E280 and D536 in this conformation relative to the Fet3 T1 Cu His ligands H621 and H540, respectively, suggesting that this protein could exhibit ferroxidase activity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-06-00821-g0006"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The iron permeases in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> sp.</title><p>A whole transcriptome sequencing strategy was performed as previously described (Lima et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The number of the reads counted for each transcript in iron replete and iron-deprived conditions was represented by scattered dots (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">4</xref>). The transcripts were represented by dots, which could present a different number of reads in each condition (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">4A</xref>). We also applied a statistical test to identify differentially expressed transcripts, represented by red dots (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">4B</xref>). A total of 549 transcripts were statistically significant (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">4B</xref>) but a cut-off of 1.5-fold change (Amich et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) generated 30 up- and 44 down-regulated transcripts (Supplementary Tables <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">2</xref>).</p><p>Previous analysis has indicated that <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. does not express a Ftr1 homolog and thus the fungus could use zinc permeases to transport iron (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Silva et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). The RNAseq analysis revealed that zinc permeases transcripts (<italic>zrt1</italic> and <italic>zrt2</italic>) are up-regulated under iron deprivation in <italic>Pb</italic>01 yeast cells, consistent with this hypothesis (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref> and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). The results also revealed that a siderophore uptake encoding transcript (<italic>mirB</italic>) and transcripts encoding enzymes, such as carbapenemantibiotics biosynthesis protein (<italic>carD</italic>) and NADP-specific glutamate dehydrogenase (<italic>gdh</italic>), involved in ornithine biosynthesis, a hydroxamate precursor, are up-regulated under iron deprivation (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref> and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). This fact points to an increase in siderophore synthesis and uptake during iron deprivation. Down-regulated transcripts are related to amino acid and lipid metabolism, which could generate acetyl-CoA, precursor for several metabolic pathways, and with heme biosynthesis, an iron-dependent molecule. The acetyl-CoA decreased production in association with the down-regulation of the electron transport chain could indicate an impaired aerobic metabolism (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). In fact, iron-sulfur proteins, such as succinate dehydrogenase iron-sulfur subunit (<italic>sdh</italic>) and cytosolic Fe-S cluster assembling factor NBP35, that also need iron as a cofactor, were down-regulated (Supplementary Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">2</xref> and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>), indicating that the fungus faces an iron-deprived condition.</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Schematic representation of up and down-regulated transcripts under iron deprivation</bold>. <italic>Pb</italic>01 yeast cells were cultivated on MMcM medium supplemented with 3.5 &#x003bc;M inorganic iron or with 50 &#x003bc;M BPS (iron deprivation) for 24 h. Then, a high-throughput mRNA sequencing (RNA-seq) strategy was used to compare transcripts expressed in iron deprivation and in presence of iron. Some transcripts obtained using this strategy was selected to construct this scheme. In iron deprivation condition, transcripts involved with siderophore synthesis (<italic>carD</italic> and <italic>gdh</italic>) and uptake (<italic>mirB</italic>) and with iron uptake using Fe/Zn permeases (<italic>zrt1</italic> and <italic>zrt2</italic>) were up-regulated. On the other hand, transcripts involved with amino acid (<italic>kynu</italic> and <italic>tyr</italic>) and lipid degradation (<italic>thio, ech</italic>and <italic>acd</italic>) and with synthesis of putative iron-dependent molecules (<italic>alas, sdh</italic>, and <italic>nbp35</italic>), such as heme and iron-sulfur proteins, were down-regulated. <italic>carD</italic>, carbapenemantibiotics biosynthesis protein; <italic>gdh</italic>, NADP-specific glutamate dehydrogenase; <italic>mirB</italic>, siderophore iron transporter; <italic>zrt1</italic> and <italic>zrt2</italic>, zinc regulated transporters; <italic>kynu</italic>, kynureninase; <italic>tyr</italic>, tyrosinase central domain-containing protein; <italic>thio</italic>, 3-ketoacyl-CoA thiolase; <italic>ech</italic>, delta(3,5)-delta(2,4)-dienoyl-CoA isomerase; <italic>acd</italic>, acyl-CoA dehydrogenase family protein; <italic>alas</italic>, 5-aminolevulinate synthase; <italic>sdh</italic>, succinate dehydrogenase iron-sulfur subunit; <italic>nbp35</italic>, cytosolic Fe-S cluster assembling factor.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-06-00821-g0007"/></fig><p>When <italic>Pb</italic>01 <italic>zrt1</italic> and <italic>zrt2</italic> transcripts were analyzed using qRT-PCR, similar results were obtained. After 24 h of iron deprivation, <italic>zrt1</italic> and <italic>zrt2</italic> expression increased (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>), indicating that these genes could play a role in iron acquisition.</p><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>Transcripts putatively encoding <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> sp. Fe/Zn permeases are iron-regulated</bold>. <italic>Pb</italic>01 yeast cells were recovered from MMcM medium, which was supplemented with 50 &#x003bc;M BPS or 3.5 &#x003bc;M inorganic iron for 3 or 24 h. After RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis, levels of <italic>Pb</italic>01 <italic>zrt1</italic> and <italic>zrt2</italic> were quantified by qRT-PCR. The expression values were calculated using alpha tubulin as the endogenous control. The values that were plotted on the bar graph were normalized against the expression data that were obtained from the iron addition condition (fold change). The data are expressed as the mean &#x000b1; SD from triplicates. <sup>*</sup>Statistically significant data as determined by Student's <italic>t</italic>-test (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-06-00821-g0008"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The iron uptake strategies in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp.</title><p>Based on previously published data (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Parente et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and those obtained in this study, an updated model regarding the iron uptake strategies used by <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. was proposed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>). Under iron deprivation, the fungus may use both ferric/ferrous iron uptake and siderophore uptake pathways, since an increase in <italic>zrts</italic> transcripts and in those involved with siderophore production and uptake was observed in this study and/or in previously published data (Parente et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Hemoglobin uptake through the hemoglobin receptors may be used preferentially in the presence of this host molecule, since <italic>Pb</italic>01 putative hemoglobin receptors present reduced transcription under iron depletion (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In the same way, transmembrane ferric reductases seem to be up-regulated in presence of host iron sources, such as transferrin and hemoglobin, since <italic>Pb</italic>01 <italic>fre3</italic> transcript (named previously as <italic>fre2</italic>) presented an increased expression during <italic>Pb</italic>01 yeast cells incubation with human plasma (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) and human blood (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>).</p><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><bold>Schematic representation of <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. activated pathways in iron-deprived condition</bold>. Forms with dark colors indicate proteins whose transcription is up-regulated and that ones with light colors do not present transcription regulation. In that way, in iron-deprived condition, siderophore uptake, and biosynthesis of extracellular siderophores (coprogen B), as well as, Fe/Zn permeases (Zrts) are up-regulated. It seems that transmembrane ferric reductases and hemoglobin receptors are up-regulated mainly in presence of host iron sources, such as transferrin and hemoglobin, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-06-00821-g0009"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>As described previously, <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. presents multiple ferric reductases (Silva et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). These proteins are very similar to homologs found in <italic>H. capsulatum, C. immitis, C. posadasii</italic>, and <italic>B. dermatitidis</italic>, as expected, since all the organisms are classified in the Onygenales order (Sharpton et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). There are five putative transmembrane ferric reductases either for <italic>Pb</italic>01 or for <italic>Pb</italic>18. Moreover these fungi present one glutathione-dependent ferric reductase homolog, whose activity has been described (Zarnowski and Woods, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. transmembrane ferric reductases present domains described for homologs from other pathogenic fungi, such as FRD, NAD and FAD-binding domains, bis-heme motif and transmembrane domains (Almeida et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Saikia et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The expression of these ferric reductases seems not to be iron-dependent, since the differences observed between the iron-replete and the iron-deprived conditions were subtle. Similar results were observed for <italic>C. neoformans</italic>, in which subtle differences in ferric reductases expression were observed in presence or absence of iron (Saikia et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). However, an increase in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. ferric reductase expression has been observed in the presence of human blood and plasma (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). This apparent inconsistency could be explained if the ferric reductase expression would be activated in the presence of human iron sources, such as transferrin, an iron source that could be used by <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p><sup>59</sup>Fe uptake assays demonstrated that <italic>Pb</italic>18 reduce and uptake iron in scarcity of this metal. On the other hand, <italic>Pb</italic>01 express an apparently inefficient RIA system, since <sup>59</sup>Fe uptake in the absence of ascorbic acid was low in any culture condition used in this work although TTC assay indicates this strain does exhibit cell surface ferric reductase activity. It has been proposed that <italic>A. nidulans</italic> also lack an efficient RIA pathway, because a siderophore-deficient strain is not able to utilize Fe<sup>3+</sup> (Eisendle et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Perhaps the main route to acquire iron in these fungi is the siderophore uptake, which has been demonstrated to be efficient either in <italic>A. nidulans</italic> (Eisendle et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>) or in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. (Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p><italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. MCOs (PAAG_06004 and PADG_05994), with a low Fet3 identity, were identified in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. genome database. To confirm if these proteins could act as ferroxidases and if the MCO domain face or not the cytoplasm, the proteins should be isolated, characterized, and cellular localized, that is our focus in future studies. What we hypothesize at this moment is that an MCO does not play a significant role in RIA pathway in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp., since in previous work (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Costa et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Parente et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), as well as in this work, ferroxidase regulation in low-iron conditions was not observed. Moreover, this pathway appears to be unusual, since it does not include an Ftr1 homolog, common to several fungi (Stearman et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Ziegler et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Similarly, a homology search in <italic>A. nidulans</italic> genome database failed to identify Fet3 and Ftr1 homologs (Eisendle et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>).</p><p>We note, however, that <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. express Zrts homologs that are induced in iron- (this work) or zinc-deprivation (Parente et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In plants and mammals, it has been demonstrated that ZIP (Zrt/Irt-like Proteins) family of membrane transporters is able to transport not only zinc, but also iron (Zhao et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Milner et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Additionally, it has been observed that <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. Zrts present more than one possible metal-binding domain (HXHXHXH) (Zhao and Eide, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>) in the sequence (Silva et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), suggesting that these domains could be responsible for zinc and iron binding. These facts corroborate the hypothesis that <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> Zrts are able to transport both iron and zinc. Moreover, it has been demonstrated that Zrt expression increases in yeast cells recovered from liver of infected mice and in presence of human plasma (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). These data suggest that the permease is regulated in iron-limited conditions either <italic>in vitro</italic> or <italic>in vivo</italic> and in presence of human iron sources, such as transferrin. Maybe the iron-regulation in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. impacts most strongly on the permeases and not on the ferric reductases.</p><p>A whole transcriptome sequencing strategy also revealed that both a siderophore transporter and the ornithine, a hydroxamate precursor (Eisendle et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>), biosynthesis are up-regulated, indicating that <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. utilize the siderophore uptake pathway during iron scarcity, as previously demonstrated (Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). At the same time, expression of Zrts is also up-regulated, indicating that the fungus use more than one iron uptake strategy to acquire this metal when in iron scarcity. On the other hand, aerobic respiration and iron-dependent molecule synthesis pathways seems to be down-regulated, such as the synthesis of iron-sulfur proteins and heme precursors. It has been observed that tricarboxylic acid cycle and electron transport chain proteins decreased in abundance under iron limiting conditions (Parente et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). It could occur because iron is used as prosthetic group in a plenty of energy metabolism pathways (Kosman, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>The RIA pathway in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. appears constitutive in that ferric reductase expression is relatively insensitive to type or concentration of iron source. In contrast, in iron-deprived condition (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>), transcripts related to siderophore uptake and biosynthesis of extracellular siderophores (coprogen B) are up-regulated as observed in this work and in others previously published (Parente et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Transcripts related to iron and zinc permeases are also up-regulated in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. This indicates that the fungus can use both RIA and siderophore uptake pathways in iron limited condition. <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. also may use hemoglobin receptors to acquire this host iron source; those receptors are activated preferentially in presence of hemoglobin instead of iron deprivation (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In addition, in presence of transferrin (abundant in human plasma) and hemoglobin (abundant in human blood), the transcription of ferric reductases is up-regulated (Bail&#x000e3;o et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). These data indicate that both RIA and siderophore uptake pathways could function under iron deprivation.</p><p>The study of iron metabolism is important to reveal novel molecules that contribute to iron uptake, an essential micronutrient for almost all organisms (Johnson, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). These proteins could function as accessible targets for drugs to block iron uptake, what could impair the pathogen's life. Moreover, iron permeases might also be exploited as vaccine targets or as route for antifungal internalization (Kronstad et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Then, <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. proteins involved with iron uptake could be used as vaccine or drug targets or as drug internalization route to inhibit the proliferation of the pathogen.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank the financial support from Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico (CNPq), Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Ensino Superior (CAPES), Financiadora de Estudos e Projetos (FINEP) and Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Apoio &#x000e0; Pesquisa do Estado de Goi&#x000e1;s (FAPEG). EB, PL, and MS received scholarships from CAPES.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2015.00821">http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2015.00821</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Table1.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><media xlink:href="Table2.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3"><media xlink:href="Image1.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4"><media xlink:href="Image2.PDF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM5"><media xlink:href="Image3.PDF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM6"><media xlink:href="Image4.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hube</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title><italic>Candida albicans</italic> iron acquisition within the host</article-title>. <source>FEMS Yeast Res.</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1000</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1012</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1567-1364.2009.00570.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19788558?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19788558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amich</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schafferer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krappmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Regulation of sulphur assimilation is essential for virulence and affects iron homeostasis of the human-pathogenic mould <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e1003573</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003573</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24009505?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24009505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andreini</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertini</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavallaro</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Decaria</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A simple protocol for the comparative analysis of the structure and occurrence of biochemical pathways across superkingdoms</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Inf. Model</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>730</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>738</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ci100392q</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21388232?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21388232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>Y. U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title><italic>Candida albicans</italic> ferric reductases are differentially regulated in response to distinct forms of iron limitation by the Rim101 and CBF transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot. Cell</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1179</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/EC.00108-08</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18503007?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18503007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rondon Caixeta Bonfim</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Castro</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>de F&#x000e1;tima da Silva</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes Giannini</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012b</year>). <article-title>Comparative transcriptome analysis of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> during <italic>in vitro</italic> adhesion to type I collagen and fibronectin: identification of potential adhesins</article-title>. <source>Res. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>163</volume>, <fpage>182</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resmic.2012.01.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22306611?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22306611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrank</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutra</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molinari-Madlum</surname><given-names>E. E. W. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felipe</surname><given-names>M. S. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Differential gene expression by <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> in host interaction conditions: representational difference analysis identifies candidate genes associated with fungal pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Microbes. Infect.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>2686</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2697</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micinf.2006.07.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16962356?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16962356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrank</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutra</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felipe</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The transcriptional profile of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> yeast cells is influenced by human plasma</article-title>. <source>FEMS Immunol. Med. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micinf.2006.07.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17608708?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17608708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>E. F. L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>K. P. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kmetzsch</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012a</year>). <article-title>Metal acquisition and homeostasis in fungi</article-title>. <source>Curr. Fungal. Infect. Rep.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>266</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12281-012-0108-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>E. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pigosso</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Castro</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Hemoglobin uptake by <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp. is receptor-mediated</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl. Trop Dis.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e2856</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002856</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24831516?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24831516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bocca</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shikanai-Yasuda</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares Felipe</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Paracoccidioidomycosis: eco-epidemiology, taxonomy and clinical and therapeutic issues</article-title>. <source>Future Microbiol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1191</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fmb.13.68</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24020744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24020744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bookout</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangelsdorf</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pesola</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>High-throughput real-time quantitative reverse transcription PCR</article-title>. <source>Curr. Protoc. Mol. Biol</source>. Chapter 15, Unit 15 18. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/0471142727.mb1508s73</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18265376?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18265376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrero</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni&#x000f1;o-Vega</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>New <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> isolate reveals unexpected genomic variability in this human pathogen</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet. Biol.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>612</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2008.02.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18364259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18364259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meirelles</surname><given-names>G. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendonca</surname><given-names>Y. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dantas</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Transcriptome profiling of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> yeast-phase cells recovered from infected mice brings new insights into fungal response upon host interaction</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>153</volume>, <fpage>4194</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4207</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.2007/009332-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18048933?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18048933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eide</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis-Kaplan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sipe</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Regulation of iron uptake in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. The ferrireductase and Fe(II) transporter are regulated independently</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>267</volume>, <fpage>20774</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20781</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1400393?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1400393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisendle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberegger</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zadra</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The siderophore system is essential for viability of <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic>: functional analysis of two genes encoding l-ornithine N 5-monooxygenase (sidA) and a non-ribosomal peptide synthetase (sidC)</article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>375</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03586.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12828635?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12828635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Microevolution during serial mouse passage demonstrates FRE3 as a virulence adaptation gene in <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic></article-title>. <source>MBio</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>e00941</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e00914</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00941-14</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24692633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24692633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Iron and siderophores in fungal-host interactions</article-title>. <source>Mycol. Res.</source>
<volume>112</volume>, <fpage>170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>183</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mycres.2007.11.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18280720?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18280720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilaire</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesuisse</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dancis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Iron acquisition from transferrin by <italic>Candida albicans</italic> depends on the reductive pathway</article-title>. <source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>5482</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5492</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.73.9.5482-5492.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16113264?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16113264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of iron uptake in fungi</article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>1185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1197</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03368.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12603727?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12603727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Multicopper oxidases: a workshop on copper coordination chemistry, electron transfer, and metallophysiology</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Inorg. Chem.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00775-009-0590-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19816718?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19816718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Iron metabolism in aerobes: managing ferric iron hydrolysis and ferrous iron autoxidation</article-title>. <source>Coord. Chem. Rev.</source>
<volume>257</volume>, <fpage>210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>217</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2012.06.030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23264695?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23264695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kronstad</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadieux</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Pathogenic yeasts deploy cell surface receptors to acquire iron in vertebrate hosts</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e1003498</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003498</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24009498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24009498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwok</surname><given-names>E. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Severance</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Evidence for iron channeling in the Fet3p-Ftr1p high-affinity iron uptake complex in the yeast plasma membrane</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>6317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6327</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi052173c</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16700543?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16700543</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>R25</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2009-10-3-r25</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19261174?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19261174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackshields</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chenna</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGettigan</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McWilliam</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2947</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2948</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm404</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17846036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17846036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>P. D. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casaletti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes Gda</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Transcriptional and proteomic responses to carbon starvation in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl. Trop Dis.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e2855</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002855</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24811072?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24811072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Paracoccidioidomycosis: the dimension of the problem of a neglected disease</article-title>. <source>Rev. Soc. Bras. Med. Trop.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>480</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0037-86822010000400034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20802960?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20802960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seamon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Craft</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochian</surname><given-names>L. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Transport properties of members of the ZIP family in plants and their role in Zn and Mn homeostasis</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>381</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ers315</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23264639?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23264639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogur</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>St. John</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957</year>). <article-title>Tetrazolium overlay technique for population studies of respiration deficiency in yeast</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>125</volume>, <fpage>928</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>929</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 13421693?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13421693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>TreeView: an application to display phylogenetic trees on personal computers</article-title>. <source>Comput. Appl. Biosci.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>358</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8902363?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8902363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricart</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Proteomic analysis reveals that iron availability alters the metabolic status of the pathogenic fungus <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e22810</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022810</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21829521?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Rezende</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Castro</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A proteomic view of the response of <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> yeast cells to zinc deprivation</article-title>. <source>Fungal Biol.</source>
<volume>117</volume>, <fpage>399</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>410</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.funbio.2013.04.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23809650?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23809650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Restrepo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Growth of <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> yeast phase in a chemically defined culture medium</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>281</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 7229010?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7229010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saikia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronstad</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Role of ferric reductases in iron acquisition and virulence in the fungal pathogen <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>850</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01357-13</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24478097?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24478097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sali</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Potterton</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Vlijmen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of comparative protein modeling by MODELLER</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>318</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>326</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prot.340230306</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8710825?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8710825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>San-Blas</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni&#x000f1;o-Vega</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iturriaga</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title><italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> and paracoccidioidomycosis: molecular approaches to morphogenesis, diagnosis, epidemiology, taxonomy and genetics</article-title>. <source>Med. Mycol.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>242</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/mmy.40.3.225.242</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12146752?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12146752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharpton</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stajich</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rounsley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wortman</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordar</surname><given-names>V. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Comparative genomic analyses of the human fungal pathogens <italic>Coccidioides</italic> and their relatives</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1722</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1731</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.087551.108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19717792?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19717792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrank</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>E. F. L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Staats</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The homeostasis of iron, copper, and zinc in <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis, Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> var. <italic>grubii</italic>, and <italic>Cryptococcus gattii</italic>: a comparative analysis</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<issue>49</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2011.00049</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21833306?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21833306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>E. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lechner</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Hydroxamate production as a high affinity iron acquisition mechanism in <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> spp</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e105805</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105805</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25157575?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25157575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sirim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pleiss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The Laccase Engineering Database: a classification and analysis system for laccases and related multicopper oxidases</article-title>. <source>Database (Oxford)</source>
<fpage>2011</fpage>:<lpage>bar006</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/database/bar006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21498547?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21498547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stearman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Iwai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klausner</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dancis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>A permease-oxidase complex involved in high-affinity iron uptake in yeast</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>271</volume>, <fpage>1552</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1557</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8599111?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8599111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Theodoro</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>F. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagagli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title><italic>Paracoccidioides lutzii</italic> sp. nov.: biological and clinical implications</article-title>. <source>Med. Mycol.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/13693786.2013.794311</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23768243?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23768243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trist&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Assun&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Ldo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dos Santos</surname><given-names>L. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva-Bail&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Predicting copper-, iron-, and zinc-binding proteins in pathogenic species of the <italic>Paracoccidioides</italic> genus</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<issue>761</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2014.00761</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25620964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25620964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>DEGseq: an R package for identifying differentially expressed genes from RNA-seq data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp612</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19855105?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19855105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Novel role of the <italic>Candida albicans</italic> ferric reductase gene CFL1 in iron acquisition, oxidative stress tolerance, morphogenesis and virulence</article-title>. <source>Res. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>165</volume>, <fpage>252</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>261</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resmic.2014.03.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24631590?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24631590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klebba</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Philpott</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The role of the FRE family of plasma membrane reductases in the uptake of siderophore-iron in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>, <fpage>10218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10223</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M010065200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11120744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11120744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zarnowski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Glutathione-dependent extracellular ferric reductase activities in dimorphic zoopathogenic fungi</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>151</volume>, <fpage>2233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2240</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.27918-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16000713?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16000713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eide</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The yeast <italic>ZRT1</italic> gene encodes the zinc transporter protein of a high-affinity uptake system induced by zinc limitation</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>2454</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2458</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8637895?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8637895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Enns</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knutson</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>ZRT/IRT-like protein 14 (ZIP14) promotes the cellular assimilation of iron from transferrin</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>285</volume>, <fpage>32141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32150</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.143248</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20682781?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20682781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terzulli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaur</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Functional characterization of the ferroxidase, permease high-affinity iron transport complex from <italic>Candida albicans</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>485</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2011.07704.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21645130?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21645130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>