<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4769537</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26921172</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2483</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-2483-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Influenza H3N2 infection of the collaborative cross founder strains reveals highly divergent host responses and identifies a unique phenotype in CAST/EiJ mice</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leist</surname><given-names>Sarah R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pilzner</surname><given-names>Carolin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van den Brand</surname><given-names>Judith M.A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dengler</surname><given-names>Leonie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Geffers</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuiken</surname><given-names>Thijs</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balling</surname><given-names>Rudi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Kollmus</surname><given-names>Heike</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Schughart</surname><given-names>Klaus</given-names></name><address><email>kls@helmholtz-hzi.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Infection Genetics, Helmholtz Centre for Infection Research, Braunschweig and University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Inhoffenstr.7, D-38124 Braunschweig, Hannover Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Viroscience, Erasmus Medical Center, Rotterdam, Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Genome Analytics, Helmholtz Centre for Infection Research, Braunschweig, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Luxembourg Centre for Systems Biomedicine (LCSB), University of Luxembourg, Esch-sur-Alzette, Luxembourg </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>University of Tennessee Health Science Center, Memphis, TN USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>143</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Leist et al. 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Influenza A virus is a zoonotic pathogen that poses a major threat to human and animal health. The severe course of influenza infection is not only influenced by viral virulence factors but also by individual differences in the host response. To determine the extent to which the genetic background can modulate severity of an infection, we studied the host responses to influenza infections in the eight genetically highly diverse Collaborative Cross (CC) founder mouse strains.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We observed highly divergent host responses between the CC founder strains with respect to survival, body weight loss, hematological parameters in the blood, relative lung weight and viral load. Mouse strain was the main factor with highest effect size on body weight loss after infection, demonstrating that this phenotype was highly heritable. Sex represented another significant main effect, although it was less strong. Analysis of survival rates and mean time to death suggested three groups of susceptibility phenotypes: highly susceptible (A/J, CAST/EiJ, WSB/EiJ), intermediate susceptible (C57BL/6J, 129S1/SvImJ, NOD/ShiLtJ) and highly resistant strains (NZO/HlLtJ, PWK/PhJ). These three susceptibility groups were significantly different with respect to death/survival counts. Viral load was significantly different between susceptible and resistant strains but not between intermediate and highly susceptible strains. CAST/EiJ mice showed a unique phenotype. Despite high viral loads in their lungs, CAST/EiJ mice exhibited low counts of infiltrating granulocytes and showed increased numbers of macrophages in the lung. Histological studies of infected lungs and transcriptome analyses of peripheral blood cells and lungs confirmed an abnormal response in the leukocyte recruitment in CAST/EiJ mice.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The eight CC founder strains exhibited a large diversity in their response to influenza infections. Therefore, the CC will represent an ideal mouse genetic reference population to study the influence of genetic variation on the susceptibility and resistance to influenza infections which will be important to understand individual variations of disease severity in humans. The unique phenotype combination in the CAST/EiJ strain resembles human leukocyte adhesion deficiency and may thus represent a new mouse model to understand this and related abnormal immune responses to infections in humans.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12864-016-2483-y) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Influenza susceptibility</kwd><kwd>Collaborative cross</kwd><kwd>Phenotyping</kwd><kwd>Mouse model</kwd><kwd>Immune response</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001656</institution-id><institution>Helmholtz Association</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>HZI Infection and Immunity</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Schughart</surname><given-names>Klaus</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>BMBF Germany</institution></funding-source><award-id>FluResearchNet (No. 01KI07137)</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Schughart</surname><given-names>Klaus</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Gesellschaft der Freunde der Tier&#x000e4;rztlichen Hochschule Hannover e.V.</institution></funding-source><award-id>PhD scholarship</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Leist</surname><given-names>Sarah R.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Background</title><p>Every year, about 500,000 people die world-wide from influenza virus infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In recent history, the emergence of new influenza subtypes has caused several pandemics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The most severe pandemic in 1918 resulted in about 30&#x02013;50 million deaths worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and a new variant of a seasonal H1N1 virus, pH1N1, caused a world-wide pandemic in 2009 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The course and outcome of an infection is determined by pathogen virulence, environmental and host factors. Genetic diversity of the host has been found as an important factor that strongly influences the host response and severity to influenza infections in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Environmental and genetic factors can be well controlled in experimental animal models. It has been shown in mouse models that the genetic make-up of the host strongly influences the disease outcome after influenza infections (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]). Subsequently, several genes have been described also in humans that contribute to disease severity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p>Mouse genetic reference populations (GRPs) have become an important experimental system that allows investigating the influence of genetic variation on human diseases (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In addition, GRPs have been used to study the influence of genetic variation on the host response to infectious pathogens (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The Collaborative Cross (CC) is a recently created population that has been generated from eight inbred mouse strains, referred to as founder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The addition of three wild-derived strains (CAST/EiJ, PWK/PhJ and WSB/EiJ) strongly enhanced the genetic diversity of the CC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Several studies in not fully inbred CC strains (pre-CC strains) and CC strains themselves led to the identification of quantitative trait loci (QTLs) influencing human diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. More recently, CC F1 hybrids have been identified that exhibited severe hemorrhagic fever, similar to humans, after infection with Ebola virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Another CC strain has been shown to represent a new model for spontaneous colitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p><p>Here, we investigated the pathology, disease severity and the host response in the eight CC founder strains to H3N2 influenza A virus infections. We observed a broad range of phenotypic outcomes for many pathological and molecular parameters. Also, we found a specific defect in highly susceptible CAST/EiJ mice that resembled leukocyte recruitment deficiency in humans.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Three different groups of susceptibility phenotypes are observed after infection of CC founder strains with H3N2 virus</title><p>Eight to twelve weeks old female and male mice of the eight founder strains were infected intra-nasally with a dose of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU of the mouse-adapted influenza virus subtype H3N2 (A/HK/01/68). Survival rates of infected mice were monitored for a period of 14&#x000a0;days (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Our results suggest three different susceptibility groups based on survival rates and mean time to death: Highly susceptible, intermediate susceptible and highly resistant strains. Pair-wise chi-square tests between the three groups revealed significant differences for the death/survival counts (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). The strains A/J, CAST/EiJ and WSB/EiJ belonged to the highly susceptible group in which all infected mice died. NZO/HlLtJ and PWK/PhJ were found to be highly resistant; all infected mice survived the infection. Three strains, C57BL/6J, 129S1/SvImJ and NOD/ShiLtJ, showed intermediate susceptibility with survival rates ranging from 10&#x000a0;% to 90&#x000a0;%. No significant differences were observed in the survival curves of male and female mice for all strains except for NOD/ShiLtJ, whereby females were more susceptible than males. At an increased infection dose of 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> FFU all mice from highly and intermediate susceptible strains (A/J, C57BL/6J, 129S1/SvImJ, NOD/ShiLtJ, CAST/EiJ and WSB/EiJ) succumbed to the infection (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In contrast, the two highly resistant strains (NZO/HlLtJ and PWK/PhJ) were also resistant to infections with higher infection doses of 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> FFU and 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> FFU (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). For all strains, except the highly resistant ones, survival rates in females and males at the lower dose were significantly higher than survival rates at higher doses (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Survival rates of the eight CC founder strains after infection with different doses of influenza A H3N2 virus infection. Eight to twelve weeks old female and male mice of the CC founder strains were infected intra-nasally with 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> (red and blue), 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> (orange and green) and 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> FFU (magenta and black) of the mouse-adapted influenza H3N2 virus (A/HK/01/68). Survival rates were monitored for 14&#x000a0;days p.i.. Mice that exhibited a weight loss of more than 30&#x000a0;% relative to their starting weight were euthanized and scored as dead. Significant sex-specific differences in survival curves were observed exclusively in NOD/ShiLtJ mice after infection with 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU (**: p-value &#x0003c; 0.01, using log rank test). Colors for the CC founder strains have been chosen according to the CC strain RGB color code displayed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://csbio.unc.edu/CCstatus/index.py">http://csbio.unc.edu/CCstatus/index.py</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p>Next, we analyzed mean time to death (MTTD) to investigate how rapidly susceptible mice succumbed to infection. At an infection dose of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU, the highly susceptible strains exhibited the lowest MTTD. The MTTD was 7 and 9&#x000a0;days p.i. whereas the intermediate susceptible strains died at day 11 to 14 p.i. (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). At higher infection dose (2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> FFU) the highly susceptible (day 5 to 6) and the intermediate susceptible group (day 7 to 8) had a lower MTTD (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). When comparing male and female mice, a significant difference of MTTD was found for NOD/ShiLtJ and WSB/EiJ mice at the low virus dose whereas at the high infection dose, only C57BL/6J mice exhibited a sex-dependent difference in MTTD (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Sex-specific differences in mean time to death at different doses of influenza A H3N2 virus infection in C57BL/6J, NOD/ShiLtJ and WSB/EiJ. The same data set and color code as in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> was used to analyze mean time to death (MTTD) of the strains (clear bars: female; dashed bars: male mice). Changes in MTTD were calculated for 14&#x000a0;days p.i., survival was scored as an MTTD value of 15. Significant sex-specific differences were calculated for infection with 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU (<bold>a</bold>) and 2x10<sup>3</sup> FFU (<bold>b</bold>). NOD/ShiLtJ and WSB/EiJ exhibited significant sex-specific differences in infections with 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU and C57BL/6J in infections with 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> FFU. The dashed line marks the end of experiment. Significances were calculated using Mann Whitney <italic>U</italic> test and are marked by stars (*: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.1; **: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Infection of CC founder strains leads to highly variable body weight changes</title><p>In a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], body weight changes in CC mice were recorded daily until day 4 after infection with H1N1 (A/PR/8/34 (PR8)) virus. In our studies, we aimed to provide a more complete phenotype description after H3N2 infection that covers all phases of the host response (innate, adaptive and recovery). Therefore, we measured body weight changes at each day after infection until recovery of body weight after 14&#x000a0;days p.i.. We also included both sexes in our study. The analysis of body weight changes over 14&#x000a0;days confirmed a large phenotypic diversity between susceptible and resistant strains and also within susceptible and resistant groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). In addition, the resistant strains were infected with a dose of 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> FFU. In this case, NZO/HlLtJ mice showed a drop in body weight (10&#x000a0;%) at day 2 which stayed low until day 14 after infection whereas PWK/PhJ showed higher body weight loss (10-20&#x000a0;%) at early days after infection and rapidly regained weight from day 4 on (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Dose-dependent differences in body weight changes after influenza A H3N2 virus infection. The same data set and color code as in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> was used. Changes in body weight were monitored for 14&#x000a0;days p.i.. Significant sex-specific differences were observed in all CC founder strains and were calculated by Mann Whitney <italic>U</italic> test (*: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.1; **: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; ***: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; black asterisk: 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU; grey asterisk: 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> FFU; blue asterisk: 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> FFU)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p>A multi-factorial analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed to investigate variation of body weight change as response to infection for the factors strains, sex and days. The analysis was limited to days 1 to 7 p.i. because for some strains (A/J, CAST/EiJ, and WSB/EiJ), more than 60&#x000a0;% of infected mice died by day 8. Thus, the surviving mice were not any more representative for the group. ANOVA (model: body weight loss&#x02009;~&#x02009;strain * sex * day and deleting the non-significant interaction strain:day:sex) revealed that all main effects (strain, sex and day) and all pair-wise interactions were significant (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2). Subsequent Tukey-HSD post-hoc test was used to determine significance of pairs (strain by day p.i.; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Table S3). The changes in body weight were most pronounced on day 7 p.i.. Strains A/J, CAST/EiJ, and WSB/EiJ exhibited the highest loss of body weight whereas NZO/HlLtJ was least affected. The broad-sense heritability was determined for each day separately and ranged from 0.28 to 0.65 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) indicating high heritability of this trait. The sex-effect (using the optimized AVOVA model) was significant from days 3 to 7 p.i. but with a lower effect size (maximum of 8&#x000a0;%, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>ANOVA-Broad-sense heritability and sex effect per day</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Days p.i.</th><th>Heritability H<sup>2</sup>
</th><th>Sex effect</th><th>
<italic>P</italic>-value sex effect</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td char="." align="char">day1</td><td align="left">0.28</td><td align="left">ns</td><td align="left">ns</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">day2</td><td align="left">0.39</td><td align="left">ns</td><td align="left">ns</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">day3</td><td align="left">0.28</td><td align="left">0.08</td><td align="left">1.91e-05</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">day4</td><td align="left">0.45</td><td align="left">0.08</td><td align="left">6.38e-07</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">day5</td><td align="left">0.58</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">3.03e-06</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">day6</td><td align="left">0.59</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">4.13e-07</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">day7</td><td align="left">0.65</td><td align="left">0.04</td><td align="left">2.9e-05</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>ns:</italic> not significant, H<sup>2</sup> broadsense heritability, Sex effect sum of squares for sex divided by total sum of squares using two-way ANOVA model: BWL&#x02009;~&#x02009;strain * sex for each day separately</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Comparisons for all strains over 14&#x000a0;days p.i. (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) confirmed that female mice from the highly and intermediate susceptible group exhibited a higher weight loss than male mice at the lower infection dose of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). For the resistant strains NZO/HlLtJ and PWK/PhJ no differences between sexes were observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). In contrast, at the higher infection dose (2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> FFU) no significant differences were observed between males and females except for some single days for C57BL/6J on day 3 and 4, PWK/PhJ on days 2, 11, 12 and 14 and WSB/EiJ on day 2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Male mice generally showed less severe changes in body weight than females. Only for the PWK/PhJ strain female mice exhibited significantly less body weight loss than male mice. However, this was only observed late after infection for days 11, 12 and 14.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Selection of infection dose and gender for further experiments</title><p>For all following studies, we decided to perform infections with a dose of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU because at this dose, variation between the founder strains was highest for survival, MTTD and body weight changes. Also, we limited the following analyses to female mice. Females were used extensively in our and other laboratories studies thus allowing better comparability to existing data than males. In addition, the sex effect was relatively small (ANOVA) compared to the strain effect. Also, in this study, we mainly focused on effects caused by genetic variation which is represented by the strain effect (heritability). Therefore, the additional information gained by including males would have been rather limited in our studies and, with respect to the 3R principle, was omitted.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Increase in relative lung weight differs among CC founder strains</title><p>The relative lung weight (wet lung weight relative to body weight on day of preparation) was investigated at different days after infection as measurement for the degree of immune cell infiltration and fluid influx into the lung (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). For highly susceptible strains the relative lung weight increased significantly on day 5 p.i.. Lung weight increased for intermediate susceptible strains and reached a peak at day 8 p.i.. Resistant strains showed only a slight increase in relative lung weight on day 5 p.i. and 8 p.i.. To confirm that the increase in relative lung weight was not simply due to the loss in body weight at the respective days p.i., we also calculated relative lung weight for the different days p.i. with reference to the starting body weight. Also in this case, we still observed a significant increase in relative lung weight in susceptible strains and no significant increase in the two resistant strains (data not shown).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Increase in relative lung weight after influenza A H3N2 infection. Eight to twelve weeks old female mice of the eight CC founder strains were infected intra-nasally with 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU of the mouse-adapted influenza H3N2 virus (A/HK/01/68). Lung weight was determined on day 3, 5, 8, 18 and 30 p.i. and for mock infected animals on day 3 post PBS treatment. CC founder strains showed comparable increase in relative lung weight up to 2&#x000a0;% except for the highly resistant NZO/HlLtJ and PWK/PhJ. Each data point represents the measurement of one animal. Additionally, the mean and the standard error of the mean are shown for each time point and strain</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Kinetics of viral load in lungs revealed large differences between resistant and susceptible CC founder strains</title><p>To investigate if the severity of infection was related to viral replication in the lungs of mice, we determined viral load at different time points (day 3, 5 and 8) post infection. All highly and intermediate susceptible strains (A/J, CAST/EiJ, WSB/EiJ, C57BL/6J, 129S1/SvlmJ, NOD/ShiLtJ) showed similar high viral loads of about 10<sup>5</sup> FFU at all time points analyzed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). In contrast, the highly resistant strains NZO/HlLtJ and PWK/PhJ had much lower viral titers in the lung (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). PWK/PhJ exhibited lowest viral loads of all strains (10<sup>3</sup> FFU/lung) and no increase between day 3 and 5 whereas NZO/HlLtJ mice showed an increase in viral load from day 3 to day 5 p.i. (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Both strains had cleared the virus from their lungs by day 8 p.i.. Viral load was significantly different on day 3 and day 5 p.i. between susceptible and resistant mice but not different between highly and intermediate susceptible mice (ANOVA, model: lg.viral.ld&#x02009;~&#x02009;suscept; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Table S4 and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Table S5).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Constant high viral load in highly and intermediate susceptible and viral clearance in resistant strains. Eight to twelve weeks old female mice of the eight CC founder strains were infected intra-nasally with 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU of influenza H3N2 virus. Lung samples were taken for mock infected animals on day 3 post treatment and on day 3, 5, and 8 p.i.. Lungs of mice of all CC founder strains showed comparable high viral loads at 10<sup>5</sup> FFU/lung from day 3 until day 5 p.i.. NZO/HlLtJ and PWK/PhJ had lower viral loads and cleared virus until day 8 p.i.. Each data point represents the measurement of one animal; mean and standard error of the mean are shown for each time point and strain</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Each CC founder strain exhibits a characteristic leukocyte profile in peripheral blood</title><p>The changes in cellular composition of the peripheral blood after infection was monitored via VetScan hematological assay (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). After infection, the percentage of lymphocytes in all strains decreased, whereby the percentage of granulocytes increased. Only the highly resistant strains NZO/HlLtJ and PWK/PhJ showed nearly constant levels of both cell types. The percentage of monocytes was similar for all strains. Comparison between the eight founder strains revealed a high percentage of granulocytes in A/J, 129S1/SvImJ, NOD/ShiLtJ and WSB/EiJ on day 3 and 5 after infection, resulting in a ratio of about 35&#x000a0;% of the leukocytes. C57BL/6J, NZO/HlLtJ, CAST/EiJ and PWK/PhJ exhibited low levels of granulocytes at day 3, 5 and 8 after infection (20&#x000a0;% or below). CAST/EiJ was the only susceptible strain showing a decrease from day 3 to day 5. Notably, granulocyte amounts in mock infected NOD/ShiLtJ mice were at 18&#x000a0;% of total WBCs in mock infection. In conclusion, CAST/EiJ, although carrying high viral loads in the lung, exhibited only very low granulocyte counts in the periphery.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Mice of each founder strain showed a characteristic leukocyte profile in peripheral blood. Blood samples were taken from the same animals used for viral load analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) and analyzed regarding granulocyte (green), lymphocyte (red) and monocyte (blue) amounts displayed as percentage of white blood cells (WBCs)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Correlation analysis of phenotypic traits</title><p>In our study, we measured changes of several phenotypic traits (body weight, hematology, relative lung weight, viral load) in single mice after infection. This allowed us to correlate these different traits within each subset. Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref> shows the correlation analysis of body weight loss, viral load and percentages of cell populations in the peripheral blood for setup 2 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref> illustrates the correlation between body weight loss, relative lung weight and percentages of cell populations in the peripheral blood for setup 3 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The analysis showed a strong negative correlation (coefficients of&#x000a0;&#x02013;0.98 and&#x000a0;&#x02013;0.97) between percentages of lymphocytes and granulocytes for both subsets which suggests that the main change in peripheral blood cell composition was mainly due to an increase in granulocytes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">b</xref>). Furthermore, we found a strong negative correlation (coefficient of &#x02212;0.87) between body weight loss and relative lung weight which suggests that the loss in body weight may serve as a surrogate for pathological changes in the lung (edema and immune cell infiltrates) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>). Body weight loss and percentage of lymphocytes appeared only weakly correlated with viral load (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">b</xref>). Similarly, body weight loss and percentage of lymphocytes were only moderately or weekly correlated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">b</xref>).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Correlation analysis of phenotypic traits. Correlation analysis of phenotypic traits from setup 2 (<bold>a</bold>) and setup 3 (<bold>b</bold>). The diagonal represents the histogram of the measured values from a given trait, the bottom left panel represents scatter plots of pairs of phenotypic measurements, the top right panel shows correlation coefficients and p-values from a linear regression analysis. Values for days 3, 5, 8 and 18 p.i. (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;41, 47, 38, and 1, respectively) were combined. BW: percent body weight, re_lung_wght: relative lung weight (in reference to body weight at time of sacrifice), WBC: weight blood cells (10<sup>9</sup> cells per l), lympho_perc: percent lymphocytes (of total white blood cells), mono_perc: percent monocytes (of total white blood cells), granu_perc: percent granulocytes (of total white blood cells), lg.virl.ld: log<sub>2</sub> viral load per lung. n&#x02009;=&#x02009;127 for subset 2, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;173 for subset 3. **: <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c;0.01, ***: <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Experimental setups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Setup</th><th>Body weight</th><th>Viral load</th><th>Hematology</th><th>Relative lung weight</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>+</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>+</td><td/><td>+</td><td>+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Three different experimental setups with combination of different phenotyping parameters were used</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Detailed analysis of unique CAST/EiJ phenotype by flow cytometry</title><p>CAST/EiJ mice were highly susceptible to H3N2 infection and showed a unique combination of high viral load in the lungs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) but low granulocyte counts in the periphery (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Therefore, a more detailed investigation of the CAST/EiJ mice in comparison to two intermediate susceptible mouse strains was performed by flow cytometry of blood and lung cells at day 3 and 5 p.i.. We chose C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvImJ mice for this comparison because 129S1/SvImJ mice exhibited a very strong response whereas C57BL/6J showed an intermediate peripheral response.</p><p>In blood, all three strains had comparable numbers of granulocytes (Ly6G<sup>+</sup>CD11b<sup>+</sup> cells) before infection (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>). At day 3 p.i., the absolute cell numbers of granulocytes increased in all strains, but much less in CAST/EiJ (1.5-fold) compared to C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvImJ mice (5-and 3-fold, respectively) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>). Furthermore, granulocyte counts significantly decreased from day 3 to day 5 in CAST/EiJ (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>) but were similar to day 3 in the other two strains (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>). After infection, monocyte (CD115<sup>+</sup> cells) numbers remained high in CAST/EiJ mice at day 5 p.i., whereas they decreased in the other two strains from day 3 to day 5 p.i. (although not statistically significant) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>). Furthermore, NK cell (NKP46<sup>+</sup> cells) numbers were lower in non-infected and at day 3 p.i. in CAST/EiJ compared to C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvImJ mice and at similar levels in CAST/EiJ mice compared to the other two strains on day 5 p.i. (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>). Also, CAST/EiJ mice exhibited the highest absolute numbers of B cells (CD19<sup>+</sup>) in non-infected animals which strongly decreased after infection (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>). CAST/EiJ mice also had low numbers of T-helper (CD4<sup>+</sup> cells) and cytotoxic cells (CD8<sup>+</sup> cells) compared to C57BL/6&#x000a0;J and 129S1/SvImJ before and after infection (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>). Both T-cell populations diminished significantly in CAST/EiJ mice on day 3. In summary, the numbers of granulocytes in the blood were lower after infection in CAST/EiJ mice compared to the other two strains whereas the number of monocytes stayed high in the blood of CAST/EiJ mice.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Flow cytometry analysis of immune cells in blood and lungs. Blood samples and lungs from infected C57BL/6J (grey bars), CAST/EiJ (green bars) and 129S1/SvImJ (pink bars) mice (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU) were prepared. Cell suspensions were analyzed by flow cytometry on days 0, 3 and 5 p.i.. After excluding dead cells fluorochrome-labeled antibodies were used to differentiate various immune cell populations in blood (<bold>a</bold>) and lungs (<bold>b</bold>): CD4<sup>pos</sup> (T helper cells); CD8<sup>pos</sup> (cytotoxic cells); CD19<sup>pos</sup> (B cells), NKp46<sup>pos</sup> (NK cells), CD11b&#x02009;<sup>pos</sup>&#x02009;Ly6G<sup>pos</sup> (granulocytes), CD115<sup>pos</sup> (monocytes) and F4/80<sup>pos</sup> (macrophages). The number of individual cell populations over time (mean +/&#x02212;SEM) was determined. For each measurement lungs and blood samples from individual animals were used. Data from two independent experiments were combined (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;6 per time point). Data of different time points were analyzed for statistically significant differences using non-parametric Mann&#x02013;Whitney-<italic>U</italic>-test (*: <italic>p</italic>-value &#x02264;&#x000a0;0.05; **: <italic>p</italic>-value &#x02264;&#x000a0;0.01)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p><p>The most remarkable difference that we observed in flow cytometry analysis of the lungs from infected CAST/EiJ mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8b</xref>) was the very low number of all investigated immune cell populations compared to C57BL/6&#x000a0;J and 129S1/SvImJ mice: granulocytes (Ly6G<sup>+</sup> cells), dendritic cells (CD11c<sup>+</sup>cells), T cells (CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> cells), and macrophages (F4/80<sup>+</sup> cells). Granulocytes in CAST/EiJ mice increased by 4-fold from day 0 to 3 p.i. with no further increase from day 3 to 5 p.i.. In contrast, granulocyte numbers in the lungs of 129S1/SvImJ and C57BL/6&#x000a0;J increased considerably from day 3 to day 5 p.i. and were 30-times higher on day 5 p.i. compared to CAST/EiJ. The number of macrophages was generally higher in 129S1/SvImJ and C57BL/6&#x000a0;J lungs compared to CAST/EiJ mice. However, the increase in macrophage numbers was much higher in CAST/EiJ (25-fold from day 0 to day 5) in comparison to 129S1/SvImJ and C57BL/6&#x000a0;J lungs (4-and 8-fold, respectively). The amount of dendritic cells (CD11c<sup>+</sup>) decreased similarly in all three strains after infection. CD4<sup>+</sup> (T helper) cells as well as CD8<sup>+</sup> (cytotoxic T) cells decreased until day 3 p.i. and then significantly increased until day 5 p.i. in all three strains. In summary, CAST/EiJ mice exhibited in general much lower numbers of immune cells in the lungs before and after infection. After infection, granulocyte numbers increased much less in CAST/EiJ lungs compared to the other two strains whereas the relative increase in macrophages was higher in CAST/EiJ.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Histopathological and immunohistochemical studies of lungs revealed differences in lung pathology of CAST/EiJ mice in comparison to C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvImJ</title><p>We investigated the lungs of CAST/EiJ mice in comparison to C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvImJ mice by histopathology and immunohistochemistry at different days after infection. C57BL/6J, 129S1/SvImJ and CAST/EiJ mice developed a multifocal mild to severe necrotizing and/or granulocytic broncho-interstitial pneumonia (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). In C57BL/6J mice at 3&#x000a0;day p.i., the alveolar septa were mildly thickened with infiltration of few granulocytes and there was mild to moderate necrosis of alveolar, bronchiolar and bronchial epithelial cells. In the alveolar, bronchiolar and bronchial lumina there were moderate inflammatory infiltrates consisting of granulocytes, increased numbers of alveolar macrophages, small amounts of proteinaceous material (edema) and fibrin, and mild hemorrhage (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Peribronchiolarly, peribronchially and perivascularly there was moderate edema and infiltration of moderate numbers of granulocytes and fewer macrophages, lymphocytes and plasma cells. At day 5 p.i., there was an increase in numbers of inflammatory cells in the alveolar lumina and amounts of intraalveolar edema and hemorrhage. Also, there was more alveolar and bronchiolar epithelial necrosis and pneumocyte type II hyperplasia. At day 8 p.i., in addition to previously described changes, there were intra-alveolar hyaline membranes and flattening of bronchiolar and bronchial epithelium. In C57BL/6J mock infected mice no significant lesions were observed. Lungs of 129S1/SvImJ mice showed less granulocyte infiltration and type II pneumocyte hyperplasia in the alveoli, less peribronchiolar, peribronchial, and perivascular infiltration, but slightly more necrosis of alveolar, bronchiolar and bronchial epithelium (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). In lungs of CAST/EiJ mice we observed lower numbers of granulocytes and mild or no peribronchiolar, peribronchial and perivascular infiltrates. There was a trend for fewer intra-alveolar granulocytes and more intra-alveolar macrophages in CAST/EiJ mice compared to C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvImJ mice at day 5 p.i. (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: Table S6). These observations were consistent with the flow cytometry data (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>) showing that CAST/EiJ mice exhibited an increase in granulocytes, macrophages and T lymphocytes whereas the absolute amount of leukocytes remained very low compared to the other susceptible strains. Immunohistochemistry showed that influenza virus antigen was present in respiratory epithelial cells of all strains (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The number of positive alveolar epithelial cells peaked at 5&#x000a0;days p.i. in all strains, with about twice as many positive cells in the CAST/EiJ mice as in C57BL/6J or 129S1/SvImJ mice. The number of positive bronchiolar and bronchial epithelial cells was higher in CAST/EiJ mice (day 3 and 5 p.i.) than in C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvImJ mice. This observation revealed that cellular distribution of virus and number of infected cells was different in CAST/EiJ lungs compared to the other highly susceptible strains although the total viral load was similar (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). This can be explained by the fact that CAST/EiJ lungs are smaller in comparison to the other analyzed strains. Thus, similar total amounts of infectious virus (viral load) in the lung of CAST/EiJ mice would result in a higher number of infected cells. In mock infected mice no virus antigen was detected in any tissue examined.<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Histopathology and immunohistochemistry of C57BL/6J, 129S1/SvImJ and CAST/EiJ lungs five days after H3N2 infection. The lesions in the lungs of the C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvImJ mice were more extensive than in the CAST/EiJ mice (top row, HE 4&#x000d7; objective) with more severe bronchiolar epithelial necrosis and peribronchiolar inflammatory infiltrates (second row, HE 20&#x000d7; objective), more severe inflammatory infiltrates in the alveoli (third row, HE 40&#x000d7; objective) and more cells with presence of virus antigen by immunohistochemistry (bottom row, IHC 40&#x000d7; objective)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Average scoring of lesions by histopathology and of virus antigen expression by immunohistochemistry in lung tissue of C57BL/6&#x000a0;J, 129S1/SvImJ and CAST/EiJ mice infected with H3N2</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th/><th colspan="7">Histopathology score</th><th colspan="2">IHC score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td char="." align="char">Strain</td><td align="left">Day post infection or mock control</td><td align="left">Extent alveolitis/alveolar damage</td><td align="left">Severity of alveolitis</td><td align="left">Severity of alveolar edema</td><td align="left">Presence of interstitial edema</td><td align="left">Presence of type II pneumocyte hyperplasia</td><td align="left">Severity of bronchiolitis/bronchitis</td><td align="left">Degree of peribronchial/perivascular cuffing</td><td align="left">Alveoli</td><td align="left">Bronchioles and bronchi</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">C57BL/6J</td><td align="left">mock d3</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">d3</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">7.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">d5</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">9.7</td><td align="left">1.3</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">d8</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">1.7</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">129S1/SvImJ</td><td align="left">mock d3</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">d3</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">0.3</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">d5</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">10.7</td><td align="left">1.3</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">d8</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">10.3</td><td align="left">2.0</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char">CAST/EiJ</td><td align="left">mock d3</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">d3</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">1.3</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">d5</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">18.7</td><td align="left">1.3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Analysis of global gene expression changes in lung and blood of CAST/EiJ mice revealed abnormal immune response after infection</title><p>To further investigate the high susceptibility of CAST/EiJ mice and to gain insights into the gene regulatory networks involved, we infected female CAST/EiJ, C57BL/6J, 129S1/SvlmJ and PWK/PhJ mice with 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU H3N2 virus and performed transcriptome analysis of the lungs and peripheral blood at 3 and 5&#x000a0;days p.i. and mock day 3. Principal component analysis (PCA) of all individual samples from the lungs revealed good grouping of biological replicates and a clear separation of infected versus mock-infected mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10a</xref>). The first principal component reflected expression changes associated with disease whereas the second principal component was driven by mouse subspecies. C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvlmJ exhibited a change in gene expression from mock-infected to infected lungs at day 3 to day 5 p.i.. Also, CAST/EiJ infected mice did show a strong change from mock-to influenza infected samples. However, samples from days 3 and 5 p.i. were not separated from each other in CAST/EiJ mice in contrast to the changes in C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvlmJ. These observations indicate a strong peak inflammatory response already at day 3 p.i. in infected CAST/EiJ mice. PWK/PhJ mice exhibited a shift from mock-infected mice to day 3 and day 5 p.i. whereby the distance to mock-treated mice was larger at day 3 than at day 5 suggesting that the low replication rate of influenza virus in the lungs of PWK/PhJ mice induced a much lower inflammatory response which was already partly resolved at day 5 p.i.. Identification of differentially expressed probe sets (DEPS, showing a 2-fold or more absolute difference in expression compared to mock-treated mice with an adjusted <italic>p</italic>-value of&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) revealed highest number of DEPS for infected versus mock-infected CAST/EiJ mice on day 3 (2054) and day 5 p.i. (2513), respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>). C57BL/6J infected mice had intermediate numbers of DEPS that were at similar levels on day 3 p.i. (966 and 975, respectively) and higher in 129S1/SvlmJ (1627) than in C57BL/6J (1108), respectively, at day 5 p.i.. Lowest number of DEPS were observed for PWK/PhJ for both days, exhibiting higher numbers on day 3 (604) compared to day 5 p.i. (306). These results corroborate the conclusions above from the PCA analysis. Analysis of 13 inflammatory genes that are strongly regulated in influenza infected mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] revealed that all infected mice exhibited a similar level of up-regulation confirming that all mice were successfully infected. In addition, these results showed that CAST/EiJ mice were able to initiate a proper inflammatory host response (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: Figure S1).<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Principle component analysis of gene expression values from infected lungs and blood. Principle component analysis (PCA) revealed separate grouping of non-infected mice and infected mice for all mouse strains in the first component as well as separation by mouse subspecies in the second component. Replicates for a given day p.i. grouped well together. (<bold>a</bold>) PCA of all probe sets from lungs; (<bold>b</bold>) PCA of 2079 probe sets from blood that were significantly regulated (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). Proportion of variances for lung: PC1: 29&#x000a0;%, PC2: 21&#x000a0;%, PC3: 13&#x000a0;%. Proportion of variances for blood: PC1: 37&#x000a0;%, PC2: 16&#x000a0;%, PC3: 11&#x000a0;%</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig><fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Differentially expressed probe sets. The number of differentially expressed probe sets (DEPS) exhibiting a log<sub>2</sub>-fold change of &#x0003e;1 and an adjusted <italic>p</italic>-value of&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 were determined by LIMMA between infected and non-infected groups for days 3 and 5 p.i.. Up-regulated DEPS are shown in blue, down-regulated in red</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig11_HTML" id="MO11"/></fig></p><p>For the PCA of the blood transcriptomes, we first performed an ANOVA analysis and selected probe sets that were significantly regulated (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). The resulting PCA of these 2079 probe sets revealed good grouping of infected and non-infected groups as well as for the different strains (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10b</xref>). Analysis of 13 inflammatory genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] showed similar up-regulation of the inflammatory response in CAST/EiJ mice compared to 129S1/SvlmJ and C57BL/6J. PWK/PhJ mice exhibited only weak up-regulation or even down-regulation of these genes (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>: Figure S2). The results again show that CAST/EiJ mice were capable to initiate a proper inflammatory response at the transcriptional level in the blood.</p><p>We also performed a Digital Cell Quantification (DCQ, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]) to investigate possible differences in immune cell populations of CAST/EiJ mice. DCQ of blood from infected CAST/EiJ mice revealed lower numbers of granulocytes and a higher number of monocytes and macrophages compared to infected 129S1/SvlmJ mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12a</xref>). DCQ analysis of the lung transcriptome showed equal numbers of monocytes and macrophages in CAST/EiJ and 129S1/SvlmJ mice and a much stronger reduction in dendritic cells in CAST/EiJ compared to 129S1/SvlmJ mice after infection (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12b</xref>).<fig id="Fig12"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>DCQ analysis of gene expression changes in blood and lung. Changes in relative numbers of immune cells were determined by DCQ for each mouse in blood (<bold>a</bold>) and in lung (<bold>b</bold>) based on changes in gene expression levels. Results from the analysis were visualized as heat maps for 217 immune cell populations that are available in the database at the DCQ server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dcq.tau.ac.il/">http://dcq.tau.ac.il/</ext-link>). Changes in cell populations that were specific for CAST/EiJ mice are shown. The detailed description of individual cell populations is provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM11" ref-type="media">11</xref>: Table S7</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig12_HTML" id="MO12"/></fig></p><p>To identify genes that may be involved in the high susceptibility in CAST/EiJ mice, we determined probe sets that were up-regulated in the lungs of C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvlmJ at days 3 and 5 p.i. compared to the mock control but not in CAST/EiJ. However, it should be noted that differences in expression signals from array analysis of the genetically diverse CC mice may also be caused by SNPs in probes. We therefore confirmed expression changes obtained from an array data set with expression changes observed by RNAseq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Only those genes were retained that were differentially regulated in both, our arrays and the RNAseq study. The filtering revealed eight genes that failed to be up-regulated in CAST/EiJ mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>): <italic>Prm1</italic> (protamine 1), <italic>Gdf3</italic> (growth differentiation factor 3), <italic>Nts</italic> (neurotensin), <italic>Plekhs1</italic> (pleckstrin homology domain containing, family S member 1), <italic>Hpse</italic> (heparanase), <italic>F830016B08Rik</italic> (RIKEN cDNA F830016B08 gene), <italic>Insrr</italic> (insulin receptor-related receptor), <italic>Wfdc17</italic> (WAP four-disulfide core domain 17). In addition, the analysis of the chemokine/cytokine KEGG pathway showed a strong down-regulation of <italic>Ccr6</italic> (chemokine (C-C motif) receptor 6) specifically in CAST/EiJ mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref>).<fig id="Fig13"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>Changes in the expression levels of probe sets that were up-regulated in 129S1/SvImJ and C56BL/6J but not in CAST/EiJ mice. Expression values represent normalized log<sub>2</sub> transformed signal intensities in the lungs of infected mice at different time points p.i. relative to expression levels in mock-infected control mice</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig13_HTML" id="MO13"/></fig><fig id="Fig14"><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><p>Changes in the expression levels of probe sets that corresponded to genes of the CCR6 regulation network. Expression values represent normalized log<sub>2</sub> transformed signal intensities in the lungs of infected mice at different time points p.i. relative to expression levels in mock-infected control mice</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig14_HTML" id="MO14"/></fig></p><p>We subsequently investigated other genes involved in the regulatory networks of <italic>Hpse</italic> and <italic>Ccr6</italic> (see discussion) and found specific gene expression changes of <italic>Ccr7</italic> (chemokine (C-C motif) receptor 7), <italic>Cxcr5</italic> (chemokine (C-X-C motif) receptor 5), <italic>Cxcr1</italic> (chemokine (C-X-C motif) receptor 1), and <italic>Hspg2</italic> (perlecan, heparan sulfate proteoglycan 2) in CAST/EiJ mice after infection (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref>).</p><p>We also filtered for genes that were up-regulated in the blood of C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvlmJ at days 3 and 5 p.i. but not in CAST/EiJ and found four DEPS: <italic>Il1b</italic> (interleukin 1 beta), <italic>Pi16</italic> (peptidase inhibitor 16) and <italic>I830012O16Rik</italic> (RIKEN cDNA I830012O16 gene). The fourth probe set belonged to a gene from which a second probe set was not lower in CAST/EiJ mice and it was therefore omitted (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>: Figure S3).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Here, we have analyzed various phenotypic traits after influence A (H3N2) infection in the CC founder strains. We found a strong influence of genetic variation on all traits and a large variation of the host response and pathology. In particular, the response in CAST/EiJ mice revealed a unique phenotype which may represent a new model for the human leucocyte recruitment deficiency disease.</p><sec id="Sec14"><title>Susceptibility and resistance to influenza infection and disease is strongly influenced by genetic variation</title><p>Our comprehensive analysis of the CC founder strains revealed highly variable phenotypes for all investigated traits (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig15" ref-type="fig">15</xref>). On the basis of mortality rate, MTTD, and body weight changes, we could distinguish three different susceptibility groups: highly susceptible strains, intermediate susceptible strains, and highly resistant strains. Amongst the resistant strains, NZO/HlLtJ only marginally lost weight (less than 10&#x000a0;%) at the low infection dose but exhibited weight loss at the higher doses whereas PWK/PhJ mice also exhibited a larger loss of body weight early after infection.<fig id="Fig15"><label>Fig. 15</label><caption><p>Phenotyping the CC founder strains after influenza A H3N2 infection. The eight CC founder strains were classified into three different subgroups (highly resistant, intermediate susceptible and highly susceptible) according to their outcome after 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU influenza A H3N2 infection. They showed high variation in changes in body weight, viral loads in lungs, hematological parameters in peripheral blood and relative lung weight</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig15_HTML" id="MO15"/></fig></p><p>In previous studies, CC founders and incipient lines of the CC had been studied after infection with H1N1 (A/PR/8/34 (PR8)) virus and the authors described a large variation on phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Here, we investigated the CC founder strains after infection with another contemporary influenza virus subtype, H3N2 (A/HK/01/68), and we also observed high diversity of phenotypic responses between the founder strains. The study by Ferris et al., phenotyped infected mice only until day 4 p.i. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. They identified a highly susceptible and a highly resistant group. Similarly, Bottomly and colleagues categorize a severe and mild response to infection based on global transcriptome profiling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In our studies, we monitored the infected mice over a much larger period, 14&#x000a0;days p.i., and also performed infections with different doses of the same virus, and we distinguish three susceptibility groups. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) for body weight changes revealed that the factor strain had the strongest effect on body weight loss indicating high heritability for this trait. These results thus demonstrate that CC founder strains and CC strains will represent a highly valuable model system to identify genetic factors that regulate susceptibility to infections and other host responses. Indeed, in an analysis of incipient pre-CC strains, several chromosomal regions were identified that influence gene expression of the host response as well as pathology in the lung [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Influence of sex on disease progression and outcome</title><p>Using ANOVA, we also found that sex had also a significant effect on body weight loss. At a dose of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU female mice exhibited higher body weight loss compared to males. However, the effect of sex was weaker than the strain effect. The influence of sex had not been reported in previous studies which were performed only in females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In pairwise comparisons of strains, we found significant sex-specific differences in body weight loss in the highly and intermediate susceptible group after infection with 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU, but not in the highly resistant group. Differential responses to H3N2 influenza A infections between female and male mice have been reported previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Also sex-specific differences to influenza A virus infections in humans have been observed. However, the present knowledge is rather limited because epidemiological data often lack information on sex. Furthermore, tendencies showing that either females or males are more prone to severe disease progression are influenced by additional factors like general life style, social behavior, coinfections or viral exposure (reviewed in: [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]). Our results suggest that influenza infections in the CC population may represent a highly valuable resource to obtain a better understanding of sex-specific responses to pathogens in mammals, including humans.</p><p>We did not observe significant differences in survival between male and female mice in the founder stains, except for NOD/ShiLtJ. NOD/ShiLtJ mice spontaneously develop insulin-dependent type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1D) which is characterized by the destruction of pancreatic cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. They also show several abnormalities in immune cells, like defective antigen presentation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], abnormalities in T [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] and NK cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] as well as impaired cytokine signaling in macrophages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Female NOD/ShiLtJ mice exhibit a strong decrease in insulin production already at the age of 12&#x000a0;weeks, which starts several weeks later in males. The incidence of spontaneous T1D is much higher in females (60-80&#x000a0;%) compared to males (20-30&#x000a0;%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Thus, the increased susceptibility to influenza A infections in females which we observed may be directly related to their pre-diabetic/diabetic state or to an abnormal immune response. It has been shown, that there was an increased risk of complications among patients with diabetes after pH1N1 infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Therefore, NOD/ShiLtJ mice may provide a valuable mouse model for investigating the role of diabetic state on influenza A infections.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Different <italic>Mx1</italic> alleles influence survival rates and viral load but are modulated by host genetic background</title><p>Many studies on influenza pathogenesis in mice were performed in classical laboratory strains which carry a mutation in the influenza resistance gene <italic>Mx1</italic> first described in the A2G mouse strain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The CC founder strains carry five different <italic>Mx1</italic> alleles ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig">16</xref>). The amino acid sequences of the protein encoded by the <italic>Mx1</italic> alleles in NZO/HlLtJ and A2G were identical to the consensus sequence from the multiple alignments. The PWK/PhJ allele encodes one and the CAST/EiJ allele two amino acid changes compared to the consensus sequence. The WSB/EiJ transcript of <italic>Mx1</italic> harbors a stop codon in its open reading frame leading to a truncated protein. All classical laboratory strains (A/J, C57BL/6J, 129S1/SvImJ and NOD/ShiLtJ) carry a deletion from the 8th to the 12th exon, resulting in a protein that has previously been shown to be non-functional [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. In our study, the presence or absence of a functional <italic>Mx1</italic> allele correlated strongly with resistance and susceptibility. PWK/PhJ and NZO/HlLtJ were highly resistant and survived a virus challenge with increasing doses of infection, 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup> FFU, 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> FFU and 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> FFU. Thus, the single amino acid difference had no influence on the protective functions of the MX1 protein. In contrast, the amino acid exchanges in the CAST/EiJ protein seemed to be detrimental leading to a highly susceptible phenotype. Similar results were obtained after infection with H1N1 (A/PR/8/34 (PR8)) virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. We recently found that the protective function of MX1 is dependent on genetic back ground [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Thus, further experiments are needed to elucidate the function of the CAST/EiJ MX1 protein and the potential contribution of the CAST/EiJ genetic background.<fig id="Fig16"><label>Fig. 16</label><caption><p>
<italic>Mx1</italic> sequence alignment of A2G and the eight CC founder strains. <italic>Mx1</italic> alleles of CC founder strains in comparison to the A2J allele are shown. The mouse <italic>Mx1</italic> gene has 14 exons (blue). Changes of the nucleotide sequence in exons (yellow) result in amino acid exchanges indicated below by showing the respective amino acid exchange. PWK/PhJ exhibits one amino acid exchange relative to A2J, CAST/EiJ two changes at different positions. A premature stop codon is present in WSB/EiJ leading to a truncated MX1 protein. The other strains (A/J, C56BL/6J, 129S1/SvImJ and NOD/ShiLtJ) possess a deletion between the 8th and the 12th exon resulting in a non-functional protein. The graph was created based on data from ncbi.com and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_Fig16_HTML" id="MO16"/></fig></p><p>MX1 is known to inhibit IAV replication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Therefore, we investigated viral load at different time points p.i. in the CC founder stains and related to the absence or presence of a functional <italic>Mx1</italic> allele. Viral load was lowest in PWK/PhJ mice, was only detected at early times p.i. and was cleared by day 8 p.i.. NZO/HlLtJ mice were also able to clear the virus, but viral titer increased until day 5. Thus, there is a clear difference in viral load even in strains that carry a functional <italic>Mx1</italic> allele which may be caused by genes that modulate the activity of MX1 or other immune response genes. In contrast, all intermediate and highly susceptible mice strains that carried the non-functional <italic>Mx1</italic> alleles exhibited high viral loads already on day 3, and virus was not cleared on day 8 or at the time of death. The CC population now offers the possibility of investigating the same <italic>Mx1</italic> allele on different genetic backgrounds and to identify potential modifying loci that interact with MX1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Correlation of viral load with other phenotypes</title><p>We did not observe a general correlation between viral load and survival in the susceptible strains. All susceptible and intermediate susceptible strains had similar viral loads. For other mouse strains it had been shown that high viral loads in the lung correlate well with increased susceptibility to IAV. For example, the highly susceptible DBA/2&#x000a0;J strain exhibited a higher viral load compared to resistant C57BL/6J mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Boon et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] studied viral load in 21 inbred mouse laboratory strains infected with H5N1 (A/HK/213/03). They found significant association of viral load and mortality whereby an increased host inflammatory response was caused by a higher viral load. However, other studies demonstrate no differences in viral load between resistant and susceptible strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Ferris et al. concluded from studies of pre-CC mice that both viral replication and virus-induced inflammation were predictors for disease severity being independent of each other. Nevertheless, when both were combined they were better predictors than either of them alone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Thus, in conclusion, either increased viral load causing extensive tissue damage or a hyper-inflammatory host response may result in a lethal outcome of an influenza infection. Therefore, the analysis of the divergent host responses in CC mice will allow investigating the biological mechanisms and the cellular and molecular networks in detail in a controlled experimental system and thus substantially contribute to better understand individual host factors that are involved in causing severe influenza disease outcomes in humans.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>CAST/EiJ mice exhibit a distinct deficiency in their immune response to influenza infections</title><p>Hematological analysis of the peripheral blood in infected CAST/EiJ mice showed only a slight increase in granulocytes in the peripheral blood compared to other strains that had high viral loads in their lungs. Thus, we hypothesized that CAST/EiJ may exhibit a specific deficiency in their response to influenza infection. We therefore studied the immune response in CAST/EiJ mice in more detail by analyzing immune cells in blood and lung in comparison to other strains. Flow cytometry studies revealed that the increase of granulocytes in the blood was much lower after infection in CAST/EiJ mice compared to the other two strains whereas the number of monocytes stayed high in the blood of CAST/EiJ mice. In the lung, CAST/EiJ mice exhibited an increase of granulocytes, macrophages and T lymphocytes. However, the absolute amount of leukocytes remained very low compared to the other susceptible strains. After infection, granulocyte numbers increased much less in CAST/EiJ lungs compared to the other two strains whereas the relative increase in macrophages was higher in CAST/EiJ. Histological analysis confirmed the low level of neutrophil infiltrations in the lung and increased macrophage numbers. Also, DCQ analysis of global gene expression changes confirmed the low neutrophil response in the blood, reduced neutrophil infiltration into the lung and an increase in macrophage numbers in the lung. In line with our results, Ferris et al. showed that CAST/EiJ mice developed high viral loads in lungs after influenza infection but showed less infiltrating immune cells in their lungs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. They and others observed low levels of T and NK cells in the blood of CAST/EiJ mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. CAST/EiJ mice are also highly susceptible to monkeypox virus (MPXV) infection lacking interferon gamma (IFN-&#x003b3;) induction which might be related to a defect in activation and recruitment of IFN-&#x003b3; producing immune cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. CAST/EiJ mice were rescued from lethal challenge with MPXV by intra-nasal administration of IFN&#x003b3; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. However, IFN&#x003b3; is not crucial for the host response to influenza infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>] whereas, interferons type I and III are essential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Therefore, we investigated if pre-treatment with IFN-I was able to rescue CAST/EiJ mice from lethal influenza A infection. We observed a shift of about two to three days in the survival curve for IFN-treated versus non-treated CAST/EiJ mice. However, IFN pre-treatment did not rescue CAST/EiJ mice from lethal infection (data not shown). In addition, we did not observe reduced levels of <italic>Ifng</italic> transcripts in CAST/EiJ compared to the other mouse strains (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: Figure S1 and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>: Figure S2).</p><p>Our observations suggest that granulocytes have a deficiency to enter the site of infection in CAST/EiJ mice. Members of the CXC chemokine family, notably CCL4 and CCL5, as well as selectins, play a major role in the recruitment of leukocytes, especially of neutrophils [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. We showed earlier that genes from these two families, notably CXC chemokines, are upregulated very early after influenza infection in lungs of C57BL/6J mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. However, we observed that after infection the transcript levels of <italic>Ccl4</italic> and <italic>Ccl5</italic> were similarly up-regulated in the lungs of CAST/EiJ as for 129S1/SvImJ and C57BL/6J (data not shown). Also, deficiencies in several CXC chemokine ligands and receptors (<italic>Cxcr2</italic>, <italic>Cxcl10</italic>, <italic>Cxcr3</italic>, <italic>Cxcl5</italic>) diminish the leukocytes influx into lungs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. The expression of <italic>Cxcl10</italic>, <italic>Cxcr3</italic> and <italic>Cxcl5</italic> was not differently regulated in CAST/EiJ compared to the two other susceptible mouse strains (data not shown). However, expression of <italic>Cxcr2</italic> dropped to base line levels at day 5 p.i. only in CAST/EiJ mice (data not shown). It was reported for various inflammation models that in mice deficient in E-, L-, or P-selectin genes (<italic>Sele</italic>, <italic>Sell</italic>, <italic>Selp</italic>), the levels of neutrophils, T lymphocytes and lung inflammation are reduced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. All selectin genes were similarly up-regulated in all three susceptible genes in the lung after infection. However, <italic>Sele</italic> was strongly down-regulated in CAST/EiJ on day 5 p.i. (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM10" ref-type="media">10</xref>: Figure S4). Furthermore, the continuous recruitment of leukocytes is regulated by a feed-forward loop in which infiltrated immune cells in the lung enhance the release of chemokines leading to the recruitment of more neutrophils [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. The depletion of neutrophils resulted in uncontrolled virus growth and increased mortality in mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. Thus, reduced granulocyte infiltration in CAST/EiJ may secondarily also affect the subsequent recruitment of more granulocytes and other immune cells. However, we do observe an increase in macrophages. Further analyses will be necessary to unravel the details of these interactions phenomenon.</p><p>In summary, the amount of granulocytes in the blood of CAST/EiJ mice increased after infection which suggests a normal primary signaling of infected cells to the hematopoietic system and the release of leukocytes into the blood. However, the number of granulocytes remained constant in the lungs of CAST/EiJ from day 3 on and did not further increase. In contrast, granulocyte numbers strongly increased in lungs of 129S1/SvImJ and C57BL/6J mice. The strong specific down-regulation of <italic>Sele</italic> at day 5 supports the hypothesis of a leukocyte recruitment deficiency in CAST/EiJ mice. Together, these results suggest that the lack of sustained neutrophil recruitment may be the primary defect in CAST/EiJ mice.</p><p>We also performed a more detailed analysis of gene expression changes at the level of gene interaction pathways and individual genes to obtain more insights into the underlying mechanism of the abnormal CAST/EiJ immune cell phenotype. The canonical inflammatory genes, interferons and interferon response genes as well as many inflammatory chemokines such as <italic>Cxcl10</italic>, are all highly up-regulated in the lungs of CAST/EiJ mice. In addition, CAST/EiJ mice showed the highest number of DEPS after infection in blood and lungs. Thus, CAST/EiJ mice exhibited not a general deficiency in the overall activation of an inflammatory response but rather a specific defect in the recruitment of cells to the lung. Seven genes were specifically not up-regulated in CAST/EiJ after infection which have not been described in the context of the host response to influenza infections, but may be also important host factors for virus defense in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Furthermore, the <italic>Hpse</italic> gene was not as strongly up-regulated after infection in CAST/EiJ compared to the other mouse strains. <italic>Hpse</italic> encodes heparanase, a mammalian endoglycosidase which degrades heparan sulfate glycosaminoglycan in extracellular space and within the cells. It was postulated that heparanase may play an important role in inflammatory and autoimmune processes including leukocyte recruitment, immune cell extravasation and migration, release of cytokines and chemokines and activation of innate immune cells (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]). Recently, the role of heparanase in regulating the migration of DCs was demonstrated in heparanase-deficient mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. When we analyzed the expression profiles of genes in the heparanase network, we found a specific down-regulation of the <italic>Hspg2</italic> gene in CAST/EiJ mice. <italic>Hspg2</italic> encodes perlecan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>] also known as basement membrane-specific heparan sulfate proteoglycan 2 (HSPG2). Perlecan is a large multi-domain proteoglycan that binds to and cross-links many extracellular matrix (ECM) components and cell-surface molecules. It is a key component of the vascular extracellular matrix, where it interacts with a variety of other matrix components helping to maintain the endothelial barrier function. Three long chains of glycosaminoglycans are attached to the perlecan core protein that plays an important role in the recruitment of leukocytes via binding to chemokines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. Also, the <italic>Wfdc17</italic> gene, encoding the AMWAP protein (activated microglia/macrophage whey acid protein domain protein), was not expressed in CAST/EiJ mice before and after infection. AMWAP has been postulated to be a negative regulator of pro-inflammatory microglia/macrophage activation and a potential modulator of innate immunity in neurodegeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. Interestingly, <italic>Wfdc17</italic> was up-regulated in lungs of C57BL/6J, 129S1/SvlmJ and PWK/PhJ after infection, but not in CAST/EiJ which is consistent with the observed increase of infiltrating macrophages in CAST/EiJ lungs. In addition, analysis of the KEGG chemokine/cytokine pathway revealed a strong down-regulation of <italic>Ccr6</italic> (chemokine (C-C motif) receptor 6) in the lung that was unique for CAST/EiJ mice. CCR6 is an important chemokine receptor that mediates recruitment of immature and mature DCs and antigen presenting cells (APCs) to the sites of epithelia inflammation in the lung (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]). Epithelial cells in the lung increase their production of CCL20, which is the only chemokine ligand for CCR6, which in turn causes a further recruitment of immature CCR6-positive DCs into the lung. <italic>Ccr6</italic> expression is down-regulated during the maturation process and accordingly <italic>Ccr7</italic> is upregulated leading to the migration of DCs to the lymph node to fulfill its APC function. The expression of <italic>Ccr6</italic> was down-regulated in all analyzed mouse strains, but very strongly in CAST/EiJ lungs, especially at day 5 after infection. Interestingly, <italic>Ccr7</italic> expression was up-regulated in all strains, but not in CAST/EiJ, where <italic>Ccr7</italic> was down-regulated. After infection a large number of immature DC continuously enter the lung tissue and then differentiate into mature DCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]. This process was reflected by the up-regulation of <italic>Ccr7</italic> in C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvlmJ. However, in CAST/EiJ mice less immature DC cells enter the lung which may be reflected by the decrease of <italic>Ccr6</italic> and <italic>Ccr7</italic> expression. Another down-regulated gene in CAST/EiJ was <italic>Cxcr1</italic>, a member of the G-protein-coupled receptor family. CXCR1 is a receptor for the CXC chemokine interleukin IL-8, which is a potent neutrophil recruiting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>] and activating factor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]. IL-8 is an important modulator of monocyte-endothelial interactions under flow conditions, since it can rapidly cause rolling monocytes to adhere firmly onto monolayers expressing E-selectin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]. Furthermore, <italic>Cxcr5</italic> was down-regulated in CAST/EiJ lungs but not in the other strains. CXCR5 is a cytokine receptor that binds to B-lymphocyte attractant (BLC) and is involved in B-cell migration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>].</p><p>Filtering for genes that were up-regulated in the blood of C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvlmJ but not in CAST/EiJ identified three genes. One of those <italic>Il1b</italic> (interleukin 1 beta) encodes IL1B which is an important inflammatory cytokine that mediates the inflammation and initiate the immune response against Influenza A virus infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. Pro-IL-1B is cleaved by caspase-1 which is activated through the formation of the NLRP3 inflammasome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>] and induces the expression of a variety of inflammatory mediators, which initiate the cascade of inflammatory responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>]. It was postulated that the synergy between CD40L and IL-1beta represents a potent, T cell-independent mechanism for DC activation during the earliest stages of inflammatory responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]. Most interestingly, in humans it has been described that genetic variants in IL1A and IL1B contribute to the susceptibility to 2009 H1N1 infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>].</p><p>In summary, the specific changes of gene expression patters that were unique in CAST/EiJ lungs belong to gene networks that play a crucial role in migration and recruiting of leukocytes. Together, these observations suggest a deficiency in CAST/EiJ mice in leukocyte adhesion and/or recruitment. The recruitment of leukocytes to the site of infection is a complex process of different steps including leucocyte rolling, activation, arrest and transmigration into the tissue which involves many proteins and interactions. Three types of leukocyte adhesion deficiencies (LADI-III) have been described in humans (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]). Mutations in ITGB2 (integrin beta 2), SLC35C1 (solute carrier family 35) and FERMT3 (fermitin family homolog 3) have been identified as the genetic cause of disease in LADI, II and III, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. However, we did not observe differences in the expression of these LAD genes in CAST/EiJ mice (data not shown). Thus the specific CAST/EiJ phenotype may be a valuable model system to identify and study additional genes related to human leukocyte adhesion and recruitment deficiencies. Of course, further functional analyses under different conditions will be necessary to describe the leukocyte phenotype in CAST/EiJ mice in more detail.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, our studies on the CC founder strains emphasize the importance of host genetic backgrounds for the course and outcome of IAV infections. The CC founder strains as well as the CC strains will thus represent an extremely valuable experimental model system to understand the biological mechanisms as well as the genetic factors that cause severe influenza disease in humans. In most cases, high mortality was associated with high viral loads and a strong immune response. However, we also observed unexpected phenotype combinations such as high viral load but a weak immune response. In particular, the CAST/EiJ strain may provide a novel model for human leukocyte adhesion and recruitment deficiencies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec21"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>All experiments in mice were approved by an external committee according to the national guidelines of the animal welfare law in Germany (BGBl. I S. 1206, 1313 and BGBl. I S. 1934). The protocol used in these experiments has been reviewed by an ethics committee (equivalent to US IACUC, according to the German law) and approved by the &#x02018;Nieders&#x000e4;chsisches Landesamt f&#x000fc;r Verbraucherschutz und Lebensmittelsicherheit, Oldenburg, Germany&#x02019; (Permit Numbers: 33.9.42502-04-051/09 and 3392 42502-04-13/1234).</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Virus, mouse strains, infection</title><p>The mouse-adapted virus strain influenza A/HK/01/68,obtained from Otto Haller, University of Freiburg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>] was produced in the allantoic cavity of 10-day-old embryonated hen eggs for 48&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The CC founder (A/J, C57BL/6J, 129S1/SvlmJ, NOD/ShiLtJ, NZO/HILtJ, CAST/EiJ, PWK/PhJ, WSB/EiJ) were purchased from Jackson Laboratories (Bar Harbor, ME) and bred in our animal facility in Braunschweig for two to six generations depending on the respective strain. All mice were maintained under specific pathogen free conditions and according to the German animal welfare law. The entire age range of mice was 7 to 13&#x000a0;weeks whereby 95.5&#x000a0;% of the mice had an age range of 8&#x02013;12 weeks. Female and male mice were anesthetized by intra-peritoneal injection with a mixture of Ketamine/Xylazine (100&#x000a0;mg/ml Ketamine and 20&#x000a0;mg/ml Xylazine) in sterile natrium chloride solution. The doses were adjusted to the individual body weight using 200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l/20&#x000a0;g body weight. Mice were then intra-nasally infected with 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l virus solution of sterile phosphate-buffered saline using different virus concentrations (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>1</sup>, 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> and 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> FFU). Body weight was determined daily as % of initial weight at day 0. Mice that lost more than 30&#x000a0;% of their body weight had to be killed for ethical reasons and were also scored as dead. Three different experimental setups with combination of different phenotyping parameters were used (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Relative lung weight</title><p>Mock-infected and infected female mice (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3-6 per strain and time point) were anesthetized using 160&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l Isofluoran (cp-pharma, Burgdorf, Germany). After exsanguinating via puncture of the retro-bulbar vein plexus, lungs were collected and weighted directly. Relative lung weight was calculated as followed: (lung weight on day of preparation/body weight on day of preparation)&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100 and displayed as percentage of total body weight.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Viral load in lungs</title><p>Viral load in infected lungs was determined on MDCK II (Madin-Darby Canine Kidney II) cells using the FFU assay as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Briefly, lungs of mice were homogenized and debris removed by centrifugation. Samples were stored in aliquots at &#x02212;70&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Serial dilutions of lung homogenates were prepared and viral titers determined by the FFU assay.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>RNA isolation for arrays</title><p>At different time points after virus infection (day 3 and 5) and mock infection (day 3 post sterile phosphate-buffered saline infection) lung and blood were taken for RNA isolation. Body weight was measured until the day of sample collection. Eye blood was collected in RNA protect animal blood tubes (Qiagen) and immediately stored at &#x02212;20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Lung RNA was isolated using Qiagen Midi Kit as described previously (104). Blood RNA was isolated with the RNeasy protect animal blood kit (Qiagen). RNA concentration was measured with the NanoDrop (Thermo Scientific).</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Microarray experiment</title><p>For DNA microarray hybridization and analysis, the quality and integrity of the total RNA was controlled on a 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies; Waldbronn, Germany). 100&#x000a0;ng of total RNA were applied for Cy3-labelling reaction using the one color Quick Amp Labeling protocol (Agilent Technologies; Waldbronn, Germany). Labeled cRNA was hybridized to Agilent&#x02019;s mouse 4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;44&#x000a0;k microarrays for 16&#x000a0;h at 68&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and scanned using the Agilent DNA Microarray Scanner. Expression values were calculated by the software package Feature Extraction 10.5.1.1 (Agilent Technologies; Waldbronn, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Statistics</title><p>Data were analyzed using GraphPad Prism version 5.04 for Windows (GraphPad Software, San Diego, California). Mean and standard error of the mean (SEM) were calculated for all groups. Dunn&#x02019;s post test with multiple testing correction was used for significance testing between individual groups (e.g. different gender, virus concentration and time points). Non-parametric Mann Whitney <italic>U</italic> test was used to determine <italic>p</italic>-values for the significance of differences between two groups. Log rank test was used to calculate significances for survival rates. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed using the lm and aov functions of the R software package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. A multi-factorial ANOVA model (weight-loss&#x02009;~&#x02009;strain * sex * day) with all interaction terms and with days (from day 1 to day 7 p.i.) as a categorical factor was used first. In this analysis, the three-way interaction term strain:day:sex was not significant and was therefore removed to generate an optimized ANOVA model (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2). Subsequent Tukey HSD post-hoc test was used to identify pairwise significant differences. A one-way ANOVA was performed using the model weight-loss&#x02009;~&#x02009;strain for each individual day separately, and the broad-sense heritability was determined by calculating the interclass correlation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]: (MSB-MSW)/(MSB+(n-1)*MSW) with MSB&#x02009;=&#x02009;mean square between groups, MSW&#x02009;=&#x02009;mean square within groups, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;mean number of mice per strain. One way ANOVA (model lg.viral.ld&#x02009;~&#x02009;suscept, see (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Table S4 and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Table S5 for details) and Tukey HSD post-hoc test was used to determine differences of viral load between strains of different susceptibility (intermediate susceptible, highly susceptible and resistant strains). Correlations for phenotypic traits were calculated and illustrated using R scripts developed by W. Venables (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://goo.gl/nahmV">http://goo.gl/nahmV</ext-link>), S. Turner (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gist.github.com/stephenturner/3492773">https://gist.github.com/stephenturner/3492773</ext-link>) and the graphics from the package PerformanceAnalytics (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/">https://cran.r-project.org/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Gene expression analysis</title><p>Array data were analyzed using the R software package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. Pre-processing steps included background correction, quantile normalization and annotation using the MmAgilentDesign026655.db [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>], limma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>], and Agi4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;44PreProcess [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>] packages. Principal component analysis (PCA) analysis were performed using the affycoretools package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>]. Multi-group comparisons and identification of differentially expressed probe sets (DEPS) were performed with the LIMMA package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>] using BH correction for multiple testing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>]. DEPS were identified based on an adjusted p-value of&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and exhibiting more than a two-fold difference in expression levels (abs [log<sub>2</sub>]&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1). Inflammatory genes that are expressed during influenza infections were selected based on our previous influenza transcriptome studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]. GO, KEGG, Reactome enrichment analysis and cluster profiling was performed with the package clusterProfiler [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>]. For the identification of genes that exhibited no change in gene expression levels after infection in the lungs of CAST/EiJ mice compared to the other strains, the full expression data set was filtered for probe sets that were not regulated in CAST/EiJ (log-fold change absolute &#x0003c;0.5) but up-regulated in C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvlmJ mice at days 3 and 5 after infection (log-fold change absolute &#x0003e;1). In addition, the data set was filtered for probe sets that were down-regulated in CAST/EiJ (log-fold change&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;&#x02212;0.5) but up-regulated in C57BL/6&#x000a0;J and 129S1/SvlmJ mice at days 3 and 5 after infection (log-fold change absolute &#x0003e;1). These filters returned 8 and 2 probe sets, respectively. It should, however, be noted that gene expression differences between strains which are observed in Agilent arrays may not always represent true differences in expression levels between strains but may also result from sequence polymorphisms in transcripts that result in mismatches between probes and transcripts, since the probes on the array are based on the C57BL/6J reference strain. Therefore, we validated true expression changes by analyzing the respective genes in a previously published RNAseq data set [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Only genes that were also differentially expressed in the RNAseq data set were further investigated. In this way, eight genes were found to be regulated in CAST/EiJ versus the other strains. The same analysis was performed for blood transcriptomes. Four DEPS were not regulated in CAST/EiJ (log-fold change absolute &#x0003c;0.5) but up-regulated in C57BL/6J and 129S1/SvlmJ mice at days 3 and 5 after infection (log-fold change absolute &#x0003e;1). KEGG pathway analysis was performed using the pathview package in R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>]. DCQ analysis was performed according to the algorithm described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Gene expression values were pre-processed by subtracting the mean of the mock-infected mice from the infected mice for each mouse strain and by selecting the most variant probe sets for genes with multiple probe sets based on the standard deviation across all groups. DCQ analysis was then performed at the public server provided by the University of Tel Aviv (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dcq.tau.ac.il/">http://dcq.tau.ac.il/</ext-link>). The results were then visualized by heatmaps using the R software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Histology</title><p>Tissues were stored in 10&#x000a0;% neutral-buffered formalin (lungs after careful inflation with formalin), embedded in paraffin, sectioned at 4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m, and stained with hematoxylin and eosin (HE) for examination by light microscopy. Semi-quantitative assessment of influenza virus-associated inflammation by histopathology in the lung was performed as reported earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>] for the extent of alveolitis and alveolar damage we scored: 0, 0&#x000a0;%; 1, 1-25&#x000a0;%; 2, 25-50&#x000a0;%; 3, &#x0003e; 50&#x000a0;%. For the severity of alveolitis, bronchiolitis and bronchitis we scored: 0, no inflammatory cells; 1, few inflammatory cells; 2, moderate numbers of inflammatory cells; 3, many inflammatory cells. For the presence of alveolar edema, alveolar hemorrhage and type II pneumocyte hyperplasia we scored: 0, no; 1, yes. Finally, for the extent of peribronchial, peribronchiolar and perivascular infiltrates we scored: 0, none; 1, one to two cells thick; 2, three to ten cells thick; 3, more than ten cells thick. Slides were examined without knowledge of the animals.</p></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>Immunohistochemistry</title><p>For detection of influenza A virus antigen, tissues were stained with a primary antibody against the influenza A nucleoprotein as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>]. In each staining procedure, an isotype control was included as a negative control. Semi-quantitative assessment of influenza virus antigen expression in the lungs was performed as reported earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>] with minor modification: for the alveoli, 25 arbitrarily chosen, 20&#x000d7; objective fields of lung parenchyma per animal were examined by light microscopy for the presence of influenza virus nucleoprotein, without the knowledge of the identity of the animals. The score for each animal was presented as the percentage of positive fields. For the bronchi and bronchioles, the percentage of positively staining epithelium was estimated on every slide to provide the score per animal: 0, 0&#x000a0;%; 1, 1-25&#x000a0;%; 2, 25-50&#x000a0;%; 3, &#x0003e; 50&#x000a0;%.</p><p>The numbers of neutrophils and intraluminal macrophages were counted in 20 arbitrarily chosen, 40&#x000d7; objective fields per animal. Slides were examined without knowledge of the identity of the animals. Viable neutrophils were identified by immunohistochemistry staining with primary antibody Ly-6G (rat-anti-mouse Ly-6G, 25&#x02013;5931, eBioscience, San Diego, USA). Binding of the primary antibody was detected using a peroxidase labeled rabbit-anti-rat IgG-HRP (p0450, DAKO, Denmark). Peroxidase activity was revealed using 3-amino-9-ethylcafrbazole (AEC) (Sigma, St Louis, MO, USA). Intraluminal macrophages were identified on the basis of their morphology and location as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>Hematology</title><p>For monitoring hematological parameters, female mice were anesthetized using 160&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l isoflourane at different time points (mock day 3, day 3, 5, 8, 18 and day 30) after infection. Time points were omitted from the analysis when less than 60&#x000a0;% of the infected mice survived infection within a strain. Blood was taken by puncture of the retrobulbar vein plexus, collected in micro tubes containing EDTA (Sarstedt) and immediately measured in the hematologic system VetScan HM5 (Abaxis). The absolute cell numbers of lymphocytes, granulocytes and monocytes were determined and calculated as percentage of white blood cells.</p></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>Flow cytometry</title><p>Immune cell populations of single animals were analyzed in cell suspensions derived from homogenized lungs or whole blood. Blood was collected as described for the haematological analysis. Antibody against CD16/32 (clone 2.4G2) was added to blood minimizing unspecific binding to Fcy receptors. Blood cells were directly stained in two different panels with the following antibodies: &#x003b1;CD4-PE (BD Bioscience, Europe), &#x003b1;CD8-APC, &#x003b1;CD11b-APC, &#x003b1;CD19-FITC, &#x003b1;CD115-Alexa Fluor 488, &#x003b1;Ly-6G-PE-Cy7 and &#x003b1;NKp46-PerCP-eFluor 710 (eBioscience). After incubation at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;minutes, in the dark, erythrocytes were lysed and cells fixed in FACS Lysing Solution (BD Bioscience), and washed twice with PBS/2%FCS. Lungs prepared from the same animals were passed through a 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m-cell strainer and a density centrifugation using Lympholyte M (Cedarlane) was performed. After washing the cells obtained from the interphase twice with PBS/2%FCS, Fcy receptors were blocked with &#x003b1;CD16/32 and subsequently stained with antibodies as described above. In addition &#x003b1;F4/80-FITC and &#x003b1;CD11c-PE (eBioscience) were used. To exclude dead cells, 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g propidium iodide was added to each sample. Samples were measured using an Accuri C6 flow cytometer (BD Bioscience). Data were analyzed using FlowJo version 7.6.5 (Tree Star, Ashland, Oregon). The marker expression and gating strategy of immune cell populations was done as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Minor subpopulations like CD8&#x02009;+&#x02009;DC were not considered.</p></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>Deposition of data</title><p>Array data have been deposited at the gene expression data base GEO (GSE74077), phenotype data will be deposited at the mouse phenome database (MPD, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>]) upon publication of the manuscript.</p></sec></sec></body><back><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec34"><title>Additional files</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_MOESM1_ESM.docx" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1: Table S1.</label><caption><p>Pairwise chi-square tests for death/survival counts between resistant, intermediate susceptible and highly susceptible strains. (DOCX 55&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_MOESM2_ESM.docx" id="MOESM2"><label>Additional file 2: Table S2.</label><caption><p>ANOVA analysis of main effects and interactions on body weight loss. Df: degrees of freedom; Sum Sq: sum of squares, Mean sq: mean sum of squares, Pr: p-value. ANOVA model: body weight loss&#x02009;~&#x02009;strain * sex * day; after deleting the non-significant three way interaction strain:day:sex. (DOCX 52&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM3"><label>Additional file 3: Table S3</label><caption><p>Results from Tukey post-hoc HSD test for the interaction of strain:day of the ANOVA analysis from Table S2. (XLSX 83&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_MOESM4_ESM.docx" id="MOESM4"><label>Additional file 4: Table S4.</label><caption><p>Post-hoc Tukey-HSD test of differences in viral loads between different groups of susceptible strains at day 3 p.i.. Results from ANOVA analysis (model: lg.viral.ld&#x02009;~&#x02009;suscept); lg.viral.ld: log2 viral load on day 3 p.i.; suscept: categories for resistant strains (resist), intermediate susceptible strains (int_susc) and highly susceptible strains (hlg_susc) are shown. Pairwise comparisons: int_susc-hlg_susc: intermediate susceptible versus highly susceptible strains, etc.; diff: difference between means of log2 viral load, p adj: adjusted p-value using Tukey HSD test. n&#x02009;=&#x02009;36. (DOCX 52&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_MOESM5_ESM.docx" id="MOESM5"><label>Additional file 5: Table S5.</label><caption><p>Post-hoc Tukey-HSD test of differences in viral load between different groups of susceptible strains at day 5 p.i. Results from ANOVA analysis (model: lg.viral.ld&#x02009;~&#x02009;suscept); lg.viral.ld: log2 viral load on day 5 p.i.; suscept: categories for resistant strains (resist), intermediate susceptible strains (int_susc) and highly susceptible strains (hlg_susc) are shown. Pairwise comparisons: int_susc-hlg_susc: intermediate susceptible versus highly susceptible strains, etc.; diff: difference between means of log2 viral load, p adj: adjusted p-value using Tukey HSD test. n&#x02009;=&#x02009;41. (DOCX 52&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_MOESM6_ESM.docx" id="MOESM6"><label>Additional file 6: Table S6.</label><caption><p>Average scoring of numbers of granulocytes and alveolar macrophages in C57BL/6&#x000a0;J, 129S1/SvImJ and CAST/EiJ lungs on day 5 after infection with H3N2 influenza virus from the histopathological study. (DOCX 53&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_MOESM7_ESM.jpg" id="MOESM7"><label>Additional file 7: Figure S1.</label><caption><p>Gene expression changes of inflammatory genes induced by influenza infection in 129S1/SvImJ, C56BL/6J, PWK/PhJ and CAST/EiJ lungs. Elevated gene expression levels of selected cytokines and chemokines in 129S1/SvImJ, C56BL/6J, PWK/PhJ and CAST/EiJ reflect influenza A infection. Expression values represent normalized log<sub>2</sub> transformed signal intensities at different time points p.i. relative to expression levels in mock-infected control mice. (JPG 713&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_MOESM8_ESM.jpg" id="MOESM8"><label>Additional file 8: Figure S2.</label><caption><p>Gene expression changes of inflammatory genes induced by influenza infection in 129S1/SvImJ, C56BL/6J, PWK/PhJ and CAST/EiJ blood. Elevated gene expression levels of selected cytokines and chemokines in 129S1/SvImJ, C56BL/6J, PWK/PhJ and CAST/EiJ reflect influenza A infection. Expression values represent normalized log<sub>2</sub> transformed signal intensities at different time points p.i. relative to expression levels in mock-infected control mice. (JPG 715&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_MOESM9_ESM.jpg" id="MOESM9"><label>Additional file 9: Figure S3.</label><caption><p>Gene expression changes of genes up-regulated in 129S1/SvImJ and C56BL/6J but not in CAST/EiJ in blood. Changes in the expression levels of probe sets that were up-regulated in 129S1/SvImJ and C56BL/6J but not in CAST/EiJ mice. Expression values represent normalized log<sub>2</sub> transformed signal intensities at different time points p.i. relative to expression levels in mock-infected control mice. (JPG 395&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_MOESM10_ESM.jpg" id="MOESM10"><label>Additional file 10: Figure S4.</label><caption><p>Gene expression of selectins in lungs. Expression values represent normalized log<sub>2</sub> transformed signal intensities at different time points p.i. relative to expression levels in mock-infected control mice. Probeset ID Sele: A_51_P455326 (JPG 652&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2483_MOESM11_ESM.docx" id="MOESM11"><label>Additional file 11: Table S7.</label><caption><p>Marker descriptions of immune cells that were studied in the DCQ analysis. (DOCX 54&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p>The authors declare that they do not have any conflict of interests.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; contributions</bold></p><p>SRL, CP, HK, RB and KS conceived and designed the experiments. SRL, CP infected the mice, RG performed the array analysis. SRL, HK, KS performed the analysis of the data. LD performed the flow cytometry analysis. JMAvdB and TK performed the histology analysis. HK, SRL and KS wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; information</bold></p><p>Heike Kollmus and Klaus Schughart contributed equally as last authors.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>This work was supported by intra-mural grants from the Helmholtz-Association (Program Infection and Immunity) and a research grant FluResearchNet (No. 01KI07137) from the German Ministry of Education and Research to KS. The PhD work of SRL was partially financed by a scholarship from the &#x0201c;Gesellschaft der Freunde der Tier&#x000e4;rztlichen Hochschule Hannover e. V.&#x0201d;. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p><p>We wish to thank Kirsten Marlen Kleemann for maintaining the CC founder colony, Stefanie Edler for excellent technical assistance, Esther Wilk for advice on immune cell phenotyping, Peter van Run, Viroscience lab, Erasmus Medical Center, Rotterdam for support with histological studies, and Irit Gat-Viks and Yael Steuerman, Cell Research and Immunology Department, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv, Israel for help with digital cell quantification. Part of this work has been performed as PhD thesis work (SRL) at the University of Veterinary Medicine, Hannover.</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fauci</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal and pandemic influenza preparedness: science and countermeasures</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2006</year><volume>194</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>S73</fpage><lpage>S76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/507550</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17163392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17163392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klenk</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Garten</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Matrosovich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of interspecies transmission and pathogenicity of influenza viruses: Lessons from the 2009 pandemic</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><year>2011</year><volume>33</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bies.201000118</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21319184?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21319184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilbourne</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza pandemics of the 20th century</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1201.051254</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16494710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16494710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genesis of a pandemic influenza virus</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>123</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2005.10.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16269328?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16269328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Updating the accounts: global mortality of the 1918&#x02013;1920 &#x0201c;Spanish&#x0201d; influenza pandemic</article-title><source>Bull Hist Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>76</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1353/bhm.2002.0022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11875246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11875246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bautista</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chotpitayasunondh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Uyeki</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical aspects of pandemic 2009 influenza A (H1N1) virus infection</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>362</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>1708</fpage><lpage>1719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1000449</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20445182?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20445182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faruqui</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukundan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2009 pandemic influenza: a review</article-title><source>Curr Opin Pediatr</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>530</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOP.0b013e32833bb81a</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20601883?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20601883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albright</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Orlando</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavia</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannon Albright</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for a heritable predisposition to death due to influenza</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>197</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/524064</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18171280?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18171280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottfredsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Halldorsson</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristjansson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristjansson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristinsson</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lessons from the past: familial aggregation analysis of fatal pandemic influenza (Spanish flu) in Iceland in 1918</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1303</fpage><lpage>1308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0707659105</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18216264?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18216264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudoyo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Viprakasit</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thai</surname><given-names>PQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>What is the evidence of a role for host genetics in susceptibility to influenza A/H5N1?</article-title><source>Epidemiol Infect</source><year>2010</year><volume>138</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268810000518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19698212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Heise</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative genetics in the study of virus-induced disease</article-title><source>Adv Virus Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-800098-4.00004-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24373313?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24373313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuniga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Buendia-Roldan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Romo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic variants associated with severe pneumonia in A/H1N1 influenza infection</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2012</year><volume>39</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>604</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00020611</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21737555?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21737555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kollmus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schughart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systems biology and systems genetics-novel innovative approaches to study host-pathogen interactions during influenza infection</article-title><source>Curr Opin Virol</source><year>2014</year><volume>6C</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coviro.2014.03.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24769047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>To</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host genes and influenza pathogenesis in humans: an emerging paradigm</article-title><source>Curr Opin Virol</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coviro.2015.04.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26079652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26079652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schughart K, Libert C, Kas MJ: Controlling complexity: the clinical relevance of mouse complex genetics. Eur J Hum Genet 2013:10.1038/ejhg.2013.1079.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo-Manuel DeVillena</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Threadgill</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The polymorphism architecture of mouse genetic resources elucidated using genome-wide resequencing data: implications for QTL discovery and systems genetics</article-title><source>Mamm Genome</source><year>2007</year><volume>18</volume><issue>6&#x02013;7</issue><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00335-007-9045-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17674098?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17674098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Robledo</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bult</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Paigen</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Svenson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mouse as a model for human biology: a resource guide for complex trait analysis</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17173058?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17173058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chesler</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Manly</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WebQTL: rapid exploratory analysis of gene expression and genetic networks for brain and behavior</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2004</year><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn0504-485</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15114364?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15114364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchner</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadeau</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contrasting genetic architectures in different mouse reference populations used for studying complex traits</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>25</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.187450.114</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25953951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25953951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solberg Woods</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QTL mapping in outbred populations: successes and challenges</article-title><source>Physiol Genomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiolgenomics.00127.2013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24326347?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24326347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The future of mouse QTL mapping to diagnose disease in mice in the age of whole-genome association studies</article-title><source>Annu Rev Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.genet.42.110807.091659</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18759635?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18759635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iraqi</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Athamni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salymah</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nashif</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heritability and coefficient of genetic variation analyses of phenotypic traits provide strong basis for high-resolution QTL mapping in the Collaborative Cross mouse genetic reference population</article-title><source>Mamm Genome</source><year>2014</year><volume>25</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00335-014-9503-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24445421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24445421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marquis</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of resistance to infections in mice: A/J meets C57BL/6&#x000a0;J</article-title><source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>321</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18727486?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18727486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Malo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquis</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forward genetic dissection of immunity to infection in the mouse</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.immunol.26.021607.090304</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17953509?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17953509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Collaborative Cross Consortium</collab></person-group><article-title>The genome architecture of the collaborative cross mouse genetic reference population</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2012</year><volume>190</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.111.132639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22345608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodstadt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Danecek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yalcin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mouse genomic variation and its effect on phenotypes and gene regulation</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2011</year><volume>477</volume><issue>7364</issue><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10413</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21921910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21921910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aylor</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdar</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Foulds-Mathes</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Buus</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdugo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baric</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of complex traits in the emerging Collaborative Cross</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1213</fpage><lpage>1222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.111310.110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21406540?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21406540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathes</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Aylor</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chesler</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>De Villena</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Architecture of energy balance traits in emerging lines of the Collaborative Cross</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2011</year><volume>300</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>E1124</fpage><lpage>E1134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00707.2010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21427413?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21427413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vered</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Durrant</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Iraqi</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Susceptibility to klebsiella pneumonaie infection in collaborative cross mice is a complex trait controlled by at least three loci acting at different time points</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>865</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-865</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25283706?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25283706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelada</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Aylor</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavarez</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Buus</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of hematological parameters in incipient lines of the collaborative cross</article-title><source>G3 (Bethesda)</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.111.001776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22384394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gralinski</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitmore</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic Profiling of Collaborative Cross Founder Mice Infected with Respiratory Viruses Reveals Novel Transcripts and Infection-Related Strain-Specific Gene and Isoform Expression</article-title><source>G3 (Bethesda)</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1429</fpage><lpage>1444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.114.011759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24902603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rasmussen AL, Okumura A, Ferris MT, Green R, Feldmann F, Kelly SM, et al. Host genetic diversity enables Ebola hemorrhagic fever pathogenesis and resistance. Science. 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogala</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gooch</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Collaborative Cross as a Resource for Modeling Human Disease: CC011/Unc, a New Mouse Model for Spontaneous Colitis</article-title><source>Mamm Genome</source><year>2014</year><volume>25</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00335-013-9499-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24487921?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24487921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Aylor</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottomly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitmore</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Aicher</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modeling host genetic regulation of influenza pathogenesis in the collaborative cross</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003196</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23468633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23468633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pommerenke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Novoselova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Geffers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global transcriptome analysis in influenza-infected mouse lungs reveals the kinetics of innate and adaptive host immune responses</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0041169</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22815957?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22815957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altboum</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Steuerman</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett-Itzhaki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Valadarsky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Keren-Shaul</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Digital cell quantification identifies global immune cell dynamics during influenza infection</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>720</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/msb.134947</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24586061?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24586061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bottomly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Aicher</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitmore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aylor</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression quantitative trait Loci for extreme host response to influenza a in pre-collaborative cross mice</article-title><source>G3 (Bethesda)</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.111.001800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22384400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pothlichet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Skamene</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Loredo-Osti</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sladek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping of clinical and expression quantitative trait loci in a sex-dependent effect of host susceptibility to mouse-adapted influenza H3N2/HK/1/68</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2012</year><volume>188</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3949</fpage><lpage>3960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1103320</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22427645?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22427645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elevated 17beta-estradiol protects females from influenza A virus pathogenesis by suppressing inflammatory responses</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002149</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21829352?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Arck</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex, immunity and influenza</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>209</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><fpage>S93</fpage><lpage>S99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiu020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24966196?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24966196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bluestone</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The NOD mouse: a model of immune dysregulation</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2005</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.immunol.23.021704.115643</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15771578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15771578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Muraoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tochino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breeding of a non-obese, diabetic strain of mice</article-title><source>Jikken dobutsu Experimental animals</source><year>1980</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><?supplied-pmid 6995140?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6995140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lew</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shortman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOD mice are functionally deficient in the capacity of cross-presentation</article-title><source>Immunol Cell Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>93</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/icb.2014.119</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25601275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25601275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Garden</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced regulatory T cell diversity in NOD mice is linked to early events in the thymus</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2014</year><volume>192</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>4145</fpage><lpage>4152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1301600</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24663675?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24663675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suwanai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Benoist</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A defective Il15 allele underlies the deficiency in natural killer cell activity in nonobese diabetic mice</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>9305</fpage><lpage>9310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1004492107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20439722?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20439722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Longacre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cytokine dysregulation induced by apoptotic cells is a shared characteristic of macrophages from nonobese diabetic and systemic lupus erythematosus-prone mice</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2004</year><volume>172</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>4834</fpage><lpage>4843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.172.8.4834</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15067061?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15067061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leclerc</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannenbaum</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diabetes and the severity of pandemic influenza A (H1N1) infection</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2010</year><volume>33</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1491</fpage><lpage>1493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc09-2215</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20587722?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20587722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindenmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lance</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The resistance of A2G mice to myxoviruses</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1963</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>942</fpage><?supplied-pmid 14050204?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14050204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staeheli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grob</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutcliffe</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza virus-susceptible mice carry Mx genes with a large deletion or a nonsense mutation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1988</year><volume>8</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>4518</fpage><lpage>4523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.8.10.4518</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2903437?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2903437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatesuer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nedelko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schughart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protection from Severe Influenza Virus Infections in Mice Carrying the Mx1 Influenza Virus Resistance Gene Strongly Depends on Genetic Background</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2015</year><volume>89</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>9998</fpage><lpage>10009</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01305-15</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26202236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26202236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>von der Malsburg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Faelber</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroder</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure of myxovirus resistance protein a reveals intra- and intermolecular domain interactions required for the antiviral function</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2011</year><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2011.07.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21962493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21962493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patzina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural requirements for the antiviral activity of the human MxA protein against Thogoto and influenza A virus</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2014</year><volume>289</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>6020</fpage><lpage>6027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M113.543892</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24448803?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24448803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dengler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatesuer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schughart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellular changes in blood indicate severe respiratory disease during influenza infections in mice</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>7</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103149</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25058639?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25058639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Blazejewska</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hessmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruder</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Geffers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Host genetic background strongly influences the response to influenza a virus infections</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004857</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19293935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19293935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Boon AC, Finkelstein D, Zheng M, Liao G, Allard J, Klumpp K, Webster R, Peltz G, Webby RJ: H5N1 Influenza Virus Pathogenesis in Genetically Diverse Mice Is Mediated at the Level of Viral Load. MBio 2011, <bold>2</bold> (5):pii: e00171-00111.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Crotta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenic potential of interferon alphabeta in acute influenza infection</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>3864</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms4864</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24844667?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24844667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillippi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenarcic</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using the emerging Collaborative Cross to probe the immune system</article-title><source>Genes Immun</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/gene.2013.59</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24195963?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24195963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Earl</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Americo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lethal monkeypox virus infection of CAST/EiJ mice is associated with a deficient gamma interferon response</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2012</year><volume>86</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>9105</fpage><lpage>9112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00162-12</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22696658?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22696658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uetani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiroi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meguro</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamisako</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohmori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influenza A virus abrogates IFN-gamma response in respiratory epithelial cells by disruption of the Jak/Stat pathway</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>38</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1559</fpage><lpage>1573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/eji.200737045</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18493979?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18493979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crotta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahlakoiv</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Desmet</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckwalter</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Type I and type III interferons drive redundant amplification loops to induce a transcriptional signature in influenza-infected airway epithelia</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><issue>11</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003773</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24278020?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24278020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koerner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalinke</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Staeheli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective role of beta interferon in host defense against influenza A virus</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2007</year><volume>81</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2025</fpage><lpage>2030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01718-06</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17151098?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17151098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mordstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Neugebauer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ditt</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Falcone</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lambda interferon renders epithelial cells of the respiratory and gastrointestinal tracts resistant to viral infections</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2010</year><volume>84</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>5670</fpage><lpage>5677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00272-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20335250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20335250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolaczkowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neutrophil recruitment and function in health and inflammation</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri3399</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23435331?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23435331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herbold</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Maus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Christman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Importance of CXC chemokine receptor 2 in alveolar neutrophil and exudate macrophage recruitment in response to pneumococcal lung infection</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2010</year><volume>78</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2620</fpage><lpage>2630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01169-09</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20368349?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20368349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Monoclonal antibody against CXCL-10/IP-10 ameliorates influenza A (H1N1) virus induced acute lung injury</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2013.25</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23419516?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23419516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balamayooran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Batra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Worthen</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Penn</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of CXCL5 in leukocyte recruitment to the lungs during secondhand smoke exposure</article-title><source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>47</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1165/rcmb.2011-0260OC</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22362385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22362385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Reng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Altered Th1/Th2 commitment contributes to lung senescence in CXCR3-deficient mice</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><year>2013</year><volume>48</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exger.2013.04.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23583952?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23583952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Strahan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Horiuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Walcheck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leukocyte ADAM17 regulates acute pulmonary inflammation</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019938</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21603616?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21603616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harp</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Onami</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Naive T cells re-distribute to the lungs of selectin ligand deficient mice</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010973</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20532047?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20532047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochetkova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Callis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Riccardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The absence of lymphoid CD8+ dendritic cell maturation in L-selectin&#x02212;/&#x02212; respiratory compartment attenuates antiviral immunity</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>181</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1345</fpage><lpage>1356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.181.2.1345</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18606689?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18606689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schelling</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for endothelial selectins in allergic and nonallergic inflammatory disease</article-title><source>Annals of allergy, asthma &#x00026; immunology : official publication of the American College of Allergy, Asthma, &#x00026; Immunology</source><year>2007</year><volume>98</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1081-1206(10)60864-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Etzioni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leukocyte adhesion deficiencies</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>1250</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2011.06389.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22276660?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22276660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Klauschen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuchen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Germain</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systems analysis identifies a feedforward inflammatory circuit leading to lethal influenza infection</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2013</year><volume>154</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.06.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23827683?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23827683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tumpey</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Sastre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Taubenberger</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Palese</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Swayne</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantin-Jackwood</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pathogenicity of influenza viruses with genes from the 1918 pandemic virus: functional roles of alveolar macrophages and neutrophils in limiting virus replication and mortality in mice</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2005</year><volume>79</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>14933</fpage><lpage>14944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.79.23.14933-14944.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16282492?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16282492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meirovitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirshoren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulvik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Versatile role of heparanase in inflammation</article-title><source>Matrix biology: journal of the International Society for Matrix Biology</source><year>2013</year><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matbio.2013.02.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23499528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Iozzo</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heparanase: multiple functions in inflammation, diabetes and atherosclerosis</article-title><source>Matrix biology: journal of the International Society for Matrix Biology</source><year>2013</year><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matbio.2013.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23499526</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodall</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Phipps</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagler</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mice deficient in heparanase exhibit impaired dendritic cell migration and reduced airway inflammation</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><year>2014</year><volume>44</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1016</fpage><lpage>1030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/eji.201343645</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24532362?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24532362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arikawa-Hirasawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishino</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nonaka</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Francomano</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural and functional mutations of the perlecan gene cause Schwartz-Jampel syndrome, with myotonic myopathy and chondrodysplasia</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>70</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1368</fpage><lpage>1375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/340390</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11941538?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11941538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iozzo</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perlecan: a gem of a proteoglycan</article-title><source>Matrix biology: journal of the International Society for Matrix Biology</source><year>1994</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0945-053X(94)90183-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7921536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kallunki</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Byers</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kestila</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shows</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tryggvason</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning of human heparan sulfate proteoglycan core protein, assignment of the gene (HSPG2) to 1p36.1----p35 and identification of a BamHI restriction fragment length polymorphism</article-title><source>Genomics</source><year>1991</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0888-7543(91)90147-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1685141?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1685141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laguri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Arenzana-Seisdedos</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lortat-Jacob</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationships between glycosaminoglycan and receptor binding sites in chemokines-the CXCL12 example</article-title><source>Carbohydr Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>343</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2018</fpage><lpage>2023</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carres.2008.01.047</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18334249?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18334249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurrer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachmann</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interleukin-1 is responsible for acute lung immunopathology but increases survival of respiratory influenza virus infection</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2005</year><volume>79</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>6441</fpage><lpage>6448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.79.10.6441-6448.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15858027?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15858027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karlstetter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walczak</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigelt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Brulle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The novel activated microglia/macrophage WAP domain protein, AMWAP, acts as a counter-regulator of proinflammatory response</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2010</year><volume>185</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3379</fpage><lpage>3390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.0903300</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20709948?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20709948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavassani</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Connett</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunkel</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CCR6 as a mediator of immunity in the lung and gut</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>317</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>619</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yexcr.2010.12.018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21376174?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21376174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lungkine, a novel CXC chemokine, specifically expressed by lung bronchoepithelial cells</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1999</year><volume>162</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>5490</fpage><lpage>5497</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10228029?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10228029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pease</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabroe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of interleukin-8 and its receptors in inflammatory lung disease: implications for therapy</article-title><source>American journal of respiratory medicine: drugs, devices, and other interventions</source><year>2002</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03257159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sallusto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanzavecchia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of chemokine receptors in primary, effector, and memory immune responses</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.immunol.18.1.593</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10837070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10837070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerszten</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Zepeda</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimbrone</surname><given-names>MA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MCP-1 and IL-8 trigger firm adhesion of monocytes to vascular endothelium under flow conditions</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>398</volume><issue>6729</issue><fpage>718</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/19546</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10227295?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10227295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patrussi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Capitani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannizzaro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Finetti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucherini</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelicci</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Negative regulation of chemokine receptor signaling and B-cell chemotaxis by p66Shc</article-title><source>Cell death &#x00026; disease</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cddis.2014.44</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elsner</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgarth</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single and coexpression of CXCR4 and CXCR5 identifies CD4 T helper cells in distinct lymph node niches during influenza virus infection</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2012</year><volume>86</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>7146</fpage><lpage>7157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.06904-11</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22532671?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22532671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yazdi</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Guarda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Ombrain</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Drexler</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammatory caspases in innate immunity and inflammation</article-title><source>J Innate Immun</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000283688</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20375549?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20375549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acosta-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Napolitani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanzavecchia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sallusto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interleukins 1beta and 6 but not transforming growth factor-beta are essential for the differentiation of interleukin 17-producing human T helper cells</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>942</fpage><lpage>949</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni1496</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17676045?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17676045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luft</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jefford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Luetjens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochrein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Masterman</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maliszewski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-1 beta enhances CD40 ligand-mediated cytokine secretion by human dendritic cells (DC): a mechanism for T cell-independent DC activation</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>168</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.168.2.713</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11777965?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11777965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of interleukin-1 beta (IL-1beta) is a critical component of lung inflammation during influenza A (H1N1) virus infection</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><year>2015</year><volume>87</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1104</fpage><lpage>1112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.24138</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25802122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25802122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sperandio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular basis of leukocyte recruitment and its deficiencies</article-title><source>Mol Immunol</source><year>2013</year><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molimm.2012.11.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23253941?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23253941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnheiter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindenmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural, genetically determined resistance toward influenza virus in hemopoietic mouse chimeras. Role of mononuclear phagocytes</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1979</year><volume>150</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.150.1.117</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 36443?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R_Core_Team: R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria 2013, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org/">http://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutledge</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aylor</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chines</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostrowski</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic Regulation of Zfp30, CXCL1, and Neutrophilic Inflammation in Mouse Lung</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2014</year><volume>198</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>735</fpage><lpage>745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.114.168138</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25114278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25114278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">99. Carlson M: MmAgilentDesign026655.db: Agilent Chips that use Agilent design number 026655 annotation data (chip MmAgilentDesign026655).R package version 2.14.0. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioconductor.org/packages/release/data/annotation/html/MmAgilentDesign026655.db.html">http://www.bioconductor.org/packages/release/data/annotation/html/MmAgilentDesign026655.db.html</ext-link> 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><label>100.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Linear models and empirical bayes methods for assessing differential expression in microarray experiments</article-title><source>Stat Appl Genet Mol Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>Article3</fpage><?supplied-pmid 16646809?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16646809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR101"><label>101.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolstad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dettling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudoit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bioconductor: open software development for computational biology and bioinformatics</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>R80</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2004-5-10-r80</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15461798?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15461798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR102"><label>102.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>affycoretools: Functions useful for those doing repetitive analyses with Affymetrix GeneChips</source><year>2008</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR103"><label>103.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: A practical and powerful apporach to multiple testing</article-title><source>J R Stat Soc</source><year>1995</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>300</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR104"><label>104.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alberts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Viegas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Geffers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Klawonn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression changes in the host response between resistant and susceptible inbred mouse strains after influenza A infection</article-title><source>Microbes Infect</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micinf.2010.01.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20114087?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20114087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR105"><label>105.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>clusterProfiler: an R package for comparing biological themes among gene clusters</article-title><source>OMICS</source><year>2012</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/omi.2011.0118</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22455463?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22455463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR106"><label>106.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Brouwer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathview: an R/Bioconductor package for pathway-based data integration and visualization</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>1830</fpage><lpage>1831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt285</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23740750?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23740750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR107"><label>107.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van den Brand</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stittelaar</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Amerongen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimmelzwaan</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Wit</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Severity of pneumonia due to new H1N1 influenza virus in ferrets is intermediate between that due to seasonal H1N1 virus and highly pathogenic avian influenza H5N1 virus</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2010</year><volume>201</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>993</fpage><lpage>999</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/651132</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20187747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20187747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR108"><label>108.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van den Brand</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stittelaar</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leijten</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Amerongen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Osterhaus</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modification of the ferret model for pneumonia from seasonal human influenza A virus infection</article-title><source>Vet Pathol</source><year>2012</year><volume>49</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0300985811429812</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22262355?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22262355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR109"><label>109.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van den Brand</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stittelaar</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Amerongen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reperant</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>De Waal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Osterhaus</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of temporal and spatial dynamics of seasonal H3N2, pandemic H1N1 and highly pathogenic avian influenza H5N1 virus infections in ferrets</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042343</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22905124?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22905124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR110"><label>110.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grubb</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bult</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogue</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mouse phenome database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>D825</fpage><lpage>D834</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1159</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24243846?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24243846</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>