<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Physiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Physiol. (Lond.)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">tjp</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Physiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-3751</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1469-7793</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Blackwell Science Inc</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4215781</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25172951</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2014.278994</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience: Development/Plasticity/Repair</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ionotropic GABA and glycine receptor subunit composition in human pluripotent stem cell-derived excitatory cortical neurones</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>Owain T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Livesey</surname><given-names>Matthew R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dando</surname><given-names>Owen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bilican</surname><given-names>Bilada</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Haghi</surname><given-names>Ghazal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rajan</surname><given-names>Rinku</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hardingham</surname><given-names>Giles E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chandran</surname><given-names>Siddharthan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kind</surname><given-names>Peter C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wyllie</surname><given-names>David J A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Centre for Integrative Physiology, University of Edinburgh</institution><addr-line>Edinburgh, EH8 9XD, UK</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Centre for Brain Development and Repair, Institute for Stem Cell Biology and Regenerative Medicine, National Centre for Biological Sciences</institution><addr-line>Bangalore, 560065, India</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>Euan MacDonald Centre for MND Research, University of Edinburgh</institution><addr-line>Edinburgh, EH16 4SB, UK</addr-line></aff><aff id="au4"><label>4</label><institution>Patrick Wild Centre, University of Edinburgh</institution><addr-line>Edinburgh, EH8 9XD, UK</addr-line></aff><aff id="au5"><label>5</label><institution>Centre for Clinical Brain Sciences, University of Edinburgh</institution><addr-line>Edinburgh, EH16 4SB, UK</addr-line></aff><aff id="au6"><label>6</label><institution>MRC Centre for Regenerative Medicine, University of Edinburgh</institution><addr-line>Edinburgh, EH16 4SB, UK</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Corresponding author</bold> D. J. A. Wyllie: Centre for Integrative Physiology, University of Edinburgh, Hugh Robson Building, George Square, Edinburgh EH8 9XD, UK. Email: <email>dwyllie1@staffmail.ed.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn><p>O. T. James and M. R. Livesey contributed equally to this work and are listed in alphabetical order.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>592</volume><issue>Pt 19</issue><fpage>4353</fpage><lpage>4363</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2014 The Authors. <italic>The Journal of Physiology</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd on behalf of The Physiological Society.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We have assessed, using whole-cell patch-clamp recording and RNA-sequencing (RNA-seq), the properties and composition of GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors (GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs) and strychnine-sensitive glycine receptors (GlyRs) expressed by excitatory cortical neurons derived from human embryonic stem cells (hECNs). The agonists GABA and muscimol gave EC<sub>50</sub> values of 278 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> and 182 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, respectively, and the presence of a GABA<sub>A</sub>R population displaying low agonist potencies is supported by strong RNA-seq signals for &#x003b1;2 and &#x003b1;3 subunits. GABA<sub>A</sub>R-mediated currents, evoked by EC<sub>50</sub> concentrations of GABA, were blocked by bicuculline and picrotoxin with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 2.7 and 5.1 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, respectively. hECN GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs are predominantly &#x003b3; subunit-containing as assessed by the sensitivity of GABA-evoked currents to diazepam and insensitivity to Zn<sup>2+</sup>, together with the weak direct agonist action of gaboxadol; RNA-seq indicated a predominant expression of the &#x003b3;2 subunit. Potentiation of GABA-evoked currents by propofol and etomidate and the lack of inhibition of currents by salicylidine salycylhydrazide (SCS) indicate expression of the &#x003b2;2 or &#x003b2;3 subunit, with RNA-seq analysis indicating strong expression of &#x003b2;3 in hECN GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs. Taken together our data support the notion that hECN GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs have an &#x003b1;2/3&#x003b2;3&#x003b3;2 subunit composition &#x02013; a composition that also predominates in immature rodent cortex. GlyRs expressed by hECNs were activated by glycine with an EC<sub>50</sub> of 167 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>. Glycine-evoked (500 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) currents were blocked by strychnine (IC<sub>50</sub> = 630 n<sc>m</sc>) and picrotoxin (IC<sub>50</sub> = 197 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>), where the latter is suggestive of a population of heteromeric receptors. RNA-seq indicates GlyRs are likely to be composed of &#x003b1;2 and &#x003b2; subunits.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text position="float"><sec><title>Key points</title><p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>This study reports a functional assessment of the subunit composition of inhibitory ionotropic GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors (GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs) and glycine receptors (GlyRs) expressed by excitatory cortical neurones derived from human embryonic stem cells (hECNs).</p></list-item><list-item><p>GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs expressed by hECNs are predominantly composed of &#x003b1;2/3&#x003b2;3&#x003b3;2 subunits; such a composition is typical of that reported for GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs expressed in rodent embryonic cortex.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Analysis of GlyRs expressed by hECNs indicates they are likely to contain &#x003b1;2 and &#x003b2; subunits &#x02013; a composition in rodents that is associated with a late embryonic/early postnatal period of development.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></boxed-text><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>&#x003b3;-Aminobutyric acid (GABA) type A receptors (GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs) are the principal inhibitory neurotransmitter receptors in the mammalian adult brain. GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs are a pentameric ligand-gated anion channels that can be potentially composed of 19 known subunits (&#x003b1;1&#x02013;6, &#x003b2;1&#x02013;3, &#x003b3;1&#x02013;3, &#x003b4;, &#x003b5;, &#x003c0;, &#x003b8; and &#x003c1;1&#x02013;3), giving rise to a large number of potential receptor stoichiometries (Olsen &#x00026; Sieghart, <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Alongside GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs, strychnine-sensitive glycine receptors (GlyRs) form another major class of pentameric ligand-gated anion channel that can be potentially composed of 5 subunits, &#x003b1;1&#x02013;4 and &#x003b2; (Lynch, <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). GABA<sub>A</sub>R and GlyR subunits are each associated with a high degree of spatial and developmental regulation within the CNS (Malosio <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Laurie <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Fritschy <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Flint <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). In this regard, GABA<sub>A</sub>R composition is currently limited to approximately 30 known variants. Moreover, subunit identity typically imparts various pharmacological specificities to the GABA<sub>A</sub>R complex and, collectively, these properties make GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs a key pharmacological target for a range of neurological disorders (Olsen &#x00026; Sieghart, <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). The increasing knowledge regarding the functions of GlyRs within the developing CNS indicates that these receptors too are likely to be relevant pharmacological targets (Avila <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">2013a</xref>).</p><p>The technological advance in the ability to generate human excitatory cortical neurones (hECNs) from pluripotent stem cells (hPSCs) gives the potential to study human-specific physiology and disease <italic>in vitro</italic>. We have previously reported a protocol that generates cultures of predominantly hECNs by 4 weeks of differentiation from anterior neural precursors derived from various stem cell lines (Bilican <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The translational impact of this technology is ultimately determined by the ability of hECNs to display properties that reflect neurones in their native environment (Yang <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b38" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Sandoe &#x00026; Eggan, <xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Indeed, we have previously identified that hECNs are a useful model to study the maturation of AMPAR composition and the reduction in intracellular Cl<sup>&#x02212;</sup> concentration that is observed in native neuronal development (Livesey <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The present study characterises the likely subunit composition of GABA<sub>A</sub>R and GlyRs expressed by hECNs and illustrates that their subunit composition are likely to be similar to those that have been described for inhibitory ionotropic receptors expressed in immature rodent cortex.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> hECN preparation</title><p>A detailed description of the derivation of hECNs can be found in Bilican <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Briefly, hECNs were differentiated from anterior neural precursors that were derived from the H9 human embryonic stem cell line (WiCell), which was obtained under ethical/IRB approval of the University of Edinburgh. Experiments were carried out on cells that had been differentiated and maintained in culture for 28&#x02013;42 days <italic>in vitro</italic> (DIV), or 49&#x02013;56 DIV. At these time points, around 70% of cells were neuronal (&#x003b2;3-tubulin<sup>+</sup>), with little contamination from neural precursor cells (nestin<sup>+</sup>), astrocytes (GFAP<sup>+</sup>) or GABA-ergic (GAD65/67<sup>+</sup>) interneurons (Bilican <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Livesey <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Neurones were consistent with an excitatory (VGLUT1<sup>+</sup>) identity that also exhibited properties of neurones of the upper and lower layers of the cortex (see Bilican <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Livesey <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Electrophysiology</title><p>The whole-cell patch-clamp configuration was used to record currents from hECNs using an Axon Multiclamp 700B amplifier (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA, USA). Patch electrodes (&#x0223c;4&#x02013;7 M&#x003a9;) were filled with an &#x02018;internal&#x02019; recording solution comprising (in m<sc>m</sc>): potassium gluconate 155, MgCl<sub>2</sub> 2, Na-HEPES 10, Na-PiCreatine 10, Mg<sub>2</sub>-ATP 2 and Na<sub>3</sub>-GTP 0.3, pH 7.3 (300 mOsmol l<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>). Coverslips containing hECNs were placed in the recording chamber, which was superfused with an &#x02018;external&#x02019; recording solution composed of (in m<sc>m</sc>) NaCl 152, KCl 2.8, HEPES 10, CaCl<sub>2</sub> 2, glucose 10, pH 7.3 (320&#x02013;330 mOsmol l<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) using a gravity-feed system at room temperature (20&#x02013;23&#x000b0;C) with a flow rate of approximately 4 ml min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Time for complete bath solution exchange was approximately 5 s, but agonist onset times were dependent on position of perfusion line and cell; the rise-time of agonist-evoked whole-cell currents was &#x0003c; 2 s and all responses were measured at steady state. We observed that faster solution exchange rates were frequently associated with hECNs detaching from coverslips. The &#x02018;external&#x02019; recording solution was supplemented with CNQX (5 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>), <sc>d</sc>-AP5 (50 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>), TTX (300 n<sc>m</sc>), and in the case of GABA<sub>A</sub>R experiments, strychnine (20 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>). Recordings were made at a holding potential of 0 mV (&#x02212;14 mV when corrected for the liquid junction potential), which gave a large driving force (&#x0223c;80 mV), resulting in inward flux of Cl<sup>&#x02212;</sup> ions. Series resistances (<italic>R</italic><sub>s</sub>) were between 10 and 30 M&#x003a9; and compensated between 50 and 80%. Experiments were terminated if series resistance shifted more than 20%.</p><p>Before each experiment, three bath applications of a given concentration of agonist that gave equivalent current amplitudes within 15% of the initial amplitude were obtained to establish a stable response. Similarly, a response to a control concentration of agonist was applied at the end of the recording to ensure stability. Data were only taken if the amplitude of the final control response was within 15% of the initial controls. Selective agonists, antagonists and allosteric modulators were purchased either from Tocris Bioscience (Bristol, UK) or Abcam (Cambridge, UK).</p></sec><sec><title>RNA-sequencing</title><p>For RNA-seq, RNA was isolated from four biological replicates using the Roche HP RNA Isolation kit according to manufacturer's instructions. Total RNA was assessed for quality (Agilent Bionalyzer) and quantity (Invitrogen Qubit) before library preparation. Illumina libraries were prepared from 1 &#x003bc;g of total RNA using TruSeq RNA Sample Prep Kit v2 with a 10 cycle enrichment step as per the manufacturer's recommendations. Final libraries were pooled in equimolar proportions before Illumina sequencing on a HiSeq 2500 platform using 100 base paired-end reads in rapid mode. Raw reads were processed using RTA 1.17.21.3 and Casava 1.8.2 (Illumina). Reads were mapped to the primary assembly of the human reference genome contained in Ensembl release 75. A genome index was built with Bowtie, version 1.0.0; default options; (Langmead <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), and then reads mapped with TopHat, version 2.0.10, (Kim <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>); for TopHat, coverage-based search for junctions was disabled, otherwise default values were used for all options. Gene expression was then estimated with Cufflinks, version 2.2.0, (Trapnell <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Roberts <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) using gene annotations from Ensembl release 75. Cufflinks was run in expression estimation mode only (-G flag), and corrections for multi-read mapping (-u flag) and bias (-b flag) were enabled; otherwise default values were used for all options. Estimates of GABA<sub>A</sub>R and GlyR subunit mRNA expression were then extracted in units of fragments per kilobase of exon per million mapped fragments, and normalised as expression relative to that of the highest expressed subunit.</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>Recordings were low-pass filtered at 2 kHz, digitised at 10 kHz <italic>via</italic> a BNC-2090A (National Instruments, TX, USA) interface, and recorded to computer using the WinEDR V2.7.6 Electrophysiology Data Recorder (J. Dempster, University of Strathclyde, UK, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://spider.science.strath.ac.uk/sipbs/software_ses.htm">http://spider.science.strath.ac.uk/sipbs/software_ses.htm</ext-link>)</p><p>Agonist concentration&#x02013;response curves were fitted individually for each cell using the Hill equation:</p><p><disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="tjp0592-4353-mu1.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>I</italic> is the current response to agonist concentration [A], <italic>n</italic><sub>H</sub> is the Hill coefficient, <italic>I</italic><sub>max</sub> is the maximum current and EC<sub>50</sub> is the concentration of agonist that produces a half-maximal response. Each data point was normalised to the fitted maximum of the concentration&#x02013;response curve, then pooled, averaged and re-fitted again with the same equation, with the maximum and minimum for each curve being constrained to asymptote to 1 and 0, respectively (Frizelle <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Wrighton <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).</p><p>Concentrations of antagonists required to inhibit agonist-evoked responses by 50% (IC<sub>50</sub>) were determined by fitting inhibition curves with the equation:</p><p><disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="tjp0592-4353-mu2.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>n</italic><sub>H</sub> is the Hill coefficient, <italic>I</italic><sub>[B]0</sub> is the predicted current in the absence of antagonist and [B] is the concentration of the antagonist. Data points were again normalised to the fitted maximum, before pooling, averaging and re-fitting as described above.</p><p>Data are presented as mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean (SEM). The number of experimental replicates (cells) is denoted as &#x02018;<italic>n</italic>,&#x02019; while &#x02018;<italic>N</italic>&#x02019; represents number of <italic>de novo</italic> preparations of batches from which &#x02018;<italic>n</italic>&#x02019; is obtained. Statistical analysis was conducted as described in the text with the significance levels indicated as: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 (*), <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 (**) and <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 (***).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor characterisation</title><p>The potency of GABA<sub>A</sub>R agonists varies considerably between GABA<sub>A</sub>R isoforms (Mortensen <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Karim <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Thus, to characterise initially the functional properties of GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs expressed by hECNs (28&#x02013;42 DIV) differentiated from anterior neural precursors derived from H9 human embryonic stem cells (Bilican <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; see Methods) we conducted concentration&#x02013;response experiments using GABA and the GABA<sub>A</sub>R-selective agonist muscimol. We previously established that hECNs robustly respond to GABA at this time point (Livesey <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). After establishing stable control responses to bath applications of GABA (100 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>), or muscimol (300 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>), increasing concentrations of agonist were applied sequentially to generate concentration&#x02013;response curves (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref><italic>A</italic>). Mean EC<sub>50</sub> values for GABA- and muscimol-activated currents were found to be 278 &#x000b1; 11 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 12, <italic>N</italic> = 2) and 182 &#x000b1; 10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 6, <italic>N</italic> = 2), respectively (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref><italic>B</italic>). GABA (EC<sub>50</sub>)-evoked current responses were blocked by GABA<sub>A</sub>R antagonists bicuculline and picrotoxin (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref><italic>C</italic>) in a concentration-dependent manner (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref><italic>D</italic>) giving respective IC<sub>50</sub> values of 2.7 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 5, <italic>N</italic> = 2) and 5.1 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 4, <italic>N</italic> = 2).</p><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Agonist and antagonist pharmacology of hECN GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs</title><p><italic>A</italic>, representative whole-cell current recordings of GABA and muscimol concentration&#x02013;response experiments. Currents were elicited by increasing concentrations of bath applications of GABA and muscimol (3 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> to 3 m<sc>m</sc>) after establishing 3 control GABA-evoked currents as indicated. Calibration bars 250 pA, 100 s. <italic>B</italic>, mean agonist concentration&#x02013;response curves for GABA and muscimol. Mean GABA data: EC<sub>50</sub> = 278 &#x000b1; 11 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, <italic>n</italic><sub>H</sub> = 1.05 &#x000b1; 0.02, <italic>n</italic> = 12, <italic>N</italic> = 2. Mean muscimol data: EC<sub>50</sub> = 182 &#x000b1; 10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>; <italic>n</italic><sub>H</sub> = 0.99 &#x000b1; 0.02; <italic>n</italic> = 6, <italic>N</italic> = 2. <italic>C</italic>, example currents illustrating the inhibition of GABA-evoked responses by increasing concentrations of picrotoxin (upper panel) and bicuculline (lower panel). Calibration bars 250 pA, 100 s. <italic>D</italic>, mean inhibition curves for picrotoxin and bicuculline antagonism of GABA (EC<sub>50</sub>) evoked currents. Mean bicuculline data: IC<sub>50</sub> = 2.7 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>; <italic>n</italic><sub>H</sub> = 0.98 &#x000b1; 0.03; <italic>n</italic> = 5, <italic>N</italic> = 2. Mean picrotoxin data: EC<sub>50</sub> = 5.1 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>; <italic>n</italic><sub>H</sub> = 1.22 &#x000b1; 0.03; <italic>n</italic> = 4, <italic>N</italic> = 2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="tjp0592-4353-f1"/></fig><p>We next performed a series of pharmacological assays to assess the presence of &#x003b3; and/or &#x003b4; subunit-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs. Applications of &#x003b3;-selective allosteric potentiator diazepam (30 n<sc>m</sc> and 3 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) to GABA (EC<sub>10</sub>; 35 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>)-mediated currents potentiated the control GABA response by 10 &#x000b1; 6 % (<italic>P</italic> = 0.1 <italic>vs</italic>. control) and 46 &#x000b1; 10 % (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 <italic>vs</italic>. control, Welch's <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>n</italic> = 17, <italic>N</italic> = 3), respectively, indicating the presence of the &#x003b3; subunit (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2</xref><italic>A</italic>). In contrast, applications of Zn<sup>2+</sup> (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> and 300 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>), which selectively inhibits GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs composed of &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; subunits only (Draguhn <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>), did not inhibit GABA (EC<sub>50</sub>)-evoked currents (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, 6 &#x000b1; 3 %, <italic>P</italic> = 0.053 <italic>vs</italic>. control; 300 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, 11 &#x000b1; 5 %, <italic>P</italic> = 0.052 <italic>vs</italic>. control; unpaired <italic>t</italic> tests; <italic>n</italic> = 9, <italic>N</italic> = 1; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2</xref><italic>B</italic>). Furthermore, the potent &#x003b4;-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>R-selective agonist gaboxadol (3 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> and 300 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>; Storustovu &#x00026; Ebert, <xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) gave only nominal currents (6.0 &#x000b1; 2.3% and 14.6 &#x000b1; 3.7%; both data <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 <italic>vs</italic>. GABA (3 m<sc>m</sc>); unpaired <italic>t</italic> tests; <italic>n</italic> = 6&#x02013;7, <italic>N</italic> = 1, respectively) compared to the maximum response that could be elicited by GABA (3 m<sc>m</sc>; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2</xref><italic>C</italic>), confirming that a population of GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs that contain &#x003b4; subunits is negligibly expressed. We confirmed that the low potency of GABA we observed was not a consequence of the specific culture conditions that we employed. Indeed GABA potency was not influenced by the culture of hECNs in atmospheric O<sub>2</sub> 48 h prior to recording (222 &#x000b1; 13 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, <italic>n</italic> = 3, <italic>N</italic> = 1), the absence of brain-derived neurotrophic factor and glial cell-derived neurotrophic factor media supplements (222 &#x000b1; 36 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, <italic>n</italic> = 5, <italic>N</italic> = 2), or maintaining hECNs for extended (49&#x02013;56 DIV) culture periods (204 &#x000b1; 17 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, <italic>n</italic> = 5, <italic>N</italic> = 2). Moreover, even for hECNs maintained for extended culture periods gaboxadol (300 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>)-evoked currents remained very low (9.7 &#x000b1; 4.1 %, <italic>n</italic> = 4, <italic>N</italic> = 1) with respect to GABA-evoked currents and indicated that hECNs maintained in culture for prolonged time periods (49&#x02013;56 DIV) did not begin to express a &#x003b4;-containing receptor population.</p><fig id="fig02" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Modulation of hECN GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs by diazepam, Zn<sup>2+</sup> and gaboxadol</title><p><italic>A</italic>, left panel: representative whole-cell recording depicting the co-application of diazepam (30 n<sc>m</sc> and 3 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, as indicated by bars) to control GABA-evoked responses. <italic>A</italic>, right panel: modulation of GABA<sub>A</sub>R-mediated currents by diazepam (30 n<sc>m</sc> and 3 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, <italic>n</italic> = 17, <italic>N</italic> = 3). Data are presented as mean percentage modulation with respect to control recordings. No difference was observed between percentage modulation and the batch from which cells were prepared. Calibration bar 50 pA, 50 s. <italic>B</italic>, left panel: example whole-cell recording depicting the co-application of Zn<sup>2+</sup> (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> and 300 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>, as indicated by bars) to control GABA-evoked responses. <italic>B</italic>, right panel: mean percentage modulation of control GABA<sub>A</sub>R-mediated currents by Zn<sup>2+</sup> (<italic>n</italic> = 9, <italic>N</italic> = 1). Calibration bar 100 pA, 50 s. <italic>C</italic>, left panel: example whole-cell recording of GABA (3 m<sc>m</sc>)-evoked currents and gaboxadol (3 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> and 300 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>)-induced currents. <italic>C</italic>, right panel: mean percentage gaboxadol-induced activation of GABA<sub>A</sub>R currents with respect to (w.r.t.) maximum GABA-evoked currents (<italic>n</italic> = 6&#x02013;7, <italic>N</italic> = 1). Calibration bar 500 pA, 50 s.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="tjp0592-4353-f2"/></fig><p>The presence of &#x003b2; subunits in hECN GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs was confirmed by the potentiation by the intravenous anaesthetic propofol (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) of GABA (EC<sub>30</sub>; 120 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>)-evoked currents which resulted in robust potentiation of the control current responses by 144 % &#x000b1; 29 % (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>; <italic>P</italic> = 0.002 <italic>vs</italic>. control, unpaired <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>n</italic> = 8, <italic>N</italic> = 2; Sanna <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>; Hill-Venning <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). Furthermore, direct activation of GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs was observed when propofol (100 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) was applied on its own (98 &#x000b1; 21 % relative to GABA (EC<sub>30</sub>; 120 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>)-evoked control; <italic>n</italic> = 7, <italic>N</italic> = 2; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>A</italic> and <italic>C</italic>). The intravenous anaesthetic etomidate (3 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>), which is selective for &#x003b2;2/3 subunit-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs (Hill-Venning <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>), also potentiated GABA (EC<sub>30</sub>; 120 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>)-evoked currents by 75 &#x000b1; 20 % (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>; <italic>P</italic> = 0.01 <italic>vs</italic>. control, unpaired <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>n</italic> = 6, <italic>N</italic> = 1) while application on its own and at a higher concentration (300 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) directly activated GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs (116 &#x000b1; 23 % relative to GABA (EC<sub>30</sub>; 120 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>)-evoked control; <italic>n</italic> = 6, <italic>N</italic> = 1). Taken together, these data suggest the presence of a large complement of &#x003b2;2/3-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs. The absence of &#x003b2;1-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs was indicated by the fact that the selective inhibitor of &#x003b2;1-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs, SCS (Thompson <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>), failed to antagonise GABA (EC<sub>30</sub>; 120 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>)-evoked currents (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>; SCS <italic>vs</italic>. control, <italic>P</italic> = 0.27 <italic>vs</italic>. control, unpaired <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>n</italic> = 8, <italic>N</italic> = 2).</p><fig id="fig03" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Modulation of hECN GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs by intravenous anesthetics, SCS, furosemide and zolipidem</title><p><italic>A</italic>, upper panel: example trace showing potentiation of GABA-mediated whole-cell currents and direct activation of GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs by propofol. <italic>A</italic>, middle panel: example trace showing potentiation of GABA-mediated whole-cell currents and direct activation of GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs by etomidate. <italic>A</italic>, lower panel: example trace showing lack of inhibition of GABA-mediated whole-cell currents by SCS. Calibration bars: 100 pA, 50 s (upper); 100 pA, 50 s (middle); 250 pA, 50 s (lower). <italic>B</italic>, mean percentage modulation GABA-induced currents by the allosteric modulators propofol (10 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>; <italic>n</italic> = 8, <italic>N</italic> = 2), etomidate (3 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>; <italic>n</italic> = 6, <italic>N</italic> = 1) and SCS (1 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>; <italic>n</italic> = 8, <italic>N</italic> = 2). <italic>C</italic>, mean percentage direct activation propofol and etomidate expressed with respect to control responses to GABA. <italic>D</italic>, upper panel: example trace showing lack of inhibition of GABA-mediated whole-cell currents by furosemide. <italic>D</italic>, lower panel: example trace showing potentiation of GABA-mediated whole-cell currents by zolpidem (<italic>n</italic> = 6&#x02013;8, <italic>N</italic> = 2 for each condition). Calibration bars: 150 pA, 50 s (upper); 100 pA, 50 s (lower). <italic>E</italic>, mean percentage modulation GABA-induced currents by the allosteric modulators furosemide (100 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) and zolpidem (50 n<sc>m</sc> and 500 n<sc>m</sc>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="tjp0592-4353-f3"/></fig><p>As illustrated above GABA-evoked currents are potentiated by diazepam which suggests that &#x003b1;4 and &#x003b1;6 subunits are absent from the GABA<sub>A</sub>R population in hECNs since typically benzodiazepines are active at &#x003b1;1, &#x003b1;2, &#x003b1;3, or &#x003b1;5-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs (Olsen &#x00026; Sieghart, <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). To rule out the possibility of the expression of &#x003b1;4 and &#x003b1;6 subunits, GABA (EC<sub>30</sub>; 120 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>)-elicited currents were shown to be insensitive to the &#x003b1;4/&#x003b1;6 subunit containing GABA<sub>A</sub>R inhibitor furosemide (100 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>; <italic>P</italic> = 0.43 <italic>vs</italic>. control, unpaired <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>n</italic> = 6, <italic>N</italic> = 2; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>D</italic> and <italic>E</italic>; Knoflach <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Wafford <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>). Furthermore, the observed low GABA and muscimol potencies (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref><italic>B</italic>) argues against the expression of &#x003b1;4 and &#x003b1;6 subunits, and also &#x003b1;5 subunits, which typically display high GABA potency (Mortensen <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Karim <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). To identify the nature of the &#x003b1; subunit we examined the actions of zolpidem (50 n<sc>m</sc> and 500 n<sc>m</sc>), which exhibits selectivity for &#x003b1;1-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs with lesser potency at &#x003b1;2- and &#x003b1;3-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs and negligible activity at &#x003b1;5-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs (Sanna <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Co-application of zolpidem to GABA (EC<sub>10</sub>; 35 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>)-evoked currents resulted in only a mild potentiation of control currents (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3</xref><italic>D</italic> and <italic>E</italic>; 50 n<sc>m</sc>: 46 &#x000b1; 10 %; 500 n<sc>m</sc>: 70 &#x000b1; 10 %, <italic>n</italic> = 8, <italic>N</italic> = 2), indicating the majority of the GABA<sub>A</sub>R population expressed by hECNs most likely contain &#x003b1;2 and/or &#x003b1;3 subunits.</p><p>To assess quantitatively the expression of GABA<sub>A</sub>R subunits we examined the relative expression of subunit mRNA transcripts via RNA-seq analysis (35 DIV). Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4</xref><italic>A</italic> shows the relative expression of &#x003b1;, &#x003b2; and &#x003b3; subunits with levels normalised to the highest expressed subunit mRNA (&#x003b2;3). These data are consistent with the pharmacological analysis of GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs expressed by hECNs described above. For &#x003b1; subunits, we found prominent mRNA expression of the &#x003b1;2 and &#x003b1;3 subunits and very little detection of &#x003b1;4 and &#x003b1;6 subunits, whilst the &#x003b1;1 and &#x003b1;5 subunit mRNAs were expressed to a moderate extent. The &#x003b2;3 subunit is prominently expressed over &#x003b2;1 and &#x003b2;2 subunits. Pharmacological data do not point to the identity of the &#x003b3; subunit(s) that are functionally expressed by hECNs; however, the RNA-seq data indicate the strongest expression of the &#x003b3;2 subunit mRNA. In agreement with the pharmacological analysis, levels of &#x003b4; subunit mRNA expression were considered to be nominal.</p><fig id="fig04" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>RNA-seq analysis of GABA<sub>A</sub>R and GlyR subunits</title><p><italic>A</italic>, mean human GABA<sub>A</sub>R subunit mRNA estimated abundances (<italic>N</italic> = 4) derived from RNA-seq analysis of hECNs (DIV 35). Data are normalised to the largest mRNA signal (&#x003b2;3 subunit). The relative expression of other GABA<sub>A</sub>R subunits (&#x003b5;, &#x003c0;, &#x003b8; and &#x003c3;) gave signals that were considered to reflect the absence of mRNA for these subunits. <italic>B</italic>, RNA-seq analysis human GlyR subunits as described in <italic>A</italic>. Data are normalised as expression relative to &#x003b1;2 subunit mRNA signal.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="tjp0592-4353-f4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Strychnine-sensitive glycine receptor characterisation</title><p>GlyR characterisation was initially performed with RNA-seq analysis of GlyR subunit mRNA transcripts in hECNs (35 DIV; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4</xref><italic>B</italic>). Both &#x003b1;2 and &#x003b2; subunits are abundantly expressed at the mRNA level, whilst &#x003b1;1 and &#x003b1;3 subunits are only nominally or weakly expressed, respectively, relative to the &#x003b1;2 subunit. As expected, the presence of &#x003b1;4 subunit mRNA was not detected given its status as a pseudogene in humans (Lynch, <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>Functional expression of GlyRs was examined by the ability of hECNs (7&#x02013;35 DIV) to respond to bath applications of glycine (500 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>). With increasing periods following differentiation the mean GlyR-mediated current density profile displays a marked increase (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">5</xref><italic>A</italic>; 3.3 &#x000b1; 2.2 pA pF<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> to 49.4 &#x000b1; 8.4 pA pF<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, unpaired <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>n</italic> = 7, <italic>N</italic> = 2), indicating a strong temporal up-regulation of functional GlyRs expressed by hECNs. Furthermore by 28 DIV all cells examined gave currents (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">5</xref><italic>A</italic>) and in all cases examined these were blocked by the GlyR antagonist strychnine (20 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>).</p><fig id="fig05" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Agonist and antagonist pharmacology of hECN GlyRs</title><p><italic>A</italic>, weekly percentage response to bath applications of glycine and the mean glycine-mediated current density. <italic>n</italic> = 25&#x02013;31, <italic>N</italic> = 3. <italic>B</italic>, representative whole-cell current recordings of glycine concentration&#x02013;response experiments. Currents were elicited by increasing concentrations of glycine after establishment of 3 control glycine-evoked currents. Calibration bar 125 pA, 50 s. <italic>C</italic>, mean (&#x000b1; SEM) agonist concentration&#x02013;response curve for glycine. Mean glycine data: EC<sub>50</sub> = 167 &#x000b1; 20 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>; <italic>n</italic><sub>H</sub> = 1.59 &#x000b1; 0.1; <italic>n</italic> = 7, <italic>N</italic> = 2. <italic>D</italic>, upper panel: example current recording of the inhibition of glycine-evoked (500 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) responses by increasing concentrations of picrotoxin. <italic>D</italic>, lower panel: strychnine inhibition of glycine-evoked (500 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) currents amplitudes. Calibration bars 125 pA, 50 s. <italic>E</italic>, mean inhibition curves for picrotoxin and strychnine antagonism of glycine-evoked currents. Mean picrotoxin data: IC<sub>50</sub> = 197 &#x000b1; 22 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>; <italic>n</italic><sub>H</sub> = 0.9 &#x000b1; 0.06; <italic>n</italic> = 5, <italic>N</italic> = 2. Mean strychnine data: EC<sub>50</sub> = 690 &#x000b1; 59 n<sc>m</sc>; <italic>n</italic><sub>H</sub> = 1.17 &#x000b1; 0.06; <italic>n</italic> = 5, <italic>N</italic> = 2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="tjp0592-4353-f5"/></fig><p>The potency of glycine-evoked currents was assessed by concentration&#x02013;response experiments (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">5</xref><italic>B)</italic>, from which a curve-fitting of mean data yielded an EC<sub>50</sub> of 167 &#x000b1; 20 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">5</xref><italic>C</italic>). Glycine-evoked (500 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc>) currents were blocked fully by strychnine in a concentration-dependent manner with an IC<sub>50</sub> of 630 &#x000b1; 59 n<sc>m</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 5, <italic>N</italic> = 2; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">5</xref><italic>D</italic> and <italic>E</italic>). Note that an increased agonist concentration, rather than the typical EC<sub>50</sub>, was used to elicit suitable current responses to measure antagonist effects. The composition of the expressed GlyRs was probed using picrotoxin, which exhibits selectivity for homomeric over heteromeric GlyR forms, as the inclusion of the &#x003b2; subunit into the GlyR results in a reduction in sensitivity to picrotoxin (Pribilla <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Wang <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Lynch, <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Inhibition of GlyRs by picrotoxin (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">5</xref><italic>D</italic> and <italic>E</italic>) gave an IC<sub>50</sub> of 197 &#x000b1; 22 &#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 5, <italic>N</italic> = 2), indicating the low potency of this antagonist at hECN GlyRs and suggesting that the majority of these receptors are heteromeric assembles contain &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; subunits.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>We have employed a variety of techniques to identify the principal subunit composition of ionotropic GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs and GlyRs expressed by hECNs. The identification of GABA<sub>A</sub>R subunit regulation and expression is relevant to neurodevelopment and neurological disease and thus the ability of hPSC-derived neurones to express GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs that reflect those seen in native neurones is essential if such <italic>in vitro</italic> preparations are to be used for human-specific development and disease modelling.</p><p>Our data establish that the predominant GABA<sub>A</sub>R &#x003b1; subunits expressed by hECNs (DIV 28&#x02013;45) are &#x003b1;2 and/or &#x003b1;3 subunits, which is consistent with an expression profile predominantly exhibited by embryonic rodent cortical neurones (Laurie <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Fritschy <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>). Given that GABA-evoked currents were not inhibited by furosemide, hECN GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs are considered to lack &#x003b1;4 and &#x003b1;6 subunits. Furthermore, the mild modulatory action of zolpidem suggests the absence of the &#x003b1;1 subunit which is perhaps to be expected given that this subunit is associated with a more mature neuronal phenotype (Laurie <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Fritschy <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>). In agreement with our pharmacological analysis, RNA-seq also showed only moderate expression of &#x003b1;1 subunits together with negligible expression of both &#x003b1;4 and &#x003b1;6 subunits compared to the relative abundance of transcripts for both &#x003b1;2 and &#x003b1;3 subunits. We considered that the functional expression of the &#x003b1;5 subunit, which is associated with high agonist potency, was unlikely given the relatively low levels of mRNA detected and the low agonist potencies of GABA and muscimol. Indeed, low potency is indicative of GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs that contain either &#x003b1;2 or &#x003b1;3 subunits (Mortensen <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Karim <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>High expression of the GABA<sub>A</sub>R &#x003b2;3 subunit has been associated with rodent immature cortical neurones (Laurie <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>), though the &#x003b2;2 subunit is often also reported to be substantially expressed in cortical neurones (Fritschy <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>). Potentiation of GABA-evoked currents by the low concentrations of intravenous anaesthetics etomidate and propofol, direct activation by high concentrations of etomidate and propofol, a lack of SCS inhibition and a high level of mRNA expression for the &#x003b2;3 subunit collectively demonstrate that hECNs are likely to predominantly express &#x003b2;3 subunit-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs, although a contribution of &#x003b2;2 to GABA<sub>A</sub>R stoichiometry cannot be ruled out.</p><p>The vast majority of GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs in the CNS are &#x003b3;2 subunit containing (Olsen &#x00026; Sieghart, <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). RNA-seq data indicate that hECNs predominantly express the &#x003b3;2 subunit, in agreement with the pharmacological findings that GABA-evoked currents were potentiated by &#x003b3; subunit-selective diazepam. Subsets of &#x003b4; subunit-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs are selectively expressed by certain cortical adult neuronal phenotypes and importantly are commonly associated with GABA<sub>A</sub>R-mediated tonic inhibition (Olsen &#x00026; Sieghart, <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Nevertheless, our data indicate that hECNs lack &#x003b4; subunit-containing GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs as gaboxadol gave rise to only low amplitude currents compared to those seen with GABA. Furthermore, the finding that Zn<sup>2+</sup> did not inhibit GABA-evoked currents is consistent with the absence of GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs containing <italic>only</italic> &#x003b1;/&#x003b2; subunits.</p><p>We have demonstrated that both RNA-seq analysis and selective GABA<sub>A</sub>R pharmacology converge on a predominant GABA<sub>A</sub>R composition of &#x003b1;2/3&#x003b2;3&#x003b3;2. Such isoforms are observed in recombinant expression systems to have low agonist potency relative to other isoforms and we similarly demonstrate that GABA<sub>A</sub>R expressed upon hECNs exhibit relatively low agonist potency (Karim <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). This GABA<sub>A</sub>R isoform is the most likely to be widely expressed in the immature rodent cortex (Laurie <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Olsen &#x00026; Sieghart, <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Nevertheless, our data cannot rule out the presence of other GABA<sub>A</sub>R isoforms expressed at a low level. However, inspection of Brainspan (Atlas of the Developing Human Brain <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.brainspan.org/rnaseq/search">http://www.brainspan.org/rnaseq/search</ext-link>) indicates that the levels of mRNA we report from the RNA-seq analysis of hECNs (35 DIV) are qualitatively similar to those seen in human cortical neurones between 12 and 21 weeks post conception. Thus, hECNs provide a system to investigate the properties of human GABA<sub>A</sub>R pharmacology and furthermore permit investigation of the role of GABA<sub>A</sub>Rs in the maturing cortical neurones (Wang &#x00026; Kriegstein, <xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>In rodents, transient functional GlyR expression is a key feature of early neocortical development (Flint <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Avila <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">2013a</xref>). Indeed, hECNS maintained for 28&#x02013;42 DIV exhibited strong responses to glycine that were blocked by the GlyR antagonist strychnine. Glycine concentration&#x02013;response experiments indicated glycine potency was lower than previously reported recombinant values (Pribilla <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>) but is generally higher than glycine potencies observed in native cortical preparations (Flint <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Okabe <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Kilb <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; but see Avila <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">2013b</xref>). The reasons for these differences are unknown, but may be related to systematic differences in the solution exchange times of these studies, where slower exchange times are more likely to give shallower observed concentration&#x02013;response curves. In this regard, the ability to examine deactivation kinetics of GlyRs expressed by hECNs in isolated patches using fast agonist application may yield further details of GlyR identity (Mangin <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Pitt <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Krashia <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Marabelli <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>GlyRs expressed by rodent forebrain neurones have been described as developing from an embryonic homomeric to postnatal heteromeric (&#x003b2; subunit-containing) composition (Lynch, <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). To investigate the functional GlyR composition we used the antagonist picrotoxin, which inhibits homomeric over heteromeric GlyRs (Lynch, <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Given the observed low sensitivity of GlyRs to picrotoxin, our results suggest that the principal GlyR identity of hECNs is likely to a heteromeric &#x003b1;/&#x003b2; assembly. Pharmacological tools to identify unambiguously the nature of the &#x003b1; subunit within the heteromer are lacking (but see Han <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>); however, RNA-seq analysis indicates that &#x003b1;2 subunit mRNA is the most abundantly expressed. As is the case for GABA<sub>A</sub>R subunit expression, levels of mRNA expression for GlyRs in our RNA-seq analysis are consistent with a development age of around 12&#x02013;21 weeks post conception (Atlas of the Developing Human Brain <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.brainspan.org/rnaseq/search">http://www.brainspan.org/rnaseq/search</ext-link>). Finally, it is of interest to note that there is transient expression of heteromeric &#x003b1;2/&#x003b2; GlyRs by rodent Cajal&#x02013;Retzius cells in early postnatal development (Okabe <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). This class of neurone is considered to form a significant population in our hECN cultures (Bilican <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and in this respect hECNs may provide a useful human model of GlyR development.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Karim Gharbi and Timothee Cezard (Edinburgh Genomics, University of Edinburgh) for their help in conducting RNA-seq analysis and the members of our lab for their many constructive comments during the course of this study.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avila</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycine receptors and brain development</article-title><source>Front Cell Neurosci</source><year>2013a</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>184</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24155690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avila</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dear</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycine receptor &#x003b1;2 subunit activation promotes cortical interneuron migration</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2013b</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>738</fpage><lpage>750</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23954789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bilican</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Livesey</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Haghi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Siller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardingham</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyllie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological normoxia and absence of EGF is required for the long-term propagation of anterior neural precursors from human pluripotent cells</article-title><source>Plos One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e85932</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24465796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Draguhn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdorn</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeburg</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional and molecular distinction between recombinant rat GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor subtypes by Zn<sup>2+</sup></article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>1990</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1702644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriegstein</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonsynaptic glycine receptor activation during early neocortical development</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>1998</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9459441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fritschy</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Paysan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Enna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Switch in the expression of rat GABA<sub>A</sub>-receptor subtypes during postnatal development: an immunohistochemical study</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1994</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>5302</fpage><lpage>5324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8083738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frizelle</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyllie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Equilibrium constants for (<italic>R</italic>)-[(<italic>S</italic>)-1-(4-bromo-phenyl)-ethylamino]-(2,3-dioxo-1,2,3,4-tetrahydroquino xalin-5-yl)-methyl]-phosphonic acid (NVP-AAM077) acting at recombinant NR1/NR2A and NR1/NR2B <italic>N</italic>-methyl-<sc>d</sc>-aspartate receptors: Implications for studies of synaptic transmission</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>2006</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1022</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16778008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective antagonism of rat inhibitory glycine receptor subunits</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>554</volume><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14645455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill-Venning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Belelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subunit-dependent interaction of the general anaesthetic etomidate with the gamma-aminobutyric acid type A receptor</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>1997</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9138677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karim</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellendorph</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Absalom</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanrahan</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chebib</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potency of GABA at human recombinant GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors expressed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes: a mini review</article-title><source>Amino Acids</source><year>2013</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>1139</fpage><lpage>1149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23385381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilb</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanganu</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Okabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sava</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu-Okabe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Luhmann</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycine receptors mediate excitation of subplate neurons in neonatal rat cerebral cortex</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>698</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18562558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TopHat2: accurate alignment of transcriptomes in the presence of insertions, deletions and gene fusions</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>R36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23618408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knoflach</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Benke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheurer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Luddens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacological modulation of the diazepam-insensitive recombinant &#x003b3;-aminobutyric acid<sub>A</sub> receptors &#x003b1;4&#x003b2;2&#x003b3;2 and &#x003b1;6&#x003b2;2&#x003b3;2</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>1996</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1253</fpage><lpage>1261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8913357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krashia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lape</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lodesani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivilotti</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The long activations of &#x003b1;2 glycine channels can be described by a mechanism with reaction intermediates (&#x0201c;flip&#x0201d;)</article-title><source>J Gen Physiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21282399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>R25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19261174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wisden</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeburg</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The distribution of thirteen GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor subunit mRNAs in the rat brain. III. Embryonic and postnatal development</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1992</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>4151</fpage><lpage>4172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1331359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livesey</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilican</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rzechorzek</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Haghi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardingham</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyllie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maturation of AMPAR composition and the GABA<sub>A</sub>R reversal potential in hPSC-derived cortical neurons</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>4070</fpage><lpage>4075</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24623784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Native glycine receptor subtypes and their physiological roles</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><year>2009</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18721822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malosio</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Marqueze-Pouey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Betz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Widespread expression of glycine receptor subunit mRNAs in the adult and developing rat brain</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1991</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2401</fpage><lpage>2409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1651228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mangin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baloul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Prado De Carvalho</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogister</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Legendre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetic properties of the &#x003b1;2 homo-oligomeric glycine receptor impairs a proper synaptic functioning</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>553</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12972628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marabelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moroni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lape</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivilotti</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The kinetic properties of the &#x003b1;3 rat glycine receptor make it suitable for mediating fast synaptic inhibition</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>591</volume><fpage>3289</fpage><lpage>3308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23613537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortensen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Smart</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GABA Potency at GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors found in synaptic and extrasynaptic zones</article-title><source>Front Cell Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22319471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilb</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu-Okabe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanganu</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Luhmann</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Homogenous glycine receptor expression in cortical plate neurons and Cajal&#x02013;Retzius cells of neonatal rat cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>2004</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14706783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieghart</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors: subtypes provide diversity of function and pharmacology</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><year>2009</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18760291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivilotti</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Beato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High intracellular chloride slows the decay of glycinergic currents</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>11454</fpage><lpage>11467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18987182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pribilla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Langosch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bormann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Betz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The atypical M2 segment of the beta subunit confers picrotoxinin resistance to inhibitory glycine receptor channels</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1992</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>4305</fpage><lpage>4311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1385113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Donaghey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinn</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving RNA-Seq expression estimates by correcting for fragment bias</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>R22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21410973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandoe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opportunities and challenges of pluripotent stem cell neurodegenerative disease models</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2013</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>780</fpage><lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23799470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanna</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Busonero</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Talani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Carta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Massa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Peis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maciocco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Biggio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the effects of zaleplon, zolpidem, and triazolam at various GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor subtypes</article-title><source>Eur J Pharmacol</source><year>2002</year><volume>451</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12231378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanna</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mascia</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Biggio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Actions of the general anesthetic propofol on recombinant human GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors: influence of receptor subunits</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>1995</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7616420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storustovu</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacological characterization of agonists at &#x003b4;-containing GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors: Functional selectivity for extrasynaptic receptors is dependent on the absence of &#x003b3;2</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>2006</year><volume>316</volume><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16272218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheat</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingrove</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillai</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adkins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wafford</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Salicylidene salicylhydrazide, a selective inhibitor of &#x003b2;1-containing GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>2004</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15100159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>van Baren</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wafford</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sikela</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of human &#x003b3;-aminobutyric acid<sub>A</sub> receptors containing the &#x003b1;4 subunit</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>1996</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>670</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8794909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriegstein</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining the role of GABA in cortical development</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>587</volume><fpage>1873</fpage><lpage>1879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19153158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moonen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Legendre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms for picrotoxin block of &#x003b1;2 homomeric glycine receptors</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>3841</fpage><lpage>3855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16344549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wrighton</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyllie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mg<sup>2</sup><sup>+</sup> and memantine block of rat recombinant NMDA receptors containing chimeric NR2A/2D subunits expressed in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> oocytes</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>586</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17962329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudhof</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wernig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induced neuronal cells: how to make and define a neuron</article-title><source>Cell Stem Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22136927</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec><title>Additional Information</title><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conception and design of the experiments: O.T.J., M.R.L., J.Q., O.D., G.E.H., S.C., P.C.K. and D.J.A.W. Collection, analysis and interpretation of data: O.T.J., M.R.L., J.Q., O.D., B.B., G.H., R.R., K.B. and D.J.A.W. Drafting the article or revising it critically for important intellectual content: O.T.J., M.R.L., O.D., G.E.H., S.C., P.C.K. and D.J.A.W. It is confirmed that all authors approved the final version of the manuscript and that all persons designated as authors qualify for authorship, and all those who qualify for authorship are listed. All experiments were performed in the laboratories of G.E.H., S.C., P.C.K. and D.J.A.W at the University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This research was funded by The Wellcome Trust (Grant 092742/Z/10/Z to D.J.A.W., S.C. and G.E.H.), the Medical Research Council (Senior Non-clinical Research Fellowship to G.E.H.), the Euan MacDonald Centre and the NC3Rs CRACK IT Programme (S.C.) and seedcorn funding from the Patrick Wild Centre/RS Macdonald Trust (P.C.K. and D.J.A.W).</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' present addresses</title><p>G. Haghi: New World Laboratories, 500 Cartier Blvd, Laval, H7V 5B7, Quebec, Canada. B. Bilican: Novartis Institutes for Biomedical Research, 100 Technology Square, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA.</p></sec></sec><glossary><def-list><def-item><term><sc>d</sc>-AP5</term><def><p>(2<italic>R</italic>)-amino-5-phosphonovaleric acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CNQX</term><def><p>6-cyano-7-nitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DIV</term><def><p>days <italic>in vitro</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GABA<sub>A</sub>R</term><def><p>&#x003b3;-aminobutyric acid receptor type A</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GFAP</term><def><p>glial fibrilary acidic protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GlyR</term><def><p>glycine receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>hECN</term><def><p>human excitatory cortical neurone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>hPSC</term><def><p>human pluripotent stem cell</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCR</term><def><p>polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNA-seq</term><def><p>RNA sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VGLUT1</term><def><p>vesicular glutamate transporter 1</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article>