<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5137438</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27596601</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw777</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Gene regulation, Chromatin and Epigenetics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Insights into the regulation of small RNA expression: SarA represses the expression of two sRNAs in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>Tony</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR3"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rouillon</surname><given-names>Astrid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR2">*</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR3"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Felden</surname><given-names>Brice</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="AFF1">Inserm U835, Biochimie Pharmaceutique, University of Rennes 1, 35000 Rennes, France</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +33 2 2323 4851; Fax: +33 2 2323 4456; Email: <email>brice.felden@univ-rennes1.fr</email></corresp><corresp id="COR2">Correspondence may also be addressed to Astrid Rouillon. Tel: +33 2 2323 4394; Fax: +33 2 2323 4456; Email: <email>astrid.rouillon@univ-rennes1.fr</email></corresp><corresp id="COR3"><label>&#x02020;</label>These authors contributed equally to the paper as first authors.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>04</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>44</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>10186</fpage><lpage>10200</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>09</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact <email>journals.permissions@oup.com</email></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="gkw777.pdf"/><abstract><p>The opportunistic pathogen <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> expresses transcription factors (TFs) and regulatory small RNAs (sRNAs) which are essential for bacterial adaptation and infectivity. Until recently, the study of <italic>S. aureus</italic> sRNA gene expression regulation was under investigated, but it is now an expanding field. Here we address the regulation of Srn_3610_SprC sRNA, an attenuator of <italic>S. aureus</italic> virulence. We demonstrate that SarA TF represses <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> transcription. DNase I footprinting and deletion analyses show that the SarA binding site on <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> belongs to an essential 22 bp DNA region. Comparative analysis also revealed another possible site, this time in the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter. SarA specifically binds these two sRNA promoters with high affinity <italic>in vitro</italic> and also represses their transcription <italic>in vivo</italic>. Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assays confirmed SarA attachment to both promoters. ChIP and electrophoretic mobility shift assays targeting &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> RNA polymerase subunit or using bacterial RNA polymerase holoenzyme suggested that SarA and the &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> bind <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoters in a mutually exclusive way. Beyond the mechanistic study of SarA repression of these two sRNAs, this work also suggests that some <italic>S. aureus</italic> sRNAs belong to the same regulon and act jointly in responding to environmental changes.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>01 December 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="SEC1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> is an opportunistic pathogen involved in a wide spectrum of diseases, including but not limited to skin infections, pneumonia, endocarditis, osteomyelitis, indwelling device infections, food poisoning and meningitis (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Approximately 20% of the human population has the bacteria on their skin and nostrils, creating a reservoir of asymptomatic carriers (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). At the same time, infections caused by antibiotic-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains have severely increased, impacting civil and military healthcare systems worldwide (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). <italic>S. aureus</italic> is remarkable in its aggressiveness and in its resistance potential to many antibiotics. Its versatility depends on its ability to sense and respond to environmental changes by modulating gene expression, using transcription factors (TFs) and regulatory small RNAs (sRNAs). The expression of <italic>S. aureus</italic> virulence factors is tightly controlled by multiple regulators, including TFs, two-component systems and sRNAs (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Many of these regulators are therefore essential for infection (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p><p>To start bacterial transcription, direct interaction is required between the RNA polymerase's sigma factors and selected gene promoters. Initiation of RNA synthesis is a highly regulated process involving TFs that bind these gene promoters (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). One of the well-studied TFs in <italic>S. aureus</italic> is SarA, a 14.7-kDa DNA-binding protein acting as a dimer. It is one of 11 members of the SarA protein family, with SarR, SarS, SarT, SarU, SarV, SarX, SarY, SarZ, Rot and MgrA. They all have a winged helix motif (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) that is required for binding AT-rich double-stranded DNA sequences such as promoters (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Directly or indirectly, SarA influences the transcription of at least 120 genes in <italic>S. aureus</italic> (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), and it can either stimulate (with <italic>cna, fnbA, agr, hla, fnta, fnb</italic> and <italic>sec</italic>) or repress (with <italic>sarV, aur, sspa, spa, rot</italic> and <italic>SarS</italic>) target gene expression (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p><p>In addition to TFs, <italic>S. aureus</italic> expresses about 160 regulatory RNAs (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), all recently compiled into a staphylococcal regulatory RNA database (SRD) (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). sRNAs are expressed from both the core and variable accessory genomes, the latter including pathogenicity islands (PIs) and transposons (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Among these <italic>S. aureus</italic> sRNAs, only a handful has identified functions including certain ones that influence staphylococcal virulence in animal models of infection (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). In <italic>S. aureus</italic>, sRNAs usually pair with target mRNAs for regulation, influencing mRNA expression by modulating its degradation and/or its translation (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Not only is the <italic>S. aureus</italic> sRNome poorly described, but little is known about the regulation of its expression. An exception to this is RNAIII, which is directly regulated by AgrA (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) and indirectly by SarA (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). AgrA also directly represses the expression of ArtR sRNA (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), termed &#x02018;Srn_4050&#x02019; in SRD. Conversely, RNAIII and ArtR negatively regulate the Rot and SarT TFs, respectively (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), and RNAIII stabilizes <italic>mgrA</italic> mRNA thereby increasing MgrA TF production (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Since TFs have numerous targets, sRNA regulation of TF expression allows sRNAs to play an important role in adaptation. These few examples highlight the need for investigation into the regulation of <italic>S. aureus</italic> sRNAs.</p><p>The small PI rna C (&#x02018;Srn_3610&#x02019; in the SRD, and referred to herein as &#x02018;Srn_3610_SprC&#x02019;) is located in the &#x003bd;SA&#x003b2; PI (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) which contains several virulence factors. We recently showed that Srn_3610_SprC attenuates <italic>S. aureus</italic> virulence and spread in an animal model of infection (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Those observations imply that its expression must decrease during infection. Interestingly, <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression drastically decreases after host cell internalization. This suggests that the gene's expression is tightly regulated during bacterial infection. Here we therefore investigated the molecular basis of this regulation <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic>, and demonstrated that SarA restrains <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression through its direct interaction with the sRNA promoter. The DNA sequence required for SarA interaction with the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter was uncovered by DNase I footprinting assays and sequential deletions. The sequence was then used <italic>in silico</italic> to search for similarities in the <italic>S. aureus</italic> genome. This led to the identification of <italic>srn_9340</italic>, a second sRNA gene whose expression is repressed by SarA. Chromatin immunoprecipitation assays (ChIP) demonstrated SarA binding onto <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoters in living bacteria. ChIP experiments targeting &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> further revealed that SarA prevents &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> binding onto the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter. Analysis of the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic>/SarA binding sequences and the electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA) data suggested that SarA transcriptional repression is similar for both, with SarA binding the promoter thus preventing &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> binding. In this report, we demonstrate that the SarA TF inhibits transcription of two sRNAs located in the same PI. Such results suggest that these sRNAs have similar functions and belong to a common regulatory network. If applied to other sRNAs, our approach could reveal sRNA clusters regulated by dedicated TFs.</p><p>While sRNAs are key adaptation modulators, to our knowledge, none of them have been described as essential genes in <italic>S. aureus</italic>. This suggests some redundancy in their actions, or a lack of knowledge about when they might be absolutely essential for the bacteria. Therefore, studying sRNA transcriptional regulation could give clues to these key moments, while allowing for the identification of clusters of sRNAs with similar functions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="SEC2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="SEC2-1"><title>Bacterial strains and culture conditions</title><p>Strains, primers and plasmids are listed in Supplementary Tables S1, 2 and 3, respectively. All mutants from the SarA family were obtained through phage transduction from 6390 <italic>S. aureus</italic> deleted strains to strain HG003 (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains were grown at 37&#x000b0;C in LB (MoBio), and 50 &#x003bc;g/ml ampicillin or kanamycin antibiotics were added when necessary. <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains were grown at 37&#x000b0;C in either brain-heart infusion (BHI) medium or tryptic soy broth (TSB; both from Oxoid), with antibiotics added when needed (10 &#x003bc;g/ml erythromycin, chloramphenicol, or tetracycline, or else 250 &#x003bc;g/ml kanamycin). All experiments were done on the HG003 <italic>S. aureus</italic> strain (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), using the RN4220 <italic>S. aureus</italic> strain as an intermediate (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-2"><title>Genetic manipulation</title><sec id="SEC2-2-1"><title>Bioinformatic analysis</title><p>The <italic>S. aureus</italic> NCTC 8325 genome (taxid: 93061) was used for all genetic locations.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-2-2"><title>Reporter gene experiments</title><p>To create pCN41c, the <italic>ermR</italic> erythromycin resistance gene from plasmid pCN41 (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) was replaced by the <italic>cat194</italic> chloramphenicol resistance gene. In pCN41c-P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic>, the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter sequence was amplified from <italic>S. aureus</italic> HG003 genomic DNA using 5&#x02032;_BamHI_P<italic>sprC</italic> and P<italic>sprC</italic>_EcoRI_3&#x02032; primers (Supplementary Table S2) digested and inserted into pCN41c.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-2-3"><title>Complementation studies</title><p>A 1624-bp fragment made up of the SarA endogenous promoter gene and terminator was amplified by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using 5&#x02032;_BamHI_P<italic>sarA</italic> and <italic>sarA_</italic>KpnI_3&#x02032; primers, then inserted into pCN36 (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-2-4"><title>ChIP experiments</title><p>Three PCR steps were required to construct pCN38-SarA6His. The following primers were used: 5&#x02032;_PstI_PsarA; PsarA_BamHI_3&#x02032;; 5&#x02032;_BamHI_sarA; sarA6his_KpnI_3&#x02032;; 5&#x02032;_KpnI_TsarA; and TsarA_KpnI_3&#x02032;. These PCR products were combined to form a 1936-bp fragment containing <italic>sarA</italic> with an in-frame tag made of 6&#x000d7; Histidine (6His) at the 3&#x02032; end of the open reading frame (ORF). The final SarA6His is controlled by its endogenous promoter and terminator.</p></sec></sec><sec id="SEC2-3"><title>RNA isolation</title><p>The protocol for total RNA extraction was adapted from Le Pabic et <italic>al</italic>. (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Overnight cultures of <italic>S. aureus</italic> were diluted to an OD<sub>600 nm</sub> of 0.1 in fresh BHI or TSB broth, then incubated at 37&#x000b0;C and 160 rpm. Hourly, cells were harvested and resuspended in lysis buffer (20 mM sodium acetate, 1 mM ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA), 0.5% sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS), pH 5.5). Cells were broken out using glass beads (Sigma-Aldrich) in a FastPrep 120 cell disrupter (MP Biomedicals). Total RNA were extracted using phenol/chloroform and precipitated in 100% ethanol supplemented with 0.3 M sodium acetate.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-4"><title>Northern blotting</title><p>Total RNA were separated on either denaturing polyacrylamide gels or on agarose gels, then transferred onto Zeta-Probe GT (Bio-Rad) or Nytran membranes (Schleicher &#x00026; Schuell), respectively. All northern blots were revealed using the Digoxigenin method per the manufacturer's instructions (Roche). We used 20 nt probes previously marked with 3&#x02032;-end DIG labeling. Signal acquisition was done using an ImageQuant LAS 4000 imager (GE Healthcare). Approximate quantifications were calculated using the ImageQuant software and normalized against transfer-messenger RNA (tmRNA) or 16S ribosomal RNA.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-5"><title>RNA end mapping by RACE</title><p>Rapid amplification of cDNA end (RACE) experiments were performed as previously described (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). R1 _srn_9340 primers was used to reverse transcribe or Srn_9340 RNA. Two PCR reactions were performed with Taq polymerase (Invitrogen) using R2-F1 and R2-F2 primer pairs, respectively. PCR products were cloned using a pGEM vector system (Promega), transformed in XL1-Blue <italic>E. coli</italic> and sequenced with M13 reverse primer (Invitrogen, ThermoFisher Scientific) using MegaBACE DNA sequencers (Amersham).</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-6"><title>Protein extraction, cell fractionation and western blotting</title><p>For protein extraction throughout bacterial growth, cells were resuspended in lysis buffer (50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl, pH 7.5, 3 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1 mg/ml lysostaphin), incubated for 20 min at 37&#x000b0;C, then kept on ice. As measured with Qubit fluorometric quantification (Invitrogen), equal amounts of total proteins were loaded on 15% polyacrylamide gels. Samples were separated on Tris-Glycine sodium dodecyl sulphate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis gels and transferred onto Hybond P PVDF membranes (Amersham). SarA proteins were revealed using rabbit anti-SarA antibodies. An ECL Prime Western Blotting Detection kit (Amersham) and an ImageQuant LAS 4000 imager were used to reveal proteins. To ensure that equal protein amounts were loaded on each lane, duplicates of these gels were stained with SYPRO Ruby (Bio-Rad) as per the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-7"><title>Functional complementation and reporter gene experiments</title><p>Overnight cultures were adjusted to an OD<sub>600nm</sub> of 0.1. For each time point, cells were centrifuged and resuspended in 1&#x000d7; phosphate-buffered saline to obtain an equal cell density throughout the assay. Cell lysis was performed using 0.7 mg/ml lysostaphin, 0.2 U/&#x003bc;l benzonase and 0.1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> at 37&#x000b0;C for 20 min. After adding 0.25 mg/ml nitrocefin (a &#x000df;-lactamase substrate), &#x000df;-lactamase activity was quantified on a BioTek instrument every 10 min for 40 min at a wavelength of 492 nm. This activity was normalized against protein quantities as determined by a Bradford assay.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-8"><title>Purification of SarA from <italic>E. coli</italic></title><p>The <italic>sarA</italic> coding sequence was inserted into pET42a in-frame with the 6His N-terminal tag (provided by Marc Hallier) and transformed in BL21 <italic>E. coli</italic>. SarA expression was induced by adding 1 mM isopropyl &#x003b2;-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG). Cells were harvested, washed and resuspended in lysis buffer (10 mM HEPES, pH 7.5, 500 mM NaCl). Purification was done as previously described (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-9"><title>Electrophoretic mobility shift assays (EMSA)</title><p>Probes were amplified from the <italic>S. aureus</italic> HG003 genome by PCR using specific primers (<italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub>, 16S<sub>P267</sub>, <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub> and 16S<sub>225</sub>), or obtained by hybridization of complementary oligonucleotides (<italic>sprC</italic><sub>47</sub>, <italic>srn_9340<sub>51</sub>, sprC<sub>30left</sub>, sprC<sub>30middle</sub>, sprC<sub>30right</sub>, srn_9340<sub>30left</sub>, srn_9340<sub>30middle</sub></italic> and <italic>srn_9340<sub>30right</sub></italic>). To construct <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub><italic><sub>&#x00394;</sub></italic><sub>47</sub><italic>, srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub><italic><sub>&#x00394;</sub></italic><sub>51</sub>, <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub><italic><sub>&#x00394;</sub></italic><sub>22</sub> and <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub><italic><sub>&#x00394;</sub></italic><sub>23</sub>, a three-step PCR was necessary. This used the following combinations of four primers: 5&#x02032;_P267<italic>&#x00394;</italic>47<italic>sprc</italic>, P267<italic>&#x00394;</italic>47<italic>sprC</italic>_3&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;_P<italic>sprC</italic> and <italic>sprC_</italic>seq_3&#x02032; for <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub><italic><sub>&#x00394;</sub></italic><sub>47</sub>; 5&#x02032;_P225<italic>&#x00394;</italic>51<italic>srn_9340</italic>, P225<italic>&#x00394;</italic>51<italic>srn_9340</italic>_3&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;_Psrn_9340 and <italic>srn_9340_</italic>seq_3&#x02032; for <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub><italic><sub>&#x00394;</sub></italic><sub>51</sub>; 5&#x02032;_P267<italic>&#x00394;</italic>22<italic>sprc</italic>, P267<italic>&#x00394;</italic>22<italic>sprC</italic>_3&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;_P<italic>sprC</italic> and <italic>sprC_</italic>seq_3&#x02032; for <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub><italic><sub>&#x00394;</sub></italic><sub>22</sub>; and 5&#x02032;_P225<italic>&#x00394;23srn_9340</italic>, P225<italic>&#x00394;23srn_9340</italic>_3&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;_Psrn_9340 and <italic>srn_9340_</italic>seq_3&#x02032; for <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub><italic><sub>&#x00394;</sub></italic><sub>23</sub>. DNA probes were labeled with [&#x003b3;-<sup>32</sup>P] adenosine triphosphate (ATP) using T4 polynucleotide kinase (New England Biolabs). Binding reactions were carried out as previously described (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Briefly, binding reaction medium (10 fmol DNA template, 20 mM HEPES-KOH, pH 7.9, 20% glycerol, 0.2 mM EDTA, 0.1 M KCl, 0.1 M MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 mM DTT and 0.2 &#x003bc;g poly(dI-dC)), was incubated when necessary with purified SarA or the <italic>E. coli</italic> RNA polymerase holoenzyme (New England Biolabs) for 30 min at 30&#x000b0;C. Samples were loaded on native polyacrylamide gels. Detection was done with a Typhoon FLA 9500 (GE Healthcare).</p><p>The dissociation constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>) was determined by comparing the free versus the shifted DNA&#x02013;protein bands (ImageQuant software), and apparent <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> was derived from the computed concentration at half-maximal binding.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-10"><title>DNase I footprinting assay</title><p>DNA probes were radiolabeled at one end. We used the HindIII restriction site, which is present in the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> gene or in the 3&#x02032; primer for <italic>srn_9340</italic>. Klenow Fragment (New England Biolabs) filled the restriction site with [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P] ATP and other unlabeled nucleotides. Binding reactions were done as previously described, then subjected to 2 or 7.5.10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> unit of DNase I (Invitrogen) for 1 min at 30&#x000b0;C after supplementing the protein buffer with 40 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. Reactions were halted by adding a stop buffer (10 &#x003bc;g/ml Invitrogen Proteinase K, 400 mM acetate sodium, 0.2% SDS, 10 Mm EDTA and 50 &#x003bc;g/ml yeast tRNA). After 15 min at 55&#x000b0;C of proteinase K action, the digested DNA samples were extracted by phenol/chloroform and ethanol precipitation. Pellets were resuspended in formamide dye mix and after denaturation were loaded on 8% denaturing polyacrylamide gels.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-11"><title>DNA sequencing</title><p>DNA probes used in the footprinting assays were sequenced according to the standard protocol (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Specific primers were end-labeled with [&#x003b3;-<sup>32</sup>P] ATP using T4 polynucleotide kinase (New England Biolabs). The ratio of G, A, T and C nucleotides was adjusted in the sequencing mixture.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-12"><title>Chromatin immunoprecipitation assays</title><p>ChIP experiments were adapted from Faith et <italic>al</italic>. (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic> carrying either pCN38 or pCN38-SarA6His was cultured for 2.5 h at 37&#x000b0;C and 160 rpm, then treated with formaldehyde. Washed cells were thawed, incubated for 30 min at 37&#x000b0;C with 50 &#x003bc;g lysostaphin in a buffer (200 mM Tris, pH 8.0, 600 mM NaCl, 4% Triton X-100 and 1 mM PMSF), then sonicated. Dilution buffer was added to supernatant (see recipe in Supplementary Table S4) and pre-cleared overnight at 4&#x000b0;C with end-over-end rotations with Protein G sepharose beads previously coated with 1% BSA and 0.1 &#x003bc;g salmon sperm. Input, ChIP, DIG, and Pol fractions were separated. The ChIP, DIG, and Pol fractions had 8 &#x003bc;g of antibodies to 6His, digoxigenin, and <italic>E. coli</italic> &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> added, respectively, then they were incubated for 8 h at 4&#x000b0;C with &#x02018;end-over-end rotation. Immunoprecipitations were carried out overnight on Protein G magnetic beads previously coated with 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA) and 0.1 &#x003bc;g salmon sperm. Bead washes and DNA elution were also done as described by Faith (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). ChIP analysis was performed by qPCR with comparative enrichment of the P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic>, P<italic><sub>srn_9340</sub></italic> and P<italic><sub>hla</sub></italic> promoters. For normalization, 25 ng yeast plasmid DNA was added to all samples before phenol&#x02013;chloroform extraction.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-13"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription assays</title><p><italic>SprC<sub>456</sub></italic> and <italic>srn_9340<sub>337</sub></italic> templates (corresponding to the sequences from promoter to terminator of genes of interest) were amplified from <italic>S. aureus</italic> genome by PCR using specific primers (5&#x02032;_BamHI_PsprC, 3&#x02032;_EcoRI_TsprC and 5&#x02032;_BamHI_Psrn_9340, 3&#x02032;_EcoRI_Tsrn_9340). <italic>In vitro</italic> transcription was realized adding 100 fmol of <italic>E. coli</italic> RNA polymerase (New England Biolabs) to 10 fmol of DNA template (<italic>sprC<sub>456</sub></italic> or <italic>srn_9340<sub>337</sub></italic>), in 5&#x000d7; <italic>E. coli</italic> RNA polymerase reaction buffer (New England Biolabs) supplementing with nucleoside triphosphate ATP, CTP, GTP (0.75 mM each) and 0.5 &#x003bc;Ci of [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P] UTP. A total of 5 pmol of purified SarA protein were added to reactions, when needed. Samples were loaded on 8% denaturing polyacrylamide gels. Detection was done with a Typhoon FLA 9500 (GE Healthcare).</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-14"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>For statistical analysis, the one-tailed Mann&#x02013;Whitney test was performed on three independent experiments and used to evaluate the significance of the ChIP assays. The two-tailed Mann&#x02013;Whitney test was used for reporter gene experiments. Data were expressed as means &#x000b1; standard deviations.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="SEC3"><title>RESULTS</title><p>Srn_3610_SprC attenuates <italic>S. aureus</italic> virulence and host cell uptake. Its expression sharply decreases after <italic>S. aureus</italic> phagocytosis by human macrophages (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). We therefore investigated whether a TF might be involved in controlling <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression.</p><sec id="SEC3-1"><title>The SarA transcription factor reduces levels of Srn_3610_SprC RNA during <italic>S. aureus</italic> growth</title><p>To initiate the study of <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> transcriptional regulation, we used Northern blotting to monitor RNA levels in six <italic>S. aureus</italic> HG003-derived strains. Each strain was deleted for a member of the sarA family: sarA, sarR, sarS, sarT, sarV or sarX (Supplementary Table S1) (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). The strains were grown in BHI medium, and total RNA extracted after the exponential phase (5 h of growth, OD<sub>600</sub> &#x0223c;6). A DNA probe specific to Srn_3610_SprC was used to compare Srn_3610_SprC RNA levels between the mutants and the parental strain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression increases in the absence of SarA. (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>Srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression in different <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains lacking transcription factors (TFs). Northern blot analysis of the Srn_3610_sprC and transfer-messenger RNA (tmRNA) transcripts in the <italic>S. aureus</italic> HG003 strain and in isogenic mutants for the SarA protein family. All samples were harvested after 5 h of growth. A total of 10 &#x003bc;g of total RNA were analyzed, and the Digoxigenin method (Roche) was used to reveal Srn_3610_sprC and tmRNA (loading control). (<bold>B</bold>) Northern blot analysis of Srn_3610_SprC and tmRNA transcript expression in <italic>S. aureus</italic> HG003 and isogenic HG003&#x00394;<italic>sarA</italic>. Samples were harvested at the specified time point, and tmRNA was used as a control. In a graph showing optical density as a function of time, the growths of HG003 (diamonds) and HG003&#x00394;<italic>sarA</italic> (triangles) are represented in a semi-logarithmic scale.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkw777fig1"/></fig><p>A significant 10-fold increase was detected in the strain deleted for <italic>sarA</italic>, suggesting that SarA is the main repressor of <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> transcription. In contrast, a slight (about 30%) decrease was detected in the HG003&#x00394;<italic>sarR</italic> strain, with no significant change observed in the other mutants (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). The contradictory effects of SarA and SarR deletion make sense, since SarR represses SarA and because these regulators have antagonistic roles in target gene transcription (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>To verify the hypothesis that SarA represses <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic>, we monitored sRNA gene expression all along growth in HG003 and HG003&#x00394;<italic>sarA</italic> strains. The growth of the HG003&#x00394;<italic>sarA</italic> strain was slightly weaker than that of the parental one (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>), which is consistent with SarA's physiological role in regulating the expression of at least 120 genes in <italic>S. aureus</italic> (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). In the HG003 strain, Srn_3610_SprC levels fluctuate during growth, and after 4&#x02013;5 h there was a peak corresponding to about a 3-fold increase (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). In the <italic>sarA</italic> mutant, <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression was &#x0223c;10&#x000d7; higher at all collected time points, with maximum RNA levels detected after 4&#x02013;5 h of growth (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). Together, these results confirm that SarA has an essential role in <italic>in vivo</italic> regulation of <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic>. However, these results also imply that other protein(s) than SarA participate(s) to the fluctuation of <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression during growth.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-2"><title>SarA negatively regulates srn_3610_sprC transcription</title><p>To provide further experimental support for a functional link between Srn_3610_SprC and SarA, we (i) did a <italic>trans</italic>-complementation assay and (ii) verified whether SarA acts on <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> at the transcriptional level. To these aims, in each of the following experiments, HG003 and HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic> strains were co-transformed with a combination of two plasmids. The first plasmid carried <italic>sarA</italic> under control of its own promoter (pCN36-SarA), or was left empty (pCN36). The second carried <italic>blaZ</italic>, encoding the &#x000df;-lactamase reporter, either promoterless (pCN41c) or under the control of the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter (pCN41c-P<sub>sprC</sub>). P<sub>sprC</sub> was defined as a 144 nt-long DNA fragment (SAOUHSC_01956:18611729_186268) ending at the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> 5&#x02032; end, as determined by RACE mapping (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). With pCN41c-P<sub>sprC</sub>, a measure of the &#x000df;-lactamase activity in the presence or absence of SarA reflect regulation of this latter on the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter, thus on the transcription level of <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic>. Total RNAs and proteins were extracted and expression of both endogenous Srn_3610_SprC and endogenous/exogenous SarA revealed by northern and western blots. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>, expression of pCN41c-P<sub>sprC</sub> did not affect Srn_3610_SprC nor SarA endogenous levels (compare lanes 1 and 2 or 3 and 4). Conversely, exogenous expression of <italic>sarA</italic> through pCN36-sarA led to a significant increase in both SarA mRNA and protein levels in HG003 and HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic> strains (lanes 3 and 4 versus 1 and 2, and 7 and 8 versus 5 and 6). From this result, we infer that both SarA mRNAs and the encoded protein are overexpressed in cells containing &#x02018;low copy&#x02019; plasmid pCN36-SarA.</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>SarA represses <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression. (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> HG003 and HG003&#x00394;<italic>sarA</italic> strains were co-transformed with: pCN36/pCN41c empty vectors (lanes 1 and 5); pCN36/pCN41c<italic>-</italic>P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> (lanes 2 and 6); pCN36-SarA/pCN41c (lanes 3 and 7); and pCN36-SarA/pCN41- P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> (lanes 4 and 8). Srn_3610_SprC and SarA transcripts levels were assessed by northern blot. A 16S rRNA probe was used to reflect total RNA loading for each lane. In parallel, SarA protein levels were checked by western blot (middle panel) and SYPRO Ruby staining of total protein extracts was done to compare loaded protein levels (bottom). (<bold>B</bold>) Effects of SarA on transcriptional activity of the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter (P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic>). <italic>S. aureus</italic> HG003 wild-type strain (HG003) and a strain lacking <italic>sarA</italic> (HG003&#x00394;<italic>sarA</italic>) were co-transformed with pCN41c or pCN41c-P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> and either pCN36 or pCN36-SarA. P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> activity was estimated by measuring &#x000df;-lactamase substrate hydrolysis. For each lane, indicated &#x000df;-lactamase activity was normalized by subtracting the background signal from the same strain where pCN41c-P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> was replaced by pCN41c empty vector (not shown). Three independent experiments were done, error bars show &#x000b1; standard deviation. (Mann&#x02013;Whitney test; *<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001.).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkw777fig2"/></fig><p>More importantly, northern blot analyses showed an &#x0223c;9-fold increase in Srn_3610_SprC level in the HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic> strain as compared to HG003 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>, lanes 1 and 2 versus 5 and 6), whereas reintroducing <italic>sarA</italic> restored endogenous Srn_3610_SprC level (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>, lanes 1 and 2 versus 7 and 8), validating that complementation occurred. Interestingly, when <italic>sarA</italic> was overexpressed in HG003 strain, Srn_3610_SprC level slightly decreased (lanes 1 and 2 versus 3 and 4), indicating an inverse correlation between the evolution of SarA and Srn_3610_SprC RNA levels.</p><p>We then measured &#x000df;-lactamase activity in all strains. The results for the strains expressing pCN41c-P<sub>sprC</sub> are depicted in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>. First, confirming the Northern blot experiment, the &#x000df;-lactamase activity underwent a 40% drop when <italic>sarA</italic> was overexpressed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>, second bar versus first bar; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.017). Second, a 9-fold increase in &#x000df;-lactamase activity was measured in HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic>_pCN36 compared to HG003_pCN36 (third bar versus first bar; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0006), while &#x000df;-lactamase activity in HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic>_pCN36-sarA strain remained at level similar to that of the parental strain (fourth bar versus first bar). All together, these results confirmed that SarA negatively controls Srn_3610_SprC levels, and implied that SarA acts on the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter to reduce RNA expression. The correlation in both &#x000df;-lactamase and Northern blot experiments indicates that SarA's repressive action is restricted to the promoter of the sRNA gene.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-3"><title>SarA interacts with the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter <italic>in vitro</italic></title><p>The above results indicate that SarA probably represses <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression by acting on the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter. To further test this hypothesis, EMSA studies were done with recombinant SarA and the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter region. For these assays, we used a 6His-tagged full-length SarA with a 267-bp <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> DNA region (<italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic>) that contains the 144 bp <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter region along with 123 bp downstream of the +1 <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> transcription start. <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic>forms a complex with purified SarA and has an apparent <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> of 86 &#x000b1; 3 nM (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). A 10-fold excess of unlabeled <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic> efficiently disrupt SarA from a preformed complex of labeled SarA/<italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic>. However, a 100-fold excess of a 267 bp unspecific fragment made up of a section of 16S DNA (<italic>16S<sub>267</sub></italic>), was unable to do so (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). This demonstrates the specificity of the complex formation between SarA and <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic>. Together, these results indicate that purified SarA directly binds the <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic> promoter <italic>in vitro</italic> and its binding is specific.</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>SarA specifically binds a region overlapping the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter and its 5&#x02032; end. (<bold>A</bold>) SarA binds the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter <italic>in vitro</italic>. Electrophoretic mobility shift assays (EMSA) were done using 10 fmol <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub> probe, a <sup>32</sup>P-labeled <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter fragment and increasing amounts of 0.1 to 8 pmol 6His-tagged SarA. (<bold>B</bold>) SarA specifically binds <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub>. EMSA was performed with 4 pmol of SarA and with increasing amounts of specific (unlabeled <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub>) or non-specific competitors (unlabeled <italic>16S</italic><sub>267</sub>). The <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub>/SarA complex is only inhibited in the presence of 50&#x02013;100&#x000d7; excesses of the specific competitor. (<bold>C</bold>) The SarA binding site overlaps the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter and gene. DNase I footprinting assays were performed in the presence of 10 fmol <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub>, 2.10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> U DNase I, and increasing amounts (0.5&#x02013;2 pmol) of 6His-SarA. Lanes 1&#x02013;4 correspond to <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub> sequencing, and the promoter region is annotated. The vertical dotted arrow indicates the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> region protected from DNase I degradation. The SarA binding site (&#x02212;32 to +15) was named &#x02018;<italic>sprC</italic><sub>47</sub>.&#x02019; (<bold>D</bold>) Schematic representation of the different DNA probes used for EMSA studies. (<bold>E</bold>) The 47 bp region protected by SarA is necessary for SarA binding with <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic>. EMSA were realized as in <italic>A</italic>, using <sup>32</sup>P-labeled <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267&#x00394;47</sub> (right) or wild-type <sup>32</sup>P-labeled <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub> (left). SarA was unable to form a complex with <italic>sprC<sub>P267&#x00394;47</sub></italic>. (<bold>F</bold>) The 47 bp protected by SarA is sufficient for SarA binding onto <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic>. EMSA were done using 10 fmol <italic>sprC</italic><sub>47</sub>, 4 pmol of 6His-tagged SarA, and increasing amounts of either unlabeled <italic>sprC</italic><sub>47</sub> as a specific competitor or unlabeled 47-bp sequence (Random<sub>47</sub>) as a non-specific competitor. SarA forms a complex with DNA (up-shifted band) that can only be disrupted by an excess of the specific competitor. (<bold>G</bold>) A 22-bp SarA binding site on <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub> was found with EMSA done in the presence of 0.5 pmol of sarA and with increasing amounts of unlabeled <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub> or unlabeled <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267&#x00394;22</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkw777fig3"/></fig></sec><sec id="SEC3-4"><title>The SarA binding site on the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter extends through the transcribed sequence</title><p>To further explore the SarA binding site on the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter, we used 3&#x02032;-end labeled <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic> probes with increasing concentrations of purified SarA to perform DNase I footprint assays. As expected, increasing amounts of SarA revealed a region protected from DNAse I cleavage within the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> DNA sequence (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>).This 47 bp-long sequence is located between positions &#x02212;32 and +15 in <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> (nts 1861616-1861570) and we named it &#x02018;<italic>sprC</italic><sub>47</sub>&#x02019; (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>).</p><p>To see whether this protected sequence was necessary for SarA binding, we created <italic>sprC<sub>P267&#x00394;47</sub></italic>, a 220 bp DNA fragment made from nucleotides &#x02212;144 to +123 but with the footprint-identified <italic>sprC</italic><sub>47</sub> sequence deleted (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">E</xref>). EMSA testing of <italic>sprC<sub>P267&#x00394;47</sub></italic> showed that SarA could not form a complex with the deleted promoter, even though it could with the native one (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref>). These results confirm the key role of <italic>sprC</italic><sub>47</sub> in SarA/P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> complex formation.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-5"><title><italic>sprC</italic><sub>47</sub> is sufficient for SarA binding onto <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter</title><p>To test whether the 47-bp protected DNA region was sufficient for SarA-specific binding, EMSA was performed using <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic> or <italic>Random</italic><sub>47</sub>, a scrambled 47-bp DNA sequence. A 50-fold excess of unlabeled <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic> disrupts the preformed complex, whereas the same amount of <italic>Random</italic><sub>47</sub> does not (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3F</xref>), so SarA specifically binds <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic>. Therefore, <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic> is necessary and sufficient for SarA binding.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-6"><title><italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter dissection</title><p>We divided the <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic> sequence into three overlapping 30 bp sequences and challenged them using EMSA. Two of the overlapping DNA sequences which share 22 bp allowed SarA binding and the third did not (Supplementary Figure S1). We thus created a 245 bp DNA fragment from nts &#x02212;144 to +123 without the shared <italic>sprC<sub>22</sub></italic> section, resulting in the mutant <italic>sprC<sub>P267&#x00394;22</sub></italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>). EMSA was performed between <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic> and purified SarA protein, and <italic>sprC<sub>P267&#x00394;22</sub></italic> was used as a competitor to assess the SarA/<italic>sprC <sub>P267</sub></italic> complex formation. The 22 bp sequence is necessary for SarA binding, since a 25-fold excess of unlabeled <italic>sprC<sub>P267&#x00394;22</sub></italic> did not disrupt the sprC<sub>P267</sub>/SarA complex, whereas the same amount of unlabeled <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic> did (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-7"><title><italic>srn_9340</italic> is another sRNA regulated by SarA</title><p>Using <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic> as a query, we did comparative sequence analysis on the HG003 strain's genome. This identified a 29 bp sequence sharing 93% identity with <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Interestingly, the sequence is located upstream of <italic>srn_9340</italic> (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), an sRNA gene identified by RNAseq (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) and recently validated by northern blot under the name S774 (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). As for <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic>, the <italic>srn_9340</italic> (NCTC 8325: 1863905&#x02013;1863790) is located in the SaPIn3 (vSa&#x000df;) PI. It is only 2338 bp downstream from <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> (1861729-1862268) and both sRNAs are expressed from the same genomic DNA strand (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, minus strand). Based on the homology between <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter sequences, we hypothesized that <italic>srn_9340</italic> transcription might also be negatively controlled by SarA.</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><italic>srn</italic>_<italic>9340</italic> possesses a putative binding site for SarA. <italic>Srn_3610_sprC</italic> belongs to the pathogenicity island SaPIn3. <italic>SprC<sub>47</sub></italic>, which can interact with SarA, possesses a 22-nt palindromic sequence (underlined). Blast analysis using <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic> as the query led to the discovery of another putative SarA binding site within SaPIn3. This sequence was identified as part of the promoter of another small RNA, Srn_9340.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkw777fig4"/></fig></sec><sec id="SEC3-8"><title>SarA represses <italic>Srn_9340</italic> transcription</title><p>Two &#x0223c;110 nt-long transcripts (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>) were detected in HG003 by northern blots using a <italic>srn_9340</italic>-specific probe. These transcripts were detected throughout bacterial growth (Supplementary Figure S2). In the HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic> mutant, <italic>srn_9340</italic> expression is about 3.5&#x000d7; higher than in the isogenic HG003 strain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). Thus, <italic>srn_9340</italic> transcription seems to be repressed by SarA, albeit to a lesser extent than SarA represses <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic>. While <italic>srn_9340</italic> seems to be expressed at lower level, compared to <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic>, their expression patterns are very similar in HG003. They reach peak expression after 3&#x02013;5 h of growth and expression levels fluctuate up to 3-fold. These observations suggest that the two sRNAs are analogously controlled. Moreover, these results also imply that other protein(s) than SarA participate(s) to the fluctuation of <italic>srn_9340</italic> expression during growth.</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>SarA binds <italic>srn_9340</italic> on its promoter and represses transcription. (<bold>A</bold>) SarA represses <italic>srn_9340</italic> expression. After 5 h of growth, 10 &#x003bc;g of total RNA were obtained from <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> HG003 and HG003&#x00394;<italic>sarA</italic>. Srn_9340 expression levels were monitored by northern blot. (<bold>B</bold>) Schematic representation of both the 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; ends of the Srn_9340 transcripts (long and short small RNAs), as determined by rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE). (<bold>C</bold>) SarA binds the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter <italic>in vitro</italic>. An EMSA was done using 10 fmol of a <sup>32</sup>P-labeled <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter fragment (<italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub>) as a probe in the presence of increasing amounts (0.01&#x02013;1 pmol) of 6His-tagged SarA. <italic>Srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub> forms an initial complex with 0.15 pmol of SarA, and a second one at 0.75 pmol. (<bold>D</bold>) SarA specifically binds <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub><italic>in vitro</italic>. EMSA was done with 10 fmol of <sup>32</sup>P-labeled <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub>, 1 pmol of 6His-SarA and increasing amounts of specific (unlabeled <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub>) or non-specific competitors (unlabeled 16S<sub>225</sub>). (<bold>E</bold>) DNase I footprinting assays were performed in the presence of 10 fmol <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub>, 7.5.10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> U DNase I and increasing amounts (0.1&#x02013;0.5 pmol) of 6His-SarA. The region protected by SarA is indicated with a vertical dotted arrow, and the numbers indicate relative positions to the previously determined transcription start site (TSS). Lanes G, A, T and C correspond to sequencing. The nucleotides from &#x02212;51 to &#x02212;1 (<italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>51</sub>) are protected by SarA against DNase I degradation. (<bold>F</bold>) Schematic representation of the DNA probes used for EMSA studies. (<bold>G</bold>) Deletion of the protected SarA sequence from the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter region abolishes SarA's capacity to bind the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter. (<bold>H</bold>) A 51 bp protected sequence is sufficient for SarA binding. EMSA were done using 10 fmol <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>51</sub> in the presence of increasing amounts of 6His-tagged SarA (0.25&#x02013;2 pmol). (<bold>I</bold>) <italic>Srn_9340</italic><sub>51</sub> competes with <italic>srn_9340<sub>225</sub></italic>for SarA binding. EMSA was performed with 10 fmol of <sup>32</sup>P-labeled <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub>, 0.4 or 1 pmol of 6His-SarA and increasing amounts of specific (unlabeled <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>51</sub>) or non-specific competitors (unlabeled <italic>Random<sub>51</sub></italic>). (<bold>J</bold>) The 23 bp SarA binding site on <italic>srn_9340<sub>225</sub></italic>was confirmed by EMSA done in the presence of 0.5 pmol sarA and with increasing amounts of unlabeled <italic>srn_9340<sub>225</sub></italic>or unlabeled <italic>srn_9340<sub>225</sub></italic><sub>&#x00394;23</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkw777fig5"/></fig><p>Going further, Srn_9340 levels were monitored by northern blots in the HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarR, &#x00394;sarS, &#x00394;sarT, &#x00394;sarV</italic> and <italic>&#x00394;sarX</italic> strains. We observed a reduction of about 50% of <italic>srn_9340</italic> expression in HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarR</italic>, but the levels were unaffected in the other strains (Supplementary Figure S3). These results are similar to those obtained for Srn_3610_SprC (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>), confirming the roles of SarA and SarR as antagonists for target gene transcription. We compared the HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic> strain transformed with pCN36 or complemented by pCN36-<italic>sarA</italic>, and the results showed that the variation in <italic>srn_9340</italic> expression levels is controlled by SarA (Supplementary Figure S4). The Srn_9340 transcript's 5&#x02032; ends were mapped by RACE at the same genomic position (1863905), implying that they share the same transcription start site (TSS). The longer transcript's 3&#x02032; end maps at genomic position 1863790, whereas that of the shorter transcript ends at 1863797 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>).</p><p>Consistent with the northern blot results (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>), the Srn_9340 transcripts are about 116 and 108 nts long (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>), with the shorter transcript lacking nucleotides at the 3&#x02032; end. No ORF was found in either sequence. The Srn_9340 transcript sizes obtained are slightly different from that of S774 (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). In addition to the size difference, M&#x000e4;der <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>. visualized a unique transcript. These differences could have been due to either genetic (HG001 versus HG003) or technical differences (gel resolution) (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-9"><title>SarA binds the <italic>Srn_9340</italic> promoter <italic>in vitro</italic></title><p>We used EMSA for binding assays of purified SarA on the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter region (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). We synthesized a PCR fragment of <italic>srn_9340</italic> nucleotides &#x02212;165 to +60 (with the coding sequence starting at +1), and named this &#x02018;<italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic>.&#x02019; We observed a distinct SarA/<italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic> complex with an apparent <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> of 11 &#x000b1; 0.2 nM (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>, middle arrow). The complex has an abundance that is positively linked to SarA quantities. A second band shift then appeared which probably correspond to protein aggregation onto the DNA probe (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>, upper band). A 10-fold excess of <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic>effectively competed with the labeled promoter fragment for SarA binding, whereas a 100-fold excess of <italic>16S<sub>225</sub></italic>, an unlabeled non-specific 225 pb 16S DNA fragment, did not displace the labeled one from the complex (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>). Together, these results indicate that SarA directly and specifically binds the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter <italic>in vitro</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-10"><title>SarA binds the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter upstream from the +1 transcription start</title><p>We performed DNase I footprinting assays using a 3&#x02032;-end labeled <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic> probe with increasing concentrations of purified SarA protein. As expected, without SarA, there was no protection against DNase I cleavage. Increasing SarA amounts revealed an <italic>srn_9340</italic> region that became protected from DNase I cleavages (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>). This 51 bp-long sequence is positioned between &#x02212;51 and &#x02212;1 within the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter (1863956&#x02013;1863904), and we named it &#x02018;<italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>51</sub>&#x02019; (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>).</p><p>To test whether this protected sequence is necessary and sufficient for SarA binding, we amplified <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225&#x00394;51</sub></italic>, a 174 bp DNA fragment (nts &#x02212;165 to +60) that does not include the <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>51</sub> sequence (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>). EMSA performed on <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225&#x00394;51</sub></italic> showed that SarA complex formation was greatly reduced as compared to EMSA performed with the native promoter (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5G</xref>). To test whether this region is sufficient for SarA binding, EMSA was performed with <italic>srn_9340<sub>51</sub></italic>. Indeed, SarA specifically binds <italic>srn_9340<sub>51</sub></italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5H</xref>), therefore, <italic>srn_9340<sub>51</sub></italic> is necessary and sufficient for SarA binding. Furthermore, a 10-fold excess of unlabeled <italic>srn_9340<sub>51</sub></italic> effectively competed with the labeled <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic> for SarA binding, whereas a 50-fold excess of <italic>Random<sub>51</sub></italic>, an unlabeled non-specific DNA fragment, did not disrupt the labeled one from the complex (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5I</xref>). Considered together, these results confirm the requirement for <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>51</sub> in complex formation between SarA and the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-11"><title><italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter dissection</title><p>To further delineate the SarA binding site on the srn_9340 promoter, the <italic>srn_9340<sub>51</sub></italic> sequence was divided into three overlapping 30-bp sequences, then tested for SarA binding by EMSA. The results (see Supplementary Figure S5) clearly indicate the importance of a specific 23 bp sequence. A 25-fold excess of unlabeled <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225&#x00394;23</sub></italic> did not disrupt the <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic>/SarA complex, whereas the same amount of unlabeled <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic> did (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5J</xref>). Therefore, removing this 23 nt sequence from the 225 nt-long DNA promoter prevents it from competing against the preformed SarA/<italic>srn_9340</italic> complex, which implies that this region is mandatory for binding SarA.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-12"><title>SarA binds <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340 in vivo</italic></title><p>In ChIP experiments, cellular macromolecular interactions are frozen and analyzed by protein IP and qPCR. Among other uses, this method allows for the comparison of enriched DNA sequences bound to a protein. We performed ChIP assays on HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic> carrying either pCN38 or pCN38-SarA6His. We used 6His antibodies to immunoprecipitate SarA6His, with <italic>hla</italic> as a positive control because SarA directly regulates <italic>hla</italic> transcription (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). IP induced about a 19-fold enrichment in P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>), while in the same extracts the <italic>srn_9340</italic> and <italic>hla</italic> promoters were respectively enriched about 6- and 16-fold. In the presence of SarA (HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic>_ pCN38-SarA6His), the average P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> retrievals in the SarA-IP experiments were statistically higher than without it (HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic>_pCN38). The obtained enrichments of P<italic><sub>hla</sub></italic> and P<italic><sub>srn_9340</sub></italic> were also statistically significant. These results confirm the presence of SarA on both the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoters <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><italic>In vivo</italic> analysis of the srn_3610_sprC and srn_9340 promoters: SarA versus &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> binding. The <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> HG003&#x00394;<italic>sarA</italic> strain was transformed either with an empty pCN38 vector (dark gray) or with pCN38-SarA6His (light gray). Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) experiments were conducted using antibodies for 6His-tag (<bold>A</bold>) or for the &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup>/&#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> RNA polymerase subunit (<bold>B</bold>). DNA enrichment was assessed by qPCR analysis using specific primers for the promoters of <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> (left panel), <italic>srn_9340</italic> (middle) or <italic>hla</italic> (right). Values beneath the bars indicate fold change between specific and non-specific interactions. (Mann&#x02013;Whitney U test; three independent experiments; *<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). (A) <italic>srn_3610_sprC, srn_9340</italic> and <italic>hla</italic> promoters co-immunoprecipitate with SarA6His. (B) SarA6His disturbs &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> binding on the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkw777fig6"/></fig><p>In <italic>S. aureus</italic>, &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> is the functional analog of &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> in <italic>E. coli</italic>. This sigma factor is the RNA polymerase subunit involved in promoter recognition (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Both <italic>S. aureus</italic> &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> and <italic>E</italic>. coli &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> RNA polymerase subunits recognize canonical promoters and are interchangeable (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). It has already been reported that <italic>srn_9340</italic> transcription depends on &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). After promoter sequence analysis, we predicted that the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter must be &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup>-dependent. We used <italic>E. coli</italic> &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> antibodies to immunoprecipitate the <italic>S. aureus</italic> &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup>, investigating its accessibility at P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> and P<italic><sub>srn_9340</sub></italic> with and without SarA. <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic> and <italic>srn_9340<sub>51</sub></italic> correspond to the DNA sequences protected by SarA, and they both contain the &#x02212;10 TATA box and partial or complete &#x02212;35 box RNA polymerase binding sites. Therefore, SarA should prevent binding of staphylococcal RNA polymerase onto both sRNA promoters. We found that the average amount of <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter in the &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup>-IP with SarA (HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA_</italic>pCN38-SarA6His) was statistically lower than that of the deleted strain (HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA_</italic>pCN38) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). The <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter amounts in the ChIP targeting &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> were also lower in the presence of SarA than without it (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Meanwhile, the presence or absence of SarA did not make a statistical difference in the amount of the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter recovered after &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup>-IP enrichment (HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA_</italic> pCN38-SarA6His and HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic>_pCN38, respectively) (Supplementary Figure S6).</p><p>Since in both promoters the SarA binding site includes the RNA polymerase loading location, we expected a similar repression model. We therefore supposed that the &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup>-IP ChIP experiment was not useful for the study of P<italic><sub>srn_9340</sub></italic>. This led us to further explore the genomic environment of <italic>srn_9340</italic>. The highly transcribed gene <italic>tRNA<sup>ser</sup></italic> is 408 bp away from <italic>srn_9340</italic>. Such a close proximity (Supplementary Figure S6) could lead to sonicated DNA fragments containing <italic>srn_9340</italic> and <italic>tRNA<sup>ser</sup></italic>, making it difficult to use ChIP data to draw any conclusions. Thereafter, we performed EMSA studies on purified SarA and bacterial RNA polymerase <italic>(E. coli)</italic> together with either <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> or the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoters.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-13"><title>SarA binding onto <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoters prevents RNA polymerase loading</title><p>Purified <italic>E. coli</italic> RNA polymerase holoenzyme binds the two <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic> and <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic>promoters (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">B</xref>) with about 0.75 and 1.8 nM affinities <italic>in vitro</italic>. To see whether SarA might prevent RNA polymerase binding onto these promoters, another set of SarA EMSA experiments was performed with and without the RNA polymerase (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">D</xref>). Similar patterns were observed for both promoters in the presence of both SarA and RNA polymerase (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">D</xref>). Multiple bands corresponding to SarA/DNA low molecular weight complexes appeared, and in the presence of RNA polymerase, high molecular weight complexes emerged. These latter complexes migrate similarly as DNA/polymerase complex (compare lanes 3, 4, 5 with, respectively, lanes 6, 7, 8), allowing the conclusion that these complexes only contain the RNA polymerase and the sRNA promoter. Moreover, using 100 fmol of RNA polymerase in the presence of SarA, we still observed a lower molecular weight sarA/promoter complexes, whereas 50 fmol of RNA polymerase is sufficient to bind nearly all <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic> and <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">B</xref>). However, even when two-fold higher RNA polymerase is added in the presence of SarA, SarA-promoter complexes are still detected (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">D</xref>). This suggests that DNA/SarA and DNA/RNA polymerase complexes co-exist, implying that when SarA is loaded onto each of the two sRNA promoters, RNA polymerase stops being able to bind. We infer from these results that SarA binding onto <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic>and <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic> promoters hampers RNA polymerase binding. To reinforce that, we performed <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription assay using the <italic>E. coli</italic> RNA polymerase and each of the DNAs encompassing the sequences from promoter to the sRNA terminators (<italic>sprC<sub>456</sub></italic> and <italic>srn_9340<sub>337</sub></italic>), in the presence/absence of the SarA protein. As shown in panels E and F from Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>, the <italic>E. coli</italic> RNA polymerase is able to produce transcripts from <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> and SarA protein severely impact these transcriptions. Altogether, it is concluded that TF SarA binds <italic>srn_3610_SprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoters and prevents transcription.</p><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>SarA and bacterial RNA polymerase holoenzyme cannot simultaneously bind <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub> and <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub>. EMSA was done using 10 fmol <sup>32</sup>P-labeled <italic>sprC</italic><sub>P267</sub> or <italic>srn_9340</italic><sub>P225</sub> probes with increasing amounts (2&#x02013;100 fmol) of purified RNA polymerase. The binding capacity of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> RNA polymerase was confirmed by EMSA experiments using <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic> (<bold>A</bold>) or <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic> (<bold>B</bold>). To demonstrate their binding exclusivity on <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic> (<bold>C</bold>) or <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic> (<bold>D</bold>), 0.5 pmol purified SarA and 50&#x02013;100 fmol <italic>E. coli</italic> RNA polymerase were simultaneously added to EMSA experiments. <italic>In vitro</italic> transcription was realized using 10 fmol of <italic>sprC<sub>456</sub></italic> (<bold>E</bold>) or <italic>srn_9340<sub>337</sub></italic> (<bold>F</bold>) and 100 fmol of <italic>E. coli</italic> RNA polymerase. A total of 5 pmol of the purified TF SarA were added, when indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkw777fig7"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="SEC4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>How sRNAs are regulated in <italic>S</italic>.<italic>aureus</italic> remains an essential but unanswered and barely addressed question. Most documented cases of sRNA regulation are in enterobacteria, where sRNAs are transcriptionally controlled by TFs and <italic>vice versa</italic> (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). In <italic>S. aureus</italic>, sRNAs also regulate the expression of TFs. For example, RNAIII represses Rot TF translation (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) and RsaA (Srn_1510) represses MgrA synthesis (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). To learn about sRNA gene regulation in <italic>S. aureus</italic>, we investigated the regulation of <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression. This sRNA was used as a model since it acts as a virulence attenuator, modulating host phagocytosis, therefore we expected its expression to be tightly controlled. The pleiotropic TF SarA is involved in <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm formation and pathogenesis, among other things (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). In our study, this TF was identified as a negative regulator of transcription initiation in <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic>. Whereas the absence of SarA correlates with a change in the expression level of at least 120 genes, it has only been shown to directly control the expression of a dozen mRNAs. Here we show that SarA is directly involved in transcriptional regulation of Srn_3610_SprC and Srn_9340 sRNAs. To our knowledge this is the first identification of SarA as a transcriptional repressor of sRNA. Beyond just a mechanistic description of a direct interaction between a TF and an sRNA promoter, our work has identified two sRNAs whose expressions are under control of one general TF. Having arrived with an exogenous PI, these two sRNAs are now negatively regulated by a TF from the core genome. This demonstrates <italic>S. aureus</italic>&#x02019; ability to take over sRNA regulation. Such a mechanism probably strengthens <italic>S. aureus</italic>' infectivity.</p><p>Based on the similarities between SarA repression of <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> transcription, their comparable expression patterns during bacterial growth, and their close genetic locations, we can guess that these two sRNAs are in part functionally related. Previous studies have shown that <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression is tightly regulated during host immune cell recognition of the bacteria for clearance during infection (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), while no functions have yet been identified for Srn_9340 (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Our work connects the control of the expression of these two sRNAs to a common TF, suggesting that Srn_9340 might also be involved in virulence and host immune response.</p><p>Without SarA, <italic>srn_9340</italic> and <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> transcription levels are respectively 3- and 9-folds higher, indicating that their expression should be repressed during bacterial growth. A TF downregulating sRNA gene expression could, upon TF release from the sRNA promoters, allow transient expression of sRNAs. This will enable the bacteria to respond rapidly and efficiently to environmental changes. SarA repression of <italic>srn_9340</italic> and <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> was confirmed by <italic>trans</italic>-complementation. In that experiment, higher <italic>sarA</italic> mRNA and protein levels were detected in the HG003<italic>&#x00394;sarA</italic>_pCN36-SarA strain than in the isogenic strain. However, <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> expression levels did not decline further (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref> and Supplementary Figure S4). This might be because the endogenous levels of SarA are sufficient to repress the transcription of both sRNAs. It also suggests that a phenotype linked to these sRNAs might be detected by stimulating their expression <italic>in vivo</italic> with an SarA-independent promoter.</p><p>Our study points out SarA binding differences and similarities for both promoters. Purified SarA protein specifically binds <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoters <italic>in vitro</italic>, with apparent binding constants of about 90 and 10 nM, respectively. These <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>s are within the same range as those previously reported for other SarA mRNA targets (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). This suggests that, <italic>in vitro</italic>, SarA binds target sRNA and mRNA gene promoters with similar efficiencies. Gel retardation (EMSA) assays between SarA and <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225</sub></italic>revealed multiple retarded bands, as previously observed for SarA and other target mRNA promoters, e.g. on the <italic>tst</italic> toxic shock promoter (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). Depending on gel composition and migration conditions, <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic>/SarA complexes appear as either double or single bands (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">G</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>). This suggests the coexistence of multiple conformations of the DNA/SarA complexes, as expected for a dimeric protein with a binding site made up of two anchor points (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>).The multiple complexes detected <italic>in vitro</italic> could also be related to several SarA binding sites or SarA could act as an architectural accessory protein rather than as a canonical TF (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Architectural DNA-binding proteins like these influence genomic DNA superhelicities and modify the number of base pairs per helical turn. Depending on the location of its binding sites, SarA could modify the spacing between the &#x02212;10 and &#x02212;35 boxes. This could lead the promoter to either have an optimal conformation for transcription initiation, or, conversely, an unfavorable spacing inducing transcription repression (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>).</p><p>DNase I protection assays between SarA and <italic>sprC<sub>P267</sub></italic> identified a 47-bp protected DNA sequence located at positions &#x02212;35 to +12. EMSA confirmed that this sequence contains the SarA binding site. When this section was deleted, SarA did not bind to the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter region, while the DNA fragment was sufficient for SarA binding <italic>in vitro</italic>, indicating that it is necessary and sufficient for SarA recruitment. As for SarA binding onto the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter, the protected section is a 51 bp sequence located upstream from the +1 transcriptional start site. This sequence is necessary and sufficient for SarA binding onto the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter. Previous studies revealed that the SarA region protected against DNAse I cleavages ranges from 31 to 144 bp (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Such differences can be excused: some protected sequences corresponded to multiple SarA binding sites, thus the 47/51 bp SarA protected regions are within the ranges previously reported.</p><p>The SarA binding sequences were able to be reduced to about 22/23 nts long after EMSA studies using 30-nt overlapping DNA sequences together with longer sequences interrupted by internal deletion (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5J</xref>). Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> sums up the experimental evidence we collected showing SarA TF binding onto the two sRNA promoters, along with the existing information from the literature. The SarA binding site identified on the sarA P3 promoter is 26 bp-long, a similar size to the 22/23 bp sequence identified on the two sRNA promoters. Moreover, the 22/23 nt sequences are similar to a previously reported 26 bp consensus sequence that is required for SarA binding (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). This consensus sequence is not always detected within the promoters of the genes directly regulated by SarA. SarA binding studies used SELEX to identify a 7 bp segment required for SarA binding <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). That same sequence was present (with a mismatch tolerance of one) at least once within the 150 bp upstream from the TSS in 72 of 102 SarA-regulated genes (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). The analysis of the <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic> and the <italic>srn_9340<sub>51</sub></italic> SarA-protected sequences revealed two adjacent palindromes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). These palindromes could anchor the SarA dimer onto the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). SarA binds DNA as a dimer (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), and although the presence of a palindromic sequence is not a prerequisite for dimer binding, it may facilitate sarA recruitment. In <italic>S. aureus</italic>, the CodY TF acts as a dimer and also binds palindromic sequences (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). Furthermore, the SarA-regulated sRNAs promoters <italic>sprC<sub>22</sub></italic> and <italic>srn_9340<sub>23</sub></italic> each contains part of a palindrome, and their absence in <italic>sprC<sub>P267&#x00394;22</sub></italic>and <italic>srn_9340<sub>P225&#x00394;23</sub></italic> prevents SarA from binding <italic>in vitro</italic>. Altogether, our data are consistent with previous studies on SarA binding and provide further evidence that sarA binding requires an ATTTTAT sequence in its target's promoter (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Moreover, SarA binding covers the TATA box and &#x02212;35 region of <italic>sarA</italic> mRNA (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), both necessary sequences for &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> subunit RNA polymerase binding prior to transcription initiation (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). SarA may repress sRNA promoter transcription through its ability to compete with the RNA polymerase for promoter binding, as proposed for mRNAs regulated by SarA (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>).</p><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Analysis of the SarA-protected sequences on the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoters. The alignment of the <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic> and <italic>srn_9340<sub>51</sub></italic> sequences was performed using Clustal Omega software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo/</ext-link>). Boxes outline the &#x02212;35 (yellow) and &#x02212;10 (red) boxes. The TSS is indicated with a black arrow; the SarA binding site defined by Sterba <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>. (5&#x02032;ATTTTAT3&#x02032;) is shown with dotted arrows (reverse complementary sequences); palindromic sequences are depicted by large arrows; and identical nucleotides are identified with stars. The 22 nt of <italic>sprC<sub>47</sub></italic> and the 23 nt of <italic>srn_9340</italic> that are necessary for SarA binding are bold.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkw777fig8"/></fig><p>We showed with ChIP that SarA binds the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter regions <italic>in vivo</italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). These experiments also revealed that when the RNA polymerase subunit &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> binds the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> promoter, P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> enrichment with anti &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> antibodies was statistically higher when SarA was deleted. Therefore, SarA and &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> probably bind P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> in a mutually exclusive manner. We performed EMSA competition studies with the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoters, purified bacterial RNA polymerase and SarA. These experiments suggested that RNA polymerase holoenzyme and SarA cannot bind the two promoters simultaneously. This is consistent with the fact that they both bind to the same area within P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic>. ChIP data for the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter region using anti-&#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> antibodies were variable from one experiment to another (Supplementary Figure S6). The &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup>-ChIP experimental procedure was not useful for the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter due to the proximity of another highly transcribed gene (<italic>tRNA<sup>ser</sup></italic>) within the 400 bp surrounding <italic>srn_9340</italic>.Through &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> binding onto <italic>tRNA<sup>ser</sup></italic>, immunoprecipitation with anti-&#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> antibodies resulted in a DNA fragment containing <italic>srn_9340</italic>. Therefore, the link between &#x003c3;<sup>A</sup> enrichment of the <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoter and the presence or absence of SarA is not relevant. This highlights the difficulty of ChIP analysis using antibodies directed against housekeeping proteins such as &#x003c3; factor when done in bacterial genomes with closely located genes. We propose that SarA binds the <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> and <italic>srn_9340</italic> promoters and prevents RNA polymerase binding. <italic>In vitro</italic> transcription assays, in the presence/absence of purified SarA, at each sRNA promoter, confirmed that hypothesis since the presence of SarA drastically reduced the synthesis of each sRNA.</p><p>We report here that sarA-mediated transcriptional repression of P<italic><sub>sprC</sub></italic> and P<italic><sub>srn_9340</sub></italic> is effective throughout bacterial growth. External signals, possibly during infection and phagocytosis, may affect SarA binding onto the two sRNA promoters. This could be through post-translational modifications (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>) or targeted degradation, with these changes inducing the release of SarA from the sRNA promoters, thus allowing their fast and efficient transcription. In the presence of oxidants, high levels of <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> hamper survival (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), implying that the SarA-mediated transcriptional control of this sRNA is essential during oxidative stress. These recent observations suggest that <italic>srn_3610_sprC</italic> expression levels must be tightly regulated, requiring timely transcription derepression for tasks that remain unidentified.</p><p>In conclusion, as far as we know these two <italic>S. aureus</italic> sRNAs gene negatively regulated by SarA are the first reported examples of joint transcriptional regulation of sRNAs. This may however represent just the tip of the iceberg, especially since coordinated regulation of several sRNAs by a single TF would be a significant advantage for bacterial fitness. We have already begun investigations aimed at exploring the functioning of Srn_9340 and at uncovering the physiological signals that remove SarA from the sRNA promoters to allow their optimal expression.</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_44_21_10186__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_gkw777_nar-01766-y-2016-File010.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank our lab colleagues, particularly Y. Augagneur; G. Pascreau, for reading the manuscript and giving advice; M. Hallier, for the strains, plasmids and technical help with SarA purification; and H. Le Pabic for her shared interest in Srn_3610_SprC. We also would like to thank A. Cheung for the SarA family mutants and E. Charpentier for the pCN plasmids.</p></ack><sec id="SEC5"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/nar/gkw777/-/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p></sec><sec id="SEC6"><title>FUNDING</title><p>Institut National de la Sant&#x000e9; et de la Recherche M&#x000e9;dicale; University of Rennes 1; R&#x000e9;gion Bretagne (to T.M.); Direction G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rale de l'Armement (DGA) (to T.M.). Funding for open access charge: Inserm.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></sec><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowy</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Staphylococcus aureus infections</article-title>
<source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>339</volume>
<fpage>520</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9709046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van&#x000a0;Belkum</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verkaik</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>de&#x000a0;Vogel</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boelens</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verveer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nouwen</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbrugh</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wertheim</surname><given-names>H.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reclassification of Staphylococcus aureus nasal carriage types</article-title>
<source>J. Infect. Dis.</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>199</volume>
<fpage>1820</fpage><lpage>1826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19419332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>H.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deleo</surname><given-names>F.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Waves of resistance: Staphylococcus aureus in the antibiotic era</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>629</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19680247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fechter</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldelari</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lioliou</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romby</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Novel aspects of RNA regulation in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>FEBS Lett.</source>
<year>2014</year>
<volume>588</volume>
<fpage>2523</fpage><lpage>2529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24873876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudkin</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feil</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van&#x000a0;den&#x000a0;Elsen</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laabei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucks</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Recker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Massey</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>From genotype to phenotype: can systems biology be used to predict Staphylococcus aureus virulence</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>791</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23070558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigneshweraraj</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of virulence gene expression</article-title>
<source>Virulence</source>
<year>2014</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>832</fpage><lpage>834</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25603428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Global regulation of virulence determinants in Staphylococcus aureus by the SarA protein family</article-title>
<source>Front. Biosci.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>d1825</fpage><lpage>1842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12133812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browning</surname><given-names>D.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The regulation of bacterial transcription initiation</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>57</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15035009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manna</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Control of thioredoxin reductase gene (trxB) transcription by SarA in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>192</volume>
<fpage>336</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19854896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishina</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manna</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>SarA of Staphylococcus aureus binds to the sarA promoter to regulate gene expression</article-title>
<source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>190</volume>
<fpage>2239</fpage><lpage>2243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18178734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manna</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriksunov</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Structural and function analyses of the global regulatory protein SarA from Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>2392</fpage><lpage>2397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16455801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manna</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Transcriptional regulation of the agr locus and the identification of DNA binding residues of the global regulatory protein SarR in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>1289</fpage><lpage>1301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16689803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrichs</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>sar Genetic determinants necessary for transcription of RNAII and RNAIII in the agr locus of Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>179</volume>
<fpage>3963</fpage><lpage>3971</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9190813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koomey</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Projan</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischetti</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of exoprotein expression in Staphylococcus aureus by a locus (sar) distinct from agr</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>89</volume>
<fpage>6462</fpage><lpage>6466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1321441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishina</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trotonda</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The SarA protein family of Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol.</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>355</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18083623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunman</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haney</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tucker-Kellogg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zagursky</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shlaes</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Projan</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Transcription profiling-based identification of Staphylococcus aureus genes regulated by the agr and/or sarA loci</article-title>
<source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>183</volume>
<fpage>7341</fpage><lpage>7353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11717293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blevins</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillaspy</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rechtin</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurlburt</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smeltzer</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The Staphylococcal accessory regulator (sar) represses transcription of the Staphylococcus aureus collagen adhesin gene (cna) in an agr-independent manner</article-title>
<source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>317</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10411748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manna</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Projan</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>SarA, a global regulator of virulence determinants in Staphylococcus aureus, binds to a conserved motif essential for sar-dependent gene regulation</article-title>
<source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>274</volume>
<fpage>37169</fpage><lpage>37176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10601279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manna</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingavale</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>van&#x000a0;Wamel</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Identification of sarV (SA2062), a new transcriptional regulator, is repressed by SarA and MgrA (SA0641) and involved in the regulation of autolysis in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>186</volume>
<fpage>5267</fpage><lpage>5280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15292128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rechtin</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillaspy</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smeltzer</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurlburt</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Characterization of the SarA virulence gene regulator of Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>307</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10411747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guillet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felden</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Emerging functions for the Staphylococcus aureus RNome</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e1003767</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24348246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sassi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Augagneur</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivain</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chabelskaya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sallou</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felden</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>SRD: a Staphylococcus regulatory RNA database</article-title>
<source>RNA</source>
<year>2015</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1017</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25805861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pichon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felden</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Small RNA genes expressed from Staphylococcus aureus genomic and pathogenicity islands with specific expression among pathogenic strains</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>14249</fpage><lpage>14254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16183745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chabelskaya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaillot</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felden</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A Staphylococcus aureus small RNA is required for bacterial virulence and regulates the expression of an immune-evasion molecule</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>e1000927</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20532214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romilly</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lays</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomasini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldelari</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benito</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammann</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geissmann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boisset</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romby</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenesch</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A non-coding RNA promotes bacterial persistence and decreases virulence by regulating a regulator in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<year>2014</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>e1003979</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24651379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romilly</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldelari</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmentier</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lioliou</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romby</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fechter</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Current knowledge on regulatory RNAs and their machineries in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>RNA Biol.</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>402</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22546940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maleki</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smeltzer</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurlburt</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Staphylococcus aureus AgrA binding to the RNAIII-agr regulatory region</article-title>
<source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>186</volume>
<fpage>7549</fpage><lpage>7555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15516566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrey</surname><given-names>D.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monod</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Coordinated regulation by AgrA, SarA, and SarR to control agr expression in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>193</volume>
<fpage>6020</fpage><lpage>6031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21908676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>ArtR, a novel sRNA of Staphylococcus aureus, regulates alpha-toxin expression by targeting the 5&#x02032; UTR of sarT mRNA</article-title>
<source>Med. Microbiol. Immunol.</source>
<year>2014</year>
<volume>203</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23955428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boisset</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geissmann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huntzinger</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fechter</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bendridi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Possedko</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Helfer</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benito</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacquier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Staphylococcus aureus RNAIII coordinately represses the synthesis of virulence factors and the transcription regulator Rot by an antisense mechanism</article-title>
<source>Genes Dev.</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>1353</fpage><lpage>1366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17545468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geisinger</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>H.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inhibition of rot translation by RNAIII, a key feature of agr function</article-title>
<source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>61</volume>
<fpage>1038</fpage><lpage>1048</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16879652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luong</surname><given-names>T.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>RNAIII of the Staphylococcus aureus agr system activates global regulator MgrA by stabilizing mRNA</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<year>2015</year>
<volume>112</volume>
<fpage>14036</fpage><lpage>14041</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26504242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le&#x000a0;Pabic</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Germain-Amiot</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordeau</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felden</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A bacterial regulatory RNA attenuates virulence, spread and human host cell phagocytosis</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<year>2015</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>9232</fpage><lpage>9248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26240382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krausz</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Bacteriophage transduction in Staphylococcus aureus: broth-based method</article-title>
<source>Methods Mol. Biol.</source>
<year>2016</year>
<volume>1373</volume>
<fpage>63</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25646607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziebandt</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlsen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hecker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Repair of global regulators in Staphylococcus aureus 8325 and comparative analysis with other clinical isolates</article-title>
<source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>78</volume>
<fpage>2877</fpage><lpage>2889</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20212089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kreiswirth</surname><given-names>B.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofdahl</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Betley</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlievert</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergdoll</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The toxic shock syndrome exotoxin structural gene is not detectably transmitted by a prophage</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>1983</year>
<volume>305</volume>
<fpage>709</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6226876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charpentier</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anton</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfonso</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Novel cassette-based shuttle vector system for gram-positive bacteria</article-title>
<source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>6076</fpage><lpage>6085</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinel-Marie</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brielle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felden</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Dual toxic-peptide-coding Staphylococcus aureus RNA under antisense regulation targets host cells and bacterial rivals unequally</article-title>
<source>Cell Rep.</source>
<year>2014</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>424</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24703849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eyraud</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tattevin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chabelskaya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felden</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A small RNA controls a protein regulator involved in antibiotic resistance in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<year>2014</year>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>4892</fpage><lpage>4905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24557948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smale</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>DNase I footprinting</article-title>
<source>Cold Spring Harb. Protoc.</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>2013</volume>
<fpage>469</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23637368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slatko</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albright</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>DNA sequencing by the dideoxy method</article-title>
<source>Curr. Protoc. Mol. Biol.</source>
<year>2001</year><comment>doi:10.1002/0471142727.mb0704as47</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faith</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayete</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaden</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogno</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wierzbowski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cottarel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasif</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Large-scale mapping and validation of Escherichia coli transcriptional regulation from a compendium of expression profiles</article-title>
<source>PLoS Biol.</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>e8</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17214507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manna</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Characterization of sarR, a modulator of sar expression in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>69</volume>
<fpage>885</fpage><lpage>896</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11159982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manna</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>SarT, a repressor of alpha-hemolysin in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>69</volume>
<fpage>4749</fpage><lpage>4758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11447147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howden</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaume</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrenzel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seemann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Francois</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinear</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Analysis of the small RNA transcriptional response in multidrug-resistant Staphylococcus aureus after antimicrobial exposure</article-title>
<source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>3864</fpage><lpage>3874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23733475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mader</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Depke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pane-Farre</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debarbouille</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>van&#x000a0;der&#x000a0;Kooi-Pol</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derozier</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiron</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarmer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Staphylococcus aureus transcriptome architecture: from laboratory to infection-mimicking conditions</article-title>
<source>PLoS Genet.</source>
<year>2016</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>e1005962</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27035918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oscarsson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tegmark-Wisell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arvidson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>SarA is a repressor of hla (alpha-hemolysin) transcription in Staphylococcus aureus: its apparent role as an activator of hla in the prototype strain NCTC 8325 depends on reduced expression of sarS</article-title>
<source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>188</volume>
<fpage>8526</fpage><lpage>8533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17012389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganguly</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanda</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandhu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jana</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sau</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sau</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Stabilization of the primary sigma factor of Staphylococcus aureus by core RNA polymerase</article-title>
<source>BMB Rep.</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>176</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20356457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belcheva</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Korenevsky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Golemi-Kotra</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Roles of DNA sequence and sigma A factor in transcription of the vraSR operon</article-title>
<source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>194</volume>
<fpage>61</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22020638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>E.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romby</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Small RNAs in bacteria and archaea: who they are, what they do, and how they do it</article-title>
<source>Adv. Genet.</source>
<year>2015</year>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>133</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26296935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beenken</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blevins</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smeltzer</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mutation of sarA in Staphylococcus aureus limits biofilm formation</article-title>
<source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>4206</fpage><lpage>4211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12819120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blevins</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elasri</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allmendinger</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beenken</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smeltzer</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Role of sarA in the pathogenesis of Staphylococcus aureus musculoskeletal infection</article-title>
<source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>516</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12496203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledo-Arana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berasain</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghigo</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amorena</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Penades</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>SarA and not sigmaB is essential for biofilm development by Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>1075</fpage><lpage>1087</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12753197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrey</surname><given-names>D.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renzoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monod</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lew</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Control of the Staphylococcus aureus toxic shock tst promoter by the global regulator SarA</article-title>
<source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>192</volume>
<fpage>6077</fpage><lpage>6085</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20870770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belcheva</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Golemi-Kotra</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Staphylococcus aureus methicillin-resistance factor fmtA is regulated by the global regulator SarA</article-title>
<source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>e43998</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22952845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sterba</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackintosh</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blevins</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurlburt</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smeltzer</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Characterization of Staphylococcus aureus SarA binding sites</article-title>
<source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>185</volume>
<fpage>4410</fpage><lpage>4417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12867449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>D.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higginbotham</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sterba</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maleki</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segall</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smeltzer</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurlburt</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Staphylococcus aureus SarA is a regulatory protein responsive to redox and pH that can support bacteriophage lambda integrase-mediated excision/recombination</article-title>
<source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>1445</fpage><lpage>1458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19919677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bronner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteil</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prevost</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of virulence determinants in Staphylococcus aureus: complexity and applications</article-title>
<source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>183</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15109784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurlburt</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Crystal structures of SarA, a pleiotropic regulator of virulence genes in S. aureus</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>409</volume>
<fpage>215</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11196648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stenz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Francois</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiteson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrenzel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The CodY pleiotropic repressor controls virulence in gram-positive pathogens</article-title>
<source>FEMS Immunol. Med. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>123</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21539625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinton</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Transcription regulation at the core: similarities among bacterial, archaeal, and eukaryotic RNA polymerases</article-title>
<source>Annu. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>113</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23768203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Didier</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cozzone</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duclos</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Phosphorylation of the virulence regulator SarA modulates its ability to bind DNA in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
<source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>306</volume>
<fpage>30</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20337713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Protein cysteine phosphorylation of SarA/MgrA family transcriptional regulators mediates bacterial virulence and antibiotic resistance</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>109</volume>
<fpage>15461</fpage><lpage>15466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22927394</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>