<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4736615</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2419</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-2419-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Structure, phylogeny, allelic haplotypes and expression of sucrose transporter gene families in <italic>Saccharum</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Qing</given-names></name><address><email>297160480@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Weichang</given-names></name><address><email>654919671@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Fan</given-names></name><address><email>fanzhu2@illinois.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Liming</given-names></name><address><email>849473519@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Qingyi</given-names></name><address><email>qyu@ag.tamu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>Ray</given-names></name><address><email>rming@life.illinois.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jisen</given-names></name><address><email>zjisen@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Center for Genomics and Biotechnology, Haixia Institute of Science and Technology (HIST), Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, Fuzhou, 350002 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Plant Biology, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, IL 61801 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>TexasA&#x00026;M AgriLife Research, Department of Plant Pathology and Microbiology, Texas A&#x00026;M University System, Dallas, TX 75252 USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>College of Life Sciences, Fujian Normal University, Fuzhou, 350117 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>88</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Zhang et al. 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Sugarcane is an economically important crop contributing to about 80&#x000a0;% of the world sugar production. Increasing efforts in molecular biological studies have been performed for improving the sugar yield and other relevant important agronomic traits. However, due to sugarcane&#x02019;s complicated genomes, it is still challenging to study the genetic basis of traits, such as sucrose accumulation. Sucrose transporters (SUTs) are critical for both phloem loading in source tissue and sucrose uptaking in sink tissue, and are considered to be the control points for regulating sucrose storage. However, no genomic study for sugarcane sucrose transporter (SsSUT) families has been reported up to date.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>By using comparative genomics and bacterial artificial chromosomes (BACs), six SUT genes were identified and characterized in <italic>S. spontaenum</italic>. Phylogenetic analyses revealed that the two pairs <italic>SsSUTs</italic> (<italic>SsSUT1</italic>/<italic>SsSUT3</italic> and <italic>SsSUT5</italic>/<italic>SsSUT6</italic>) could be clustered together into two separate monocot specific SUT groups, while <italic>SsSUT2</italic> and <italic>SsSUT4</italic> were separated into the other two groups, with members from both dicot and monocot species. Gene structure comparison demonstrated that the number and position of exons/introns in <italic>SUTs</italic> were highly conserved among the close orthologs; in contrast, there were variations among the paralogous <italic>SUTs</italic> in <italic>Sacchuarm</italic>. Though with the high polyploidy level, gene allelic haplotype comparative analysis showed that the examined four <italic>SsSUT</italic> member<italic>s</italic> exhibited conservations of gene structures and amino acid sequences among the allelic haplotypes accompanied by variations of intron sizes. Gene expression analyses were performed for tissues from seedlings under drought stress and mature plants of three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species (<italic>S.officinarnum</italic>, <italic>S.spotaneum</italic> and <italic>S.robustum</italic>). Both <italic>SUT1</italic> and <italic>SUT4</italic> expressed abundantly at different conditions. <italic>SUT2</italic> had similar expression level in all of the examined tissues, but <italic>SUT3</italic> was undetectable. Both of <italic>SUT5</italic> and <italic>SUT6</italic> had lower expression level than other gene member, and expressed stronger in source leaves and are likely to play roles in phloem loading. In the seeding plant leave under water stress, four genes <italic>SUT1</italic>, <italic>SUT2</italic>, <italic>SUT4</italic> and <italic>SUT5</italic> were detectable. In these detectable genes, <italic>SUT1</italic> and <italic>SUT4</italic> were down regulated, while, <italic>SUT2</italic> and <italic>SUT5</italic> were up regulated.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this study, we presented the first comprehensive genomic study for a whole gene family, the SUT family, in <italic>Saccharum</italic>. We speculated that there were six <italic>SUT</italic> members in the <italic>S. spotaneum</italic> genome. Out of the six members, <italic>SsSUTs</italic>, <italic>SsSUT5</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6</italic> were recent duplication genes accompanied by rapid evolution, while, <italic>SsSUT2</italic> and <italic>SsSUT4</italic> were the ancient members in the families. Despite the high polypoidy genome, functional redundancy may not exist among the SUTs allelic haplotypes supported by the evidence of strong purifying selection of the gene allele. <italic>SUT3</italic> could be a low active member in the family because it is undetectable in our study, but it might not be a pseudogene because it harbored integrated gene structure. <italic>SUT1</italic> and <italic>SUT4</italic> were the main members for the sucrose transporter, while, these <italic>SUTs</italic> had sub-functional divergence in response to sucrose accumulation and plant development in <italic>Saccharum</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12864-016-2419-6) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Saccharum</italic> species</kwd><kwd>Sucrose transporter</kwd><kwd>Gene family</kwd><kwd>Allelic haplotype</kwd><kwd>Polyploidy</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100002855</institution-id><institution>Ministry of Science and Technology of the People's Republic of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2013AA100604</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jisen</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China (CN)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>31201260</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jisen</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Fujian Provincial Department of Education</institution></funding-source><award-id>JA12082</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jisen</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p>Sucrose transporters (SUTs) are important for both phloem loading in source tissue and sucrose uptake into some sink cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. SUTs are considered to be the control points for sucrose storage in plant because they can carry sucrose across cell membranes and play an important role in loading sucrose into phloem systems in a series of steps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Plant SUTs belong to the glycoside-pentoside-hexuronide (GPH) cation symporter family (TC2.A.2) that is part of the major facilitator super-family (MFS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Transporters in the GPH family have the primary characteristics of MFS proteins that contain 12 transmembrane spanning domains with N- and C-termini in the cytoplasm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Since the first plant sucrose transporter SoSUT1 was functionally identified using an elegant yeast complementation strategy from spinach (<italic>Spinacea Oleracea</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], SUTs have been demonstrated to effect on the multiple aspects of plant development such as biomass partitioning, pollen germination, restraining plant growth, fruit size reduction and ethylene biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p>Comprehensive understanding of the molecular structure and evolution of a gene family in plant species is the first step towards understanding their physiological roles and metabolic mechanism involved in different growth phases. Recent studies have revealed that <italic>SUT</italic> was a small gene family that consisted of at least four <italic>SUT</italic> genes in the most plant species. The SUT family members have been identified from a number of plant species such as <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], populus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], sorghum (<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and pineapple (<italic>Ananas comosus</italic>) (Unpublished, Zhang and Ming) as well. Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>SUT</italic> family suggested that the plant <italic>SUT</italic> could be divided into five subgroups including two monocot specific subgroups, one dicot specific and two monocot-dicot subgroups. <italic>SUT</italic> family members in many plant species are divergent in function and deferentially expressed in different tissues types or at different plant developmental stages. For instance, in rice, <italic>OsSUT1</italic> expression has been detected in germinated seeds, leaf blades, leaf sheaths and panicles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]; the expressions of both <italic>OsSUT3</italic> and <italic>OsSUT5</italic> are dramatically lower in embryos than those of <italic>OsSUT1</italic>, <italic>OsSUT2,</italic> and <italic>OsSUT4</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]; <italic>OsSUT4</italic> has been detected in most tissues such as roots, leaves, and panicles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], and could play a role in sucrose loading into the sheath phloem of the upper leaves during the post-heading period for sucrose transport to developing grains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], <italic>AtSUC2</italic> has been detected in phloem and companion cells in source leaves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] and functions in loading sucrose into the phloem sieve elements (SEs), correspond with the result identified by tissue-specific complementation of different promoters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] and by <sup>14</sup>C labeling studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]; <italic>AtSUC3</italic> and <italic>AtSUC4</italic> are expressed in minor veins of source leaves of mature plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p><p>Sugarcane (<italic>Saccharum spp.)</italic> is one of the world&#x02019;s most produced crops (FAOSTAT, 2015), and contributes to about 80&#x000a0;% of the world sugar and about 40&#x000a0;% of ethanol production worldwide. Modern sugarcane cultivar has one of the most complex genome among all the crops; by being both aneupoid and autopolypoid with an extreme ploidy level that can range from octoploidy (x&#x02009;=&#x02009;8) to dodecaploidy (x&#x02009;=&#x02009;12). Approximately 80&#x000a0;% of cultivars&#x02019; chromosomes are derived from <italic>S. officinarum</italic> and 10&#x02013;20&#x000a0;% is derived from <italic>S.spontaneum</italic> with the remained from interspecific recombination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Sugarcane is not only an economically important crop species, but also serves as an important model crop for studying sucrose transporters because its remarkable ability to accumulate vast amounts of sucrose in its stems that can reach close to 700&#x000a0;mM or in excess of 50&#x000a0;% of the dry weight (DW) (DW) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. But to date, limited works in characterizing these <italic>SUT</italic> genes have been reported, except for <italic>SUT1</italic> (transcripts accession:AY780256.1, GU812864.1 and BU925792). In an earlier study based on sugarcane Expressed Sequence Tag (EST) database survey, <italic>SUT1</italic> was revealed to be more abundant in the mature internodes than the other tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. This result was confirmed by a study for Hawaiian sugarcane cultivar, in which the <italic>SUT1</italic> transcript levels increased during maturation and sucrose storage, whereas, <italic>SUT1</italic> expression was observed to be not affected by sugarcane yellow leaf virus (SCYLV) infection in sugarcane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Biochemical analysis of sugarcane <italic>SUT1</italic> suggested that SUT1 was highly selective for sucrose, but had a relatively low affinity for sucrose, inhibited by sucralose and played key role in sucrose loading from the vascular tissues into the storage sites in parenchyma cells of sugarcane stems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Besides <italic>SUT1</italic>, the gene family of <italic>SUTs</italic> is not understood in sugarcane due to the formidable challenge caused by its high degree of polyploidy and heterozygosity genome.</p><p>In this study, to gain comprehensive understandings of the molecular and evolutionary characterization as well as the possible functions of <italic>SUT</italic> family in sugarcane, based on combination of comparative genomics strategies and high genome coverage of bacterial artificial chromosomes (BACs) libraries resources, we identified and characterized <italic>SUT</italic> gene families in <italic>Saccharum</italic> species and investigated their transcriptional expression patterns. The analysis in this study mainly focused on: (1) identifying the gene members and allele haplotypes of the <italic>SUT</italic> gene family in sugarcane; (2) analyzing evolutionary relationship, exon/intron organization of the <italic>SUT</italic> gene family; and (3) characterizing the expression patterns of the SUT gene family in three progenitor <italic>Saccharum</italic> species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant materials</title><p>Three varieties of <italic>Saccharum</italic> species were used in the study: LA-Purple (<italic>S. officinarum</italic>, 2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;8x&#x02009;=&#x02009;80), Molokai6081 (<italic>S. robustum</italic>, 2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;8x&#x02009;=&#x02009;80) and SES208 (<italic>S. spontaneum</italic>, 2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;8x&#x02009;=&#x02009;64) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Plants were grown in plastic pots under greenhouse conditions and standard growing practices. Tissue samples were obtained from 10-month old plants (as replicates) for leaf roll, leaf, top immature internode (i.e. internode number 3), premature internode (i.e. internode number 9 for &#x02018;LA Purple&#x02019; and Molokai6081 due to short internode, and internode number 6 for SES208 due to long internode) and mature internode (i.e. internode number 15 for &#x02018;LA Purple&#x02019; and Molokai6081, and internode number 9 for SES208 due to long internode &#x02013; most SES208 plants have about 12 internodes). The internodes were numbered from top to bottom according to the method of Moore [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Stem and leaf tissues from seedlings of the three species were collected at 35&#x000a0;days after planting. For drought stress treatment, the 35&#x000a0;day-old seedlings were treated with PEG6000 (30&#x000a0;%) for 48&#x000a0;h, and stem and leaf tissues were collected. The tissues were immediately frozen using liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C prior to RNA isolation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>BAC libraries</title><p>The haploid of <italic>S. Spontaneum</italic> SES208, Ap85-441 (2n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4x&#x02009;=&#x02009;32), was used to construct the BAC library. Nuclei were isolated from the young leaf tissues of AP85-441 following the method described by Ming <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The high molecular weight DNA embedded in agarose was partially digested using <italic>HindIII</italic>. Fractions at approximately 100&#x000a0;kb were recovered and cloned into pSMART BAC vector (Lucigen, LA). 38,400 clones from AP85-441 BAC libraries were picked and stored in 100 384-well plates with freezing medium. BAC clones were grided onto Performa II Nylon Filters (Genetix) using Q-Pix 2 (Genetix).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Database search for the SUT gene family and phylogenetic analyses</title><p>The sequence data used in this study were collected using the keyword &#x0201c;sucrose transporter&#x0201d; and a query search in the GenBank using the known SUT gene sequences from sorghum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Matches achieved similarity scores of 50.0 and probability scores &#x0003e;50.0 and e-value &#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> were collected.</p><p>The amino acid sequences of sucrose transporter gene family members in 6 monocotyledons (<italic>Zea mays</italic>, <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic>, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>, <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>, <italic>Setaria italica</italic> and <italic>Saccharum spontaneum</italic>) and 5 dicotyledons (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic>, <italic>Glycine max</italic>, <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> and Vitis vinifera,) identified by searching public databases available at various resources. The phylogenetic trees were constructed with the MEGA5.2.1 program with ClustalW alignment using default parameter.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Identification and sequencing of SUT families from BAC library</title><p>BAC library screening was carried out as described by Yu <italic>et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. The BAC clones representing different haplotypes were selected. The insert size of BAC clones was estimated by comparing with standard size markers using CHEF gel electrophoresis. The BAC DNAs were isolated using PhasePrep<sup>TM</sup> TMBAC DNA kit (Sigma-Aldrich, NA0100-1KT) and the sequencing libraries were prepared individually with unique barcode for each clone. The sequencing libraries were then pooled and sequenced with 150&#x000a0;bp, pair-end reads on Illumina Hiseq2500 at Center for Genomics and Biotechnology in Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University. The raw reads were then assembled using SPAdes Genome Assember v. 3.1.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinf.spbau.ru/en/spades">http://bioinf.spbau.ru/en/spades</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Genomic sequence annotation and functional prediction</title><p>The genomic sequences of SUT genes were annotated by DNA subway (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnasubway.iplantcollaborative.org/">http://dnasubway.iplantcollaborative.org/</ext-link>), and the corresponding CDS sequences were translated into protein by the EXPASy-translate tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://web.expasy.org/translate/">http://web.expasy.org/translate/</ext-link>). The exon-intron structures were graphed using online tool GSDS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gsds.cbi.pku.edu.cn/">http://gsds.cbi.pku.edu.cn/</ext-link>). The putative conserved domains of sucrose transporter protein were detected by using BLASTp (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>) and InterPro (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/scan.html">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/scan.html</ext-link>). The protein transmembrane helices domain was predicted using TMPRED (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/TMPRED_form.html">http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/TMPRED_form.html</ext-link>). The isoelectric point and relative molecular mass of the protein were predicted using ExPASy (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://web.expasy.org/compute_pi/">http://web.expasy.org/compute_pi/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Analysis of sucrose transporter gene co-expression profiling</title><p>The sorghum gene models were used as reference to align the <italic>Saccharum</italic> RNA-seq database by using NOVOALIGN (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.novocraft.com/">http://www.novocraft.com/</ext-link>) with default parameter. The normalization and statistical evaluation of differential gene expression has been performed using EDGE-R with a <italic>p</italic>-value cut-off of 0.05 and using the Benjamini-Hochberg (1995)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] method for multiple testing corrections. The raw data was normalized according to the default procedure of the differential expression analysis package used. The dispersion was estimated using the pooled setting. The expression values were log-transformed, and cluster analyses were performed using a software cluster with Euclidean distances and the hierarchical cluster method of &#x0201c;complete linkage clustering&#x0201d;. The clustering tree was constructed and viewed in JAVA Treeview.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Experimental validation of expression levels of SUT gene by qRT-PCR</title><p>The expression levels of six SUT genes in three tissues (internode 9, 15 and leaf roll in LA-Purple, internode 8,13 and leaf roll in Molokai6081, and internode 6, 9 and leaf roll in SES208) of three Saccharum species were validated by qRT-PCR. Gene-specific primer pairs were designed by using Integrated DNA Technologies (IDT) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.idtdna.com/Primerquest/Home/Index">http://www.idtdna.com/Primerquest/Home/Index</ext-link>). After treated with DNase I (Tiangen, China), two microgram of RNA was used in reverse transcription with the SuperScript VILO cDNA Synthesis Kit (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s guidelines. The real-time qPCR was performed by using Multicolor Real-Time PCR Detection System (Bio-Rad) with conditions for all reactions were 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30s, 40&#x000a0;cycles of 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;s, followed by 60&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30s, and 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 10s. Melting curve analysis were performed to confirm the PCR specificity. The glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase gene (<italic>GAPDH</italic>) and Eukaryotic elongation factor 1a (<italic>eEF-1a</italic>) were selected as internal standard for normalization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], and three replicates were completed for each sample. The relative expression level for each SUT gene in different tissues of three Saccharum species were calculated by using the 2-&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct method. The correlation coefficient was calculated between the transcript accumulation levels obtained by RNAseq and qRT-PCR using Excel.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Identification of six SUT genes in Sugarcane</title><p>20 positive BAC clones from AP85-441 were identified using 6 probes (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) designed from six well-annotated <italic>SUTs</italic> genomic regions in <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). To determine haplotypes, the PCR fragments of the six <italic>SUTs</italic> were cloned by using these probe primers and sequenced, which confirmed 14 of these 20 BAC clones contains different paralogous and homologous haplotypes. The six <italic>S.spontaneum SUTs</italic> were referred to <italic>SsSUT1</italic>-<italic>SsSUT6</italic> according to sequence similarity with sorghum <italic>SUTs</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In the 14 <italic>SUT</italic> sequences, both <italic>SsSUT1</italic> and <italic>SsSUT5</italic>, both <italic>SsSUT3</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6</italic> and remaining two <italic>SUTs</italic> have 2, 4 and 1 allelic haplotypes, respectively. The allelic haplotypes of each <italic>SUTs</italic> were indicated additional&#x0201c;-h1&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;-h4&#x0201d; to the gene name end. Using the gene model sequences of the annotated <italic>SUT</italic> genes as queries, both the in-house EST and Genbank database were extensively searched. The results showed that all the <italic>SsSUTs</italic> had the corresponding ESTs in the Genbank database except <italic>SsSUT3</italic> (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Information of the putative SUT genes in sorghum</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gene name</th><th>Gene ID</th><th>Location of the gene</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT1</italic>
</td><td>
<italic>Sb</italic>01g045720</td><td>NC_012870.1|:68807992-68813945 chromosome 1</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT2</italic>
</td><td>
<italic>Sb</italic>04g038030</td><td>NC_012873.1|:67544380-67548965 chromosome 4</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT3</italic>
</td><td>
<italic>Sb</italic>01g022430</td><td>NC_012870.1|:c28297080-28293801 chromosome 1</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT4</italic>
</td><td>
<italic>Sb</italic>08g023310</td><td>NC_012877.1|:c55444565-55438275 chromosome 8</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT5</italic>
</td><td>
<italic>Sb</italic>04g023860</td><td>NC_012873.1|:c53548702-53545522 chromosome 4</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT6</italic>
</td><td>
<italic>Sb</italic>07g028120</td><td>NC_012876.1|:c63108611-63106213 chromosome 7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>The six <italic>SsSUTs</italic> containing complete ORFs (open reading frames) with the predicted molecular weights ranged from 51.84 to 63.41&#x000a0;kDa in sugarcane (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Comparing with the <italic>SUT</italic> family from sorghum, <italic>SsSUT5</italic> showed a lower molecular weight, and the remaining gene pairs between these two species were consistent. <italic>SsSUT5</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6</italic> shared a higher similarity of protein sequences (82&#x000a0;%) in contrast to the other 14 pairwise sequences between the remaining four genes in the SUT families (39&#x02013;69&#x000a0;%) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The analyses of the deducted protein sequences of the <italic>SUT</italic> genes in sugarcane revealed that all these gene families had highly conserved MFS domains and contained 12 membrane-spanning helices (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). A conserved histidine residue was presented in the first loop domain corresponding to His-65 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] and amino acids which corresponded to the G-X-X-X-D/E-R/K-X-G-[X]-R/K-R/K motif reside in the second and eighth loop domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Additionally, <italic>SsSUT4</italic> contained a LXXLL motif in the N-terminal domain, indicating that it might be targeted to the tonoplast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of the characterization of the SUTs between sugarcane and sorghum</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="6">Sorghum</th><th colspan="7">Sugarcane</th></tr><tr><th>Gene name</th><th>Amino acids size</th><th>Molecular weights (kDa)</th><th>Domains</th><th>Isoelectric point (pI)</th><th>Transmembrane helices</th><th>Gene name</th><th>Amino acids size</th><th>Molecular weights (kDa)</th><th>Domains</th><th>Isoelectric point (pI)</th><th>Transmembrane helices</th><th>Identity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT1</italic>
</td><td>519</td><td>54.99</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>8.86</td><td>12</td><td>
<italic>SsSUT1</italic>
</td><td>521</td><td>55.08</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>8.79</td><td>12</td><td>96&#x000a0;%</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT2</italic>
</td><td>594</td><td>63.33</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>6.00</td><td>12</td><td>
<italic>SsSUT2</italic>
</td><td>598</td><td>63.41</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>5.94</td><td>12</td><td>96&#x000a0;%</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT3</italic>
</td><td>507</td><td>53.20</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>6.58</td><td>12</td><td>
<italic>SsSUT3</italic>
</td><td>508</td><td>53.47</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>7.46</td><td>12</td><td>96&#x000a0;%</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT4</italic>
</td><td>501</td><td>53.44</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>8.60</td><td>12</td><td>
<italic>SsSUT4</italic>
</td><td>501</td><td>53.44</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>8.60</td><td>12</td><td>98&#x000a0;%</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT5</italic>
</td><td>534</td><td>56.38</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>8.72</td><td>12</td><td>
<italic>SsSUT5</italic>
</td><td>495</td><td>51.84</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>7.97</td><td>12</td><td>83&#x000a0;%</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SbSUT6</italic>
</td><td>536</td><td>56.36</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>8.45</td><td>12</td><td>
<italic>SsSUT6</italic>
</td><td>554</td><td>58.86</td><td>MFS domain</td><td>8.46</td><td>12</td><td>88&#x000a0;%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Amino acid sequences pairwise comparisons (% similarity) between SUT gene members in sugarcane</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>
<italic>SsSUT1</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>SsSUT2</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>SsSUT3</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>SsSUT4</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>SsSUT5</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>SsSUT6</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>SsSUT2</italic>
</td><td>55&#x000a0;%</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SsSUT3</italic>
</td><td>69&#x000a0;%</td><td>53&#x000a0;%</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SsSUT4</italic>
</td><td>47&#x000a0;%</td><td>43&#x000a0;%</td><td>45&#x000a0;%</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SsSUT5</italic>
</td><td>50&#x000a0;%</td><td>43&#x000a0;%</td><td>49&#x000a0;%</td><td>39&#x000a0;%</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SsSUT6</italic>
</td><td>53&#x000a0;%</td><td>47&#x000a0;%</td><td>53&#x000a0;%</td><td>41&#x000a0;%</td><td>82&#x000a0;%</td><td>-</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Allelic haplotype analysis of <italic>SsSUTs</italic></title><p>Genomic sequence comparisons within the allelic haplotypes from the four <italic>SUTs</italic> revealed that these allelic haplotypes shared very high similarity above 99&#x000a0;%. Slight variations were observed within the allelic haplotypes of <italic>SsSUTs</italic>. The deducted protein sequences were compared within the four <italic>SsSUTs</italic>. The results showed that, for the protein sequence of allelic haplotypes, both <italic>SsSUT3</italic> and <italic>SsSUT5</italic> shared identities of 98.38&#x000a0;%, while, <italic>SsSUT5</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6</italic> had 98.38 and 97.79&#x000a0;% sequence similarity, respectively. The specific amino acids variations were discovered through the alignment of the allelic haplotypes from each <italic>SUT</italic>s. 2, 5, 8 and 5 amino acids within <italic>SsSUT1</italic>, <italic>SsSUT3</italic>, <italic>SsSUT5</italic>, <italic>SsSUT6</italic> respectively were observed to be vary among the allelic haplotypes (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). In addition, in <italic>SsSUT6</italic>, compared with h3 and h4, h1 and h2 had shorter peptides with 20 amino acids deletion caused by the shift of exon structure (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Furthermore, in <italic>SsSUT5</italic>, 7 of the variant amino acids were located at the sixth loop domain (T280I; G301S; K333R and T337K) and transmembrane helixes (F44L; N348S and I433V), indicating that potential functional variation existed among these allelic haplotypes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The variation of deducted amino acid sequences among allelic haplotypes within the four SsSUT</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>SUT</th><th>No. of variations (SsSUT-h1 vs other haplotype)</th><th>Amino acid variations</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>SsSUT1</italic>
</td><td>2</td><td>S21A,T329S</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SsSUT2</italic>
</td><td>N/A</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SsSUT3</italic>
</td><td>5</td><td>A10S, G18 insertion, G28E, I109T, E200D</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SsSUT4</italic>
</td><td>N/A</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SsSUT5</italic>
</td><td>8</td><td>F44L, T280I, G301S, K333R, T337K, N348S, I433V, G482 insertion</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>SsSUT6</italic>
</td><td>6</td><td>V5 deletion, S28 insertion, G39S, Q78&#x02026;A97 deletion, D345N, I404M</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Alignment of the amino acid sequences of <italic>SsSUT</italic> haplotypes. Amino acid sequences of haplotypes were aligned using the DNAMAN program. Similarity in amino acids across all the sequences is indicated by stars. The difference between haplotypes was shown in a red box</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p>In general, gene structures of the <italic>SsSUTs</italic> allelic haplotypes presented high conservation for exon/intron numbers and exon sizes, while, for intron size, in <italic>SsSUT3</italic>, <italic>SsSUT3-h3&#x02019;s</italic> first intron was larger than other allelic haplotypes; and in <italic>SsSUT6</italic>, both <italic>SsSUT6-h3</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6-h4</italic> contained a smaller second exon than <italic>SsSUT6-h1</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6-h2</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of the allelic gene structures of <italic>SsSUT</italic>s. Boxes represent exons, triangles represent transposons</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p>Nonsynonymous to synonymous substitution ratio (Ka/Ks) was analyzed to investigate evolutionary function constraint in <italic>S.spontaneum</italic>. To identify the evolutionary forces acting on four SUT genes having alleles (<italic>SsSUT1</italic>, <italic>SsSUT3</italic>, <italic>SsSUT5</italic>, <italic>SsSUT6</italic>) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), the Ka/Ks was calculated. Within the coding regions, the Ka/Ks ratio was much less than 1, indicating that purifying selection was the dominant force driving the evolution of <italic>SsSUT</italic> genes.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The Ka/Ks of <italic>SsSUT</italic> haplotypes and <italic>SbSUT</italic>-<italic>SsSUT</italic>. The lower value of Ka/Ks was indicated by stars</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Comparative analysis of gene structure between <italic>SsSUT</italic> and other plant <italic>SUT</italic></title><p>The gene structures of <italic>SsSUT</italic> family has a great variation with exon numbers ranging from five to fourteen, and their introns were aligned accordance with the GT-AG rule for splicing sites. <italic>SsSUT1, SsSUT3</italic> and <italic>SsSUT4</italic> had larger first introns than the other SUT genes. Both <italic>SsSUT3</italic> and <italic>SsSUT4</italic> only have five exons that were lesser than the other <italic>SsSUTs</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). In addition, comparative analysis of <italic>SsSUT</italic> families suggested that, the fifth exon in <italic>SsSUT3</italic> were presumed to split into 3&#x02013;4 exons, and the first, second, and fifth exons in <italic>SsSUT4</italic> were presumed to evolve into 2&#x02013;4 exons (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). <italic>SsSUT5</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6</italic> shared highest similarity of exon/intron pattern in spite of the great size variation between the second introns, which correlated to their amino acids similarities (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of the gene structure of the six members of the <italic>SsSUT</italic> gene family. Three monocotyledons (<italic>Zea mays, Sorghum bicolor, Oryza sativa</italic>) and dicotyledons (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana, Solanum tuberosum, Vitis vinifera</italic>) SUT gene family are also shown for comparison. Boxes represent exons, triangles represent transposons</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p>To investigate the evolutionary mechanisms underlying the genesis of gene families, we performed comparative analyses of the <italic>SsSUT</italic> structures with the <italic>SUT</italic> families from sorghum, rice, <italic>Arabidopsis (Arabidopsis thaliana)</italic>, maize, grape (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>) and potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum)</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The <italic>SUTs</italic> from these species could be divided into five groups SUT1 to SUT5, which were consistent with previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The results showed that <italic>SUTs</italic> in the same group had the similar gene structures. In the dicot specific group SUT1, most of the genes had two to four exons, in which the first exons were large and the second ones were small. In this group, the only exception was <italic>StSUT2,</italic> which had a smaller first exon, due to the possible exon splitting comparing with the other dicot species. In group SUT4 that was closely related to group SUT1, all the genes had first two large exons that were likely originated from SUT1 first exon splitting based on sequence comparison. It was interesting that in SUT4 group, the dicot genes and the monocot genes had siminar number of exons, 5 and 6, respectively, and the sequences of the fifth and sixth exons in dicot were presumed to originated from the monocot fifth exon splitting. Furthermore, based on the genomic and amino acids sequence comparisons among the 16 sequences from the seven plant species in group SUT1 and SUT4, the common ancestral gene of monocots and dicots were suggested to have two exons and the exon members have differentiated in a later period of evolution caused by exon splits and partial exon fusions.</p><p>The genes in group containing SUT2 had similar exon number of 13 or 14 for both dicot and monocot species. Gene size expansion due to intron size stretching in dicot plant grape and potato were observed in this group. In the SUT3 group, besides <italic>ZmSUT1</italic> with an additional small intron caused by the first exon splitting, the remaining SUT3 group genes harbor large first introns, which included wheat <italic>TaSUT1D</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and tomato LeSUT2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. In contrast to SUT2 group, the SUT3 group had varied number of exons ranging from 6 to 14; among them, <italic>SsSUT3</italic>, <italic>SbSUT3</italic> and <italic>ZmSUT3</italic> had six exons, the other genes in the subfamilies contained 10&#x02013;14 exons; both of <italic>OsSUT</italic>s in this group had more exons number than their orthologous genes. In monocot specific group SUT5, similar to the high identities shown by the alignment of amino acid sequence of <italic>SsSUT5</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6</italic>, high conservation of exon/intron structures were observed from the schematic representation; <italic>SsSUT5</italic> had larger second exon than the other genes; similar to SUT3 group, <italic>OsSUT</italic> had more exon number than their orthologous genes. Scrutiny of the exon/intron structure of the 22 genes in branch with SUT3/SUT2/SUT5 revealed that the exons could be corresponding to six exons, in which the first and the last two exons were observed to be fused/spited. These results suggested that the genes in this branch might originate from common ancestral gene containing six exons for both monocots and dicots.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>SsSUT</italic> and other plant <italic>SUT</italic> homologs</title><p>To comprehensively analyze the evolutionary relationships of <italic>SUT</italic> families between <italic>S. spontaneum</italic> and other plant species, we aligned 62 plant amino acid sequences from 5 dicots and 6 monocots including <italic>S.spontaneum,</italic> using ClustalX to construct an unrooted tree with Neighbor-Joining method (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Same as the distribution above, the <italic>SUTs</italic> were phylogenetically distributed into five groups, SUT1, SUT2, SUT3, SUT4 and SUT5, respectively. Among these five groups, SUT1 genes are only found in dicotyledonous, in contract, genes in SUT3 and SUT5 groups are only from monocotyledonous. Whereas, the remaining two groups, SUT2 and SUT4, are found in both dicot and monocot, and could be well classified into two distinct subclades. These results strongly suggested that plant SUTs were diverged from a recent evolutionary event after the common ancestor of dicots and monocots. In addition, the SUT families could be divided into two branches in the phylogenetic tree, with SUT1 and SUT4 groups in one branch and the other three groups in another branch, indicting two ancestral genes were the origins of SUTs in both dicot and monocot.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic analysis of <italic>SsSUT</italic> and other plant <italic>SUT</italic> homologs. Unrooted phylogenetic tree of plant SUT proteins constructed using the neighbour-joining method with MEGA 5.2.1 program. <italic>ZmSUT</italic>: <italic>Zea mays</italic>, <italic>SbSUT</italic>: <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic>, <italic>BdSUT</italic>: <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic>, <italic>OsSUT</italic>: <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>, <italic>AtSUT</italic>: <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, <italic>CsSUT</italic>: <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic>, <italic>GmSUT</italic>: <italic>Glycine max</italic>, <italic>StSUT</italic>: <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>,<italic>VvSUT</italic>: <italic>Vitis vinifera, SiSUT: Setaria italica</italic>, <italic>SsSUT</italic>:<italic>Saccharum spontaneum</italic>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p>In dicot specific SUT1 group, the paralogous genes from each of the dicot species were observed to be closely related, indicting recent gene duplications after the divergence of dicotyledons (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). In addition, both <italic>SUT</italic> gene number and sequences had great variations among the dicot plant species, suggesting rapid evolutionary dynamics exist in the dicotyledonous SUT families (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). In SUT4 group, all dicots and monocots had only one gene member, which the phylogenetic distribution were generally consistent with the plant species taxonomy (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). In SUT2, as description above, the genes from dicot and monocot species could be further classified into two subclades, respectively. In this group, dicot plants have d 1-2 gene members, while, all the monocot plants only hadone gene member, which suggestted that dicot plants SUT2 group were undergoing expansion. In the monocot specific SUT3, the examined monocot species consisted of two paralogous genes from two separated clades, suggesting the gene duplication event occurred before the divergence of these dicot plants. In contract to SUT3 group, in SUT5 group, recent gene duplication events were observed in the <italic>Andropogoneae</italic> plants (<italic>S. sponteneum</italic>, <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> and <italic>Zea Mays</italic>) and <italic>Bambusa oldhamiias</italic> shown by the closest phylogenetic distribution of genes within these plant species.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>The distribution of <italic>SUT</italic> family member in monocotyledon (6 species) and dicotyledon (5 species)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p>In the <italic>SsSUT</italic> family, <italic>SsSUT4</italic> was the solo member in a branch, but <italic>SsSUT1, SsSUT2</italic>, <italic>SsSUT3</italic>, <italic>SsSUT5</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6</italic> were clustered together and shared a more recent common ancestral gene. Thus, <italic>SsSUT4</italic> was suggested to be the oldest gene, while, both of <italic>SsSUT5</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6</italic> should be younger than the splitting of <italic>Trib</italic>, <italic>Andropogoneae</italic> Dumort and <italic>Zea Mays</italic>. In addition, <italic>SsSUT5</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6</italic> were observed to be undergoing rapid evolution as shown by lower amino acids sequences similarity than other orthologous genes between the sorghum and <italic>Saccharum</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Gene expression of <italic>SUTs</italic> among three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species</title><p>To investigate the possible physiological functions for SUTs, we performed comparative transcriptome profiling among three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species at different developmental stages of seedling and five different tissues from the mature leaf (mature and leaf roll) and stalks (mature, maturing and immature) by using RNA-seq method. The RNA-seq results were verified by qRT-PCR in three tissues (leaf roll, mature stalk and maturing stalk) from each of the three Saccharum speices (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>). There is a significant positive relationship ( R2&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.711 and <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) between the Reads Per Kilobases per Million reads (RPKM) based on RNA-seq and the relative expression level based on qRT-PCR (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>The SUT gene family expression based on RPKM in different tissues of different stage in three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species. The expression level of 6 SUT genes in seeding stage and mature stage of nature condition. <bold>a</bold> correlation coefficient between RNAseq (X-axe) and qRT-PCR (Y-axe) of six SUT genes. <bold>b</bold>, and in seeding stage of drought stress condition (<bold>c</bold>). IN, internode; LR, leaf roll. Internnodes 3, 9, 15, internodes 3, 8, 13 and internodes 3, 6, 9 were from <italic>Saccharum officinarum</italic> (LA-Purple), <italic>Saccharum robustum</italic> (Molokai6081) and <italic>Saccharum spontaneum</italic> (SES208), respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p>In SUT families, the transcription of <italic>SUT3</italic> was undetectable in all the examined tissues from <italic>Sacchaurm</italic> plants, which was consistent with that of <italic>SUT3</italic> in sorghum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The other gene expression levels had significant variations with a clear trend of transcript levels from higher to lower <italic>SUT1</italic>, <italic>SUT4</italic>, <italic>SUT2</italic>, <italic>SUT5</italic> and <italic>SUT6</italic>. Of them, <italic>SUT1</italic> and <italic>SUT4</italic> had predominant expression levels among the gene families, indicating that the two genes were the fundamental members in SUT families.</p><p><italic>SUT1</italic> transcripts were abundant in both source and sink organs, and were the most expressed gene in all tissues except for the mature leaf, indicating <italic>SUT1</italic> was the key member. The gene displayed a higher expression level in sink tissues (stem) than the source tissue (leaf) in mature plant. However, it was the opposite in seedling plants, suggesting the gene was more important in phloem loading for seedlings than the mature plant. Comparing with both <italic>S. sponteanum</italic> and <italic>S. robustum</italic>, <italic>SUT1</italic> displayed a lower expression level in the high sucrose <italic>S. officinarum</italic> (LA-Purple), in all examined tissues. In addition, under drought stress, <italic>SUT1</italic> was observed to be down regulated in <italic>S. robustum</italic>.</p><p><italic>SUT2</italic> was expressed in all the organs examined for the three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species. In the seedling plants, similar expressions were observed in both stem and leaves among these <italic>Saccharum</italic> species. In the mature plants, <italic>SUT2</italic> displayed a lower expression level in the source tissue of leave and leafroll for two lower sucrose accumulating <italic>Saccahurm</italic> species, <italic>S. sponteneum</italic> and <italic>S. robustum</italic>, while, high sugar <italic>S. officinarum</italic> had a more uniform <italic>SUT2</italic> expression level in all of the examined tissues (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>). Under drought stress, twofold lower levels of expressions were observed in the three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species than their control (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c</xref>).</p><p><italic>SUT4</italic> had higher expression level in the seedling than the mature plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>), suggesting it might contribute more for sucrose loading at the early age of plant development; whereas, <italic>SUT4</italic> displayed similar expression level in the examined tissues from both seedling and mature plants. Obviously, <italic>SUT4</italic> was not correlated to the sucrose content differential among the <italic>Saccharum</italic> species. Under drought stress, in contrast to <italic>SUT1</italic> and <italic>SUT2</italic>, <italic>SUT4</italic> was up regulated in the leaf of three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species.</p><p><italic>SUT5</italic> displayed dramatically higher expression level in sink tissues (stem) than in source (leave) in the seeding plant; in contract, in the mature plants, the expression level were lower in leave than the other tissues. Similar to <italic>SUT4</italic>, <italic>SUT5</italic> showed up-regulation under water stress. <italic>SUT6</italic> was undetectable in the seeding plants and had similar expression pattern as <italic>SUT5</italic> in the mature plants that gene expression exhibited higher in leave than the other tissues.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussions</title><p>Genomic study for the gene families is the first step toward the gene functional study. However, the identifications of gene family in sugarcane is still a formidable challenge caused by its complex genomes. Recently, the whole genome sequencing of sorghum and other relative species of <italic>Saccharum</italic> provides the references for comparative genomics to identify the gene families in <italic>Saccharum</italic> species. In previous studies, based on comparative genomics, the gene families of phosphoenol pyruvate carboxylase gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], sucrose synthase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], sucrose phosphate synthase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], ATP-dependent phosphofructokinase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">37</xref>] were identified by using the EST database, DNA fragment, and cDNA cloning. However, none of these studies has investigated on the genomics of whole gene families because of the lack of genomic sequences for sugarcane. Our study through comparative genomics and BACs sequencing is the first report for the structure of a gene family and their gene allelic haplotypes in <italic>Saccharum</italic>.</p><sec id="Sec17"><title>Evolutionary conservation and divergence of <italic>SsSUT</italic></title><p>Plant SUTs had been well documented in previous studies for gene phylogenetic analyses two classifications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. One classification was to divide plant SUTs into three types, type I, type II and type III, with the reference of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], in which, type I and type II SUTs were localized to the plasma membrane, while type III SUTs were associated with vacuolar membrane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Another classification was to group the SUTs into five groups SUT1, SUT2, SUT3, SUT4 and SUT5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Comparing these two classifications, SUT1 was included in type I, SUT2 was in type II, and SUT3, SUT4 and SUT5 were in type III. The former classification is likely associated with dicot plants studies, while, the latter is used for both dicot and monocot plants, especially for gene evolution studies. In this study, we used large amount of plant <italic>SUT</italic>s for phylogenetic analysis, and the results confirmed the later classification, by revealing the existence of one dicot specific and two monocots specific groups and the independence evolution process in plant SUT families (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Furthermore, the comparative analysis of these plant <italic>SUT</italic>s showed that genes in SUT3 group were more conservative than the genes in SUT5 group, and further provided the direct evidence of the recent duplication event occurred after monocot/dicot divergence. The evolution history of <italic>SsSUTs</italic>, which was sorted by age in duplicated descending order, <italic>SsSUT4, SsSUT2</italic>, <italic>SsSUT2</italic>/<italic>SsSUT3</italic>, and <italic>SsSUT5/SsSUT6</italic>.</p><p>The comparative analyses could be used to predict the number of SUT gene family members in <italic>Saccharum</italic>. Without the whole genome sequences for <italic>Saccharum</italic>, it could be debatable to conclude that we have discovered all <italic>SUTs</italic> in <italic>Sacchaurm,</italic> in spite of our high coverage BACs libraries. In this study, both phylogenetic analysis and sequences comparison revealed that <italic>Saccharum spontaneum</italic> and <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> were both composed of six <italic>SUTs</italic> members and each gene pairs were orthologous between the two species (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Beside SUT1 group, which was dicot specific, monocot plants have the same gene numbers in SUT2, SUT3 and SUT4 groups, the remaining group SUT5 had the same gene number in <italic>Andropogoneae</italic> plants, which were found to be the result of a recent duplication (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Therefore, it is less likely that any SUT gene duplication events had occurred after the diverging of sorghum and <italic>Saccharum,</italic> knowing no additional gene in this study. Hence, we concluded that the six <italic>SsSUTs</italic> comprise the <italic>SUT</italic> family in the <italic>Saccarhum spontanum</italic> genome. Further experiments such as Southern Blot could be used to verify the conclusion.</p><p>The exon&#x02013;intron structure differences were demonstrated to be accomplished by three main types of mechanisms, exon/intron gain/loss, exonization/pseudoexonization, and insertion/deletion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. In this study, comparative analyses of gene structures for <italic>SsSUT</italic> made it possible to evaluate the <italic>SUT</italic> gene structure evolution in plant (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). All SUTs genes, including <italic>SsSUT</italic>s, had a great variation of exon numbers, ranging from 2 to 14. Comparing with the gene structure variation, the protein sequences were more conserved among the paralogous genes in <italic>Sacchaurm</italic>, as shown by all SUT members containing 12 membrane-spanning helices and similar protein sizes. A common feature of plant SUTs was that the 12 membrane-spanning helices were distributed roughly uniformly in the deducted peptides of each gene in conserved position. Thus, the gene structure evolution after these plant divergences did not cause significant coding region variations. Therefore, the <italic>SUT</italic> structures variations were mainly evolved from intron gain/lost and insertion/deletion but not from exonization/pseudoexonization.</p><p><italic>Sorghum</italic> is one of the closest relative diploid genera of <italic>Sacchaurm</italic>. Comparative analysis of the orthologous between <italic>SsSUTs</italic> and <italic>SbSUTs</italic> made it possible to investigate the specific evolutionary events after the polyploidzation of <italic>Saccharum</italic>. In <italic>SsSUTs</italic>, <italic>SsSUT5</italic> harbored a much larger second intron than its closest paralogous <italic>SsSUT6</italic> and the other orthologs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Similarly, <italic>SsSUT3</italic> contained a larger first intron than its orthologous gene <italic>SbSUT2</italic>. In addition, <italic>SsSUT4</italic> were observed to have a putative TE (Transposable elements) insertion in the last intron (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Our results suggested that the <italic>SsSUT</italic> families were undergoing gene extension following polyploidization in <italic>S.spontaneum</italic>. The estimated monoploid genome size of <italic>S. spontaneum</italic> (843&#x000a0;Mb) and <italic>S. Officinarum</italic> (985&#x000a0;Mb) were both larger than the monoploid genome size of sorghum at 760&#x000a0;Mb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], supporting the conclusion that the genome of <italic>Saccharum</italic> expanded in general after polyploidization. Our results demonstrated the first case that expansion in intron regions of a gene families contribute to genome expansion in <italic>Sacchaurm</italic>.</p><p>In this study, allelic haplotype sequences for <italic>SsSUT1</italic>, <italic>3</italic>, <italic>5</italic> and <italic>6</italic> were comparatively analyzed for gene structures and Ka/Ks. Relative conservative gene structures were observed among allelic haplotypes within each of the four <italic>SsSUTs</italic>, whereas, <italic>SsSUT3-h3</italic> contained a larger first intron than the other three haplotypes, both <italic>SsSUT6-h1</italic> and <italic>SsSUT6-h2</italic> had larger second exons (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In addition, the Ka/Ks ratios, which are all under 0.4, revealed that all the SUTs allelic haplotypes were under strong purifying selection (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Multiple alleles in polypoidy are considered to be functional redundant at the time of origin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]; the conservation and constraint purification within the allelic haplotypes of <italic>SsSUTs</italic> were likely due to the key function of SUT in <italic>Saccharum</italic>. It would be worthy to note that the transcription of <italic>SsSUT3</italic> was undetectable in the examined tissues while its haplotypes were under constrain selection, indicating that <italic>SsSUT3</italic> might have a necessary function for <italic>Sacchaurm</italic>. In paleopolyploids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], and recent allopolyploid species, such as wheat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>] and Tragopogon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], eliminations and pseudogenizations of key functional genes after polyploidzation have been well documented. The allelic gene variations supposed to the key topics for studying the genome dosage of <italic>Sacchaurm</italic> species and further investigation for them would provide the foundation to understand the molecular basis of sugarcane genetics.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Gene expression and functions of <italic>SUTs</italic> in <italic>Saccharum</italic></title><p>Examination of SUT gene expressions in <italic>Saccharum</italic> species in source and sink tissues of seedling and mature plants proves an insightful indication regarding the roles of gene functions. Previous studies of gene expression were mostly done on <italic>Saccharum</italic> hybrids with combined genetic background of <italic>S.officinarum</italic> and <italic>S.sponteneum</italic>. To simplify genetic backgrounds, in this study, three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species, high-sucrose <italic>S.offcinarum</italic>, low-sucrose <italic>S.robustum</italic> (the potential domestic progenitor of <italic>S.officinarum</italic>) and stress-tolerant <italic>S.spontaneum</italic> were used for studying the <italic>SUTs</italic> expression profiles.</p><p><italic>SUT1</italic> was the only gene in SUT family, which had been well documented in <italic>Saccharum</italic> hybrid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. In these previous studies, <italic>ShSUT1</italic> had been shown to have high expression level in premature stem tissue, and decreased expression level in mature internodes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. <italic>ShSUT1</italic> was demonstrated to be highly selective for sucrose, inhibited by sucralose and had the function in loading sucrose from the vascular tissue into the stem parenchyma cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Consistent with previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], our results suggested that the expression of <italic>SUT1</italic> was higher in mature stems than the mature leave from all three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>), and thus supported the previous conclusions. Moreover, <italic>Saccharum SUT1s</italic> displayed much higher expression level in the seedling leave tissues than in both of the seedling stems and all the mature tissues, suggesting <italic>SUT1</italic> may play an enhanced role in directing sucrose in source tissue before sucrose accumulation in <italic>Sacchaurm</italic> species. Similar to the expression of <italic>SbSUT1</italic> in sorghum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], the <italic>SUT</italic> family expression analysis revealed that <italic>SUT1</italic> was the most expressed among SUTs in <italic>Saccharum</italic> species. Nevertheless, the only direct evidence for the SUT1 function was from the <italic>Saccharum</italic> close related maize <italic>sut1</italic> mutant, which exhibited a phenotype of shorter stature and carbohydrate accumulation in their source leaves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. <italic>SUT1</italic> in <italic>Saccharum</italic> may have similar function as <italic>ZmSUT1</italic> since the two orthologs shared high sequence similarity.</p><p>Comparative analyses of <italic>SUT</italic> expression among the three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species revealed that <italic>SUT1</italic> had lower expression level in all tissue types from high sugar species (<italic>S.officinarum</italic>) than the lower sugar species (<italic>S.spontaneum</italic> and <italic>S.robustum</italic>), which was consistent to sorghum that <italic>SUT1</italic> had lower gene expression in high sucrose <italic>Rio.</italic> than in the grain type genotype <italic>RTx623</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Similar to <italic>SUT1</italic>, besides the leaf tissues, <italic>SUT2</italic> was more abundant in <italic>S.spontaneum</italic> and <italic>S.robustum</italic> than in <italic>S.officinarum</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>). These results supported the notion that sinks demand in the mature plant might be stronger than in the lower sucrose content plants of <italic>Andropogoneae</italic> tribe.</p><p>We compared the expression level of <italic>SUTs</italic> of all <italic>Saccharum</italic> species in both mature and seedling plant. In mature plants, <italic>SUT1</italic> had higher expression level in sink than source tissues; in contrast, <italic>SUT1</italic> had a lower expression level in sink than source tissues. <italic>SUT4</italic> showed a higher expression level in seedling than the mature plants. <italic>SUT1</italic> and <italic>SUT4</italic> accounted for above 70&#x000a0;% of transcripts in this gene family (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). These results indicated that sucrose transport were active before the sucrose accumulation and both <italic>SUT1</italic> and <italic>SUT4</italic> were involved in the plant development in <italic>Saccharum</italic>.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Total accumulative expression level of the <italic>SUTs</italic> in tissues and in stage of three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species. IN, internode; LR, leaf roll. Internnodes 3, 9, 15, internodes 3, 8, 13 and internodes 3, 6, 9 were from Saccharum officinarum LA-Purple, Saccharum robustum Molokai6081 and Saccharum spontaneum SES208 respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p><p>In the <italic>Saccharum</italic> species, <italic>SUT4</italic> showed similar expression level in both seedling and mature stage tissues. These results were different from its close orthologs including <italic>OsSUT2</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>], <italic>PtaSUT4</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], and <italic>SbSUT2</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Thus, SUT4 might contribute to the characteristics of sucrose accumulation in <italic>Saccharum</italic> species. The orthologous of <italic>SUT4</italic> phylogenetic group was proved to be localized in the tonoplast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. In model plant <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>], SUT4 played a role for transporting sucrose from mesophyll vacuoles to their cytoplasm. This information may not be sufficient for discovering the gene function of <italic>SUT4,</italic> but is an indication for further functional study of <italic>SUT4</italic> in sugarcane.</p><p>Both <italic>SUT5</italic> and <italic>SUT6</italic> in SUT5 group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) were revealed to be recent duplication and through rapid evolution accompanied by the multiple amino acid differences in their allelic haplotypes (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>), suggesting that these two genes may have similar gene expression profiles. Gene expression analysis showed that these two genes have much lower gene expression level among the SUTs families and had similar gene expression profiles in the mature tissues (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>), supporting that the two genes were derived from a recent duplication. Nevertheless, in the seedling plants, <italic>SUT6</italic> was absent while <italic>SUT5</italic> had higher expression in stems than leaves (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>), hence, SUT5 may contribute to phloem loading before the sucrose accumulation in <italic>Saccharum.</italic> In <italic>sorghum</italic>, great variation of gene expression level for <italic>SbSUT5</italic> and <italic>SbSUT6</italic> were observed among the tissues from of vegetative stages and anthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Of them, <italic>SbSUT5</italic> showed higher expression in spikelet tissue and inflorescence, and thus was suggested to play a role for inflorescence development; similarly, <italic>SUT6</italic> in <italic>Saccharum</italic> species was more abundant in leaves than the other tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Based on above genomic analysis, <italic>SUT5</italic> and <italic>SUT6</italic> have gone through rapid evolution after the split of <italic>Sorghum</italic> and <italic>Saccharum</italic>, suggesting that these two genes have functional divergence between these two species. These two gene expression profiles in <italic>Saccharum</italic> and <italic>Sorghum</italic> were different from their closest orthologous <italic>OsSUT5</italic>, which exhibited broad expression level across source and sink tissues as well as in filling rice grains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Phylogenetic and comparative analysis revealed that there was a single <italic>SUT</italic> in group SUT5 from rice. These differences can be explained by the single gene <italic>OsSUT5</italic> in rice response for function of two duplication genes in the <italic>Andropogoneae</italic> tribe.</p><p>Soluble sugar such as sucrose usually increases in plant under drought stress. to identify which SUT gene responsible to drought stress, we examined the <italic>SUTs</italic> expression level under drought stress in the seedling plant leaves of three <italic>Saccharum</italic> species. Under drought stress, in the four detectable <italic>SUTs</italic> in the seeding, <italic>SUT1</italic> and <italic>SUT2</italic> were down regulated, in contrast, <italic>SUT4</italic> and <italic>SUT5</italic> were up regulated, indicating that the SUT4 and SUT5 are important in response to drought stress and may involved in transporting sugar into cell for osmotic adjustment. SUT families in <italic>Saccharum</italic> presented a great gene expression diversity in response to drought stress. <italic>SUT4</italic> was the predominant expression member in the SUTs families in <italic>Saccharum</italic>, therefore, the up-regulation of <italic>SUT4</italic> expression resulted in the higher total <italic>SUTs</italic> transcript level. A possible explanation for this phenomenon could be that the source tissue reduced the sucrose product level under drought stress thus down regulated the <italic>SUT</italic> expression level. An expression profile for <italic>Saccharum</italic> plants under water stress with different time points could be further used for verifying this notion. Similar experiment was performed for the five SUT members in rice, which revealed that <italic>OsSUT2</italic> was only member display up-regulated during drought and salinity treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. Therefore, it is most likely that plant SUT gene members possess diversity pattern in response to stress tolerance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In this study, we presented the first report of a gene family consists of six <italic>SUTs</italic> in <italic>Saccharum</italic>. We provided the comprehensive evaluation of the evolutionary genesis, gene allelic haplotypes, phylogenetic relationships, gene structure, and gene expression pattern for the SUT gene family in <italic>Saccharum</italic> species. Our results revealed that <italic>SsSUT</italic>5 and <italic>SsSUT6</italic> were recent duplication genes companied by rapid evolution, while, <italic>SsSUT2</italic> and <italic>SsSUT</italic>4 were the ancient members in the families. Gene size extensions caused by sequence insertions in introns were observed in the SUT families. Despite the high polyploidy level, the examined SUTs exhibited conserved gene structures and amino acid sequences among the allelic haplotypes. Both <italic>SUT1</italic> and <italic>SUT4</italic> had predominant expression in <italic>Saccharum</italic> SUT families. <italic>SUT1,</italic> which displayed lower expression in the high sucrose species <italic>S.officinarum,</italic> might be involved in saccharide unloading in the sink tissue of mature plant, phloem loading in early developmental stage of <italic>Saccharum. SUT2</italic> likely contributed to both phloem loading and sink development. <italic>SUT4</italic> was more important at early developmental stage than in mature plants. Both <italic>SUT5</italic> and <italic>SUT6</italic> had lower expression level than other gene members, and had higher expression in source leaves than in other tissues, thus, supposed to play roles in phloem loading. In the seedling plant leaves with drought stress treatment, four genes <italic>SUT1</italic>, <italic>SUT2</italic>, <italic>SUT4</italic> and <italic>SUT5</italic> were detectable, among which, <italic>SUT1</italic> and <italic>SUT4</italic> were down regulated, while, <italic>SUT2</italic> and <italic>SUT5</italic> were up regulated. To further reveal these genes&#x02019; roles under stress, experiments such as, characterizing the spatio-temporal expression dissection, enzyme activity assay, and gene editing technology like CRISPR-Cas9 system, would be necessary. The results offered useful foundation and framework for future research for understanding the physiological roles for each SUT gene and molecular mechanisms of sucrose metabolism in sugarcane.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Availability of supporting data</title><p>The 14 sequences of <italic>SsSUTs</italic>(allele haplotypes) were deposited into Genbank (accession numbers: KT284760-KT284773).</p><p>Phylogenetic data (alignments and phylogenetic trees) have been deposited to TreeBase and are accessible via the URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.org/phylo/treebase/phylows/study/TB2:S18751">http://purl.org/phylo/treebase/phylows/study/TB2:S18751</ext-link>.</p></sec></body><back><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec21"><title>Additional files</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_MOESM1_ESM.doc" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p>
<bold>The probe primers for SUT BAC hybridization in</bold>
<bold><italic>S. spontaneum</italic></bold>
<bold>.</bold> (DOC 32&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_MOESM2_ESM.doc" id="MOESM2"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p>
<bold>BLAST results for</bold>
<bold><italic>SsSUTs</italic></bold>
<bold>EST in NCBI database.</bold> (DOC 32&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_MOESM3_ESM.doc" id="MOESM3"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p>
<bold>Alignment of the amino acid sequences of</bold>
<bold><italic>SsSUT</italic></bold>
<bold>haplotypes.</bold> (DOC 114&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_MOESM4_ESM.doc" id="MOESM4"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p>
<bold>The qRT-PCR primers for</bold>
<bold><italic>SUTs</italic></bold>
<bold>in this study.</bold> (DOC 32&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2419_MOESM5_ESM.doc" id="MOESM5"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p>
<bold>qRT-PCR verification of SUT gene expressions in partial issues of three Saccharum species.</bold> (DOC 824&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>BACs</term><def><p>bacterial artificial chromosomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>eEF-1a</term><def><p>Eukaryotic elongation factor 1a</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EST</term><def><p>Expressed Sequence Tag</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GAPDH</term><def><p>glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPKM</term><def><p>Reads Per Kilobasesper Million reads</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SUTs</term><def><p>Sucrose transporters</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; contributions</bold></p><p>QZ and JZ conceived the study and designed the experiments. QZ,WH, FZ, LW, QY, RM and JZ carried out the experiments and analyzed the data. QZ and JZ wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final paper.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This project was supported by grants from the 863 program (2013AA100604), NSFC (31201260) and Fujian Provincial Department of Education (No. JA12082). We are grateful for the invaluable help and comments of Dr. Jianping Wang.</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slewinski</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current perspectives on the regulation of whole-plant carbohydrate partitioning</article-title><source>Plant Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>178</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2010.01.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Studley</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Saier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny as a guide to structure and function of membrane transport proteins (Review)</article-title><source>Mol Membr Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09687680410001720830</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15204625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15204625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Families of transmembrane sugar transport proteins</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>699</fpage><lpage>710</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2000.01759.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10692148?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10692148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riesmeier</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Willmitzer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Frommer</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of a sucrose carrier cDNA from spinach by functional expression in yeast</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1992</year><volume>11</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>4705</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><?supplied-pmid 1464305?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1464305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hackel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sucrose transporter LeSUT1 and LeSUT2 inhibition affects tomato fruit development in different ways</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02572.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16367963?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16367963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sivitz</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinders</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis sucrose transporter AtSUC1 is important for pollen germination and sucrose-induced anthocyanin accumulation</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>147</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.118992</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18359840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18359840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganesan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>IO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayre</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effective carbon partitioning driven by exotic phloem-specific regulatory elements fused to the Arabidopsis thaliana AtSUC2 sucrose-proton symporter gene</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-9-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19154603?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19154603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Payyavula</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tay</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The sucrose transporter family in Populus: the importance of a tonoplast PtaSUT4 to biomass and carbon partitioning</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2011</year><volume>65</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2010.04463.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21261761?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21261761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chincinska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Krugel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Liesche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Photoperiodic regulation of the sucrose transporter StSUT4 affects the expression of circadian-regulated genes and ethylene production</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>26</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2013.00026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23429841?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23429841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arabidopsis Genome</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the genome sequence of the flowering plant Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>408</volume><issue>6814</issue><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35048692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11130711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Scofield</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitfeld</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Furbank</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The sucrose transporter gene family in rice</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcg030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12668768?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12668768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitfeld</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoeren</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Scofield</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Three sucrose transporter genes are expressed in the developing grain of hexaploid wheat</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>50</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1019846832163</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12369621?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12369621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrt</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Grof</surname><given-names>CPL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are sucrose transporter expression profiles linked with patterns of biomass partitioning in Sorghum phenotypes?</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>223</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2013.00223</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23805151?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23805151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Imaizumi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Scofield</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Furbank</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohsugi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cDNA cloning and tissue specific expression of a gene for sucrose transporter from rice (Oryza sativa L.)</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>38</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1389</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.pcp.a029134</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9522469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9522469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scofield</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Furbank</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the sucrose transporter, OsSUT1, in germination and early seedling growth and development of rice plants</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2007</year><volume>58</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erl217</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17138625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17138625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Siao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hormone and sugar effects on rice sucrose transporter OsSUT1 expression in germinating embryos</article-title><source>Acta Physiologiae Plantarum</source><year>2010</year><volume>32</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11738-009-0459-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of OsSUT2 Expression and Regulation in Germinating Embryos of Rice Seeds</article-title><source>Rice</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12284-011-9063-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular regulation of sink-source transition in rice leaf sheaths during the heading period</article-title><source>Acta Physiologiae Plantarum</source><year>2008</year><volume>30</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11738-008-0160-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Truernit</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The promoter of the Arabidopsis thaliana SUC2 sucrose-H+ symporter gene directs expression of beta-glucuronidase to the phloem: evidence for phloem loading and unloading by SUC2</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1995</year><volume>196</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00203657</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7647685?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7647685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Oparka</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantification of plasmodesmatal endoplasmic reticulum coupling between sieve elements and companion cells using fluorescence redistribution after photobleaching</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>142</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.085803</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16905664?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16905664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganesan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>IO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayre</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of the Arabidopsis AtSUC2 Sucrose/H+ symporter by tissue-specific complementation reveals an essential role in phloem loading but not in long-distance transport</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>148</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.124776</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18650401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18650401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottwald</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Krysan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Evert</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sussman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic evidence for the in planta role of phloem-specific plasma membrane sucrose transporters</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><issue>25</issue><fpage>13979</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.250473797</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11087840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11087840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weise</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalonde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Buschmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Frommer</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A new subfamily of sucrose transporters, SUT4, with low affinity/high capacity localized in enucleate sieve elements of plants</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1345</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.12.8.1345</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10948254?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10948254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Weise</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SUT2, a putative sucrose sensor in sieve elements</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1153</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.12.7.1153</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10899981?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10899981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aoki N, Hirose T, Furbank RT. Sucrose transport in higher plants: from source to sink. In: Photosynthesis. Springer; 2012. 34:703&#x02013;729.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuadrado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Acevedo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno Diaz de la Espina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jouve</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Torre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome remodelling in three modern S. officinarumxS. spontaneum sugarcane cultivars</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2004</year><volume>55</volume><issue>398</issue><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erh093</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14990623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14990623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D'Hont</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grivet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berding</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaszmann</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of the double genome structure of modern sugarcane cultivars (Saccharum spp.) by molecular cytogenetics</article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>250</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02174028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8602157?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8602157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piperidis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Christopher</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Berding</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Hont</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular contribution to selection of intergeneric hybrids between sugarcane and the wild species Erianthus arundinaceus</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2000</year><volume>43</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/gen-43-6-1033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11195335?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11195335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temporal and spatial regulation of sucrose accumulation in the sugarcane stem</article-title><source>Funct Plant Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>79</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casu</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Grof</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rae</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimmock</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a novel sugar transporter homologue strongly expressed in maturing stem vascular tissues of sugarcane by expressed sequence tag and microarray analysis</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>52</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1023957214644</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12856943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12856943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>ElSayed</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Komor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of sucrose transporter (ShSUT1) in a Hawaiian sugarcane cultivar infected with Sugarcane yellow leaf virus (SCYLV)</article-title><source>Physiol Mol Plant P</source><year>2010</year><volume>75</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmpp.2010.08.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rae</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Perroux</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Grof</surname><given-names>CPL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sucrose partitioning between vascular bundles and storage parenchyma in the sugarcane stem: a potential role for the ShSUT1 sucrose transporter</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2005</year><volume>220</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-004-1399-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15517352?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15517352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinders</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivitz</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grof</surname><given-names>CPL</given-names></name><name><surname>Perroux</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sugarcane ShSUT1: analysis of sucrose transport activity and inhibition by sucralose</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ</source><year>2006</year><volume>29</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1871</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.2006.01563.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16930313?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16930313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haplotype analysis of sucrose synthase gene family in three Saccharum species</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>314</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-14-314</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23663250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23663250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Heinz</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anatomy and morphology</article-title><source>Sugarcane Improvement through Breeding</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>142</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zee</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction and characterization of a papaya BAC library as a foundation for molecular dissection of a tree-fruit genome</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>102</volume><issue>6-7</issue><fpage>892</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220000448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>de Kochko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Byers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Navajas-Perez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Langston</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Micro-collinearity and genome evolution in the vicinity of an ethylene receptor gene of cultivated diploid and allotetraploid coffee species (Coffea)</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2011</year><volume>67</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04590.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21457367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21457367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Benjamini Y, Hochberg Y. Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing. J Royal Stat Soc Series B (Methodological). 1995;57:289&#x02013;300.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Que</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive selection of reference genes for gene expression normalization in sugarcane by real time quantitative rt-PCR</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097469</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24823940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24823940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>His-65 in the proton-sucrose symporter is an essential amino acid whose modification with site-directed mutagenesis increases transport activity</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>9025</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.15.9025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9671798?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9671798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemoine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sucrose transporters in plants: update on function and structure</article-title><source>Biochimica et biophysica acta</source><year>2000</year><volume>1465</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0005-2736(00)00142-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10748258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10748258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pazdernik</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Matzke</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessen-Marshall</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooker</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roles of charged residues in the conserved motif, G-X-X-X-D/E-R/K-X-G-[X]-R/K-R/K, of the lactose permease of Escherichia coli</article-title><source>J Membr Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>174</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002320001029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10741430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10741430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Osakabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizoi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional Analysis of an Arabidopsis thaliana Abiotic Stress-inducible Facilitated Diffusion Transporter for Monosaccharides</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>285</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1138</fpage><lpage>1146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.054288</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19901034?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19901034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000fc;hn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grof</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sucrose transporters of higher plants</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2010.02.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Besnard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pincon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Hont</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoarau</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Offmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of the phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase gene family in sugarcane (Saccharum spp.)</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>107</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-003-1268-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12759729?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12759729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goode</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordeiro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bundock</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliott</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of alleles of the sucrose phosphate synthase gene family in sugarcane and their association with sugar-related traits</article-title><source>Mol Breeding</source><year>2015</year><volume>35</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-015-0286-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and genes expression analysis of ATP-dependent phosphofructokinase family members among three Saccharum species</article-title><source>Funct Plant Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>40</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/FP12182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinders</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivitz</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of plant sucrose uptake transporters</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2012.00022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22639641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22639641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deol</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Brule-Babel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stasolla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayele</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of the three homeologues of a new sucrose transporter in hexaploid wheat (Triticum aestivum L)</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>181</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-13-181</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24237613?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24237613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divergence of duplicate genes in exon-intron structure</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1187</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1109047109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22232673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22232673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Evolution by gene duplication</source><year>1970</year><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Splitting pairs: The diverging fates of duplicated genes</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg928</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12415313?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12415313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Conery</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The origins of genome complexity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>302</volume><issue>5649</issue><fpage>1401</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1089370</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14631042?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14631042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanc</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Widespread paleopolyploidy in model plant species inferred from age distributions of duplicate genes</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1667</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.021345</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15208399?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15208399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Following tetraploidy in an Arabidopsis ancestor, genes were removed preferentially from one homeolog leaving clusters enriched in dose-sensitive genes</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>934</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.4708406</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16760422?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16760422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bias in plant gene content following different sorts of duplication: tandem, whole-genome, segmental, or by transposition</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.043008.092122</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19575588?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19575588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Throude</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pont</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarda</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Quraishi</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure and expression analysis of rice paleo duplications</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1248</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn1048</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19136467?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19136467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozkan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allopolyploidy-induced rapid genome evolution in the wheat (Aegilops-Triticum) group</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>13</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1735</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.13.8.1735</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11487689?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11487689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chantret</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Salse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Laubin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular basis of evolutionary events that shaped the hardness locus in diploid and polyploid wheat species (Triticum and Aegilops)</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.104.029181</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15749759?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15749759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evolution and expression of homeologous loci in Tragopogon miscellus (Asteraceae), a recent and reciprocally formed allopolyploid</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>173</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.106.057646</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16648586?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16648586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buggs</surname><given-names>RJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chamala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnable</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of duplicate gene evolution in the recent natural allopolyploid Tragopogon miscellus by next-generation sequencing and Sequenom iPLEX MassARRAY genotyping</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2009.04469.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20331776?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20331776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rae</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Grof</surname><given-names>CPL</given-names></name><name><surname>Casu</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnett</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sucrose accumulation in the sugarcane stem: pathways and control points for transport and compartmentation</article-title><source>Field Crop Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>92</volume><issue>2-3</issue><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2005.01.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slewinski</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Meeley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sucrose transporter1 functions in phloem loading in maize leaves</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>881</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ern335</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19181865?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19181865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eom</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinders</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuan</surname><given-names>PQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impaired function of the tonoplast-localized sucrose transporter in rice, OsSUT2, limits the transport of vacuolar reserve sucrose and affects plant growth</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>157</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.176982</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21771914?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21771914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schelbert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Weschke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of a vacuolar sucrose transporter in barley and Arabidopsis mesophyll cells by a tonoplast proteomic approach</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>141</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.079533</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16581873?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16581873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okubo-Kurihara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Higaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutsuna</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasezawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sucrose transporter NtSUT4 from tobacco BY-2 involved in plant cell shape during miniprotoplast culture</article-title><source>J Plant Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>124</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10265-010-0377-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20941637?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20941637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyhl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marten</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wormit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Poschet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proton-driven sucrose symport and antiport are provided by the vacuolar transporters SUC4 and TMT1/2</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2011</year><volume>68</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04672.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21668536?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21668536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibraheem</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Dealtry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of drought and salinity on the expressional levels of sucrose transporters in rice (Oryza sativa Nipponbare) cultivar plants</article-title><source>Plant Omics</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>74</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>