<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4382326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25830330</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120854</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-42876</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Selection of Reference Genes for Transcriptional Analysis of Edible Tubers of Potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.)</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Reference Genes for <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Mariot</surname><given-names>Roberta Fogliatto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>Luisa Abruzzi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Voorhuijzen</surname><given-names>Marleen M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Staats</surname><given-names>Martijn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hutten</surname><given-names>Ronald C. B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>Jeroen P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>Esther</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Frazzon</surname><given-names>Jeverson</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label><addr-line>Food Science Department, Food Science and Technology Institute, Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label><addr-line>Genetics Department, Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff003"><label>3</label><addr-line>RIKILT, Wageningen UniversityR, Wageningen, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff004"><label>4</label><addr-line>Plant Breeding, Wageningen UR, Wageningen, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bie</surname><given-names>Zhilong</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Huazhong Agricultural University, CHINA</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: EK JF. Performed the experiments: RFM LAO MS RH. Analyzed the data: RFM LAO MS JPVD. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RFM MMV. Wrote the paper: RFM LAO.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>jeverson.frazzon@ufrgs.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e0120854</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mariot et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0120854.pdf"/><abstract><p>Potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>) yield has increased dramatically over the last 50 years and this has been achieved by a combination of improved agronomy and biotechnology efforts. Gene studies are taking place to improve new qualities and develop new cultivars. Reverse transcriptase quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR) is a bench-marking analytical tool for gene expression analysis, but its accuracy is highly dependent on a reliable normalization strategy of an invariant reference genes. For this reason, the goal of this work was to select and validate reference genes for transcriptional analysis of edible tubers of potato. To do so, RT-qPCR primers were designed for ten genes with relatively stable expression in potato tubers as observed in <italic>RNA-Seq</italic> experiments. Primers were designed across exon boundaries to avoid genomic DNA contamination. Differences were observed in the ranking of candidate genes identified by <italic>geNorm</italic>, <italic>NormFinder</italic> and <italic>BestKeeper</italic> algorithms. The ranks determined by <italic>geNorm</italic> and <italic>NormFinder</italic> were very similar and for all samples the most stable candidates were <italic>C2</italic>, exocyst complex component sec3 (<italic>SEC3</italic>) and <italic>ATCUL3/ATCUL3A/CUL3/CUL3A</italic> (<italic>CUL3A</italic>). According to <italic>BestKeeper</italic>, the importin alpha and ubiquitin-associated/ts-n genes were the most stable. Three genes were selected as reference genes for potato edible tubers in RT-qPCR studies. The first one, called <italic>C2</italic>, was selected in common by <italic>NormFinder</italic> and <italic>geNorm</italic>, the second one is <italic>SEC3</italic>, selected by <italic>NormFinder</italic>, and the third one is <italic>CUL3A</italic>, selected by <italic>geNorm</italic>. Appropriate reference genes identified in this work will help to improve the accuracy of gene expression quantification analyses by taking into account differences that may be observed in RNA quality or reverse transcription efficiency across the samples.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by National Council of Technological and Scientific Development of Brazil (CNPq) (J.F.grant #300912/2012-9, #473181/2013-4) and the Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior (CAPES) of Brazil. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>A wide range of biological processes leads to changes in mRNA transcription levels, and these variations are important to ensure timely cellular responses. Based on this, mRNA transcriptional profiling has become a popular research field in functional genomics studies, as it can be used to evaluate complex regulatory gene networks [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Reverse transcriptase quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR) has been commonly used to analyze gene expression in different organisms and under numerous conditions, since it permits specific and reproducible quantification of nucleic acids [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, the stability of the expressed housekeeping gene is a fundamental factor in the appropriate standard normalization of the data, which is usually normalized to more than one reference gene to avoid differences in complementary DNA (cDNA) quantity, purity, RNA stability, and enzymatic efficiency of cDNA synthesis and subsequent PCR amplifications [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The assortment of an appropriate reference gene is an absolute requirement to minimize non-biological variation between samples and achieve precise results [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]; hence, the selection of suitable reference genes is crucial to RT-qPCR analysis. The ideal reference gene would be stably expressed through all examined samples [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Many reference genes have already been identified for several crops under different treatments and conditions, particularly for model plants [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, the expression of putative reference genes differs across individual sets of organs and experimental conditions [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In this context, several free software packages such as <italic>geNorm</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], <italic>NormFinder</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] or <italic>BestKeeper</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], may be used in order to the best internal controls from a group of candidate normalization genes for a specific set of biological samples.</p><p>The goal of this study was to examine by RT-qPCR the stability of ten putative reference genes selected from <italic>RNAseq</italic> experiments. We have focused the investigation of control genes by evaluating the expression variability of 10 genes with relatively high stability levels in potato tubers.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Ethics statements</title><p>The field experiments in both years (in this case normal yield trials) were performed on a trial field in the proximity of Wageningen (GPS coordinates: 51.95230, 5.63490) owned by Wageningen UR. No specific permission was required to carry out these potato trials.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Field experimental design</title><p>Eight potato edible tubers from four distinct genotypes, experimental lines, obtained in duplicates, one grown in 2011 and the other in 2012, with a post-harvest storage time of 13 and 28 days, and cultivated at Plant Breeding Sciences&#x02014;Wageningen University and Research Center (WUR)&#x02014;Wageningen, The Netherlands.</p><p>The varieties HZ 94 DTA 11 and RH00-386-2 are diploid, and the varieties RH4X-029-2 and RH4X-036-11 are tetraploid potato breeding clones. Although, all 4 clones have a wild potato species clone as a grandparent, they are all considered and treated as &#x0201c;normal&#x0201d; potatoes (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>).</p><p>All potato samples are listed and detailed on <xref rid="pone.0120854.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0120854.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120854.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Field information of the eight potato samples used in this study for experimental validation of candidate reference genes.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0120854.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0120854.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sample ID</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Varieties</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Parents</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Grand parents</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Year of Harvest</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Time Post-harvest (days)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HZ-2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HZ94DTA11</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">RH90-012-2 x RH89-039-16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH87-217-34 <bold>x</bold> TAR 24717&#x02013;4 (S. tarijense)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HZ94-2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HZ94DTA11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BC 1034 <bold>x</bold> SUH 2293</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH00-2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH00-386-2</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">RH97-649-11 x 96-2039-10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IVP92-057-17 <bold>x</bold> SPG 15458-B18 (S. spegazzinii)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH386-1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH00-386-2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH89-050-25 <bold>x</bold> RH89-035-38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH-029-2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH4X-029-2</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">M 94-110-2 x FRIESLANDER</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93-71-3 (S. hougasii) <bold>x</bold> W 72-38-720</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH29-2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH4X-029-2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GLORIA <bold>x</bold> 74 A 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH036-1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH4X-036-11</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">M 94-125-1 x FRESCO</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BILDTSTAR <bold>x</bold> 93-114-5 (S. fendleri)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH36-1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RH4X-036-11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CEB 60-15-28 <bold>x</bold> PROVITA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Samples preparation</title><p>Four average sized tubers were selected; of these, opposite eights were pooled to minimize variation effects in the tuber. Potato tubers were washed in water at room temperature dried with paper and chopped using a food processor into 1 cm<sup>3</sup> cubes. Potato cubes were immediately frozen in liquid N<sub>2</sub> to avoid tuber oxidation, packed in plastic bags and stored in an ultra-freezer at -80&#x000b0;C. Samples were sent to ZIRBUS Technology, Tiel, The Netherlands, for lyophilisation, milling and vacuum packaging. Potato powder was stored at room temperature until use.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>RNA isolation and quality assessment</title><p>RNA was isolated from 0.5 g of each freeze-dried sample, according to the hexadecyltrimethylammonium bromide (CTAB) buffer lysis method, followed by chloroform/isoamyl alcohol extraction and overnight precipitation with lithium chloride (LiCl) proposed by van Dijk et al. (2009) [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], with some modifications, as follows. Lysis was performed with the extraction buffer pre-warmed to 60&#x000b0;C before use; the chloroform/isoamyl alcohol extraction was repeated three times before the LiCl precipitation; and the final precipitation with 96% ethanol was performed with the tubes kept on ice and then centrifuged at 4&#x000b0;C for 15 min at 14,000 g. Total RNA isolated was dissolved in 100 &#x003bc;L of 10 mM Tris (pH 7,0) and warmed to 65&#x000b0;C for 10 min. Total RNA was stored at -80&#x000b0;C until use.</p><p>RNA purity and concentration were assessed by absorbance measurements using a Nanodrop 1000 instrument (Thermo Fisher Scientific, NanoDrop Technologies Wilmington, DE, USA). For integrity evaluation, 1 &#x003bc;g of RNA was migrated by electrophoresis (10 min at 80 V and 50 min at 100 V) in denaturing agarose gel (1% agarose, 5% formamide, 1X TBE) stained with ethidium bromide. Gels were visualized in Gel Doc XR+ Systems (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Life Technologies Corporation, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and analyzed using Quantity One 1-D (Bio-Rad Laboratories).</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Candidate gene selection and primer design</title><p>Candidate potato reference genes with stable expression levels in tubers were selected from a large collection of <italic>RNAseq</italic> profiles generated for 90 potato tubers grown under diverse range of growth conditions, locations, and growth year. Ten potato genes with more than 50 counts per million reads and with lowest interquartile range (IQR) were selected using R version 3.01 [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] for further evaluation with RT-qPCR (<xref rid="pone.0120854.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Information about candidate genes was determined using Ensembl Plant Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plants.ensembl.org/index.html">http://plants.ensembl.org/index.html</ext-link>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0120854.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120854.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Candidate potato reference genes with more than 50 counts per million reads (highest expression), lowest inter quartile ranges (IQRs) and known functions, used for experimental validation.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0120854.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0120854.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IQR</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene Code</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Location</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Transcript Code</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Forward/Reverse primer</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Amplicon (bp)</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PCR efficiency (%)</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold><sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3 subunit</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">12.84</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400009231</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">11:9004475&#x02013;9012212</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400023872</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>3&#x02019;GCGAAGATCCCAGTGAACAA5&#x02019;</monospace></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">123</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">93.6</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.998</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>5&#x02019;CAGCATCTTCACCAGCACTTA3&#x02019;</monospace></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">dead-box atp-dependent rna helicase 39<xref rid="t002fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">17.25</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400023195</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">12:54853693&#x02013;54861561</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400059671</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>3&#x02019;TATGGGTGCCAAAGGGAAAG5&#x02019;</monospace></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">116</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">86</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.998</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400059672</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>5&#x02019;CGTCTACTGAGAGAGACTCCAA3&#x02019;</monospace></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">3-oxoacyl-(acyl-carrier protein) reductase</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">17.61</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG401026981</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">6:52692660&#x02013;52698742</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400069374</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>3&#x02019;AGTTGAAGCTCCGGTTGTTATT5&#x02019;</monospace></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">96.9</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.998</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>5&#x02019;GTTCACAAGGACCTTACAACCA3&#x02019;</monospace></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">importin subunit alpha</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">17.66</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400007289</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">6:100326&#x02013;106781</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400018802</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>3&#x02019;ACCTCGATAAGAAGCTGGAGA5&#x02019;</monospace></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">96</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.996</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400018803</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>5&#x02019;AGTTTCCGGAACTGTGTTGT3&#x02019;</monospace></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">exocyst complex component sec3</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">17.75</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG402015451</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">12:56757079&#x02013;56759688</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400039945</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>3&#x02019;GGAGCAGTATATCCAAGGACAA5&#x02019;</monospace></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">75</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">90.3</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.995</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>5&#x02019;AGGAACATTGTAGTGACAAACTTAG3&#x02019;</monospace></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1"><italic>ATCUL3/ATCUL3A/CUL3/CUL3A</italic></td><td rowspan="3" align="char" char="." colspan="1">17.80</td><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400001321</td><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1">2:46264503&#x02013;46268790</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400003337</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>3&#x02019;GAGGACCGGTGAAGTGATAAAC5&#x02019;</monospace></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1">120</td><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1">90</td><td rowspan="3" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.994</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400003338</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><monospace>5&#x02019;TCAGCCGAGACATCAAGAAAC3&#x02019;</monospace></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400003339</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">ubiquitin-associated/ts-nTS-N domain-containing protein</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">19.03</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG402005949</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">6:54204271&#x02013;54209252</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400015247</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>3&#x02019;TGAGAAGGCTGAAGAGACTTTG5&#x02019;</monospace></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">131</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">101</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.996</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400015248</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>5&#x02019;GTAAGTTCTGGGTGGTGGTATT3&#x02019;</monospace></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><italic>C2</italic></td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">19.90</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400023712</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">10:57539858&#x02013;57542161</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400060959</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>3&#x02019;GGCCACTCAGATTGTCTCTATG5&#x02019;</monospace></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">118</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">88,1</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.998</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>5&#x02019;AGCTTTGCTTCTCCTCATACTC3&#x02019;</monospace></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">dck/dgk-like deoxyribonucleoside kinase</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">20.49</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400009278</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">11:13898057&#x02013;13903160</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400023985</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>3&#x02019;GATATTGAAGCAAAGAGGCAGTATG5&#x02019;</monospace></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">112</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">95.5</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.997</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>5&#x02019;GATTGCCCTTAGGCTGTTCT3&#x02019;</monospace></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">2-isopropylmalate synthase b</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">21.25</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400016337</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">6:39132151&#x02013;39142170</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMT400042133</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>3&#x02019;AAAGTGGCATCCATCAGGA5&#x02019;</monospace></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">104</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">104.5</td><td rowspan="2" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.998</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><monospace>5&#x02019;GACAATACCAGATTTATTAGCACGA3&#x02019;</monospace></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>*Gene with alternative-splicing isoforms.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> genes, cDNA sequences, and exon-intron-exon junctions were also obtained from Ensembl Plant Database. All primers were designed using the Primer Quest tool from IDT DNA (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.idtdna.com/primerquest/Home/Index">http://www.idtdna.com/primerquest/Home/Index</ext-link>) with melting temperatures between 58&#x000b0;C and 62&#x000b0;C, GC contents from 45 to 65% and amplicon lengths ranging from 75 to 150 bp (<xref rid="pone.0120854.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The Oligo Analyzer software from IDT DNA was also used to infer primer secondary structures (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.idtdna.com/analyzer/applications/oligoanalyzer/">http://www.idtdna.com/analyzer/applications/oligoanalyzer/</ext-link>).</p><p>Since 4 out of the 10 candidate genes display alternative splicing (see <xref rid="pone.0120854.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), BLAST searches were performed, in order to design oligonucleotides complementary to a region of homology between the different transcripts of a given gene.</p><p>To determine PCR efficiencies, standard curves were constructed with four points in five-fold dilutions starting from a 1/5 cDNA concentration (1:5, 1:25, 1:125 and 1:625), according to Perini, et al. (2014) [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and strongly suggested by Bustin, et al. (2009) [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Reaction efficiencies (E) and correlation coefficients (r<sup>2</sup>) were estimated using <italic>StepOne Software v</italic>.<italic>2</italic>.<italic>3</italic> (<italic>Life Technologies</italic>), based on the slopes of the plots and the Cps (crossing points) versus log input of cDNA. E and r<sup>2</sup> values for each reaction performed are also presented in <xref rid="pone.0120854.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Complementary DNA synthesis</title><p>Each RNA sample was converted into cDNA in triplicates, as recommended by Bustin, et al. (2009) [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. One microgram of total RNA was used for synthesis according to the manufacturer&#x000b4;s protocol, using the <italic>iScript</italic> cDNA Synthesis Kit (BIORAD). Specificity of the primers was checked for the 24 resulting cDNAs by end-point PCR followed by electrophoresis in agarose gel and melting curve analysis. The cDNA samples were stored at -20&#x000b0;C until use.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Quantitative PCR (qPCR)</title><p>qPCR chain reactions were carried out in a <italic>StepOne</italic> Plus Real Time PCR System (Life Technologies) using SYBR Green (BIORAD; 1:10,000 dilution) for monitoring double strand DNA synthesis during qPCR. Reactions were performed in a 20 &#x003bc;L final volume with 10 &#x003bc;L of diluted cDNA (1:50), 0.2 &#x003bc;M of each primer, 0.1 mM of dNTPs, 0.25 units of Platinum Taq DNA Polymerase (Life Technologies) 1X Buffer Solution, and 1.5 mM of MgCl<sub>2</sub>. Each cDNA was analyzed in four technical replicates, and negative controls were included. PCR cycling conditions were as follows: 94&#x000b0;C for 5 min, 40 cycles at 94&#x000b0;C for 15 seconds, 60&#x000b0;C for 10 seconds, 72&#x000b0;C for 15 seconds and 60&#x000b0;C for 35 seconds, and a final melting curve between 50 and 99&#x000b0;C (&#x00394;0.3&#x000b0;C/s).</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Gene expression stability analyses</title><p>All results from RT-qPCR were compared using <italic>NormFinder</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], <italic>geNorm</italic>&#x02014;v. 3.5 [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] software and <italic>BestKeeper</italic> an Excel-based program [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>The <italic>NormFinder</italic> algorithm ranks candidate genes based on their stability of expression and determines the best pair of genes for using as endogenous controls for the samples. <italic>geNorm</italic> calculates the average expression stability (M-value), defining the mean variation of a certain gene in relation to the other candidate genes. Following, <italic>geNorm</italic> determines the best number of reference genes through the pairwise variation estimation (V). Vandesompele et al. (2002) [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] suggested a V cut-off value of 0.15, below which the inclusion of an additional reference gene would not be required. Finally, <italic>BestKeeper</italic> estimates the reference genes with the greatest expression stability by assessing a <italic>BestKeeper</italic> Index specific for each sample, which is calculated as the geometric mean of the Cp values of its candidate housekeeping genes [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec011"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec012"><title>RT-qPCR analysis of candidate reference genes</title><p>In order to select a reliable set of reference genes for gene expression studies in potato edible tubers, RT-qPCR assays were performed for 10 candidate housekeeping genes. The correlation coefficients (r<sup>2</sup>) for all resulting amplification curves were higher than 0.99, and all 10 primer pairs allowed amplification efficiencies (E) between 86 and 104.5% (<xref rid="pone.0120854.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Considering the optimal PCR efficiency as 100%, which allows duplication of the whole target cDNA at each PCR cycle during the exponential phase, the observed efficiency values were considered acceptable; hence, the amplification products of each reaction were comparable to each other.</p><p>Primers for elongation factor 1 alpha, <italic>18S rRNA</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and actin [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] genes were initially included in the data set; however, they were discarded from the analysis due to unexpected amplification products.</p><p>Next, Cp values [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] were used to analyze the steady state mRNA levels of each candidate gene in eight different potato samples, showing a relative wide range of Cp values (<xref rid="pone.0120854.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). In all tested samples, the lowest mean Cp value was observed for the gene eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3 subunit, followed by exocyst complex component sec3 (<italic>SEC3</italic>).</p><fig id="pone.0120854.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120854.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Expression profiles of the tested reference genes in raw Cp values for all 8 samples.</title><p>Expression data are displayed as raw Cp values for each reference gene across all samples. The line denotes the median and boxes indicate the 25/75 percentiles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0120854.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Analyses of reference genes stability via <italic>geNorm</italic>, <italic>NormFinder</italic> and <italic>BestKeeper</italic> algorithms</title><p>Three different algorithms, <italic>NormFinder</italic>, <italic>geNorm</italic> and <italic>BestKeeper</italic>, were applied in computational assessment of gene expression stability in order to minimize potential biases intrinsic to each software.</p><p><italic>NormFinder</italic> uses a mathematical modelling that allows an estimation of gene expression based in a variation of reference genes and in a subgroup of sample sets, considering the best genes those with the lowest stability value, with minimal intra and inter group variation, and indicate the best combination of gene pairs groups and subgroups [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. <xref rid="pone.0120854.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> presents the ranking of the candidate reference genes according to their stability value for the samples, as determined by <italic>NormFinder</italic>. This algorithm identified <italic>C2</italic>, followed by <italic>SEC3</italic>, as the most stably expressed genes in all 8 different samples.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0120854.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120854.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Ranking of candidate reference genes according to the estimated values of stability of expression, as calculated by the <italic>NormFinder</italic> algorithm and M value calculated using <italic>geNorm</italic> estimated M&#x02013;values, for the candidate reference genes.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0120854.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0120854.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene Code</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Rank by <italic>NormFinder</italic></bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Stability by <italic>NormFinder</italic></bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>M-value by <italic>geNorm</italic></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C2</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400023712</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,010</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.647</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exocyst complex component sec3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG402015451</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,015</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.716</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ATCUL3/ATCUL3A/CUL3/CUL3A</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400001321</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,016</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.658</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dead-box atp-dependent rna helicase 39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400023195</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,018</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.736</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ubiquitin-associated /ts-n domain-containing protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG402005949</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,019</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.756</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">importin subunit alpha</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400007289</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,019</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.709</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dck/dgk-like deoxyribonucleoside kinase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400009278</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,021</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.829</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-isopropylmalate synthase b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400016337</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,021</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.763</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3 subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400009231</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.734</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-oxoacyl-(acyl-carrier protein) reductase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG401026981</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,084</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.222</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Best combination of 2 genes (<italic>SEC3</italic> and <italic>C2</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p>*Lowest M value by <italic>geNorm</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><xref rid="pone.0120854.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> describes the ranking of candidate genes as assessed by <italic>geNorm</italic>. Also, pairwise variations (V) were calculated for obtaining the optimal number of normalization factors and the use of 2 primer pairs were definitively enough for this dataset. <xref rid="pone.0120854.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref> shows the M-values and pairwise variation (V) calculated by <italic>geNorm</italic> for all candidates and their best partners for the potato samples. The most stable candidate gene was <italic>C2</italic>, followed by <italic>ATCUL3/ATCUL3A/CUL3/CUL3A</italic> (<italic>CUL3A</italic>), with M-values above 0.7 for both. In agreement, the best gene pair consisted also of the <italic>C2</italic> and <italic>CUL3A</italic> (see <xref rid="pone.0120854.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Additionally, the V-values were below the established 0.15 threshold suggested by Vandesompele et al. (2002) [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], corroborating that the inclusion of an additional gene is not required for data normalization.</p><fig id="pone.0120854.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120854.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Average values of stability of gene expression for the selected reference genes assessed by <italic>geNorm</italic>.</title><p>The plots indicate expression profiles and the determination of the optimal number of control genes for the eight samples.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0120854.g002"/></fig><p>According to the <italic>BestKeeper</italic> algorithm, the importin subunit alpha and ubiquitin-associated/ts-n domain-containing protein genes were the most stably expressed ones in <italic>S</italic>. <italic>tuberosum</italic> edible tubers across all eight samples, with a standard deviation (SD) of 0.66 for both candidates (<xref rid="pone.0120854.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Only 3-oxoacyl-(acyl-carrier protein) reductase and dck/dgk-like deoxyribonucleoside kinase (less stable) were considered to be inconsistent for <italic>BestKeeper</italic> quality parameters ([&#x000b1;Cp] &#x0003e; 1.00), with SDs 1.01 and 3.05, respectively.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0120854.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120854.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Descriptive statistics of candidate reference gene expression patterns, as measured by BestKeeper.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0120854.t004g" xlink:href="pone.0120854.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene Code</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Geometric Mean [CP]</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Arithmetic Mean [CP]</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>min [CP]</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>max [CP]</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Standard Deviation [&#x000b1; CP]</bold><xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Coefficient of Variation [% CP]</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>min [x-fold]</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>max [x-fold]</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Standard Deviation [&#x000b1; x-fold]</bold><xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3 subunit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400009231</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.33</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.37</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.55</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.86</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.48</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.45</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.77</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dead-box ATP-dependent RNA helicase 39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400023195</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.17</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.61</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.70</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.89</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.87</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-oxoacyl-(acyl-carrier protein) reductase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG401026981</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.93</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.14</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.30</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.90</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.24</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-6.19</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">126.03</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">importin subunit alpha</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400007289</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.08</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.60</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66b</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.72</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.80</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.24</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exocyst complex component sec3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG402015451</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.17</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.20</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.73</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.87</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.12</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.86</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ATCUL3/ATCUL3A/CUL3/CUL3A</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400001321</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.60</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.62</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.71</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.01</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.71</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.32</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ubiquitin-associated /ts-n domain-containing protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG402005949</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.04</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.06</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.79</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.06</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.38</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.06</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C2</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400023712</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.65</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.01</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.21</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dCK/dgk-like deoxyribonucleoside kinase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400009278</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.31</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.34</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.49</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.85</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.54</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.83</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-isopropylmalate synthase b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGSC0003DMG400016337</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.17</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.62</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.87</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.90</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.28</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t004fn001"><p><sup>a</sup>Genes with standard deviations [&#x000b1;Cp] &#x0003e; 1.00 are considered to have inconsistent expression patterns (3-oxoacyl-(Acyl-carrier protein) reductase and dck/dgk-like deoxyribonucleoside kinase).</p></fn><fn id="t004fn002"><p><sup>b</sup>Based on the standard deviations (SDs), genes can be ranked from most stably (lowest SD, importin subunit alpha and ubiquitin-associated /ts-n domain-containing protein) to least stably (highest SD, 3-oxoacyl-(acyl-carrier protein) reductase) expressed.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec014"><title>Discussion</title><p>Recently, the quantification of RNA transcripts has become increasingly rapid and precise due to advances in gene quantification strategies. Associated with that, newly identified reference genes showing more stable expression patterns than traditional normalization genes have been reported by analyzing microarray and transcriptome sequencing data [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], and these high throughput techniques might be excellent potential sources of good candidate reference genes, as showed in the present work.</p><p>The accuracy of RT-qPCR results is highly dependent on a reliable normalization strategy that employs an invariant (i.e. stably expressed) reference gene [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. For example, Nicot et al. (2005) and Lopez-Pardo, Ruiz de Galarreta and Ritter (2013) [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] already performed this analysis testing several reference genes, including the elongation factor 1 alpha, with successfully results. Different of our data, the analysis was based on candidates chosen from the literature, not on gene expression experiments, such as microarray or <italic>RNAseq</italic>. In addition, Nicot et al. (2005) [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] did not use samples derived from edible tubers, but samples from a pool of all parts of the potato plant, both under biotic and abiotic stresses, without any distinction between different plant organs. Still, Lopez-Pardo, Ruiz de Galarreta and Ritter (2013) [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] used potato edible tubers as samples, but specifically under cold stress.</p><p>It has become clear that no single gene is constitutively expressed in all cell types and under all experimental conditions. For instance, the expression of the so-called &#x02018;housekeeping&#x02019; genes, although constant under some experimental conditions, can vary considerably in other cases, implying that the stability of the proposed control gene has to be tested before each new experiment [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Normalization with multiple reference genes is becoming a common practice and the gold standard for the technique, but reports that identify such genes in plant investigations are still limited [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p><p>In the present work we evaluated by RT-qPCR 10 reference genes displaying relatively stable expression in edible tubers. Results obtained by <italic>geNorm</italic> and <italic>NormFinder</italic> were very similar to each other and more different than those obtained by <italic>BestKeeper</italic>. While the <italic>geNorm</italic> and <italic>NormFinder</italic> algorithms correct for inter-sample variations, <italic>BestKeeper</italic> does not regard differences in RNA quality or cDNA conversion efficiency across samples, which might influence the distinct findings observed here. Differently from the pairwise approach used by <italic>geNorm</italic>, <italic>NormFinder</italic> selects the top rank candidates with minimal variation rather than correlated expression, which is less influenced by co-regulated genes. Moreover, <italic>NormFinder</italic> takes into consideration systematic differences between sample subgroups [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120854.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Hence, it is expected that the comparison of these three algorithms, as performed here, might provide a more reliable set of reference genes under specific experimental conditions. In this sense, our study provides evidence for the use of certain genes as normalizers in gene expression experiments for potato edible tubers, which is essential for obtaining accurate and reliable gene expression data profiles.</p><p>From our analysis three genes called <italic>SEC3</italic>, <italic>CUL3A</italic> and <italic>C2</italic> were selected as the best normalizers in gene expression of potato edible tubers. However, for each set of samples a validation are needed, and the best reference gene may be different, this could be observed in this present work that the rank for ten candidates to be reference genes for our 8 samples were not exactly the same order of the rank as RNAseq database.</p><p>The gene <italic>SEC3</italic> as well as <italic>SEC5</italic>, <italic>SEC6</italic>, <italic>SEC8</italic>, <italic>SEC10</italic>, <italic>SEC15</italic>, <italic>EXO70</italic>, and <italic>EXO84</italic> genes are part of an evolutionarily conserved octameric protein complex of secretory vesicles [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome encodes single or multiple isoforms of all exocyst subunits [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], and homologous structural models of plant exocyst subunits indicate well conserved rod-like structural features, including putative phosphatidylinositol phosphate binding sites on SEC3 and EXO70 subunits. Through interaction with RAB and RHO GTPases, these proteins are known to be crucial for the proper targeting of the exocyst to membranes [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</p><p>The <italic>CUL3</italic> gene is a constituent of ubiquitin ligase complexes [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, both CUL3A and CUL3B proteins interact with the RING-H2 finger protein RBX1 and with several members of plant BTB domain proteins [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], suggesting that they form similar CUL3-based E3 complexes. However, <italic>cul3a</italic> loss-of-function mutants are viable and fertile, exhibiting only slightly delayed flowering and reduced sensitivity to far red light [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. This viability might be attributed to functional redundancy between the two <italic>CUL3</italic> genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, since disruption of both genes causes embryo lethality, indicating that CUL3 plays important roles during early steps of plant development [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Indeed, CUL3 seems to regulate the ethylene-independent distal root patterning and primary root growth by a novel ethylene-dependent pathway, thus implicating CUL3 in the division and organization of the root stem cell niche and columella root cap cells [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</p><p>Finally, the gene that is referred to in the EnsemblPlants database and hence in this paper as <italic>C2</italic> is actually coding for a yet uncharacterized protein, designated M1C6S3_SOLTU in the UniProt database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/M1C6S3">http://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/M1C6S3</ext-link>). In this entry it is mentioned that the protein contains three C2 domains. The C2 domain polypeptide is one of the most prevalent eukaryotic lipid-binding domains used in diverse functional contexts. This structural domain helps target proteins to cell membranes, and its typical version (PKC-C2) has a beta-sandwich conformation composed of 8 &#x003b2;-strands that co-ordinate two or three calcium ions, which bind in a cavity formed by the first and final loops of the domain on the membrane binding face [<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120854.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Transcriptome data such as those obtained from microarray and <italic>RNAseq</italic> experiments provide an excellent resource of selecting candidate RT-qPCR reference genes. Here, through bioinformatics and experimental data, we show the selection and validation of ten putative reference genes for RT-qPCR studies in potato samples. The <italic>C2</italic>, <italic>SEC3</italic>, and <italic>CUL3A</italic> genes were found to be the most stable and suitable normalizers for potato edible tubers expression studies. In summary, these findings provide useful tools for the normalization of RT-qPCR experiments and will enable more accurate and reliable gene expression studies related to functional genomics in potato.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thanks M.Sc. Eduardo Preusser de Mattos for critical english review of the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0120854.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arden</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nitsche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Real-time PCR in virology</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1292</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1305</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11884626?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11884626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Radoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thulke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Landt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siegert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nitsche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Guideline to reference gene selection for quantitative real-time PCR</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2004</year>; <volume>313</volume>: <fpage>856</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>862</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14706621?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14706621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Obrero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Die</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nadal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Verdejo</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>. <article-title>Selection of reference genes for gene expression studies in Zucchini (<italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic>) using qPCR</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>5402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5411</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/jf200689r">10.1021/jf200689r</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21476515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21476515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Derveaux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vandersompele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hellemans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>How to do successful gene expression analysis using real-time PCR</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>230</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ymeth.2009.11.001">10.1016/j.ymeth.2009.11.001</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19969088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19969088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pfaffl</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>. <article-title>A new mathematical model for relative quantification in real time RT-PCR</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>2002</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2007</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Selection of reference genes for quantitative gene expression studies in <italic>Platycladus orientalis</italic> (<italic>Cupressaceae</italic>) using real-time PCR</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e33278</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0033278">10.1371/journal.pone.0033278</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22479379?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22479379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mauriat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pelloux</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bellini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wuytswinkel</surname><given-names>UV</given-names></name>. <article-title>Towards a systematic validation of references in real time RT PCR</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1734</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1735</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.108.059774">10.1105/tpc.108.059774</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 18664615?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18664615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bustin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantification of mRNA using real-time reverse transcription PCR (RT-PCR): trends and problems</article-title>. <source>J Mol Endocrinol</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12200227?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12200227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>&#x000d8;rntoft</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Normalization of real-time quantitative reverse transcription-PCR data: a model-based variance estimation approach to identify genes suited for normalization, applied to bladder and colon cancer data sets</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>5245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5250</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15289330?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15289330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Czechowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genome-wide identification and testing of superior reference genes for transcript normalization in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16166256?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hruz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wyss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Docquier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pfaffl</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Masanetz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borghi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>RefGenes: identification of reliable and condition specific reference genes for RT-qPCR data normalization</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-12-156">10.1186/1471-2164-12-156</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21418615?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21418615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vandesompele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Preter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pattyn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poppe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Roy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Paepe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Accurate normalization of real-time quantitative RT&#x02013;PCR data by geometric averaging of multiple internal control genes</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pfaffl</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tichopad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prgomet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neuvians</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Determination of stable housekeeping genes, differentially regulated target genes and sample integrity: <italic>BestKeeper</italic>&#x02014;Excel-based tool using pair-wise correlations</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Lett</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15127793?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15127793</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cankar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheffer</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beenen</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shepher</surname><given-names>LVT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Transcriptome analysis of potato tubers effects of different agricultural practices</article-title>. <source>J. Agric Food Chem</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1612</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1623</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/jf802815d">10.1021/jf802815d</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19173602?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19173602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Core Team [2014] R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing, Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org">http://www.R-project.org</ext-link>. Accessed 2013 Dec 3.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Perini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pasquali</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>PRD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Revers</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reference genes for transcriptional analysis of flowering and fruit ripening stages in apple (<italic>Malus</italic> X <italic>domestica</italic> Borkh.)</article-title>. <source>Mol Breed</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>842</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bustin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benes</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hellemans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huggett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kubista</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The MIQE guidelines: minimum information for publication of quantitative real-time PCR experiments</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>622</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1373/clinchem.2008.112797">10.1373/clinchem.2008.112797</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19246619?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19246619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nicot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hausman</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Evers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Housekeeping gene selection for real-time RT-PCR normalization in potato during biotic and abiotic stress</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>2907</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2914</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16188960?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16188960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lopez-Pardo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruiz de Galarreta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ritter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Selection of housekeeping genes for qRT-PCR analysis in potato tubers under cold stress</article-title>. <source>Mol Breed</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genome-wide analysis and expression profiling of the <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> aquaporins</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>392</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>404</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2013.10.025">10.1016/j.plaphy.2013.10.025</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 24215931?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24215931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>A Technique whose time has come</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>296</volume>: <fpage>557</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>559</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11964485?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11964485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Demidenko</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Logacheva</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Penin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Selection and validation of reference genes for quantitative real-time PCR in buckwheat (<italic>Fagopyrum esculentum</italic>) based on transcriptome sequence data</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e19434</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0019434">10.1371/journal.pone.0019434</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21589908?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21589908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S-U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Selection of new appropriate reference genes for <italic>RT-qPCR</italic> analysis via transcriptome sequencing of Cynomolgus Monkeys (<italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic>)</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e60758</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0060758">10.1371/journal.pone.0060758</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23613744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23613744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Identification of suitable reference genes for gene expression normalization in qRT-PCR analysis in watermelon</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e90612</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0090612">10.1371/journal.pone.0090612</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 24587403?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24587403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of reference genes for gene expression analysis using quantitative RT-PCR in <italic>Azospirillum brasilense</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e98162</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0098162">10.1371/journal.pone.0098162</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 24841066?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24841066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Volkov</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Panchuk</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;ffl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Heat-stress dependency and developmental modulation of gene expression: the potential of house-keeping genes as internal standards in mRNA expression profiling using real-time RT&#x02013;PCR</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>2343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2349</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14504302?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14504302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gu&#x000e9;nin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mauriat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pelloux</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Wuytswinkel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bellini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Normalization of qRT&#x02013;PCR data: the necessity of adopting a systematic, experimental conditions-specific, validation of references</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>493</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jxb/ern305">10.1093/jxb/ern305</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19264760?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19264760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bastolla</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Margis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frazzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Reference genes for the normalization of gene expression in <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> species</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>405</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>422</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/pcp/pcr187">10.1093/pcp/pcr187</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22197885?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22197885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Coker</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Selection of candidate housekeeping controls in tomato plants using EST data</article-title>. <source>Biotechniques</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>740</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>748</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14579739?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14579739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yakovlev</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Validating internal controls for quantitative plant gene expression studies</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15317655?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15317655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Exposito-Rodr&#x00131;guez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borges-P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>J&#x000c1;</given-names></name>. <article-title>Selection of internal control genes for quantitative real-time RT-PCR studies during tomato development process</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-8-131">10.1186/1471-2229-8-131</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19102748?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19102748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of putative reference genes for gene expression normalization in soybean by quantitative real-time RT&#x02013;PCR</article-title>. <source>BMC Mol Biol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2199-10-93">10.1186/1471-2199-10-93</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19785741?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19785741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>L&#x000f8;vdal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lillo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reference gene selection for quantitative real-time PCR normalization in tomato subjected to nitrogen, cold, and light stress</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>387</volume>: <fpage>238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>242</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ab.2009.01.024">10.1016/j.ab.2009.01.024</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19454243?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19454243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paolacci</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanzarella</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Porceddu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ciaffi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification and validation of reference genes for quantitative RT-PCR normalization in wheat</article-title>. <source>BMC Mol Biol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2199-10-11">10.1186/1471-2199-10-11</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19232096?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19232096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruedell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ricachenevsky</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sperotto</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pasquali</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fett-Neto</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reference gene selection for quantitative reverse transcription&#x02013;polymerase chain reaction normalization during <italic>in vitro</italic> adventitious rooting in <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> Labill</article-title>. <source>BMC Mol Biol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2199-11-73">10.1186/1471-2199-11-73</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20854682?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20854682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bahn</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification and testing of superior reference genes for a starting pool of transcript normalization in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1694</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1706</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/pcp/pcq128">10.1093/pcp/pcq128</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20798276?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20798276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kulcheski</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marcelino-Guimar&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nepomuceno</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abdelnoor</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Margis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>The use of microRNAs as reference genes for quantitative polymerase chain reaction in soybean</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>406</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>192</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ab.2010.07.020">10.1016/j.ab.2010.07.020</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20670612?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20670612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maroufi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Bockstaele</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Loose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Validation of reference genes for gene expression analysis in chicory (<italic>Cichorium intybus</italic>) using quantitative real-time PCR</article-title>. <source>BMC Mol Biol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2199-11-15">10.1186/1471-2199-11-15</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20156357?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20156357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stable internal reference genes for normalization of real-time RT&#x02013;PCR in tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>) during development and abiotic stress</article-title>. <source>Mol Genet Genomics</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00438-010-0511-1">10.1007/s00438-010-0511-1</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20098998?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20098998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KLC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lurin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of ethylene gas biosynthesis by the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ETO1 protein</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>428</volume>: <fpage>945</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>950</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15118728?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15118728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoenemann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hohe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Selection of reference genes for normalization of quantitative real-time PCR in cell cultures of <italic>Cyclamen persicum</italic></article-title>. <source>Electron J Biotechnol</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2225/vol14-issue1-fulltext-8">10.2225/vol14-issue1-fulltext-8</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>TerBush</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maurice</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>The exocyst is a multiprotein complex required for exocytosis in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>6483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6494</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8978675?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8978675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hazuka</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davanger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The mammalian brain rsec6/8 complex</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1219</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8982167?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8982167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Synek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schlager</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quentin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zarsky</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>. <article-title>AtEXO70A1, a member of a family of putative exocyst subunits specifically expanded in land plants, is important for polar growth and plant development</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16942608?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16942608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Z&#x00103;rsk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cvr&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Potock&#x000fa;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>H&#x000e1;la</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Exocytosis and cell polarity in plants&#x02014;exocyst and recycling domains</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>183</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.02880.x">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.02880.x</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19496948?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19496948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dieterle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Renou J-</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parmentier</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cognat</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lemonnier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Molecular and functional characterisation of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Cullin 3A</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>386</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>399</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15659098?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15659098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bernhardt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dieterle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mutlu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Arabidopsis AtCUL3a and AtCUL3b form complexes with members of the BTB/POZMATH protein family</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15618422?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15618422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thomann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brukhin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dieterle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gheyeselinck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vantard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title><italic>Arabidopsis CUL3A</italic> and <italic>CUL3B</italic> genes are essential for normal embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>448</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16045478?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16045478</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gusmaroli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Serino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Habashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Arabidopsis has two redundant Cullin3 proteins that are essential for embryo development and that interact with RBX1 and BTB proteins to form multisubunit E3 Ubiquitin Ligase complexes in vivo</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1180</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1195</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15772280?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15772280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aravind</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification of novel families and classification of the C2 domain superfamily elucidate the origin and evolution of membrane targeting activities in eukaryotes</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>469</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gene.2010.08.006">10.1016/j.gene.2010.08.006</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20713135?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20713135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120854.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aravind</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Novel transglutaminase-like peptidase and C2 domains elucidate the structure, biogenesis and evolution of the ciliary compartment</article-title>. <source>Cell Cycle</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>3861</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4161/cc.22068">10.4161/cc.22068</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22983010?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22983010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>