<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4300822</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25477200</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6790</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-1066</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Unique aspects of fiber degradation by the ruminal ethanologen <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 7 revealed by physiological and transcriptomic analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Christopherson</surname><given-names>Melissa R</given-names></name><address><email>melissachristopherson@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff49"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>John A</given-names></name><address><email>jadawson@uab.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff51"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>David M</given-names></name><address><email>dmstevenson@wisc.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff50"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>Andrew C</given-names></name><address><email>andy.cunningham@doit.wisc.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff49"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bramhacharya</surname><given-names>Shanti</given-names></name><address><email>BramhacharyaS@my.hiram.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff49"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>Paul J</given-names></name><address><email>pjweimer@wisc.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff49"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff50"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kendziorski</surname><given-names>Christina</given-names></name><address><email>kendzior@biostat.wisc.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff51"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Suen</surname><given-names>Garret</given-names></name><address><email>gsuen@wisc.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff49"/></contrib><aff id="Aff49"><label/>Department of Bacteriology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 5159 Microbial Sciences Building, 1550 Linden Drive, Madison, WI 53706-1521 USA </aff><aff id="Aff50"><label/>U.S. Dairy Forage Research Center, U.S. Department of Agriculture-Agricultural Research Services, (USDA-ARS), Madison, WI 53706 USA </aff><aff id="Aff51"><label/>Department of Biostatistics and Medical Informatics, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI 53706-1521 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>1066</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Christopherson et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Bacteria in the genus <italic>Ruminococcus</italic> are ubiquitous members of the mammalian gastrointestinal tract. In particular, they are important in ruminants where they digest a wide range of plant cell wall polysaccharides. For example, <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 7 is a primary cellulose degrader that produces acetate usable by its bovine host. Moreover, it is one of the few organisms that ferments cellulose to form ethanol at mesophilic temperatures <italic>in vitro</italic>. The mechanism of cellulose degradation by <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 is not well-defined and is thought to involve pilin-like proteins, unique carbohydrate-binding domains, a glycocalyx, and cellulosomes. Here, we used a combination of comparative genomics, fermentation analyses, and transcriptomics to further clarify the cellulolytic and fermentative potential of <italic>R. albus</italic> 7.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A comparison of the <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 genome sequence against the genome sequences of related bacteria that either encode or do not encode cellulosomes revealed that <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 does not encode for most canonical cellulosomal components. Fermentation analysis of <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 revealed the ability to produce ethanol and acetate on a wide range of fibrous substrates <italic>in vitro</italic>. Global transcriptomic analysis of <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 grown at identical dilution rates on cellulose and cellobiose in a chemostat showed that this bacterium, when growing on cellulose, utilizes a carbohydrate-degrading strategy that involves increased transcription of the rare carbohydrate-binding module (CBM) family 37 domain and the tryptophan biosynthetic operon.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our data suggest that <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 does not use canonical cellulosomal components to degrade cellulose, but rather up-regulates the expression of CBM37-containing enzymes and tryptophan biosynthesis. This study contributes to a revised model of carbohydrate degradation by this key member of the rumen ecosystem.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/1471-2164-15-1066) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic></kwd><kwd>Cellulose utilization</kwd><kwd>Ethanol production</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p>Ruminococci are established members of the gastrointestinal tract (GIT) microbiota of ruminants, hindgut-fermenters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and monogastrics such as humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. For example, 6 <italic>Ruminococcus</italic> species are among the 57 bacteria that define the &#x0201c;core gut microbiome&#x0201d; found in 90% of humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The fibrolytic capabilities of many ruminococci make them key players in the dynamics of gut microbial communities and these bacteria have been linked to activities that influence gastrointestinal health in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] as well as fiber degradation in ruminants. In the bovine rumen, ruminococci are major contributors to the conversion of fibrous feeds into the organic acids utilized by the host as nutrients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Importantly, ruminococci account for up to 10% of the 16S rRNA gene copies in the bovine rumen, and play a fundamental role in cellulose degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Although <italic>Ruminococcus</italic> isolates from the rumen can hydrolyze crystalline cellulose, their activity on other fibrous substrates has not been well-characterized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Investigating how ruminococci degrade fibers will facilitate our understanding of the role that this group plays in host nutrition. In addition, the fermentative capacity of ruminococci, including ethanol production by <italic>R. albus</italic> 7, could inform industrial efforts to convert cellulosic material into commercially relevant bioproducts.</p><p>Among the ruminococci, cellulose digestion is best characterized for <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Fiber adherence in <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> is mediated in part by multienzyme complexes called cellulosomes. Cellulosomes contain cell-anchored scaffold proteins that coordinate fibrolytic enzymes <italic>via</italic> interlocking dockerin and cohesin domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The scaffold and fibrolytic enzymes are attached to the substrate by carbohydrate binding modules (CBMs), thus localizing the fibrolytic enzymes and hydrolytic products near the cell surface (for a review see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]). However, the mechanism of adherence to cellulose for other ruminococci such as <italic>R. albus</italic> is less defined.</p><p>Cellulosomes have been suspected in some strains of <italic>R. albus</italic>
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], but studies have failed to identify key cellulosomal components in these bacteria. For example, two cellulases were identified in <italic>R. albus</italic> 8 that lacked dockerin domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], but instead contained a unique family 37 CBM found only among <italic>R. albus</italic> strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Additionally, a Pil-family protein was found to be involved in fiber adherence in <italic>R. albus</italic> 8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] leading to the suggestion that a combination of cellulosomes, cell-anchored cellulases, and Type IV pili may be involved in fiber adherence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. <italic>R. albus</italic> strains also produce a thick matrix of extracellular polysaccharide, called a glycocalyx, when grown on cellulose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Although details of the glycocalyx composition are known [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], the role of the glycocalyx in fiber degradation has not been established.</p><p>Given these observations, we hypothesized that <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 does not utilize cellulosomes to degrade crystalline cellulose. To test this, we compared the recently sequenced genome for this bacterium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] to the genome sequences of other cellulolytic and non-cellulolytic ruminococci and show the lack of complete canonical cellulosomes. We then performed a global transcriptomic analysis of <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 cultures grown on either cellulose or cellobiose to reveal previously unconsidered aspects of cellulose degradation by this bacterium. Finally, we show that <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 utilizes, and produces ethanol from, a number of complex fibrous substrates <italic>in vitro</italic>. Our results contribute to a revised model for fiber degradation by <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 and underscore the important role that ruminococci may play within the mammalian GIT microbiota.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title><italic>R. albus</italic>7 and <italic>R. albus</italic>8 are distinct from that of <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic>FD-1</title><p>To assess the genomic differences between ruminant-derived ruminococci, we compared the genome sequences of three cellulolytic ruminococci: <italic>R. albus</italic> 7, <italic>R. albus</italic> 8, and <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> FD-1. We employed OrthoMCL, an analysis tool that identifies orthologs by collapsing paralogous proteins and orthologous proteins into orthologous clusters. Using this method, organisms can be differentiated by the presence or absence of clusters. <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 and 8 shared nearly four times as many clusters with each other than with <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> FD-1 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). Based on a protein family (Pfam) annotation of these clusters, we found that some of the differences between <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> and the <italic>R. albus</italic> strains included predicted carbohydrate-active enzymes (CAZymes). Overall, we identified 1,234 ortholog clusters common to all 3 bacterial strains, 55 of which contain open reading frames (ORFs) predicted to code for CAZymes. There were few ortholog clusters unique to each organism.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Functional relationships between sequenced ruminococci. A)</bold> OrthoMCL was used to identify unique and shared proteins among three cellulolytic ruminococci: <italic>R. albus</italic> 7, <italic>R. albus</italic> 8, and <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> FD-1. Total number of shared orthologous clusters within each group are indicated and the number of orthologous clusters annotated as carbohydrate-active enzymes are shown in parentheses. <bold>B)</bold> Comparison of the three cellulolytic ruminococci (light gray) with non-fibrolytic ruminococci (dark gray), and amylolytic <italic>Ruminococcus bromii</italic> L2-63 (unshaded) emphasized the number of carbohydrate-active enzymes that were specific to these physiologically distinct groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2014_6790_Fig1_HTML" id="d30e560"/></fig></p><p>We further refined our CAZyme-containing ortholog clusters to those specific for cellulose utilization by comparing them with five other non-cellulolytic ruminococci (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). More than half of the 55 CAZymes common to the cellulolytic ruminococci were shared with non-cellulolytic ruminococci. As expected, many of these predicted CAZymes were involved with general sugar metabolism, such as glycosyl transferases (GT), carbohydrate esterases (CE), or non-cellulolytic families of glycosyl hydrolases (GH) and were therefore not considered further in this study. The remaining CAZyme ortholog clusters are listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1 and include numerous cellulases, including three distinct clusters of GH9 cellulases that were common to each of the cellulolytic ruminococci. One of these clusters was similar to the dockerin-containing Cel9A cellulase from <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> F-40 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><italic>R. albus</italic>strains lack most canonical cellulosome components</title><p>We investigated the relative abundance of core cellulosome components and cellulases within several sequenced Clostridiales genomes. Specifically, we chose organisms from the genera <italic>Ruminococcus</italic> and <italic>Clostridium</italic> that have well-characterized canonical cellulosomes (<italic>C. thermocellum</italic> ATCC 27405<italic>, C. cellulovorans</italic> 743B<italic>, C. cellulolyticum</italic> ATCC 35319<italic>, R. flavefaciens</italic> FD-1), cellulolytic organisms not known to contain cellulosomes (<italic>C. phytofermentans</italic> ISDg, <italic>R. albus</italic> 7, <italic>R. albus</italic> 8), and non-cellulolytic organisms (<italic>C. perfringens</italic> ATCC13124<italic>, R. torques</italic> L2-14<italic>, R. bromii</italic> L2-63). We performed a correlation-based clustering analysis and determined the relative similarity between these bacteria (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Despite the known diversity among molecular components of cellulosomes, all organisms with characterized cellulosomes that we tested formed a single group distinct from organisms that lacked characterized cellulosomes or from non-cellulolytic organisms. Dockerins, cohesins, and cellulosomal cellulases were generally lacking among the non-cellulolytic organisms with the exception of the amylolytic <italic>R. bromii</italic> L2-63 that had numerous representatives in two of the dockerin families (IPR018242 and IPR016134). The number of representatives in each of the cohesin and dockerin families and the GH9 family were higher among the organisms with canonical cellulosomes (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Comparison of cellulolytic components between cellulolytic and non-cellulolytic bacteria.</bold> Representatives from cellulolytic enzyme families (cellulases) and cellulosome components (dockerins and cohesins) were tabulated in bacteria with unconfirmed cellulosomes (light-gray), confirmed cellulosomes (dark gray), and non-cellulolytic bacteria (unshaded). Sums in each category were used to generate a distance matrix that distinguished groups of these bacteria. Although the cellulolytic <italic>Clostridium phytofermentans</italic> ISDg does not have a confirmed cellulosome, it is highlighted in black to emphasize its relative distinction from the other groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2014_6790_Fig2_HTML" id="d30e643"/></fig></p><p>The <italic>R. albus</italic> strains we examined did not group with any of the cellulosome-containing or non-cellulolytic organisms. Our analysis showed that both <italic>R. albus</italic> strains encode for dockerin-containing proteins, as has been noted previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], but lacked representatives of the dockerin family IPR002105 as well as in both cohesin families. Only one putative cohesin (family IPR002102) was found in <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 (Rumal_2328). Moreover, homologs of recognized scaffoldin proteins from <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> FD-1 (Sca) and <italic>C. thermocellum</italic> ATCC 27405 (Cip) were absent from the <italic>R. albus</italic> strains.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><italic>R. albus 7</italic>ferments ethanol and acetate from a wide range of substrates</title><p><italic>R. albus</italic> 7 is known to produce ethanol, acetate, H<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> from cellulose in pure culture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. We verified this and further tested a number of other polysaccharides by measuring ethanol, acetate, and reducing sugar concentrations in batch culture as shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. We found that <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 hydrolyzed and utilized a variety of plant polysaccharides, including cellulose and hemicelluloses (homoxylan from tobacco stalk, 4-<italic>O</italic>-methylglucuronoxylan from larchwood). The strain also fermented the storage polysaccharides lichenan (a mixed polymer of &#x003b2;-1,3-, &#x003b2;-1,4-glucose), glucomannan (a mixed polymer of &#x003b2;-1,4-linked glucose and mannose), and the highly complex polysaccharides from soybeans (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Although <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 hydrolyzed citrus pectin and inulin (a polymer of fructose) to generate reducing sugars, it did not utilize these substrates as shown by the absence of fermentation products. <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 did not hydrolyze or utilize resistant starch (amylose), complex branched polysaccharides (Type II arabinoglacatan), or the storage glucans curdlan (&#x003b2; -1,3-glucan) and laminarin (a mixed &#x003b2;-1,3-, &#x003b2;-1,6 glucan). <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 produced a similar molar ratio (roughly 3:2) of ethanol:acetate regardless of substrate utilized despite slightly higher production of total fermentation products on lichenan and lower production of fermentation products on soy polysaccharides (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The yield of ethanol produced by <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 per gram of crystalline cellulose was similar to the amount of ethanol produced by other reported ethanologenic cellulolytic organisms grown in batch culture (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Hydrolysis and fermentation of polysaccharides by</bold>
<bold><italic>R. albus</italic></bold>
<bold>7</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Polysaccharide</th><th>Ethanol
<sup>1</sup>
</th><th>Acetate
<sup>1</sup>
</th><th>Reducing sugars
<sup>2</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Cellulose</td><td align="center">3.89&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.20</td><td align="center">2.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.16</td><td align="center">0.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td></tr><tr><td>Xylan (tobacco stalk)</td><td align="center">3.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.29</td><td align="center">2.24&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19</td><td align="center">19.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3</td></tr><tr><td>Xylan (larchwood)</td><td align="center">3.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.01</td><td align="center">1.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.84</td><td align="center">5.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td></tr><tr><td>Glucomannan</td><td align="center">3.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.12</td><td align="center">2.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td><td align="center">6.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td></tr><tr><td>Lichenan</td><td align="center">4.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.38</td><td align="center">2.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.2</td></tr><tr><td>Soy polysaccharides</td><td align="center">1.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19</td><td align="center">0.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19</td><td align="center">15.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.2</td></tr><tr><td>Citrus pectin<sup>3</sup>
</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">44.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.9</td></tr><tr><td>Inulin<sup>3</sup>
</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">54.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>1</sup>Product formed during growth (mmol/g dry polysaccharide substrate).</p><p>
<sup>2</sup>Reducing sugars in supernatant (% of dry polysaccharide substrate).</p><p>
<sup>3</sup>Substrate was hydrolyzed to produce reducing sugars but was not utilized.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p><italic>Continuous culture fermentations.</italic> Steady-state cultures grown on cellulose showed a different fermentation pattern than batch cultures, producing more acetate than ethanol (roughly 5:4) with higher levels of each of these fermentation products. Continuous cultures grown on cellulose consumed 1.97&#x000a0;g cellulose/L, equivalent to 10.94&#x000a0;mM glucose equivalents, and produced 11.4&#x000a0;mM ethanol and 14.8&#x000a0;mM acetate. Continuous cultures grown on cellobiose consumed 4.62&#x000a0;g glucose equivalents/L (25.67&#x000a0;mM) and produced 26.9&#x000a0;mM ethanol and 27.7&#x000a0;mM acetate. Cell protein concentrations from cellulose and cellobiose cultures were 0.185 and 0.315&#x000a0;g/L, equivalent to cell yields of 0.188 and 0.136&#x000a0;g/g glucose equivalent, respectively, assuming cells are 50% protein by dry weight.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>The global <italic>R. albus</italic>7 transcriptome revealed differences in gene expression between cellulose- and cellobiose-grown cultures</title><p>To identify components important for cellulose degradation, we compared the transcriptome of <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 grown in either a cellulose- or cellobiose-limited chemostat culture. Growth rate has been reported to influence cellulase expression in other cellulolytic organisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], and thus a constant 0.033&#x000a0;h<sup>-1</sup> dilution rate was used for both cellulose and cellobiose in our substrate-limited chemostat. This allows for direct comparison of the effect of substrate type, independent of the confounding effect of growth rate that would result from batch culture cultivation. Ribosome-free RNA was purified from samples taken from steady-state cultures over three days on each substrate and subjected to high-throughput sequencing using Illumina-based RNA-seq, generating at least 9.9 million reads per sample (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3). In most cases, over 90% of the transcripts could be mapped back to the <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 genome sequence, with the remaining unmapped reads representing sequencing errors or unaligned reads due to SNP variation. Over half of the total transcripts were differentially expressed between cellobiose and cellulose substrates with nearly 28% of predicted proteins increased by two-fold or more in response to growth on cellulose (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1). This broad transcriptional response spanned the entire chromosome as well as the four plasmids, and contained reproducible expression patterns across each replicate chemostat sample with the exception of one cellobiose sample (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S2). Incompletely digested chromosomal DNA or an RNAase may have contaminated this sample and it was not included in any further analysis. Predicted open reading frames (ORFs) with lower transcription on cellulose, as compared to cellobiose, are described in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Supplementary Information 1 and Table S4.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Increased transcription of cellulases during <italic>R. albus</italic>7 growth on cellulose compared to cellobiose</title><p>Thirteen predicted CAZymes, including cellulases and hemicellulases, exhibited greater than 4-fold higher transcription when grown on cellulose, as compared to cellobiose. All of the 27 predicted cellulases encoded by the <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 genome sequence had higher transcription on cellulose than cellobiose, although only 4 exhibited greater than 4-fold expression (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). These included two GH9 cellulases (Rumal_1569 and Rumal _2448) and two GH5 cellulases (Rumal_0896 and Rumal_2599). Fourteen of the twenty-seven predicted cellulases were not differentially expressed (had a fold-change less than two, data not shown) and none of the predicted cellulases had lower transcription when <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 was grown on cellulose. Using the PRED-TAT software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], we found that all of the predicted cellulases and hemicellulases contained signal peptides for Sec-dependent secretion (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Genes with greater than 4-fold higher transcription during growth of</bold>
<bold><italic>R. albus 7</italic></bold>
<bold>on cellulose compared to cellobiose as the sole carbohydrate source assessed by RNA-Seq</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gene (Rumal_)</th><th>Annotation
<sup>1</sup>
</th><th>Fold Change
<sup>2</sup>
</th><th>Signal sequence
<sup>3</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">1715</td><td>Indole-3-glycerol-phosphate synthase</td><td align="center">15.50</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1714</td><td>chorismate mutase</td><td align="center">15.49</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1716</td><td>anthranilate phosphoribosyltransferase</td><td align="center">14.90</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1712</td><td>tryptophan synthase subunit alpha</td><td align="center">14.90</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1713</td><td>tryptophan synthase subunit beta</td><td align="center">14.10</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1717</td><td>anthranilate synthase component I</td><td align="center">13.62</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3687</td><td>transcriptional regulator, ArsR family</td><td align="center">11.53</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3686</td><td>protein of unknown function DUF1648</td><td align="center">11.32</td><td align="center">Sec</td></tr><tr><td align="center">0360</td><td>helix-turn-helix domain-containing protein</td><td align="center">10.04</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3688</td><td>protein of unknown function UCP033101</td><td align="center">9.98</td><td align="center">TM</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2652</td><td>putative multiple sugar transport system substrate-binding protein</td><td align="center">9.80</td><td align="center">Sec</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2572</td><td>ECF subfamily RNA polymerase sigma-24 subunit</td><td align="center">8.82</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2573</td><td>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">8.18</td><td align="center">TM</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>0897</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>fibronectin type III domain-containing protein (CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>7.93</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3780</td><td>Resolvase domain</td><td align="center">7.91</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>2448</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>Cellulase (GH9 CBM3 CBM37 CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>7.70</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3766</td><td>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">7.42</td><td align="center">Sec</td></tr><tr><td align="center">0953</td><td>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">7.00</td><td align="center">Sec</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3796</td><td>ABC transporter family protein</td><td align="center">5.91</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>1569</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>Cellulase (GH9 CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>5.56</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3775</td><td>ABC transporter family protein</td><td align="center">5.53</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>3757</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>Endo-1,4-beta-xylanase (GH11 CBM22 GH10 CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>5.51</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3776</td><td>IstB domain protein ATP-binding protein</td><td align="center">5.21</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>0896</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>Cellulase (GH5 CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>5.15</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>1952</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>fibronectin type III domain-containing protein (PL1 CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>5.00</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3963</td><td>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">4.84</td><td align="center">TM</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1427</td><td>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">4.74</td><td align="center">TM</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>0487</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>Ricin B lectin (CE12 CBM13 CBM35 CE12)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.74</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3179</td><td>Capsule synthesis protein CapA</td><td align="center">4.68</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>2739</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>endo-1,4-beta-xylanase (GH11 CBM22 CE1 CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.63</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>1262</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>fibronectin type III domain-containing protein (PL11 CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.61</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>0908</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>endo-1,4-beta-xylanase (GH11 CBM22 CE4 CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.59</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3944</td><td>chaperone protein DnaK</td><td align="center">4.48</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1426</td><td>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">4.37</td><td align="center">Sec</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1821</td><td>family 1 extracellular solute-binding protein</td><td align="center">4.36</td><td align="center">Sec</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3777</td><td>Integrase catalytic region</td><td align="center">4.33</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1428</td><td>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">4.30</td><td align="center">TM</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1602</td><td>transaldolase</td><td align="center">4.26</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>2599</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>glycoside hydrolase family 5 (GH5 CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.23</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3940</td><td>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">4.22</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3798</td><td>IS66 Orf2 family protein</td><td align="center">4.22</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3186</td><td>family 1 extracellular solute-binding protein</td><td align="center">4.18</td><td align="center">Sec</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>1951</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>fibronectin type III domain-containing protein (CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.17</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Sec</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3184</td><td>binding-protein-dependent transport systems inner membrane component</td><td align="center">4.16</td><td align="center">TM</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3185</td><td>binding-protein-dependent transport systems inner membrane component</td><td align="center">4.12</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3774</td><td>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">4.10</td><td align="center">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center">
<bold>1044</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>spore coat protein CotH (CBM37)</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.09</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>Tat</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3263</td><td>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">4.02</td><td align="center">No</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>1</sup>Each gene reported here was significantly DE, with a PP of DE greater than 0.95</p><p>
<sup>2</sup>Predicted signal sequence predicted by PRED-TAT. Sec&#x02009;=&#x02009;Sec-dependent; TM&#x02009;=&#x02009;transmembrane.</p><p>
<sup>3</sup>Genes containing predicted CBM37 domains are presented in bold.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Of the CAZymes found to be up-regulated on cellulose, relative to cellobiose, all but one contained one or more CBM37 domains. We identified 64 proteins containing one or more CBM37 domains in the <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 genome sequence, and 39 of them had more than 2-fold higher transcription when grown on cellulose, relative to cellobiose. The CAZyme with the highest differential expression (Rumal_0897) contained a single CBM37 as its only predicted CAZy domain. <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 has 35 proteins predicted to contain binding modules with no adjacent catalytic domains, including 26 containing a single CBM37, 8 that each contain 2 CBM37 domains, 1 that contains a CBM37 and a CBM2 domain, 1 that contains 2 CBM37 domains, and 2 containing a CBM13 and a CBM37 domains. In addition to these ORFs, we also investigated whether or not putative pilin-like genes and genes involved in glycocalyx biosynthesis had higher transcription on cellulose, relative to cellobiose, and found that none of these genes were differentially expressed (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figures S3 and S4).</p><p>In addition to CAZymes, ORFs found to be expressed more than 4-fold or higher on cellulose, relative to cellobiose, include those predicted to be involved in transcription, and primary metabolism. There were also several clusters of ORFs that were differentially expressed including four putative ABC transporter operons that each had 4-fold or higher transcription in response to growth on cellulose (Rumal_3686 &#x02013; Rumal_3688, Rumal_3184 &#x02013; Rumal_3187, Rumal_3774 &#x02013; Rumal_3777, and Rumal_1427 &#x02013; Rumal_1429). Most notably, the entire tryptophan biosynthetic operon had over 13-fold higher transcription in response to cellulose, and is discussed in the following section.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Tryptophan enrichment among CAZymes is widespread among cellulolytic organisms</title><p>The tryptophan biosynthetic operon was the most highly expressed set of ORFs in the <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 chemostat culture grown on cellulose, as compared to cellobiose (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). This finding was further verified using reverse transcription quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR) of the tryptophan biosynthetic gene, Rumal_1716, normalized to 16S rRNA, which was found to be expressed 7.2 fold higher on cellulose, relative to cellobiose. Despite the highly regulated nature of this pathway, induction of the tryptophan operon in response to growth on cellulose has been previously observed in <italic>C. phytofermentans</italic> where it was thought to involve an increased need for tryptophan in the CAZymes important for growth on cellulose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. We tested this hypothesis for <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 and found that CAZymes in this bacterium also showed a significantly higher percentage of tryptophans compared to all other genes in the genome (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). An analysis of CAZymes from a range of other cellulolytic, amylolytic and hemicellulolytic species also showed a significant enrichment for tryptophan as well as tyrosine (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01), but not for non-aromatic amino acids like methionine (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). This indicates that a specific enrichment for aromatic amino acids among CAZymes is widespread among cellulolytic bacteria, and not specific to <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 or <italic>C. phytofermentans</italic>.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Aromatic amino acid enrichment among CAZymes</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="3">Percentage Tryptophan
<sup>1</sup>
</th><th colspan="3">Percentage Tyrosine
<sup>2</sup>
</th><th colspan="3">Percentage Methionine
<sup>2</sup>
</th></tr><tr><th>Organism</th><th>In all proteins</th><th>In CAZymes</th><th>P-Value</th><th>In all proteins</th><th>In CAZymes</th><th>P-Value</th><th>In all proteins</th><th>In CAZymes</th><th>P-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>Acidothermus cellulolyticus</italic> 11B</td><td align="center">1.4</td><td align="center">9.7</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.1</td><td align="center">9.2</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.6</td><td align="center">5.0</td><td align="center">0.99</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold><italic>Actinoplanes missouriensis</italic></bold>
<bold>431</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>1.6</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>10.0</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>2.0</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>9.9</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>1.8</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>5.5</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>1.00</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold><italic>Butyrivibrio proteoclasticus</italic></bold>
<bold>B316</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>0.9</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>16.9</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.6</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>11.9</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>3.0</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>8.6</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>1.00</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Caldicellulosiruptor bescii</italic> DSM6725</td><td align="center">0.9</td><td align="center">15.5</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">4.3</td><td align="center">7.9</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.2</td><td align="center">5.8</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold><italic>Caldicellulosiruptor kristjanssonii</italic></bold>
<bold>177R1B</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>0.8</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>12.8</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.2</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>7.6</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>2.2</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>5.2</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>1.00</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Caldicellulosiruptor saccharolyticus</italic> DSM8903</td><td align="center">0.9</td><td align="center">15.4</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">4.3</td><td align="center">8.4</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.2</td><td align="center">5.9</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Cellulomonas fimi</italic> ATCC484</td><td align="center">1.6</td><td align="center">13.0</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.8</td><td align="center">12.3</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.4</td><td align="center">6.8</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Cellulomonas flavigena</italic> DSM20109</td><td align="center">1.6</td><td align="center">11.0</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.8</td><td align="center">11.2</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.4</td><td align="center">6.6</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Cellulomonas gilvus</italic> ATCC13127</td><td align="center">1.6</td><td align="center">12.0</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.8</td><td align="center">11.4</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.5</td><td align="center">6.0</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Cellvibrio japonicus</italic> Ueda107</td><td align="center">1.5</td><td align="center">15.8</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">3.2</td><td align="center">13.0</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.2</td><td align="center">8.1</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Clostridium acetobutylicum</italic> ATCC824</td><td align="center">0.7</td><td align="center">15.6</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">4.3</td><td align="center">9.1</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.6</td><td align="center">6.3</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Clostridium cellulolyticum</italic> H10</td><td align="center">0.9</td><td align="center">163</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">4.1</td><td align="center">9.4</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.6</td><td align="center">6.6</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Clostridium cellulovorans</italic> 743B</td><td align="center">0.8</td><td align="center">16.5</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">4.3</td><td align="center">9.7</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.4</td><td align="center">7.2</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Clostridium phytofermentans</italic> ISDg</td><td align="center">0.9</td><td align="center">16.3</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">4.4</td><td align="center">9.7</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.8</td><td align="center">6.5</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Clostridium thermocellum</italic> ATCC 27405</td><td align="center">0.9</td><td align="center">17.1</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">4.2</td><td align="center">10.3</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.5</td><td align="center">6.7</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Cytophaga hutchinsonii</italic> ATCC33406</td><td align="center">1.1</td><td align="center">10.6</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">4.4</td><td align="center">7.3</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.2</td><td align="center">5.6</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Fibrobacter succinogenes</italic> S85</td><td align="center">1.3</td><td align="center">15.3</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">3.7</td><td align="center">11.7</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.6</td><td align="center">9.1</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold><italic>Flavobacterium johnsoniae</italic></bold>
<bold>UW101</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>1.1</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>12.8</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.2</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>8.1</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>2.1</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>6.8</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>0.97</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Micromonospora aurantiaca</italic> ATCC27029</td><td align="center">1.6</td><td align="center">8.6</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.0</td><td align="center">8.8</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.6</td><td align="center">5.1</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold><italic>Prevotella ruminicola</italic></bold>
<bold>23</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>1.4</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>17.9</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.3</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>12.5</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>3.0</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>9.7</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>1.00</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 7</td><td align="center">0.9</td><td align="center">13.8</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">4.3</td><td align="center">8.0</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.9</td><td align="center">5.6</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 8</td><td align="center">0.9</td><td align="center">12.5</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">4.2</td><td align="center">7.4</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.9</td><td align="center">5.1</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold><italic>Ruminococcus bromii</italic></bold>
<bold>L2-63</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>0.7</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>9.0</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.1</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>5.7</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>2.7</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.0</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>0.69</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Ruminococcus flavefaciens</italic> FD1</td><td align="center">0.9</td><td align="center">15.9</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">4.4</td><td align="center">9.3</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.8</td><td align="center">7.0</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold><italic>Ruminococcus torques</italic></bold>
<bold>L2-14</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>0.98</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>7.8</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>4.0</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>5.4</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>&#x0003c; 0.01</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>3.2</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>3.9</bold>
</td><td align="center">
<bold>1.00</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Streptomyces flavogriseus</italic> ATCC33331</td><td align="center">1.5</td><td align="center">8.2</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.1</td><td align="center">8.2</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.8</td><td align="center">4.4</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Streptomyces sp.</italic> ACTE</td><td align="center">1.5</td><td align="center">8.8</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.0</td><td align="center">8.5</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.7</td><td align="center">4.5</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Teredinibacter turnerae</italic> T7901</td><td align="center">1.4</td><td align="center">12.2</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">3.1)</td><td align="center">8.7</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.2</td><td align="center">5.7</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Thermobifida fusca</italic> YX</td><td align="center">1.5</td><td align="center">7.6</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.2</td><td align="center">6.7</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.7</td><td align="center">4.1</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Thermomonospora curvata</italic> DSM43183</td><td align="center">1.5</td><td align="center">4.1</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.1</td><td align="center">4.0</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">1.9</td><td align="center">2.9</td><td align="center">0.73</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Trichoderma reesei</italic> QM6a</td><td align="center">1.5</td><td align="center">6.1</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.7</td><td align="center">5.6</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.2</td><td align="center">3.8</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Xanthomonas campestris</italic> ATCC33913</td><td align="center">1.6</td><td align="center">8.6</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.4</td><td align="center">8.0</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.01</td><td align="center">2.1</td><td align="center">5.2</td><td align="center">1.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>1</sup>Non-cellulolytic strains are bolded.</p><p>
<sup>2</sup>Percentage of selected amino acid in all proteins with percentage of selected amino acid in predicted CAZymes in parenthases. <italic>P</italic>-value based on Fisher&#x02019;s exact test for the enrichment of the selected amino acid among CAZymes.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Since CAZymes account for only 6.5% of the proteins predicted to be encoded by the genome sequence of <italic>R. albus</italic> 7, a small enrichment (~2-fold) of tryptophan in CAZymes is unlikely to require a 13-fold increase in transcription of the tryptophan biosynthetic operon. This is supported by our finding that tRNA transcription and transcription of other aromatic amino acid biosynthetic pathways, including tyrosine, were unaffected by growth on cellulose (data not shown). An alternative hypothesis is that exogenous tryptophan accumulates in <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 when grown on cellulose. We tested this and found that extracellular tryptophan did not accumulate in <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 batch cultures grown on cellulose (data not shown).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Ruminococci are ubiquitous members of mammalian GIT microbial communities and play an important role in plant fiber degradation in the bovine rumen. As key members of the rumen ecosystem, <italic>Ruminococcus</italic> spp. are known for their ability to degrade a wide range of plant polysaccharides, including cellulose. Here we use both genomic and transcriptomic evidence to show that <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 is distinct from other cellulosome-utilizing ruminococci. Adherence to fiber is required for cellulose hydrolysis by <italic>R. albus</italic> strains and several mechanisms for fiber-digestion have been proposed by others. Importantly, four components have been implicated in <italic>R. albus</italic> fiber adherence including: pilin-like appendages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], a glycocalyx [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], cellulosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], and the unique carbohydrate binding module CBM37 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. These findings led to the model that a combination of these four components may be involved in fiber attachment in <italic>R. albus</italic>
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p>We examined both genomic and transcriptomic evidence for each of the four components implicated in <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 fiber adherence. First, we were able to identify pilin-like genes encoded by a <italic>pil</italic>/<italic>sec</italic> locus in the <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 genome sequence with high similarity and identical organization to the loci identified in <italic>R. albus</italic> 20 and <italic>R. albus</italic> 8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. However, our transcriptional analysis did not detect changes in this locus in response to growth on cellulose (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S3). A molecule required for optimal growth on cellulose, 3-phenylpropanoic acid (PPA), was shown by others to increase transcription of the <italic>pilA1</italic> (<italic>cbpC</italic>) gene in <italic>R. albus</italic> 8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. We did not observe an increase in expression for this ORF in <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 but PPA was present under all growth conditions tested in our experiments.</p><p>Second, <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 forms a glycocalyx when grown on cellulose comprised of proteins, uronic acids and sugars including glucose, xylose, some mannose and other sugars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. We identified genes in <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 with putative roles in the anabolic sugar pathways for xylose, mannose, and fructose. However, key enzymes in the synthesis of UDP-xylose, such as a UDP-galactose decarboxylase or a glucose-1-phosphate uridyltransferase were not present in the <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 genome (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4). This is surprising because as much as 20% of the glycocalyx in <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 is composed of xylose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] and it may indicate that synthesis of UDP-xylose is achieved by a different biosynthetic route, or that UDP is not involved in xylose synthesis. Although glycocalyx biosynthetic genes have not been experimentally identified in <italic>R. albus</italic> 7, none of the anabolic sugar pathway genes with a predicted role in glycocalyx formation had significantly higher transcription during growth on cellulose and a few of these genes had lower transcription during growth on cellulose (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4). These findings suggest that, at the transcriptional level, glycocalyx synthesis is not induced during growth on cellulose.</p><p>Third, microscopic evidence for &#x0201c;cellulosome-like protuberances&#x0201d; in some strains of <italic>R. albus</italic>
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] along with molecular evidence for cellulosomal components in <italic>R. albus</italic> F-40 and <italic>R. albus</italic> SY3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] led to the proposal that at least some <italic>R. albus</italic> strains produce cellulosomes. However, several endoglucanases and xylanases in <italic>R. albus</italic> F-40 and <italic>R. albus</italic> SY3 lack dockerin domains and fibrolytic activity in <italic>R. albus</italic> SY3 did not associate with high molecular-weight protein complexes. These results suggested that non-cellulosomal glycanases may also be present in these <italic>R. albus</italic> strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In our analysis, <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 contained few homologs of known cellulosome components, consistent with previous reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Scaffoldins, like those found in <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> FD-1 or <italic>C. thermocellum</italic> ATCC 27405, were entirely absent and only one putative cohesin was identified. This cohesin (Rumal_2328) had an average of 2.72-fold higher transcription when grown on cellulose compared to cellobiose. Moreover, <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 contained fewer dockerins than bacteria with confirmed cellulosomes and most of these belong to the Interpro families IPR018242 or IPR016134, which were also abundant in other non-cellulolytic ruminococci like <italic>R. bromii</italic> L2-63 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). This finding could imply a physiological role for these dockerins that is distinct from their role in cellulosomes. In support of this hypothesis, a global analysis of dockerins and cohesins identified their widespread presence among non-cellulolytic organisms in all three domains of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. These non-cellulosomal dockerins and cohesins are also suspected in cellulolytic organisms that form multi-enzyme cellulolytic complexes. For instance, dockerin domains were identified in the <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> FD-1 genome in ORFs that lacked CAZymes but contained leucine-rich repeat, transglutaminase, and serine protease inhibitor modules instead [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p>Fourth, in the absence of cellulosomes, <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 and <italic>R. albus</italic> 8 may instead rely on alternate carbohydrate-binding modules, such as CBM37s, to facilitate coordination of secreted carbohydrases. This conclusion is supported by our finding that all of the CAZymes with 4-fold or higher transcription on cellulose contained CBM37 domains, with the exception of Rumal_0487. We identified 34 proteins containing one or more CBM37 domains that lacked adjacent catalytic domains. We analyzed these proteins and found that nearly half of them also contained leucine-rich repeat domains. Leucine-rich repeats have been implicated in protein-protein interaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], and it is possible that CBM37 functions to coordinate an extracellular complex of carbohydrases. Our results also indicated that, in general, genes that had higher transcription during growth on cellulose were distinct from genes encoding pilin structures and glycocalyx components that have been shown by others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] to be affected by PPA. Future work will be needed to define these regulons.</p><p>The cellulolytic capacity of <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 has historically been correlated to the production of a number of fermentation products like acetate and ethanol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Our analysis expands on these findings to further reveal that <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 can utilize more polysaccharides than other ruminal cellulolytic bacteria like <italic>F. succinogenes</italic> S85 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], suggesting that it may be more of a carbohydrate generalist in the rumen. Moreover, we found that <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 hydrolyzed several components of the plant cell wall and produced yields of ethanol and acetate comparable to other ethanologenic cellulolytic organisms. Although we observed different ratios of ethanol:acetate in batch <italic>versus</italic> continuous culture, the ethanol:acetate ratio has been shown to vary with dilution rate in continuous cultures of <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. We found more reducing sugars were produced from homoxylan purified from tobacco stalk than from the more complex larchwood xylan. The difference in reducing sugars likely indicates less fermentation of the larchwood xylan because lower amounts of fermentation products were produced from this substrate. In contrast, we found higher cell yields when <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 was grown on cellulose, relative to cellobiose, and we believe that this observation likely reflects the higher net ATP yield from phosphorolytic cleavage of cellodextrins compared to that on cellobiose, as has been previously proposed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p><p>In the rumen, <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 encounters plant biomass that includes complexes of cellulose, hemicelluloses, and other polysaccharides. When grown on crystalline cellulose as the sole carbon source, we found that <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 had a broad transcriptional response that included increased transcription of hemicellulases and other carbohydrases for substrates that were not present in the growth medium. Importantly, the transcriptional differences that we observed were not confounded by growth rate, a factor that is known to affect differential genes expression in other cellulolytic bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], as the growth of <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 was controlled using the same dilution rate with each substrate. This may indicate that cellulose initiates a generalized transcriptional response to plant fibers in <italic>R. albus</italic> 7, or that cellobiose represses such a response, although this hypothesis remains to be tested.</p><p>We were surprised to find that the tryptophan biosynthetic operon was highly transcribed when <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 was grown on cellulose, relative to cellobiose in chemostat cultures. Although increased transcription of tryptophan biosynthesis is not a typical observation for other cellulolytic organisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], a similar response has been noted for <italic>C. phytofermentans</italic> ISDg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. <italic>C. phytofermentans</italic> ISDg is also an ethanologenic, cellulolytic organism, but is distinguished from <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 by the relative abundance of cohesins, dockerins and cellulases (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). It is reasonable to propose that increased transcription of the tryptophan operon is due to increased demand for tryptophan in CAZymes, however, we found that tryptophan enrichment (and tyrosine enrichment) in carbohydrate-active enzymes is widespread, even among non-fibrolytic organisms. We did not detect an increase of the tyrosine biosynthetic pathway or any other (non-tryptophan) amino acid biosynthetic pathway in response to growth on cellulose. Based on these findings it is unlikely that the transcriptional increase of the tryptophan biosynthetic pathway could be explained by increased production of CAZymes. Taken together, these results could suggest a role for tryptophan in a peripheral metabolic activity concomitant with, but distinct from, growth on cellulose. For instance, tryptophan may confer ethanol stress tolerance as has been reported for yeast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Alternatively, tryptophan or their derivatives could be used as signaling molecules, as tryptophan-derived tryptophols are reported to serve as quorum-sensing molecules under nitrogen-poor conditions in yeast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. A similar mechanism might be employed by <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 to coordinate fiber adherence, but future work will be needed to determine the exact role of tryptophan in cellulose degradation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study provides the first comprehensive transcriptomic analysis for any ruminococcal species, in addition to characterizing the fermentative capabilities of <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 on a wide range of fibrous substrates. Analysis of the <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 transcriptome suggests that it initiates a broad transcriptional response to growth on cellulose, including an increase in the tryptophan biosynthetic operon and a range of CBM37-containing coding regions. Our data suggest that <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 relies heavily on CBM37-containing proteins to coordinate a fibrolytic response instead of using cellulosomes. We also found little evidence to support a role for pil-like proteins or glycocalyx components in the transcriptional response of <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 grown on cellulose. Taken together, our findings reveal unique aspects of fiber degradation by <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 and contribute to a revised model for the cellulolytic strategy employed by this important ruminococcal species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Growth conditions</title><p>The culture medium contained the following (per liter) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]: 1.50&#x000a0;g KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 1.13&#x000a0;g NaCl, 0.91&#x000a0;g NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, 5.0&#x000a0;g Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, 0.11&#x000a0;g MgCl<sub>2</sub><sup>.</sup>6H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.082&#x000a0;g CaCl<sub>2</sub><sup>.</sup>2H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.026&#x000a0;g FeSO<sub>4</sub><sup>.</sup>7H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.032&#x000a0;g MnCl<sub>2</sub><sup>.</sup>4H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.0024&#x000a0;g CoCl<sub>2</sub><sup>.</sup>6H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.0022&#x000a0;g ZnCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.13&#x000a0;g yeast extract, 0.004&#x000a0;g 3-phenylpropionic acid, 0.002&#x000a0;g resazurin, 12.5&#x000a0;mL vitamin mix (mg per L: 20 thiamine HCl, 20 Ca-D-pantothenate, 20 nicotinamide, 20 riboflavin, 20 pyridoxine HCl, 1.0 p-aminobenzoic acid, 0.5 biotin, 0.2 vitamin B12, 0.125 folic acid, 0.124 tetrahydrofolic acid ), 8.4&#x000a0;mL volatile fatty acid mix (per L: 10&#x000a0;mL of each isobutyric, 2-methylbutyric, isovaleric, and <italic>n</italic>-valeric acids pH to 7), 0.63&#x000a0;g cysteine HCl, and an energy source (5.36&#x000a0;g cellobiose or 5.0&#x000a0;g Sigmacell 50 microcrystalline cellulose; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO). The fully reduced medium was inoculated with 10&#x000a0;mL of a <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 (ATCC 21270) culture grown for 24&#x000a0;h on the same medium. Cultures were grown at a dilution rate of 0.033&#x000a0;h<sup>-1</sup> under continuous gassing with CO<sub>2</sub> at 39&#x000b0;C in a 760&#x000a0;mL bioreactor employing a segmented slurry delivery system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. After reaching steady state (&#x0003e;3 volumetric dilutions) samples were withdrawn once daily for 3 or 4&#x000a0;days for RNA extraction and chemical analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Chemical analysis</title><p>Samples (1500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L) were centrifuged (12,000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>, 5&#x000b0;C, 10&#x000a0;min) and culture supernatants were assayed for soluble sugars using the phenol-sulfuric acid method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] with glucose as a standard. Fermentation products were determined by HPLC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Cell pellets were washed with saline (9&#x000a0;g NaCl L<sup>-1</sup>), lyophilized, resuspended in 0.2&#x02009;<italic>N</italic> NaOH and boiled for 30&#x000a0;min. The resulting cell lysates were clarified by centrifugation and protein content was determined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. For chemostat cultures grown with cellulose, an additional culture sample (~20&#x000a0;mL, weighed to 0.001&#x000a0;g) was collected each day and residual cellulose was determined gravimetrically as acid-detergent fiber [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] and the detergent-treated residue was collected on GF/D glass fiber filters (Pall Gelman, Port Washington, NY).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>RNA isolation</title><p>RNA was extracted from 9&#x000a0;mL of culture using a phenol-chloroform extraction followed by ethanol precipitation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Ribosomes were removed from the RNA samples using a RiboZero Gram-positive rRNA removal kit (Epicentre, Madison, WI) according to manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. All samples were then barcoded, library prepared, and sequenced using a single channel of a flow cell on an Illumina HiSeq 2000 Sequencer at the University of Wisconsin-Madison Biotechnology Center.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Polysaccharide hydrolysis and growth measurements</title><p>Experiments were conducted under a CO<sub>2</sub> gas phase in triplicate 60&#x000a0;mL glass serum vials that contained 10&#x000a0;mL of modified Dehority medium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] supplemented with the indicated polysaccharide in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Cultures were incubated without shaking at 39&#x000b0;C for 72&#x000a0;h. Hydrolysis of polysaccharides was measured as the release of reducing sugars by the dinitrosalicylic acid method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], using glucose as a standard. Growth on polysaccharides was not measured directly, but was instead assumed from measurement of product (viz., ethanol and acetate) formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], using HPLC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Ortholog analysis and CAZyme annotation</title><p>Predicted protein sequences from one complete and seven draft ruminococcal genome sequences (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) were obtained from the National Center for Biotechnological Information (NCBI) and combined into one file. These include <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 (Accession: PRJNA51721, complete), <italic>R. albus</italic> 8 (PRJNA47357, draft), <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> FD-1 (PRJNA55965, draft), <italic>R. bromii</italic> L2-63 (PRJNA197158, draft), <italic>R. lactaris</italic> ATCC 29176 (PRJNA54903, draft), <italic>R. torques</italic> ATCC 27756 (PRJNA54511, draft), <italic>R. gnavus</italic> ATCC 24149 (PRJNA54537, draft), and <italic>R. obeum</italic> ATCC 29174 (PRJNA54509, draft). Protein pairs and their similarity scores were identified using the OrthoMCL Algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] in a series of steps outlined as described in the OrthoMCL software version 2.0 guide. The protein pairs were clustered using the Markov Cluster Algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. From each cluster, we chose one representative sequence per organism, based on the sequence that produced the highest aggregate blast bit score when blasted against every other sequence. The bit scores were used to eliminate paralogs. Using these representative sequences, we determined the number of sequences that were unique and those that were shared between all organisms. The representative sequences from each cluster were annotated for Carbohydrate-active Enzymes (CAZy) using the CAZy Analysis Toolkit (CAT) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mothra.ornl.gov/cgi-bin/cat.cgi">http://mothra.ornl.gov/cgi-bin/cat.cgi</ext-link>; Pfam rule based annotations) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Cellulosome component analysis</title><p>CAZyme annotations for the predicted proteomes from ten Clostridiales genome sequences were obtained from the CAZy database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cazy.org/">http://www.cazy.org/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. The organisms analyzed include: <italic>C. thermocellum</italic> ATCC 27405<italic>, C. cellulovorans</italic> 743B<italic>, C. cellulolyticum</italic> ATCC 35319<italic>, R. flavefaciens</italic> FD-1, <italic>C. phytofermentans</italic> ISDg, <italic>R. albus</italic> 7, <italic>R. albus</italic> 8, <italic>C. perfringens</italic> ATCC13124<italic>, R. torques</italic> L2-14<italic>,</italic> and <italic>R. bromii</italic> L2-63. CAZyme annotations pertaining to known cellulases (GH5, GH8, GH9, GH12, GH44, GH48, GH74, and GH124) were selected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Annotations corresponding to known dockerin (IPR01824, IPR016134, IPR002195) and cohesin (IPR002102 and IPR018452) domains were obtained from Interpro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>] through the DOE JGI IMG database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. A cellulosome-component matrix was constructed based on total counts for each annotation for all genomes, with each row corresponding to each of the ten organisms and each column a given cellulosomal annotation. A similarity matrix was constructed by calculating the correlation between all organismal pairs using Spearman's rank correlation (with tie-correction). A dendrogram was generated from the similarity matrix using the neighbor-joining program that is part of the PHYLIP package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://evolution.genetics.washington.edu/phylip.html">http://evolution.genetics.washington.edu/phylip.html</ext-link>). A second identical analysis was performed where total counts for each annotation were normalized against the number of predicted proteins in each respective genome, producing an identical dendrogram.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>RNAseq analysis</title><p>A single FASTA file containing the <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 chromosome and its four plasmids was obtained from the NCBI (Accession: PRJNA51721). A FASTA files containing reads obtained from our RNA-seq experiments were aligned to the reference genome using the Burrows-Wheeler Aligner (BWA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], an alignment algorithm that allows for gaps (indels), using the default settings. The resulting SAM files were converted into sorted and indexed BAM files using SAMtools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3 contains the total number of reads for each sample and reads aligned to the <italic>R. albus</italic> 7 genome by BWA.</p><p>We counted the number of reads per gene using tools from the open-access RsamTools package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>], an add-on library to the freely-available statistical software and programming language R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Analysis of differential expression was done using EBSeq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>] and DESeq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Median normalization technique of Deseq was used to account for differences in sequencing depth. Results generated using EBSeq are reported here as a &#x02018;posterior probability of differential expression&#x02019; (PP of DE) for each of the 3,872 genes on the central chromosome and four plasmids. Genes were declared differentially expressed at a false discovery rate controlled at 100x (1-&#x003b1;) % by taking all genes with PP of DE greater than 1 - &#x003b1;.</p><sec id="Sec19"><title>RT-qPCR validation of RNAseq results</title><p>Total RNA from the chemostat samples subjected to RNA-seq (3 cellulose and 2 cellobiose) were reverse transcribed using iScript RT enzyme, according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol (Biorad, USA). The resulting cDNA was used to quantify the Rumal_1716 and 16S rRNA genes by amplification using the iQ Sybr Green Supermix according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol (Biorad, USA) on a BioRad CSX-Connect qPCR machine. Amplification of Rumal_1716 and 16S rRNA was performed using the following primer pairs: Rumal_1716<italic>:</italic> ATGCCGTTAAGGAAGCG and CACACCTATCGCCTGATA; and 16S rRNA: CCCTAAAAGCAGTCTTAGTTCG and CCTCCTTGCGGTTAGAACA. Relative expression (fold change) was calculated for Rumal_1716, normalized to the 16S rRNA gene, between cellulose and cellobiose samples. No amplification was observed in our negative controls, which consisted of samples not treated with reverse transcriptase and samples with nucleic acids omitted.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Quantitation of tryptophan</title><p><italic>In silico measurement of tryptophan enrichment of CAZymes</italic>. Amino acid sequences for each gene in a given genome were downloaded in FASTA format from the NCBI database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>). The Reference Accessions for each predicted CAZyme in a given genome were obtained from the CAZY database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cazy.org">http://www.cazy.org</ext-link>). and submitted to the NCBI Batch Entrez database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/batchentrez">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/batchentrez</ext-link>) to obtain the related amino acid sequences. Total amino acid counts, as well as counts for tryptophan, tyrosine, and methionine were tabulated within the entire genome and compared to the counts within the subset of CAZymes. Fisher&#x02019;s exact test was used to calculate statistical significance for over- and under-enrichment.</p><p><italic>Quantification of extracellular tryptophan. R. albus</italic> 7 was grown in triplicate in 100&#x000a0;mL of modified Dehority medium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] on cellulose or cellobiose. Resazurin was omitted from the medium because it interfered with the colorimetric assay. After 30&#x000a0;h of growth (mid-exponential phase), cells were removed by centrifugation for 20&#x000a0;minutes at 4000 x <italic>g</italic> and spent media was concentrated 50-fold by lyophilization. Concentrated spent media (235&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L) was analyzed in a 0.5&#x000a0;mL reaction containing 3.67% formic acid and 6&#x000a0;N HCl in a glass vial. Absorbance at 595&#x000a0;nm was measured after incubation at 50&#x000b0;C for 48&#x000a0;hours and compared to a standard curve of pure L-tryptophan prepared in modified Dehority medium. The limit of detection by this assay was 0.1&#x000a0;mM.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Chemicals</title><p>Sigmacell 20 microcrystalline cellulose, cellobiose, larchwood xylan, lichenan, amylose (Type III), inulin (from chicory) and citrus pectin were from Sigma-Aldrich. Laminarin was from United States Biochemical. Curdlan was from Wako Pure Chemical Industries. Homoxylan was purified from tobacco stalks as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>].</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Availability of supporting data</title><p>The data sets supporting the results of this article are included within the article and its additional supplementary file. All reads and the final transcriptome described in the manuscript are available in the GenBank repository under BioProject accession PRJNA238076 at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/238076">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/238076</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec23"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12864_2014_6790_MOESM1_ESM.doc"><caption><p>Additional file 1:
<bold>Supplementary Information 1.</bold> Genes with lower transcription during growth of <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 7 on cellulose compared to cellobiose. <bold>Table S1.</bold> Ortholog clusters with CAZy annotations among cellulolytic ruminococci. <bold>Table S2.</bold> Ethanol yields by model organisms in batch culture. <bold>Table S3.</bold> Total and aligned RNAseq reads. <bold>Table S4.</bold> Genes with 4-fold lower transcription during growth of <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 7 on cellulose compared to cellobiose as the sole carbohydrate source assessed by RNA-Seq. <bold>Figure S1.</bold> Graphical representation of differential expression (DE). <bold>Figure S2.</bold> Expression of genes from each biological replicate. <bold>Figure S3.</bold> Putative pil/sec locus in <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 7 is not transcriptionally changed by growth on cellulose compared to cellobiose. <bold>Figure S4.</bold> Putative biosynthetic genes for glycoside components of the glycocalyx were not significantly upregulated by growth on cellulose in <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 7. (DOC 493 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p>The authors declare that they no competing interests.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; contributions</bold></p><p>MRC and GS designed and coordinated the study. DS and PJW performed chemostat fermentations, chemical analysis, polysaccharide hydrolysis and growth measurements. MRC carried out samplings, RNA extraction and purification and quantified extracellular tryptophan. MRC, JD, CK, and GS analyzed the genomic and transcriptomic data, performed the annotations and statistics, and interpreted the results. MRC, AC, SB, and GS performed the comparative genomic analyses including ortholog analysis, CAZyme annotation, and amino acid enrichment. MRC and GS wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by a DOE BER Early Career Research Program Award DE&#x02013;SC0008104 and funding from the Wisconsin Bioenergy Initiative to GS, an NIH award GM102756 to CK, and a USDA-Agricultural Research Service CRIS project 3655-41000-007-00D to PJW. MRC was supported by a DOE GLBRC/BACTER Post-doctoral Research Fellowship. We thank J. M. Hackney for supplying glucomannan from <italic>Ochris</italic> tubers, P. Brumm for Soy polysaccharides, and members of the Suen lab for critical reading of the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic diversity of bacterial communities in bovine rumen as affected by diets and microenvironments</article-title><source>Folia Microbiol (Praha)</source><year>2011</year><volume>56</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12223-011-0066-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21901294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rochet</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigottier-Gois</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design and validation of 16S rRNA probes to enumerate members of the <italic>Clostridium leptum</italic> subgroup in human faecal microbiota</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>933</fpage><lpage>946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2005.00763.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15946290?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15946290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chassard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Del'homme</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dapoigny</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernalier-Donadille</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of metabolic diversity within the intestinal microbiota from healthy humans using combined molecular and cultural approaches</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source><year>2008</year><volume>66</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6941.2008.00595.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18811647?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18811647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Raes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arumugam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgdorf</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Manichanh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Levenez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mende</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tap</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertalan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Batto</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Paslier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Linneberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A human gut microbial gene catalogue established by metagenomic sequencing</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>464</volume><issue>7285</issue><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08821</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20203603?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20203603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ince</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Holtrop</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ze</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stares</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergerat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnstone</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobley</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dominant and diet-responsive groups of bacteria within the human colonic microbiota</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2010.118</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20686513?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20686513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Arce</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile fatty acids: their production, absorption, utilization, and roles in human health</article-title><source>Clin Gastroenterol</source><year>1986</year><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3536209?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3536209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macfarlane</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Macfarlane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacteria, colonic fermentation, and gastrointestinal health</article-title><source>J AOAC Int</source><year>2012</year><volume>95</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5740/jaoacint.SGE_Macfarlane</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22468341?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22468341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blaut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecology and physiology of the intestinal tract</article-title><source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source><year>2011</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22120885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carberry</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of phenotypic residual feed intake and dietary forage content on the rumen microbial community of beef cattle</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>78</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>4949</fpage><lpage>4958</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.07759-11</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22562991?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22562991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmonari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mertens</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruywagen</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>pH dynamics and bacterial community composition in the rumen of lactating dairy cows</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>93</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2009-2207</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20059926?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20059926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dominance of <italic>Prevotella</italic> and low abundance of classical ruminal bacterial species in the bovine rumen revealed by relative quantification real-time PCR</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2007</year><volume>75</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-006-0802-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17235560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17235560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stiverson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Populations of select cultured and uncultured bacteria in the rumen of sheep and the effect of diets and ruminal fractions</article-title><source>Int J Microbiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>2011</volume><fpage>750613</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2011/750613</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21822435?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21822435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hungate</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><source>The rumen and its microbes</source><year>1966</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press, Inc.</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matulova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nouaille</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Capek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pean</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Delort</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Forano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NMR study of cellulose and wheat straw degradation by <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 20</article-title><source>FEBS J</source><year>2008</year><volume>275</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>3503</fpage><lpage>3511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2008.06497.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18513327?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18513327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berg Miller</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonopoulos</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rincon</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Band</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Akraiko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thimmapuram</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Borovok</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Jindou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity and strain specificity of plant cell wall degrading enzymes revealed by the draft genome of <italic>Ruminococcus flavefaciens</italic> FD-1</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e6650</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006650</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19680555?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19680555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rincon</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cepeljnik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barak</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unconventional mode of attachment of the <italic>Ruminococcus flavefaciens</italic> cellulosome to the cell surface</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>7569</fpage><lpage>7578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.187.22.7569-7578.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16267281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16267281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rincon</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polysaccharide utilization by gut bacteria: potential for new insights from genomic analysis</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1817</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18180751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18180751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fontes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellulosomes: highly efficient nanomachines designed to deconstruct plant cell wall complex carbohydrates</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>2010</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-biochem-091208-085603</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20373916?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20373916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hungate</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of 3-phenylpropanoic acid on capsule and cellulases of <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 8</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1984</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16346590?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16346590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devillard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodheart</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Karnati</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Miron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 8 mutants defective in cellulose degradation are deficient in two processive endocellulases, Cel48A and Cel9B, both of which possess a novel modular architecture</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.186.1.136-145.2004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14679233?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14679233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ezer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Matalon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jindou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Borovok</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Atamna</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell surface enzyme attachment is mediated by family 37 carbohydrate-binding modules, unique to <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2008</year><volume>190</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>8220</fpage><lpage>8222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00609-08</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18931104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18931104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Atamna</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel family of carbohydrate-binding modules identified with <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> proteins</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>2004</year><volume>566</volume><issue>1&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2004.04.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15147860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15147860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pegden</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adherence of the gram-positive bacterium <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> to cellulose and identification of a novel form of cellulose-binding protein which belongs to the Pil family of proteins</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1998</year><volume>180</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>5921</fpage><lpage>5927</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9811650?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9811650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adhesion to cellulose by <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic>: a combination of cellulosomes and Pil-proteins?</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2000</year><volume>185</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2000.tb09047.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10754233?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10754233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroukamp</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Joubert</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfaardt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Zyl</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies of the extracellular glycocalyx of the anaerobic cellulolytic bacterium <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> 7</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>7559</fpage><lpage>7566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01632-06</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17028224?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17028224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Irvin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Costerton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrastructure and adhesion properties of <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1975</year><volume>122</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><?supplied-pmid 47323?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">47323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chertkov</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Detter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Detter</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyrpides</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Land</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapidus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ovchinnikova</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitluck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Woyke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyum</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complete genome of the cellulolytic ruminal bacterium ruminococcus albus 7</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><year>2011</year><volume>193</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>5574</fpage><lpage>5575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.05621-11</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21914885?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21914885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Karita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohmiya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence of egV and properties of EgV, a <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> endoglucanase containing a dockerin domain</article-title><source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source><year>2000</year><volume>64</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1271/bbb.64.80</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10705451?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10705451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavlostathis</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fermentation of insoluble cellulose by continuous cultures of <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic></article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1988</year><volume>54</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2655</fpage><lpage>2659</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16347769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16347769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of 17 genes in <italic>Clostridium thermocellum</italic> ATCC 27405 during fermentation of cellulose or cellobiose in continuous culture</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>71</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>4672</fpage><lpage>4678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.8.4672-4678.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16085862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16085862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riederer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Takasuka</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bukhman</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsen</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global gene expression patterns in <italic>Clostridium thermocellum</italic> as determined by microarray analysis of chemostat cultures on cellulose or cellobiose</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>77</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1243</fpage><lpage>1253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02008-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21169455?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21169455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagos</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaou</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Liakopoulos</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsirigos</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combined prediction of Tat and Sec signal peptides with hidden Markov models</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>2811</fpage><lpage>2817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq530</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20847219?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20847219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tolonen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chilaka</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Aach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteome-wide systems analysis of a cellulosic biofuel-producing microbe</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>461</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/msb.2010.116</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21245846?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21245846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rakotoarivonina</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Girardeau</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaillard-Martinie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Forano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosoni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> pilA1-pilA2 locus: expression and putative role of two adjacent pil genes in pilus formation and bacterial adhesion to cellulose</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>151</volume><issue>Pt 4</issue><fpage>1291</fpage><lpage>1299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.27735-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15817796?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Naimark</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgenstern</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specialized cell surface structures in cellulolytic bacteria</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1987</year><volume>169</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3792</fpage><lpage>3800</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3301817?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3301817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Karita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohmiya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the cellulolytic complex (cellulosome) from <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic></article-title><source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source><year>2000</year><volume>64</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1271/bbb.64.254</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10737178?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10737178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobovitch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Ghedalia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subcellular distribution of glycanases and related components in <italic>Ruminococcus albus</italic> SY3 and their role in cell adhesion to cellulose</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>91</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2672.2001.01434.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11576305?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11576305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dassa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Borovok</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruimy-Israeli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosoni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeoman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rumen cellulosomics: divergent fiber-degrading strategies revealed by comparative genome-wide analysis of six ruminococcal strains</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>e99221</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099221</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24992679?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24992679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Borovok</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Noncellulosomal cohesin- and dockerin-like modules in the three domains of life</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2009</year><volume>291</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2008.01420.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19025568?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19025568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kajava</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The leucine-rich repeat as a protein recognition motif</article-title><source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0959-440X(01)00266-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11751054?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aylward</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyum</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Deneke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Drinkwater</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikhailova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chertkov</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brumm</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The complete genome sequence of <italic>Fibrobacter succinogenes</italic> S85 reveals a cellulolytic and metabolic specialist</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e18814</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0018814</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21526192?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21526192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynd</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zyl</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial cellulose utilization: fundamentals and biotechnology</article-title><source>Microbiology and Molecular Biology Reviews</source><year>2002</year><volume>66</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>506</fpage><lpage>577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.66.3.506-577.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12209002?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12209002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirasawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakakura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagahisa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Furusawa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Katakura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shioya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of target genes conferring ethanol stress tolerance to <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> based on DNA microarray data analysis</article-title><source>J Biotechnol</source><year>2007</year><volume>131</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2007.05.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17604866?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17604866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feedback control of morphogenesis in fungi by aromatic alcohols</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1150</fpage><lpage>1161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1411806</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16618799?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16618799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Odt</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A segmented gas&#x02013;liquid delivery system for continuous culture of microorganisms on insoluble substrates and its use for growth of <italic>Ruminococcus flavefaciens</italic> on cellulose</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biot</source><year>1991</year><volume>36</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00164416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DuBois</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebers</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colorimetric method for determination of sugars and related substances</article-title><source>Analytical Chemistry</source><year>1956</year><volume>28</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>350</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ac60111a017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>1976</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(76)90527-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 942051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goering</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Soest</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name></person-group><source>Forage fiber analyses</source><year>1970</year><publisher-loc>Washington, U.S.</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Agricultural Research Service</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Competition among three predominant ruminal cellulolytic bacteria in the absence or presence of non-cellulolytic bacteria</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2001</year><volume>147</volume><issue>Pt 1</issue><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11160797?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11160797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Glennon</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurement of carboxymethylcellulase activity</article-title><source>Analytical Biochemistry</source><year>1960</year><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(60)90004-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maglione</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics of cellulose digestion by <italic>Fibrobacter succinogenes</italic> S85</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>63</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>669</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16535519?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16535519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enright</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dongen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouzounis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An efficient algorithm for large-scale detection of protein families</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1575</fpage><lpage>1584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/30.7.1575</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11917018?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11917018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Syed</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Karpinets</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Parang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leuze</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Uberbacher</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BESC knowledgebase public portal</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22238270?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22238270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantarel</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rancurel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Carbohydrate-Active EnZymes database (CAZy): an expert resource for Glycogenomics</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D233</fpage><lpage>D238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn663</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18838391?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18838391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medie</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Drancourt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome analyses highlight the different biological roles of cellulases</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22266780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Attwood</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Binns</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Daugherty</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Duquenne</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haft</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Laugraud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Letunic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonsdale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Madera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maslen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McAnulla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McDowall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mistry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Natale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Orengo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>InterPro: the integrative protein signature database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D211</fpage><lpage>D215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn785</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18940856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18940856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Markowitz</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mavromatis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyrpides</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving microbial genome annotations in an integrated database context</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e54859</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054859</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23424620?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23424620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>1754</fpage><lpage>1760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp324</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19451168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolstad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dettling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudoit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornik</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hothorn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Iacus</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leisch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maechler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossini</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawitzki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tierney</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioconductor: open software development for computational biology and bioinformatics</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>R80</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2004-5-10-r80</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15461798?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15461798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R DCT</collab></person-group><source>A languange and environment for statistical computing</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc><publisher-name>R Foundation for statistical computing</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Steward</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruotti</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rissman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smits</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kendziorski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><collab>EBSeq</collab></person-group><article-title>An empirical Bayes hierarchical model for inference in RNA-seq experiments</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1035</fpage><lpage>1043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt087</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23428641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23428641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>R106</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20979621?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackney</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fermentation of a bacterial cellulose/xylan composite by mixed ruminal microflora: implications for the role of polysaccharide matrix interactions in plant cell wall biodegradability</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>48</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1727</fpage><lpage>1733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf991372y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10820086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10820086</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>