<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ACS//DTD ACS Journal DTD v1.02 20061031//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName ACSJournal-v102.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.02?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName acs2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ACS Chem Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ACS Chem. Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">cb</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">acbcct</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ACS Chemical Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1554-8929</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1554-8937</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American ChemicalSociety</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4076015</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cb500062n</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterizing the Altered Cellular Proteome Induced
by the Stress-Independent Activation of Heat Shock Factor 1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1"><name><surname>Ryno</surname><given-names>Lisa M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2"><name><surname>Genereux</surname><given-names>Joseph
C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3"><name><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>Tadasuke</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4"><name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>Richard I.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath5"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>Evan T.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath6"><name><surname>Shoulders</surname><given-names>Matthew D.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">&#x02225;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath7"><name><surname>Wiseman</surname><given-names>R. Luke</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>&#x02020;</label>Department
of Molecular &#x00026; Experimental Medicine, Department of Chemical Physiology, <institution>The Scripps Research Institute</institution>, La Jolla, California 92037, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02021;</label>Department
of Molecular Biosciences, Rice Institute for Biomedical Research, <institution>Northwestern University</institution>, Evanston, Illinois 60208, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>&#x000a7;</label>Department
of Chemistry, <institution>The Scripps Research Institute</institution>, La Jolla, California 92037, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>&#x02225;</label>Department
of Chemistry, <institution>Massachusetts Institute of
Technology</institution>, Cambridge, Massachusetts 02139, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Department of Molecular &#x00026; Experimental
Medicine, Department of Chemical Physiology, The Scripps Research
Institute, MEM 220, La Jolla, CA 92037. Phone: <phone>858-784-8820</phone>. Fax: <fax>858-784-8891</fax>. E-mail: <email>wiseman@scripps.edu</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>20</day><month>06</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1273</fpage><lpage>1283</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>01</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 American
Chemical Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>American
Chemical Society</copyright-holder><license><license-p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/page/policy/authorchoice_termsofuse.html">Terms of Use</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p content-type="toc-graphic"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb-2014-00062n_0007" id="ab-tgr1"/></p><p>The heat shock response is an evolutionarily
conserved, stress-responsive
signaling pathway that adapts cellular proteostasis in response to
pathologic insult. In metazoans, the heat shock response primarily
functions through the posttranslational activation of heat shock factor
1 (HSF1), a stress-responsive transcription factor that induces the
expression of cytosolic proteostasis factors including chaperones,
cochaperones, and folding enzymes. HSF1 is a potentially attractive
therapeutic target to ameliorate pathologic imbalances in cellular
proteostasis associated with human disease, although the underlying
impact of stress-independent HSF1 activation on cellular proteome
composition remains to be defined. Here, we employ a highly controllable,
ligand-regulated HSF1 that activates HSF1 to levels compatible with
those that could be achieved using selective small molecule HSF1 activators.
Using a combination of RNAseq and quantitative proteomics, we define
the impact of stress-independent HSF1 activation on the composition
of the cellular proteome. We show that stress-independent HSF1 activation
selectively remodels cytosolic proteostasis pathways without globally
influencing the composition of the cellular proteome. Furthermore,
we show that stress-independent HSF1 activation decreases intracellular
aggregation of a model polyglutamine-containing protein and reduces
the cellular toxicity of environmental toxins like arsenite that disrupt
cytosolic proteostasis. Collectively, our results reveal a proteome-level
view of stress-independent HSF1 activation, providing a framework
to establish therapeutic approaches to correct pathologic imbalances
in cellular proteostasis through the selective targeting of HSF1.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement><funding-source>National Institutes of Health, United States</funding-source></funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name><meta-value>cb500062n</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name><meta-value>cb-2014-00062n</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name><meta-value/></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="sec1">Intracellular protein homeostasis
(or proteostasis) is maintained by stress-responsive signaling pathways
such as the heat shock response (HSR).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup> The HSR is
an evolutionarily conserved, stress-responsive signaling pathway that
adapts the composition of cytosolic proteostasis pathways in response
to environmental, genetic, or aging-related stress.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> The
HSR is induced by the accumulation of misfolded proteins within the
cytosol, resulting in the activation of stress-responsive transcription
factors that induce transcriptional programs including proteostasis
network components such as chaperones, cochaperones, folding enzymes,
and quality control factors. In mammals, the HSR primarily functions
through activation of the winged-helix transcription factor heat shock
factor 1 (HSF1).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> During heat shock, HSF1 activity
is regulated through a complex, posttranslational mechanism involving
nuclear localization, trimerization, and numerous modifications including
phosphorylation and SUMOylation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></sup> Once activated, trimeric HSF1
induces a transcriptional program that remodels the cytosolic proteostasis
network in an effort to resolve proteotoxic stress.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></sup></p><p>HSF1 directly
affects cytosolic proteostasis at the level of gene
regulation, making HSF1 an attractive therapeutic target to intervene
in human diseases etiologically linked to imbalances in cellular proteostasis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> HSF1 overexpression attenuates
the pathologic intracellular aggregation of several misfolding-prone
proteins, including mutant huntingtin (a protein whose aggregation
is pathologically associated with Huntington&#x02019;s disease).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Furthermore, overexpression of HSF1 in mice attenuates symptoms
associated with Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease (AD),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> a neurodegenerative disorder that also involves imbalances
in intracellular proteostasis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> The ability of HSF1 overexpression
to attenuate pathologic imbalances in intracellular proteostasis associated
with these diseases has led to significant effort to identify small-molecule
activators of HSF1.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup> Despite advances
in high throughput screening efforts to discover HSF1 activators,
further efforts are necessary to hone the response and selectivity
of HSF1 activation by small molecules.</p><p>In the absence of selective
and stress-independent small-molecule
HSF1 activators, current approaches have either employed HSF1 overexpression
or cell-based assays using heat shock promoter reporter constructs
to explore the therapeutic potential for HSF1 activation in ameliorating
pathologic imbalances in cytosolic proteostasis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup> HSF1 overexpression often leads to sustained extremely high levels
of HSF1 activity, whereas cell-based assays for the heat shock response
may identify compounds that cause proteotoxic damage and mimic cell
stress. Consequently, critical questions remain regarding the therapeutic
potential for HSF1 activation to treat human disease. Exactly how
would sustained stress-independent HSF1 activation similar to what
can be achieved using small-molecule HSF1 activators remodel cellular
proteostasis pathways? What effects (if any) does stress-independent
HSF1-dependent remodeling of cellular proteostasis pathways have on
the composition and function of the endogenous cellular proteome not
transcriptionally targeted by HSF1? Is there a therapeutic window
for HSF1 activation to correct imbalances in cellular proteostasis
without resulting in negative physiologic consequences of HSF1 hyperactivation
associated with increased tumorigenesis?<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></sup></p><p>Here, we evaluate
the impact of stress-independent HSF1 activation
on cellular proteostasis capacity and global proteome composition.
We recently described a ligand-regulated, constitutively active HSF1
fused to a destabilized mutant of FKBP (FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1) that allows
dose-dependent, ligand-mediated induction of HSF1 target genes in
the absence of stress.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> We now show that
ligand-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation induces the expression
of HSF1 target genes to levels nearly identical to those observed
during heat shock and significantly less than the levels obtained
using more traditional tetracycline (tet)-inducible cHSF1 overexpression.
This shows that stress-independent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation allows
for the increased expression of HSF1 target genes to levels consistent
with those that could be obtained using selective HSF1 activators.
We employ FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 to characterize the remodeling of cellular
proteostasis networks induced by stress-independent HSF1 activation
using a combined RNAseq transcriptional profiling and whole cell quantitative
proteomics approach. Through these efforts, we demonstrate that stress-independent
HSF1 activation does not significantly influence the global proteome
not transcriptionally targeted by HSF1. Furthermore, we find that
the high levels of HSF1 overexpression employed in previous studies
are not required to obtain the beneficial consequences of proteostasis
network remodeling. Instead, lower levels of HSF1 activation selectively
attenuate intracellular aggregation of misfolding-prone proteins and
promote cellular survival in response to stress. Collectively, our
results provide an essential framework to evaluate stress-independent
HSF1 activation as a therapeutic strategy to correct pathologic imbalances
in cellular proteostasis associated with human disease.</p><sec id="sec2"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
Allows Stress-Independent Activation of the
HSF1 Transcriptional Program</title><p>We established a genetically
encoded, small-molecule-regulated fusion between a destabilized mutant
of FK506 binding protein 12 and constitutively active HSF1 (FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1;
Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> When
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 is expressed in mammalian cells, the entire fusion
protein is rapidly degraded by the proteasome, repressing HSF1 transcriptional
activity. This degradation is prevented by the addition of the FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
pharmacologic chaperone Shield-1, which stabilizes the entire protein
against degradation and allows cHSF1 transcriptional activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup></p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization induces
the expression
of HSF1 target genes. (A) Illustration showing the posttranslational,
Shield-1-mediated regulation of FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> (B) Illustration showing doxycycline-mediated induction
of cHSF1 expression in cells stably expressing the tetracycline-repressor.
(C) Immunoblot of the nuclear fraction from HEK293T-REx cells stably
expressing FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 or dox-regulated cHSF1. Cells were treated
for 15 h with vehicle, Shield-1 (1 &#x003bc;M), or dox (2.25 &#x003bc;M),
as indicated. As a control, cells stably expressing FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
were heat shocked at 42 &#x000b0;C for 1 h and allowed to recover for
2 h prior to lysis. (D) qPCR of <italic>HSPA1A</italic> in HEK293T-REx
cells stably expressing FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 or dox-regulated cHSF1. Cells
were treated for 15 h with either Shield-1 (1 &#x003bc;M) or dox (2.25
&#x003bc;M), as indicated. HEK293T-Rex cells were also subjected to
a 1 h heat shock at 42 &#x000b0;C and a 2 h recovery. Error bars show
95% confidence intervals. (E) qPCR of <italic>DNAJB1</italic> in HEK293T-REx
cells stably expressing FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 (blue) or dox-regulated cHSF1
(orange). Shield-1 (1 &#x003bc;M) or dox (2.25 &#x003bc;M) was added for
the indicated time. The expression of <italic>DNAJB1</italic> was
normalized to the maximal expression observed at 24 h. Error bars
show 95% confidence interval. (F) qPCR of <italic>DNAJB1</italic> in
HEK293T-REx cells stably expressing FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 and treated with
increasing doses of Shield-1 for 15 h. Error bars show 95% confidence
intervals. (G) qPCR of <italic>DNAJB1</italic> in HEK293T-REx cells
stably expressing dox-regulated cHSF1 and treated with increasing
doses of dox for 15 h. Error bars show 95% confidence intervals. (H)
Graph showing the growth of HEK293T-Rex cells stably expressing dox-regulated
cHSF1. Dox (2.25 &#x003bc;M) was added, as shown, for the indicated
time. Error bar shows SEM for <italic>n</italic> = 4. ***<italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.01. (I) Graph showing the growth of HEK293T-Rex cells
stably expressing FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1. Shield-1 (1 &#x003bc;M) was added
for the indicated time.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb-2014-00062n_0001" id="gr1" position="float"/></fig><p>Here, we further characterize the Shield-1-dependent regulation
of FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1. We employed HEK293T-Rex cells stably expressing
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> We previously showed
that FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 affords tight, ligand-dependent control over
the expression of HSF1 target genes with no increased expression of
these genes in the absence of activating ligand.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> An analogous HEK293T-Rex cell line expressing tet-inducible,
unconjugated cHSF1 was prepared for comparison. In these cells, cHSF1
overexpression is induced by the addition of doxycycline (dox) (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). These cells show tight, dox-dependent regulation
of HSF1 target gene expression (Figure S1A, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting
Information</xref>). We confirmed ligand-dependent regulation of FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
and tet-inducible cHSF1 by immunoblotting, showing nuclear HSF1 accumulation
upon addition of the appropriate activating ligand (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C). Similarly, protein levels of the HSF1 target
genes increase following Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization
or dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression (Figure S1B,C, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). In the absence of activating ligand,
the levels of these proteins were identical to controls, further reflecting
the tight ligand-dependent control over HSF1 activity in these cells.</p><p>qPCR shows ligand-dependent increases in the expression of the
HSF1 target gene <italic>HSPA1A</italic>, which encodes heat shock-inducible
HSP70 in each of these cell lines (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>D). The extent of <italic>HSPA1A</italic> mRNA induction by Shield-1-dependent
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization is nearly identical to that observed
in HEK293T-Rex cells subjected to heat shock (42 &#x000b0;C; 1 h) and
significantly less than that observed for dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression
(Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>D). Similar results were observed
for the alternative HSF1 target gene <italic>DNAJB1</italic>, which
encodes a heat shock-inducible HSP40 (DNAJB1) (Figure S1D, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Since the increased
expression of <italic>HSPA1A</italic> and <italic>DNAJB1</italic> observed
during heat shock reflects levels of gene expression obtainable through
endogenous HSF1, these results demonstrate that Shield-1-dependent
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 allows for the activation of HSF1 to levels consistent
with those obtainable using potential selective small-molecule HSF1
activators.</p><p>We next compared the rate of ligand-dependent HSF1
transcriptional
activation in cells expressing FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 or tet-inducible cHSF1.
Posttranslational Shield-1-dependent activation of FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
results in a rapid increase in <italic>DNAJB1</italic> expression,
with significant induction observed in &#x0003c;3 h (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>E).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> In contrast, dox-dependent
induction of cHSF1 does not significantly increase <italic>DNAJB1</italic> mRNA levels following 3 h, although dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression
ultimately results in higher <italic>DNAJB1</italic> expression (Figure
S1E, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Similar results
were observed for the alternative HSF1 target gene <italic>HSP90AA1</italic> (Figure S1F, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>).</p><p>We further evaluated the differing capacities for FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
and tet-inducible cHSF1 activation to regulate the HSF1 transcriptional
program in cells treated with increasing concentrations of the appropriate
activating ligand (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>F,G). As reported
previously,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> Shield-1-dependent stabilization
of FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 affords dose-dependent induction of HSF1 target
genes such as <italic>DNAJB1</italic>. Dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression
is not readily dosable, showing increased <italic>DNAJB1</italic> expression
only once a threshold dox concentration is reached.</p><p>The poor
dosability of dox-dependent HSF1 activation results in
levels of HSF1 activity significantly higher than those observed following
heat shock. This is important because it does not realistically represent
what selective, small-molecule HSF1 activators could achieve, and
very high levels of HSF1 activity could be detrimental to cell viability.
Indeed, we found that dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression reduces cellular
viability (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>H). This decrease in cell
viability is greater than that observed upon acute heat shock where
HSF1 activity is regulated through endogenous stress-dependent signaling
(Figure S1G, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). In
contrast, Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization results
in only a mild growth defect (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>I).</p><p>Collectively, these results show that Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
stabilization enables the rapid, dosable stress-independent activation
of HSF1 transcriptional targets to levels similar to those observed
by heat shock. Importantly, these results demonstrate our ability
to separate the heat-dependent posttranslational regulation of HSF1
from activation of this transcription factor in the absence of high
levels of HSF1 transcriptional activity observed using the nondosable,
dox-dependent induction of cHSF1. While HSF1 activity during heat
shock involves additional levels of transcriptional regulation mediated
through stress-dependent processes (e.g., posttranslational modification,
chromatin remodeling, and heterooligomerization with other HSF transcription factors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup>), our establishment
of FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
provides a mechanism to explore alterations in cellular proteostasis
that could be induced by stress-independent activation of HSF1 to
levels achievable using small-molecule HSF1 activators.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
Stabilization Activates the HSF1 Transcriptional
Program</title><p>We characterized the impact of stress-independent
HSF1 transcriptional activation by Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
stabilization on gene expression using RNAseq. An analogous experiment
was performed to characterize the impact of dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression
as a control. We observed a total of 397 genes whose expression was
altered &#x0003e;2-fold (up- or down-regulated) upon Shield-1-dependent
stabilization
of FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 (FDR &#x0003c; 0.01; Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A and Table S1, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Of these 397 genes, 375 were <italic>increased</italic> while
22 were <italic>decreased</italic>. Alternatively, dox-dependent activation
of cHSF1 altered the expression of 1122 genes (fold-change &#x0003e;2-fold;
FDR &#x0003c; 0.01) (Table S1, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Of these 1122 genes, 906 were <italic>increased</italic> while
216 were <italic>decreased</italic>. Genes significantly affected
by FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 overexpression overlap with those induced by dox-dependent
cHSF1 overexpression (96.8% overlap), indicating that the fusion to
FKBP does not significantly impact stress-independent HSF1 transcriptional
activity (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). Genes highly induced
by dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression and Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
include many well-known HSF1 target genes induced during heat shock
including proteostasis factors such as <italic>HSPA1A</italic>, <italic>HSPA6</italic>, <italic>DNAJB1</italic>, and <italic>BAG3</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>)(Figure S2A, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>).
However, a direct comparison of genes induced by FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 versus
those induced by heat shock<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup> show that stress-independent
HSF1 activation and heat shock have distinct but overlapping transcriptional
profiles (Figure S2A, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). These differences likely reflect the additional layers of transcriptional
regulation involved in the stress-induced heat shock response including
chromatin remodeling, HSF1 posttranslational modification, and the
involvement of additional transcription factors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></sup> This directly demonstrates the importance
of using stress-independent HSF1 activation to evaluate the therapeutic
potential of HSF1 to influence cellular proteostasis in the context
of human disease, as selective small-molecule HSF1 activators will
not activate these other stress-dependent transcriptional regulation
pathways. Importantly, we did not observe significant increases in
transcriptional markers of other stress-responsive signaling pathways
such as the unfolded protein response (e.g., <italic>BiP</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref>) or the mitochondrial
unfolded protein response (e.g., <italic>DNAJA3</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref></sup> Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref>), showing that
stress-independent HSF1 activation does not induce global cellular
stress.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>RNAseq transcriptional profiling of stress-independent HSF1 activation.
(A) Diagram showing the overlap of genes with &#x0003e;2-fold change (FDR
&#x0003c; 0.01) in HEK293T-REx cells following dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression
or Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization. (B) Plot showing
the correlation between gene expression in HEK293T-REx cells following
Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation or dox-dependent cHSF1
overexpression. Only genes whose expression is significantly affected
(FDR &#x0003c; 0.01) by dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression are shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb-2014-00062n_0002" id="gr2" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>mRNA and Protein
Level Alterations
for Select Cellular Proteostasis Factors Induced by Stress-Independent
HSF1 Activation<xref rid="tbl1-fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="center"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="2" align="center">fold change
in RNAseq<hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center">fold change in proteomics<hr/></th></tr><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">gene symbol</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">cHSF1</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">cHSF1</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" style="border:none;" align="center">Cytosolic Components
of ATP-Dependent Chaperoning
Pathways</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPA1A</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">6.6</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5.1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.7</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPA1B</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">7.5</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.0</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.5</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPA1L</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">15.4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">8.4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.7</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPA6</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">40.0</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">73.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.6</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">DNAJA1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3.8</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3.2</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.8</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.4</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">DNAJB1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">13.0</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">15.5</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">8.5</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5.4</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPH1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">17.9</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">12.2</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3.8</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.3</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPA4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4.4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.8</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.4</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">BAG3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">19.1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">19.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">7.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3.8</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">CCT4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.2</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSP90AA1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">7.2</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5.1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.7</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.5</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">CHORDC1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.6</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.3</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">AHSA1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3.1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.7</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" style="border:none;" align="center">Small Heat Shock
Proteins</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPB1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">17.6</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">21.4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">19.5</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">7.8</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPB8</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">33.5</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">34.4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">ND</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">ND</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPB9</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4.0</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">5.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.4</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.3</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">CRYAB</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">35.5</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">53.1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">ND</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">ND</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" style="border:none;" align="center">ER Folding Chaperones</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPA5 (BiP)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">GRP94</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" style="border:none;" align="center">Mitochondrial Folding
Chaperones</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPD1 (HSP60)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4.6</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4.6</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.7</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.5</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPE1
(HSP10)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4.0</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3.0</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.3</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">DNAJA3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">NS</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="center">HSPA9 (mtHSP70)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.5</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.10</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.10</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1-fn1"><label>a</label><p>NS indicates not significant
(FDR &#x0003c; 0.01 in RNAseq; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.1 in proteomics).
ND indicates protein not quantified in our TMT-MuDPIT proteomic analysis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The large number of genes altered
&#x0003e;2-fold by dox-dependent cHSF1
overexpression relative to FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation likely results
from the high levels of cHSF1 activation elicited by the tet-inducible
system. Consistent with this notion, a plot of the ligand-dependent
expression of genes significantly (FDR &#x0003c; 0.01) altered by dox-dependent
cHSF1 overexpression versus the expression of the same genes following
Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B) revealed a linear correlation (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.78). The slope of this line was 0.64 &#x000b1; 0.01,
reflecting the higher levels of HSF1 activation induced by dox-dependent
cHSF1 overexpression. Similar results were observed by qPCR where
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1-dependent induction of HSF1 target genes including <italic>DNAJB1</italic>, <italic>BAG3</italic>, and <italic>GRPEL1</italic> were induced &#x0223c;0.64-fold relative to dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression
(see Figures S1D and S2B, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). These results further show that the FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 fusion does
not influence HSF1 transcriptional selectivity but results in a more
modest induction of HSF1 target genes. Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref> shows mRNA fold changes for select HSF1 target genes altered by
Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization or dox-dependent
cHSF1 overexpression.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Stress-Independent HSF1 Activity Increases
Cellular Proteostasis
Capacity</title><p>Functional clustering of the 397 genes whose expression
is significantly altered by stress-independent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation
shows enrichment for cellular proteostasis pathways (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A and Table S2, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). By correlation analysis on the expression of 116 primary cellular
proteostasis factors (see Table S3, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting
Information</xref>) following activation of FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 or cHSF1,
we identify a cluster of cytosolic factors whose expression is affected
similarly by stress-independent HSF1 activation (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B,C and Figure S3A, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). This gene network is highly enriched for small heat shock proteins,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref></sup> components of the cytosolic HSP70 chaperoning
pathway,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref></sup> and components of the cytosolic HSP90 chaperoning
pathway.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref></sup></p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Stress-independent HSF1 activation remodels
cytosolic proteostasis
pathways. (A) Image showing the functional clustering of GO annotations
identified in genes showing a &#x0003e;2-fold change (FDR &#x0003c; 0.01) in
HEK293T-REx
cells following Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization.
See Table S2 (<xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>) for
additional GO annotations identified in this analysis. (B) Dendrogram
of primary proteostasis factors (see Table S3, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>) whose expression is highly correlated
following stress-independent HSF1 activation. The color indicates
the fold change in mRNA levels observed for specific highly correlated
proteostasis factors following Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
stabilization, as indicated by the legend. * indicates a gene only
identified in cHSF1 overexpression RNAseq. (C) Cluster analysis of
primary proteostasis factors whose expression is highly correlated
following stress-independent HSF1 activation. The color indicates
the fold change in mRNA levels observed for specific highly correlated
proteostasis factors following Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
stabilization, as indicated for B. A full correlation of the proteostasis
factors described in Table S3 (<xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>) is shown in Figure S2A (<xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). (D) Bar graph showing the log<sub>2</sub> fold change mRNA of
promiscuous (red) and nonpromiscuous (gray) client binding cytosolic
HSP40 cochaperones in HEK293T-REx cells following Shield-1-dependent
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization. ***<italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.005.
See Table S3 (<xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>) for
the identity of the specific HSP40s used in this analysis. (E) Graph
showing the genes whose expression is highly correlated with <italic>DNAJB1</italic> following HSF1 activation. The color indicates the
fold-change in mRNA levels induced by FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb-2014-00062n_0003" id="gr3" position="float"/></fig><p>Increases in cytosolic proteostasis
capacity induced by stress-independent
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation are best illustrated by the selective increase
in cytosolic HSP40s that bind misfolded, aggregation-prone proteins.
HSP40s function as cochaperones in the HSP70 chaperoning pathway through
the recruitment of misfolded client proteins to HSP70 for ATP-dependent
chaperoning and/or promoting HSP70 ATPase activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref></sup> HSP40s can be classified into four categories defined by their binding
to substrates: (1) promiscuous client binding, (2) selective client
binding, (3) no client binding, and (4) unknown client binding.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref></sup> Stress-independent HSF1 activation selectively
induces the expression of promiscuous cytosolic HSP40s (e.g., <italic>DNAJB1</italic> and <italic>DNAJA1</italic>) but not HSP40s that
demonstrate selective or no client binding (e.g., <italic>DNAJC10</italic> and <italic>DNAJC11</italic>) (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>D).
Since promiscuous HSP40s are the cochaperones most responsible for
recruiting misfolded, aggregation-prone proteins to ATP-dependent
HSP70 chaperoning,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref></sup> selective remodeling of the HSP40 cochaperone pool will result in
the increased flux of misfolded, aggregation-prone clients to HSP70s
for ATP-dependent chaperoning to the exclusion of more selective,
pathway-specific HSP70 activities.</p><p>This expression of promiscuous
HSP40s induced by stress-independent
HSF1 activation is highly correlated with other proteostasis factors
that cooperatively prevent intracellular protein aggregation. We observe
strong correlations between the promiscuous client binding HSP40 <italic>DNAJB1</italic> and other components of the cytosolic HSP70 chaperoning
pathway including cytosolic HSP70s (e.g., <italic>HSPA1A</italic>, <italic>HSPA1B</italic>, and <italic>HSPA6</italic>) and cytosolic nucleotide
exchange factors (e.g., <italic>HSPH1</italic> and <italic>HSPA4L</italic>) (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>E). Furthermore, the increased
expression of <italic>DNAJB1</italic> correlates with the increased
expression of small heat shock proteins (e.g., <italic>HSPB1</italic> and <italic>HSPB9</italic>), potentially reflecting functional cooperation
between small heat shock proteins and the HSP70 chaperoning pathways
for attenuating intracellular protein aggregation through stress-independent
HSF1 activation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> Similar correlations
are observed for other promiscuous cytosolic HSP40 cochaperones (Figure
S3B,C, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Quantitative
Proteomics Reveals Remodeling of Cytosolic Proteostasis
Pathways Induced by Stress-Independent HSF1 Activation</title><p>We
quantified proteome-level remodeling of cytosolic proteostasis pathways
induced by stress-independent HSF1 activation using tandem mass tag
(TMT)-multidimensional protein identification technology (MuDPIT)
quantitative proteomics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref></sup> We performed TMT-MuDPIT proteomics
in triplicate on whole cellular proteomes isolated from HEK293T-Rex
cells in the presence or absence of Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
stabilization or dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression. The conditions
used for this TMT-MuDPIT analysis were identical to those employed
in our RNAseq analysis (see <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref> for details). In each TMT-MuDPIT experiment, we quantified intracellular
levels of &#x0003e;2400 mammalian proteins (Table S4, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Select TMT-MuDPIT data for proteostasis
proteins are reported in Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref>.</p><p>Proteostasis
factors whose mRNA levels are significantly increased by Shield-1-dependent
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization also have increased protein levels (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A). Identical results were observed for dox-dependent
cHSF1 overexpression (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B). Despite the
qualitative correlation between gene expression and protein levels,
our results show that mRNA fold changes are generally greater than
those observed at the protein level. This observation confirms the
importance of combining transcriptional and proteomic profiling of
cHSF1 or FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation to obtain an accurate picture
of HSF1-dependent remodeling of cellular proteostasis pathways.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup></p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>TMT-MuDPIT shows proteome level remodeling of cytosolic
proteostasis
pathways induced by stress-independent HSF1 activation. (A) Plot showing
the log<sub>2</sub> fold change in proteomics vs the log<sub>2</sub> fold change in RNAseq for primary proteostasis factors (see Table
S3, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>) in HEK293T-REx
cells following Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization.
(B) Plot showing the log<sub>2</sub> fold change in proteomics vs
the log<sub>2</sub> fold change in RNAseq for primary proteostasis
factors (see Table S3, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>) in HEK293T-REx cells following dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression.
(C) Plot showing the Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization
vs log<sub>2</sub> fold change protein levels for proteostasis factors
following dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression. The proteins are colored
by intracellular localization: cytosolic/nuclear (red), blue (ER),
green (mitochondrial), and membrane-associated (orange). (D) Illustration
showing the protein-level remodeling of the highly correlated cellular
proteostasis network shown in Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C. (E)
Graph showing the fold increase in protein levels of cytosolic HSP40
proteins identified in our TMT-MuDPIT analyses. HSP40 proteins are
categorized based on their client binding; promiscuous HSP40s are
shown in red, and nonpromiscuous HSP40s are shown in gray.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb-2014-00062n_0004" id="gr4" position="float"/></fig><p>We observe a strong correlation between alterations
in protein
levels of cellular proteostasis factors induced by Shield-1-dependent
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization or dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression
(<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.95) (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C). The slope of this correlation is 0.69 &#x000b1; 0.02, which is nearly
identical to that observed for a similar comparison of mRNA increases
afforded by FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 and cHSF1 activation (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B), further demonstrating that Shield-1-dependent
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation does not significantly affect stress-independent,
HSF1-mediated proteostasis remodeling but offers more subtle remodeling
of proteostasis pathways as compared to dox-dependent cHSF1 overexpression.</p><p>Mapping alterations in cytosolic proteostasis factors induced by
Shield-1-dependent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 stabilization at the protein level
on the gene network identified in our bioinformatics analysis (see
Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C) confirm that a central core of cytosolic
proteostasis factors are altered by stress-independent HSF1 activation
(Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D). In particular, core pathways that
attenuate pathologic protein aggregation are remodeled, including
small heat shock proteins and components of cytosolic HSP70/HSP90
chaperoning pathways. Furthermore, our proteomic analysis confirms
that stress-independent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation increases cytosolic
HSP40 cochaperones that have promiscuous client binding but not those
that have selective or no client binding (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>E). Collectively, these results substantiate the stress-independent,
HSF1-mediated remodeling of cytosolic proteostasis pathways observed
by transcriptional profiling and provide a framework to identify proteostasis
network components and pathways accessible through stress-independent
HSF1 activation that can be targeted to alleviate pathologic intracellular
accumulation of misfolded proteins involved in human disease.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>Stress-Independent
HSF1 Activation Does Not Globally Disrupt
the Cellular Proteome</title><p>A potential consequence of cytosolic
proteostasis remodeling induced by stress-independent HSF1 activation
is nontranscriptional alterations in the stability of cellular proteins.
These nontranscriptional alterations in protein stability would be
reflected by altered steady-state concentrations of proteins whose
expression is not affected by stress-independent HSF1 activation.
We plotted the &#x02212;log <italic>p</italic>-value vs log<sub>2</sub> fold-change of protein of alterations in intracellular protein levels
induced by FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation to identify such nontranscriptional
alterations in protein levels (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A).
This analysis identified 24 proteins whose intracellular levels significantly
increased (fold change &#x0003e;1.4 fold; <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c;
0.1).
Alternatively, we observed no proteins whose intracellular levels
decreased (fold-change &#x0003e;1.4; <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.1).
Importantly,
these proteins were transcriptionally induced by FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B). Similar results were observed for dox-dependent
cHSF1 overexpression (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>C,D). While we
cannot rule out alterations in intracellular levels of proteins not
identified in our MuDPIT analyses, these results suggest that stress-independent
HSF1 activation does not globally remodel the composition of the cellular
proteome in HEK293T-Rex cells. These results indicate that stress-independent
HSF1 activation may provide a therapeutic approach to selectively
reduce intracellular protein aggregation without significantly impacting
cellular proteome function.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>HSF1 activation does not globally disrupt the
composition of the
cellular proteome. (A) Plot of &#x02212;log <italic>p</italic>-value
vs log<sub>2</sub> fold change (Shield-1/vehicle) for proteins identified
in our TMT-MuDPIT analysis of HEK293T-REx cells stably expressing
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 &#x000b1; Shield-1 (1 &#x003bc;M; 15 h). (B) Plot showing
log<sub>2</sub> fold change proteomics (Shield-1/vehicle) vs log<sub>2</sub> fold change RNAseq (Shield-1/vehicle) for proteins identified
in HEK293T-REx cells stably expressing FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1. Only proteins
showing a <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.1 in the TMT-MuDPIT proteomic
analysis are shown. (C) Plot of &#x02212;log <italic>p</italic>-value
vs log<sub>2</sub> fold change (dox/vehicle) for proteins identified
in our TMT-MuDPIT analysis of HEK293T-REx cells stably expressing
dox-regulated cHSF1 and treated with or without dox (2.25 &#x003bc;M;
15 h). (D) Plot showing log<sub>2</sub> fold change proteomics (dox/vehicle)
vs log<sub>2</sub> fold change RNAseq (dox/vehicle) for proteins identified
in HEK293T-REx cells stably expressing FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1. Only proteins
showing a <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.1 in the TMT-MuDPIT proteomic
analysis are shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb-2014-00062n_0005" id="gr5" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title>Stress-Independent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
Activation Attenuates the
Toxicity Induced by Cellular Stress</title><p>We evaluated the capacity
of stress-independent HSF1 transcriptional activity to protect the
cytosolic proteostasis environment by monitoring the capacity of FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
activation to attenuate cellular toxicity induced by heat stress or
the environmental toxin arsenite (As(III)), two cellular insults that
induce imbalances in cytosolic proteostasis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref></sup> FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
activation afforded a small but significant increase in cellular viability
when HEK293T-Rex cells are challenged with heat (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A) or As(III) (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B), consistent
with the capacity of stress-independent HSF1 activation to protect
cells against stress.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Stress-independent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation attenuates
intracellular
aggregation of an aggregation-prone model protein. (A) Plot showing
the resazurin fluorescence at 24 h of HEK293T-REx cells overexpressing
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 or tet-inducible cHSF1 following heat shock (43 &#x000b0;C
for 3 h). Cells were pretreated for 15 h with Shield-1 (1 &#x003bc;M)
or dox (2.25 &#x003bc;M), as indicated. Error bar shows SEM for <italic>n</italic> = 6; **<italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.002 and *<italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.01. (B) Plot showing resazurin fluorescence
for HEK293T-Rex cells overexpressing FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1. Cells were pretreated
with 15 h with vehicle or Shield-1 (1 &#x003bc;M) then subjected to
a 10 h treatment with the indicated concentration of As(III). Resazurin
fluorescence was measured following a 24 h recovery. Error bar shows
SEM for <italic>n</italic> = 6; *<italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.01.
(C) Fluorescence image of HEK293T cells cotransfected with plasmids
encoding polyQ<sub>0</sub>-tdTomato, poly-Q<sub>67</sub>-tdTomato,
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1, or FKBP&#x000b7;YFP, as indicated. Shield-1 (1 &#x003bc;M)
was added 36 h prior to imaging, as indicated. (D) Immunoblot of soluble
and insoluble fractions from HEK293T cells cotransfected with a combination
of plasmids encoding polyQ<sub>0</sub>-tdTomato or poly-Q<sub>67</sub>-tdTomato, and FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 or FKBP&#x000b7;YFP, as indicated. Shield-1
(1 &#x003bc;M) was added 36 h prior to lysis. (E) Quantification of
insoluble polyQ<sub>67</sub>-tdTomato from immunoblots as shown in
D. ** indicates a <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c; 0.002; <italic>n</italic> = 3.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb-2014-00062n_0006" id="gr6" position="float"/></fig><p>We next evaluated the capacity
of stress-independent HSF1 activation
to attenuate cytosolic aggregation of a model, misfolding-prone protein.
Cytosolic protein aggregation is a pathologic hallmark of numerous
human diseases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref></sup> Remodeling of the cytosolic
proteostasis environment by stress-dependent HSF1 activation or HSF1
overexpression attenuates pathologic intracellular aggregation of
destabilized, misfolding-prone proteins such as polyQ.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref></sup> To explore whether stress-independent FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation
can attenuate pathologic aggregation of destabilized proteins, we
transfected FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 into HEK293T cells stably expressing a
protein fusion between an aggregation-prone polyglutamine sequence
consisting of 67 glutamine residues and fluorescent tdTomato (polyQ<sub>67</sub>-tdTomato). polyQ<sub>67</sub>-tdTomato efficiently aggregates
in these cells shown by the fluorescent puncta observed by fluorescence
microscopy (Figure S4, <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>). Cells expressing the nonaggregation-prone polyQ<sub>0</sub>-tdTomato
show disperse fluorescence, reflecting the lack of aggregation. FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
activation decreases the population of intracellular polyQ<sub>67</sub>-tdTomato puncta, indicating decreased intracellular aggregation
(Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>C). FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation also
attenuates the accumulation of polyQ<sub>67</sub>-tdTomato into insoluble
aggregates (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>D,E). Importantly, these
effects cannot be attributed to alterations in intracellular polyQ<sub>67</sub>-tdTomato, as total protein levels were not significantly
affected by FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>D). The addition of Shield-1 did not influence puncta formation or
incorporation of polyQ<sub>67</sub>-tdTomato into insoluble aggregates
in cells transfected with a control plasmid expressing FKBP&#x000b7;YFP
(Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>C&#x02013;E). These results show that
stress-independent activation of HSF1 to levels achievable with potential
small-molecule HSF1 activators is sufficient to increase cytosolic
proteostasis capacity and attenuate pathologic protein aggregation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Concluding Remarks</title><p>The holistic activation of stress-responsive
signaling pathways
has been demonstrated to be more effective in correcting pathological
imbalances in proteostasis associated with human disease than the
isolated activation of an individual proteostasis network component.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></sup> The control that HSF1 exhibits over cytosolic
proteostasis makes it an attractive therapeutic target to attenuate
pathologic imbalances in intracellular proteostasis associated with
human disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref></sup> The comparisons presented herein between FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 and tet-inducible
cHSF1 validate FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 as a highly regulatable genetic approach
to induce the stress-independent HSF1 transcriptional program, providing
a critical resource to explore the therapeutic potential for stress-independent
HSF1 activation to ameliorate pathologic imbalances in intracellular
protein aggregation associated with human disease. We show that stress-independent
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation alters the composition of the cytosolic
proteostasis network to promote cellular viability and prevent intracellular
aggregation of misfolding-prone proteins. Additionally, we demonstrate
the capacity for stress-independent activation of FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
to attenuate intracellular protein aggregation and increase cellular
viability in response to proteotoxic insult. Furthermore, transcriptional
and proteomic profiling of FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 activation provides significant
insight into the proteome remodeling afforded by stress-independent
HSF1 activation and reveals unique, highly coordinated networks of
HSF1-regulated genes that promote cytosolic proteostasis maintenance.
Our results validate stress-independent HSF1 activation as a strategy
to correct pathologic imbalances in cellular proteostasis associated
with human disease, providing significant motivation to identify selective
small-molecule HSF1 activators.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec4"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec4.1"><title>Reagents,
Plasmids, and Antibodies</title><p>Sodium (meta)arsenite
was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich Co. Shield-1 was purchased from Clontech.
FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1&#x000b7;pDEST40, FKBP&#x000b7;YFP&#x000b7;pDEST40, and tet-inducible
cHSF1&#x000b7;pTREX-Dest30 were prepared as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> To construct ptdtomato-N1-polyQ<sub>67</sub>-tdtomato plasmid, the DNA fragment corresponding to the polyQ coding
sequence was amplified by PCR using DNA oligonucleotides, 5&#x02032;-
CCGGAATTCGCCGCCACCATGCACCATCACCACCAGCAACAG-3&#x02032;
and 5&#x02032;-GGTGGATCCCCGCCCTCCAGTGGGTGGGGAAA-3&#x02032;
as primers and pEYFP-N1-82Q as the template.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref></sup> The PCR product was digested with <italic>Eco</italic>RI and <italic>Bam</italic>HI, and cloned into <italic>Eco</italic>RI- and <italic>Bam</italic>HI-digested ptdTomato-N1. The following antibodies were
used in this analysis: rabbit polyclonal &#x003b1;-matrin-3 (Bethyl
Laboratories), rabbit polyclonal &#x003b1;-HSF1 (Stressgen), and rabbit
polyclonal &#x003b1;-RFP.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title>Cell Culture</title><p>HEK293T-REx (Invitrogen)
cells were cultured
in DMEM (CellGro) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (CellGro)
and 1% penicillin/streptomycin/glutamine (CellGro). HEK293T-REx cells
were cultured in 5 mg/mL blasticidin (InvivoGen) to maintain the tet
repressor. HEK293T-REx cells were transiently transfected using calcium
phosphate. Stable, clonal HEK293T-REx cell lines were selected from
transiently transfected populations using 500 &#x003bc;g/mL G-418 sulfate
(Cellgro) for cells expressing pcDNA-DEST40 or pTREx-DEST30 vectors.
All stable cell lines were maintained in the appropriate selective
antibiotics.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><title>Nuclear Extractions and Western Blot Analyses</title><p>HEK293T-REx
cells were harvested by scraping, and cell pellets were obtained by
centrifugation at 1500 rpm. Cells were lysed in 10 mM Hepes (pH 7.5),
50 mM NaCl, 0.5 M sucrose, 0.1 mM EDTA, 0.5% Triton X-100, and complete
EDTA-free protease inhibitors (Roche). Nuclear lysates were prepared
as previously described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> Protein concentrations
were normalized by Bradford assays (Bio-Rad). The normalized nuclear
lysates were separated by SDS&#x02013;PAGE and transferred to nitrocellulose
membranes. Following blocking and incubation with appropriate primary
antibodies, membranes were incubated with 680 and 800 nm fluorophore-labeled
secondary antibodies (Li-COR Biosciences) and detected with the Odyssey
Infrared Imaging System (Li-COR Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><title>Quantitative RT-PCR</title><p>The relative mRNA expression levels
of target genes were measured using quantitative RT-PCR. The protocol
is detailed in the <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>; primers used are listed in Table S3 (<xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting
Information</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5"><title>RNA-seq Analyses</title><p>FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1
or cHSF1(dox) cells
in 6-well plates were treated for 12 h with vehicle, 1 &#x003bc;M Shield-1
(for FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1), or 2.25 &#x003bc;M dox (for cHSF1(dox)) in biological
triplicate at 37 &#x000b0;C. Cells were harvested, and RNA was extracted
using the RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen). Genomic DNA was removed by on-column
digestion using the RNase-free DNase Set (Qiagen). Detailed protocols
for the RNA-seq analyses are provided in the <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting
Information</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.6"><title>Tandem Mass Tag Liquid Chromatography&#x02013;Mass
Spectrometry
Analyses</title><p>FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1 or cHSF1(dox) cells in 6-well plates
were treated for 12 h with vehicle, 1 &#x003bc;M Shield-1 (for FKBP&#x000b7;cHSF1),
or 2.25 &#x003bc;M dox (for cHSF1(dox)) in biological triplicate at
37 &#x000b0;C. TMT-labeled peptides were prepared from RIPA-lysed cells
according to standard protocols and analyzed by MuDPIT mass spectrometry.
Detailed protocols for cell lysis and mass spectrometric analyses
are provided in the <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>.</p></sec></sec></body><back><notes id="notes-1" notes-type="si"><title>Supporting Information Available</title><p>Supplemental experimental protocols,
complete data tables of RNA-Seq, TMT-MuDPIT, and GO annotation analyses,
and supplemental figures supporting the data presented in the main
text. This material is available free of charge via the Internet at <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org">http://pubs.acs.org</uri>.</p></notes><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb500062n_si_001.pdf"><caption><p>cb500062n_si_001.pdf</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile2"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb500062n_si_002.xlsx"><caption><p>cb500062n_si_002.xlsx</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile3"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb500062n_si_003.xlsx"><caption><p>cb500062n_si_003.xlsx</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile4"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb500062n_si_004.xlsx"><caption><p>cb500062n_si_004.xlsx</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile5"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cb500062n_si_005.xlsx"><caption><p>cb500062n_si_005.xlsx</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><notes id="NOTES-d3293e1487-autogenerated" notes-type="conflict-of-interest"><p>The authors declare no
competing financial interest.</p></notes><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>J.C.G. thanks NHLBI (HL099245) for financial support. T.N.
thanks the Uehara Memorial Foundation for a postdoctoral fellowship.
M.D.S. thanks the American Cancer Society for a postdoctoral fellowship.
R.L.W. thanks the Ellison Medical Foundation, Arlene and Arnold Goldstein,
and the National Institutes of Health (AG036634 and AG046495 for funding).
R.I.M. and T.N. were supported by the Ellison Medical Foundation,
the National Institutes of Health (GM038109, GM081192, AG026647, and
NS047331), and the Daniel F. and Ada L. Rice Foundation. We also thank
J. Kelly, M. Petrascheck, and the TSRI DNA Core Facility for fruitful
discussions and experimental assistance.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit1"><name><surname>Calamini</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Protein homeostasis
as a therapeutic target for diseases
of protein conformation</article-title>. <source>Curr. Top. Med. Chem.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>2623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2640</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23339312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>E. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dillin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Balch</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Biological
and chemical approaches to diseases of proteostasis deficiency</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>
<volume>78</volume>, <fpage>959</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>991</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19298183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Anckar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sistonen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Regulation of HSF1 function in the heat stress response:
implications in aging and disease</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev.
Biochem.</source>
<volume>80</volume>, <fpage>1089</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21417720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Akerfelt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sistonen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Heat shock
factors: integrators of
cell stress, development and lifespan</article-title>. <source>Nat.
Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>555</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20628411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>Raychaudhuri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Loew</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Korner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pinkert</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Theis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hayer-Hartl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>F. U.</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Interplay of acetyltransferase
EP300 and the proteasome system in regulating heat shock transcription
factor 1</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>156</volume>, <fpage>975</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>985</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24581496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit6"><name><surname>Mendillo</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Santagata</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Koeva</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tamimi</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fraenkel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ince</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Whitesell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lindquist</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>HSF1 drives a transcriptional program distinct from
heat shock to support highly malignant human cancers</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>150</volume>, <fpage>549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>562</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22863008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sikder</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pluta</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wolfinger</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kodadek</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide
analysis of human HSF1
signaling reveals a transcriptional program linked to cellular adaptation
and survival</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biosyst.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>639</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17216044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Trinklein</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The role
of heat shock transcription factor 1 in the genome-wide regulation
of the mammalian heat shock response</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol.
Cell</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1254</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1261</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14668476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>de
Billy</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Workman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Drugging the
heat shock factor 1 pathway: exploitation of the critical cancer cell
dependence on the guardian of the proteome</article-title>. <source>Cell Cycle</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>3806</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3808</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19901525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Gestwicki</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Garza</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Protein quality
control in neurodegenerative disease</article-title>. <source>Prog.
Mol. Biol. Transl. Sci.</source>
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>353</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22482455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit11"><name><surname>Whitesell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lindquist</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Inhibiting the transcription factor HSF1 as an anticancer
strategy</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin. Ther. Targets</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>478</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19335068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Westerheide</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Heat shock response
modulators as therapeutic tools
for diseases of protein conformation</article-title>. <source>J. Biol.
Chem.</source>
<volume>280</volume>, <fpage>33097</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16076838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit13"><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Takaki</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kitaura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Active HSF1
significantly suppresses
polyglutamine aggregate formation in cellular and mouse models</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>280</volume>, <fpage>34908</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34916</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16051598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit14"><name><surname>Krobitsch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lindquist</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Aggregation of huntingtin in yeast varies with the
length of the polyglutamine expansion and the expression of chaperone
proteins</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>97</volume>, <fpage>1589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1594</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10677504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nachman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bar-Nun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Aggregation of polyQ
proteins is increased upon yeast aging and affected by Sir2 and Hsf1:
novel quantitative biochemical and microscopic assays</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e44785</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22970306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Chafekar</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Duennwald</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Impaired heat shock response in cells expressing full-length polyglutamine-expanded
huntingtin</article-title>, <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>7</volume>, DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0037929</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit17"><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Podlutskaya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Halloran</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hussong</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>P. Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Burbank</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Galvan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Over-expression of
heat shock factor 1 phenocopies the effect of chronic inhibition of
TOR by rapamycin and is sufficient to ameliorate Alzheimer&#x02019;s-like
deficits in mice modeling the disease</article-title>. <source>J. Neurochem.</source>
<volume>124</volume>, <fpage>880</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>893</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23121022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit18"><name><surname>Scheper</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nijholt</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hoozemans</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The unfolded
protein response and
proteostasis in Alzheimer disease: preferential activation of autophagy
by endoplasmic reticulum stress</article-title>. <source>Autophagy</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>910</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>911</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21494086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>F. U.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bracher</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hayer-Hartl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Molecular
chaperones in protein folding
and proteostasis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>475</volume>, <fpage>324</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>332</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21776078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit20"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Aging, protein
aggregation, chaperones, and neurodegenerative disorders: mechanisms
of coupling and therapeutic opportunities</article-title>. <source>Rambam
Maimonides Med. J.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>e0021</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23908845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>Neef</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Turski</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Modulation
of heat shock transcription
factor 1 as a therapeutic target for small molecule intervention in
neurodegenerative disease</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e1000291</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20098725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit22"><name><surname>Calamini</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Madoux</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hutt</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chalfant</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Saldanha</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hodder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tait</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Garza</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Balch</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Small-molecule
proteostasis
regulators for protein conformational diseases</article-title>. <source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22198733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Au</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>I. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Identification of small-molecule
HSF1 amplifiers by high content screening in protection of cells from
stress induced injury</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Biophys. Res.
Commun.</source>
<volume>390</volume>, <fpage>925</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>930</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19852939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit24"><name><surname>Bersuker</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hipp</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Calamini</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kopito</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Heat shock
response activation exacerbates inclusion body formation in a cellular
model of Huntington disease</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>288</volume>, <fpage>23633</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23638</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23839939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Heat shock
transcription factor 1 attenuates TNFalpha-induced cardiomyocyte death
through suppression of NFkappaB pathway</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<volume>527</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23769970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Jolly</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Role of the heat
shock response and molecular chaperones
in oncogenesis and cell death</article-title>. <source>J. Natl. Cancer
Inst.</source>
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>1564</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1572</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11018092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit27"><name><surname>Shoulders</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ryno</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cooley</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wiseman</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Broadly
applicable methodology for the rapid and dosable small molecule-mediated
regulation of transcription factors in human cells</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>8129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8132</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23682758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit28"><name><surname>Shalgi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hurt</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Krykbaeva</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Taipale</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lindquist</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Widespread regulation of translation by elongation
pausing in heat shock</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>452</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23290915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit29"><name><surname>Vabulas</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Raychaudhuri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hayer-Hartl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>F. U.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Protein folding
in the cytoplasm and the heat shock response</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspect. Biol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>a004390</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit30"><name><surname>Shoulders</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ryno</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Genereux</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moresco</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names><suffix>III.</suffix></name>; <name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>A. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wiseman</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Stress-independent activation of XBP1s and/or ATF6
reveals three functionally diverse ER proteostasis environments</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>1279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1292</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23583182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit31"><name><surname>Aldridge</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Horibe</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hoogenraad</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Discovery of genes activated by the
mitochondrial unfolded protein response (mtUPR) and cognate promoter
elements</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>e874</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17849004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit32"><name><surname>Kampinga</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>HSPBs: small proteins with big implications in human
disease</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>1706</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1710</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22721753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit33"><name><surname>Hageman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Waarde</surname><given-names>M. A. W. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zylicz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Walerych</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kampinga</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The diverse
members of the mammalian HSP70 machine show distinct chaperone-like
activities</article-title>. <source>Biochem. J.</source>
<volume>435</volume>, <fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21231916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit34"><name><surname>Kampinga</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The HSP70 chaperone machinery: J
proteins as drivers
of functional specificity</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell
Biol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>592</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20651708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit35"><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morishima</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Osawa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Proposal for a role
of the Hsp90/Hsp70-based chaperone machinery in making triage decisions
when proteins undergo oxidative and toxic damage</article-title>. <source>Exp Biol. Med. (Maywood, NJ, U.S.)</source>
<volume>235</volume>, <fpage>278</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>289</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit36"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Agashe</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Siegers</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>F. U.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Pathways of chaperone-mediated
protein folding in the cytosol</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Mol.
Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>781</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>791</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15459659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit37"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kukushkin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Konagai</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hipp</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hayer-Hartl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>F. U.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>PolyQ proteins interfere
with nuclear degradation of cytosolic proteins by sequestering the
Sis1p chaperone</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>154</volume>, <fpage>134</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>145</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23791384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit38"><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Seraphim</surname><given-names>T. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mokry</surname><given-names>D. Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cyr</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Identification of regions involved
in substrate binding
and dimer stabilization within the central domains of yeast Hsp40
Sis1</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e50927</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23227221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit39"><name><surname>Rauniyar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>McClatchy</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names><suffix>III.</suffix></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Comparison of
protein expression ratios observed by sixplex and duplex TMT labeling
method</article-title>. <source>J. Proteome Res.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1031</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1039</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23214967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit40"><name><surname>Washburn</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ulaszek</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Deciu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schieltz</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names><suffix>III.</suffix></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Analysis of quantitative proteomic
data generated via
multidimensional protein identification technology</article-title>. <source>Anal. Chem.</source>
<volume>74</volume>, <fpage>1650</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1657</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12043600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit41"><name><surname>Washburn</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ulaszek</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names><suffix>III.</suffix></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Reproducibility
of quantitative proteomic analyses of complex biological mixtures
by multidimensional protein identification technology</article-title>. <source>Anal. Chem.</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>5054</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5061</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14708778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit42"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Arsenic
trioxide induces Hsp70 expression via reactive oxygen species and
JNK pathway in MDA231 cells</article-title>. <source>Life Sci.</source>
<volume>77</volume>, <fpage>2783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2793</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15978632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit43"><name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>I. J.</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Targeted
disruption of heat shock transcription factor 1 abolishes thermotolerance
and protection against heat-inducible apoptosis</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>273</volume>, <fpage>7523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7528</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9516453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit44"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Abrogating HSP response
augments cell death induced by As2O3 in glioma cell lines</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Neurol. Sci.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>504</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>511</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20724260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit45"><name><surname>Gidalevitz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ben-Zvi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brignull</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Progressive
disruption of cellular protein folding in models of polyglutamine
diseases</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>311</volume>, <fpage>1471</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1474</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16469881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit46"><name><surname>Sittler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lurz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lueder</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Priller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lehrach</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hayer-Hartl</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>F. U.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wanker</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Geldanamycin
activates
a heat shock response and inhibits huntingtin aggregation in a cell
culture model of Huntington&#x02019;s disease</article-title>. <source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1315</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11406612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit47"><name><surname>Neef</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Heat shock transcription factor 1
as a therapeutic target in neurodegenerative diseases</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Drug Discovery</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>930</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>944</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit48"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nollen</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bindokas</surname><given-names>V. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>R. I.</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Polyglutamine
protein aggregates are dynamic</article-title>. <source>Nat. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>826</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>831</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12360295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>