<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><?origin nihpa?><?iso-abbr Nature?><?submitter-system nihms?><?submitter-canonical-name Nature Publishing Group?><?submitter-canonical-id NATURE-STRUCTUR?><?submitter-userid 8068858?><?submitter-authority myNCBI?><?submitter-login nature-structure?><?submitter-name Nature Publishing Group?><?domain nihpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">0410462</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">6011</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nature</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nature</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0028-0836</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1476-4687</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4708089</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26675724</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature16483</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">nihpa741417</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The <italic>C. elegans</italic> adult neuronal IIS/FOXO transcriptome reveals adult phenotype regulators</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaletsky</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lakhina</surname><given-names>Vanisha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arey</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">$</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>April</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">$</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>Jessica</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>Jasmine</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>Coleen T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><aff id="A1">Department of Molecular Biology &#x00026; LSI Genomics, Princeton University, Princeton NJ 08544</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02020;</label>Corresponding Author: <email>ctmurphy@princeton.edu</email></corresp><fn id="FN1" fn-type="equal"><label>*, $</label><p id="P1">These authors contributed equally.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>7</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>529</volume><issue>7584</issue><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1038/nature16483--><permissions><license><license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</uri></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P2">Insulin/IGF-1 signaling (IIS) is a critical regulator of an organism&#x02019;s most important biological decisions, from growth, development, and metabolism to reproduction and longevity. It primarily does so through the activity of the DAF-16/FOXO transcription factor, whose global targets were identified in <italic>C. elegans</italic> using whole-worm transcriptional analyses more than a decade ago<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. IIS and FOXO also regulate important neuronal and adult behavioral phenotypes, such as the maintenance of memory<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> and axon regeneration<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> with age, in both mammals<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> and <italic>C. elegans,</italic> but the neuron-specific IIS/FOXO targets that regulate these functions are still unknown. By isolating adult <italic>C. elegans</italic> neurons for transcriptional profiling, we identified both the wild-type and IIS/FOXO adult neuronal transcriptomes for the first time. IIS/FOXO neuron-specific targets are distinct from canonical IIS/FOXO-regulated longevity and metabolism targets, and are required for IIS/<italic>daf-2</italic> mutants&#x02019; extended memory. We also discovered that the activity of the forkhead transcription factor FKH-9 in neurons is required for <italic>daf-2&#x02019;s</italic> ability to regenerate axons with age, and its activity in non-neuronal tissues is required for <italic>daf-2&#x02019;s</italic> long lifespan. Together, neuron-specific and canonical IIS/FOXO-regulated targets enable the coordinated extension of neuronal activities, metabolism, and longevity under low insulin-signaling conditions.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="P3">The <italic>C. elegans</italic> IIS pathway acts both cell autonomously and non-autonomously to control longevity, growth, dauer formation, metabolism, and reproduction<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> through its regulation of DAF-16/FOXO&#x02019;s nuclear localization and transcriptional activation. The canonical IIS/FOXO gene set, which identified primarily intestinal and hypodermal targets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Extended Data Fig. 1A&#x02013;B</xref>)<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>, has been instructive in our understanding of how insulin signaling regulates a diverse range of activities, including metabolism, autophagy, stress resistance, and proteostasis. However, IIS mutants also exhibit <italic>daf-16</italic>-dependent neuronal phenotypes, including extended positive olfactory learning<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, increased short- and long-term associative memory<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, increased thermotaxis learning<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>, improved neuronal morphology maintenance<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>, and improved axon regeneration<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. These phenotypes are unlikely to be regulated by the known intestinal and hypodermal IIS/FOXO targets<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Therefore, to understand how IIS/<italic>daf-2</italic> animals extend behavioral functionality, we must identify the neuronal targets of FOXO/DAF-16.</p><p id="P4">We first profiled the expression of <italic>daf-16;daf-2</italic> worms with <italic>daf-16</italic> rescued in specific tissues<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). Intestinal <italic>daf-16</italic> rescue correlates best with whole-worm profiles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Extended Data Fig. 1A, C</xref>). By contrast, neuronal <italic>daf-16</italic> rescue profiles are anti-correlated with the intestinal DAF-16 and whole-worm profiles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Extended Data Fig. 1A, C</xref>). Surprisingly, many genes induced by neuronal DAF-16 rescue are expressed (Wormbase) or predicted to be expressed in non-neuronal tissues<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Extended Data Fig. 1D</xref>), and have non-neuronal functions (e.g., collagens<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Extended Data Fig. 1B, 1E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). Thus, whole-worm transcriptional analyses of neuronally-rescued DAF-16 failed to reveal targets that account for <italic>daf-2</italic> mutants&#x02019; <italic>daf-16</italic>-dependent age-related behaviors. Therefore, we needed to specifically examine transcription in IIS-mutant neurons.</p><p id="P5">The tough outer cuticle prevents dissociation of adult tissues<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>, thus the wild-type adult neuronal transcriptome has not been described. To solve this problem, we used rapid, chilled chemomechanical disruption followed immediately by FACS to isolate GFP-marked neurons from wild-type worms, then RNA-sequenced these isolated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A&#x02013;C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2A&#x02013;C,F,G</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 3</xref>). This method is gentle enough to preserve the integrity of cells and some neurites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2A</xref>), does not involve cell culturing prior to FACS, in contrast to previous methods<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>, and does not affect transcription (Actinomycin D; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2D,E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). Downsampling analysis showed that sufficient sequencing depth was achieved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2H</xref>).</p><p id="P6">We compared gene expression in isolated wild-type neurons with whole-worm expression to identify genes that are enriched in neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A&#x02013;C</xref>). Of the 1507 &#x0201c;neuron enriched&#x0201d; genes (False Discovery Rate (FDR)&#x0003c;0.1; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A,B</xref>), only 4% have previously-described expression patterns exclusively in non-neuronal tissues, and &#x0201c;Neuron&#x0201d; is the only significantly-enriched tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2F</xref>), suggesting the method is highly selective for neuronal transcripts. Gene promoter-gfp tests of previously uncharacterized genes from our &#x0201c;neuron enriched&#x0201d; list confirmed neuronal expression, with no bias for particular neuron types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data Fig. 3A</xref>). We also detected genes previously reported to be expressed only in single neurons or small subsets of neurons, including <italic>glr-3</italic> (RIA), <italic>ttx-3</italic> (AIY/AIA), and <italic>npr-14</italic> (AIY) (Wormbase).</p><p id="P7">The wild-type neuron-enriched set includes synaptic machinery, ion channels, neurotransmitters, and signaling components (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 3</xref>), as well as &#x0003e;700 previously-uncharacterized genes; these genes are predicted to have &#x0201c;neuronal&#x0201d;-like character and function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>). Comparison of the wild-type embryonic and larval neuronal transcriptomes with the adult neuronal transcriptome at the same FDR revealed a shift in functional categories from developmental processes to neuronal function/behavior in the adult neuronal transcriptome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data Fig. 3B,C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 5</xref>), suggesting that previous isolation methods<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>, either due to early developmental stage isolation or to re-culturing, biased expression toward developmental genes rather than neuronal/behavioral genes.</p><p id="P8">To identify adult neuronal IIS/FOXO targets, we sequenced RNA from isolated <italic>daf-2</italic> and <italic>daf-16;daf-2</italic> neurons on Day 1 of adulthood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Extended Data Fig. 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 6, 8</xref>). The IIS/FOXO neuron-isolated gene set is enriched for neuronal expression: 86% and 92% of the up- and down-regulated genes, respectively, are expressed in wild-type neurons. While several of DAF-16&#x02019;s top Class I targets, including <italic>hil-1, sip-1, mtl-1, nnt-1, ins-6,</italic> and <italic>daf-16</italic> itself, were upregulated in both <italic>daf-2</italic> neurons and <italic>daf-2</italic> whole worms (Group B; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>), most of the IIS/FOXO neuronally-regulated set differs from the canonical whole-worm IIS/FOXOs set<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Specifically, in contrast to the metabolism-dominated functions of canonical whole-worm IIS/FOXO targets<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>, the neuronal IIS set GO terms reflect neuron-like functions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Extended Data Fig. 5B</xref>): serpentine receptors, GPCRs, syntaxin, globins, kinesins, insulins, ion channels, potassium channels, seven-transmembrane receptors, the NPR-1 neuropeptide receptor, and the SER-3 octopamine receptor are upregulated in <italic>daf-2</italic> neurons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). A few genes (<italic>fat-3</italic> and <italic>crh-1</italic>/CREB) are upregulated in <italic>daf-2</italic> neurons but downregulated in whole <italic>daf-2</italic> animals.</p><p id="P9">The IIS/FOXO downregulated set includes serpentine receptors, guanylate cyclases, signaling peptides and receptors (NLPs, FLPs, and NPRs), and the vesicle trafficking G protein <italic>rab-28</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). Expression of the sensory neuron cilia protein IFTA-2, which co-localizes with DAF-2 and whose loss increases lifespan<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>, is downregulated in <italic>daf-2</italic> mutants, consistent with the longevity of <italic>daf-2</italic> and ciliated sensory neuron mutants<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. Similarly, <italic>sams-1</italic> (S-adenosyl methionine synthetase), which is downregulated under long-lived Dietary Restriction conditions<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>, and <italic>sma-5</italic> and <italic>dbl-1</italic>, components of TGF-beta pathways linked with IIS<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>, are downregulated, perhaps coordinating the longevity and reproductive output of these pathways.</p><p id="P10">Unlike canonical IIS/FOXO targets<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>, neuronal IIS/FOXO gene promoters are not enriched for the DBE (DAF-16 Binding Element, GTAAAt/cA), but the overlapping, upregulated (Group B) targets&#x02019; promoters contain twice as many DBEs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Extended Data Fig. 5A</xref>). The overlapping downregulated (Group F) targets are enriched for the PQM-1<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>/DAE motif (CTTATCA<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 7</xref>). DAF-16 may regulate neuronal activities indirectly through activation of ~60 IIS/FOXO-upregulated transcription factors (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 6</xref>).</p><p id="P11">We next tested the roles of top-scoring genes in <italic>daf-2</italic>-regulated neuronal phenotypes. Long-term and short-term associative memory are both extended in <italic>daf-2</italic> mutants in a <italic>daf-16</italic>-dependent manner<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended Data Fig. 6</xref>). The bZIP transcription factor CREB, which is required for long-term memory in many organisms, including <italic>C. elegans</italic><sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, is upregulated by IIS/FOXO in neurons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 6</xref>), correlating with <italic>daf-2&#x02019;s</italic> increased long-term memory<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. However, short-term associative memory (STAM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>) is CREB-independent<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, and the genes that enable <italic>daf-2&#x02019;s</italic> STAM extension are unknown. While the DAF-16 non-neuronal target <italic>sod-3</italic> had no effect on <italic>daf-2&#x02019;s</italic> extended STAM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended Data Fig. 6B&#x02013;D</xref>), knockdown of 8 of the 10 top-ranked, upregulated IIS/FOXO targets significantly decreased <italic>daf-2(e1370)</italic>&#x02019;s STAM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D,E</xref>), both in whole-life and adult-only RNAi tests. (Neuronal RNAi is effective in learning, STAM, and LTAM tests<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>.) The variety of genes (ion channels, transcription factors, G-proteins, vesicle fusion proteins) required for <italic>daf-2&#x02019;s</italic> extended STAM suggests that decreased insulin signaling affects a broad network of memory extension genes. Several of these genes are also required for wild type&#x02019;s learning and memory (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended Data Fig. 6G</xref>) suggesting that <italic>daf-2</italic> mutants maintain neuronal function, rather than utilizing an alternative short-term memory mechanism.</p><p id="P12"><italic>daf-2</italic> mutants also maintain motor neuron axon regeneration ability with age in a <italic>daf-16</italic>-dependent manner<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>, and we found this is also true for mechanosensory neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A,B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7A&#x02013;D</xref>). To identify factors that enable axon regeneration with age, we isolated and RNA-sequenced six adult mechanosensory neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 9</xref>); this set includes 94 known larval regeneration genes from limited candidate screens<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> (p&#x02264; 1.82 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;20</sup>). To find <italic>daf-2/daf-16</italic>-dependent axon regeneration candidates, we identified mechanosensory genes that are also regulated by neuronal IIS/FOXO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 9</xref>; p&#x0003c;0.002). The forkhead transcription factor FKH-9 is a neuronal IIS/FOXO target (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 6</xref>) and a canonical Class I target<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>, and is expressed in mechanosensory neurons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 9</xref>). <italic>fkh-9&#x02019;s</italic> promoter is occupied by DAF-16, which we confirmed by chIP-qPCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Extended Data Fig. 8A, B</xref>). FKH-9::GFP localized to nuclei, and neurons were the primary site of differential FKH-9::GFP levels in <italic>daf-2</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Extended Data Fig. 8C</xref>), all suggesting a role for FKH-9 in <italic>daf-2/daf-16</italic>-mediated neuronal function.</p><p id="P13">While there is no effect on the first day of adulthood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7E,F</xref>), loss of <italic>fkh-9</italic> severely impairs <italic>daf-2&#x02019;s</italic> axon regeneration ability in aged (Day 5) worms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>), correlating with an increased difference in <italic>fkh-9</italic> expression levels between wild-type and <italic>daf-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). Pan-neuronal <italic>fkh-9</italic> expression rescues the ability of Day 5 <italic>daf-2;fkh-9</italic> worms to regenerate PLM axons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B,C</xref>). <italic>fkh-9</italic> levels are critical for neuron morphology, as <italic>fkh-9</italic> neuronal overexpression causes axonal defects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7G</xref>)</p><p id="P14">Adult-specific and whole-life reduction of <italic>fkh-9</italic> also severely impair <italic>daf-2&#x02019;s</italic> extended STAM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Extended Data Fig. 9</xref>). <italic>daf-2;fkh-9</italic> double mutants are defective in both STAM and learning, and neuronal <italic>fkh-9</italic> expression rescues these defects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Extended Data Fig. 9D,E</xref>), suggesting <italic>fkh-9</italic> is required for <italic>daf</italic>-2&#x02019;s extended memory and normal neuronal development. Day 1 and 5 <italic>fkh-9</italic> expression levels correlate with STAM and axon regeneration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3D</xref>). <italic>fkh-9</italic> reduction delays development, and reduction during adulthood causes severe matricide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 10A&#x02013;C</xref>). <italic>fkh-9</italic> knockdown in adult <italic>daf-2</italic> worms treated with FUdR to block matricide<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> significantly shortens lifespan (40&#x02013;50%; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4F</xref>). Pan-neuronal <italic>fkh-9</italic> expression does not rescue lifespan (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 10D</xref>), suggesting that FKH-9 acts in non-neuronal tissues to regulate lifespan. Thus, IIS/FOXO-regulated FKH-9 function is important for both neuronal and non-neuronal growth and development, as well as adult memory and axon regeneration. Interestingly, FKH-9&#x02019;s mammalian homolog FoxG1 is required for axon outgrowth<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> and is the most highly-induced gene in spinal cords treated with radial glial cell transplant following spinal cord injury<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P15">Network analysis using <italic>fkh-9</italic> and the other 8 neuronal DAF-16 STAM genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4G</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 10</xref>) identified <italic>casy-1</italic>, which is required for several forms of associative learning and memory<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>, <italic>apl-1</italic>, the <italic>C. elegans</italic> ortholog of amyloid precursor protein (APP) that can disrupt sensory plasticity<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>, and <italic>dlk-1</italic>, the only previously known regulator of age-dependent axon regeneration<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>. Additionally, genes involved in neuronal degeneration (<italic>mec-17</italic>), neuronal development (<italic>egl-44, sem-4),</italic> neuronal function (<italic>egl-21, rnc-1, vab-9, cysl-1</italic>), synaptic regulation and function (<italic>cab-1, hlb-1, magu-4, sph-1, unc-64</italic>), and axon outgrowth (<italic>unc-14</italic>) and regeneration (<italic>egl-8, fos-1, pmk-3</italic>), were connected to the STAM genes. PQM-1<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>, whose motif (DAE) is overrepresented in neuronal IIS target promoters, and other IIS (<italic>akt-2, dct-6, hlh-30</italic>), TGF-&#x003b2; (<italic>daf-14, sma-4, crm-1, sma-9, sma-1, sta-1</italic>), and MAPK pathway (<italic>vhp-1, pmk-3</italic>) components emerged in the network. Transcriptional regulation by IIS/FOXO and its targets may lead to broader, indirect transcriptional and non-transcriptional regulation of genes with important neuronal functions.</p><p id="P16">Plasticity in development, reproduction, and longevity allows organisms to respond appropriately to nutrient availability and changes in their environment. The IIS pathway is a critical mediator of these decisions, with FOXO selecting transcriptional targets to execute specific biochemical functions in each tissue, including factors that maintain cognitive function with age. <italic>daf-2</italic> worms maintain neuronal behaviors with age by utilizing a set of transcriptional targets that are distinct from previously-identified metabolic and stress resistance targets expressed in other tissues. These genes may regulate additional neuronal targets through non-transcriptional mechanisms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4G</xref>). The regulation of tissue-specific transcriptional programs is important to coordinate phenotypic responses, extending neuronal abilities in concert with <italic>daf-2&#x02019;s</italic> extended longevity and reproductive span.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="S1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S2"><title>Adult cell isolation</title><p id="P17">Day 1 adult neuronally GFP-labeled worms (<italic>Punc119::GFP or Pmec-4::GFP</italic>) were prepared for cell isolation as previously described<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> with modifications (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2</xref>). Synchronized adult worms were washed with M9 buffer to remove excess bacteria. The pellet (~250 &#x000b5;l) was washed with 500 &#x000b5;l lysis buffer (200 mM DTT, 0.25% SDS, 20 mM Hepes pH 8.0, 3% sucrose) and resuspended in 1000 &#x000b5;l lysis buffer. Worms were incubated in lysis buffer with gentle rocking for 6.5 minutes at room temperature. The pellet was washed 6&#x000d7; with M9 and resuspended in 20 mg/ml pronase from <italic>Streptomyces griseus</italic> (Sigma-Aldrich). Worms were incubated at room temperature (&#x0003c;20 minutes) with periodic mechanical disruption by pipetting every 2 min. When most worm bodies were dissociated, leaving only small debris and eggs, ice-cold PBS buffer containing 2% fetal bovine serum (Gibco) was added. RNA from FACS-sorted neurons was prepared for RNA-seq and subsequent analysis (see Extended Data for details).</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Short-term associative memory assay</title><p id="P18">Memory assays were performed as described<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Axon Regeneration Assays</title><p id="P19">In vivo laser axotomy of PLM neurons was performed as described<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="extended-data" id="S5"><title>Extended Data</title><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 1</label><caption><p id="P20">A) DAF-16 tissue-specific transgenics; heat map of all genes with expression differences &#x02265;1.5-fold in &#x02265;3 arrays. B) Significant Gene Ontology (GO) cluster terms from <italic>Punc-119::daf-16</italic>-regulated up- and down-regulated genes (Enrichment score &#x0003e;1). C) Pairwise Pearson correlations between arrays of DAF-16-up-regulated or down-regulated targets. The red box highlights the negative correlation between neuronal DAF-16 rescued targets (<italic>Punc-119::daf-16::gfp;daf-16;daf-2 vs daf-16;daf-2</italic>) and intestinal DAF-16 targets (<italic>Pges-1::daf-16::gfp;daf-16;daf-2 vs daf-16;daf-2</italic>), while the blue box shows the positive correlation between intestinal DAF-16 targets (<italic>Pges-1::daf-16::gfp;daf-16;daf-2 vs daf-16;daf-2</italic>) and whole worm DAF-16 targets (<italic>Pdaf-16::daf-16::gfp; daf-16;daf-2 vs daf-16;daf-2</italic>). The green box shows the weak correlation between neuronal rescued and whole worm DAF-16 targets. D) Tissue enrichment analysis (Mean &#x000b1; SEM) of significant DAF-16-rescued up- and down-regulated genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>) (FDR &#x0003c; 0.5). E) Significant Gene Ontology (GO) terms (adjusted p-value &#x0003c; 0.05) for DAF-16 up-regulated and down-regulated genes from whole worm, intestine-, neuron-, and muscle-rescued DAF-16 strains. Genes used for GO analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>) were derived from SAM analysis of the microarrays in (A) and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f5"/></fig><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 2</label><caption><p id="P21">A) Pipeline for isolation of adult cells for FACS and RNA sequencing. B) Workflow for RNAseq data analysis of isolated neurons. C) Heat map of wild type neuron-expressed relative to whole worm-expressed genes. D) Actinomycin D (transcription inhibitor) treatment (100 &#x000b5;g/ml) during the cell isolation process demonstrates that the neuron isolation technique induces minimal transcriptional changes in wild type animals. Gene Ontology (GO) Terms represent genes up-regulated in the absence of Actinomycin D (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). E) The 26 differentially expressed genes from Actinomycin D treatment are listed. F) <italic>C. elegans</italic> tissue gene expression prediction confirms neuronal character of adult wild-type neuron-enriched genes. Neuron-enriched genes were divided among equal bins according to p-value. Bin 1: FDR&#x0003c;0.003%; Bin 2: 0.003%&#x02013;0.03%; Bin 3: 0.03%&#x02013;1.3%; Bin 4: 1.3%&#x02013;4%; Bin 5: 4&#x02013;10%. G) Principal component analysis (PCA) shows a clear separation between wild-type adult neuronal and whole-worm samples. H) Down-sampling of wild-type neuron sequencing reads demonstrates sufficient sampling depth. The number of genes detected at the 3 counts per million threshold (for expressed genes) with different proportions of total sequencing depth analyzed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f6"/></fig><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 3</label><caption><p id="P22">A) Promoter::GFP transcriptional fusions of candidate uncharacterized neuronal genes (Day 1 of adulthood). B) Gene Ontology clusters were generated from the categories in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1E</xref>. Non-overlapping GO Terms suggest a transition from development-related processes in embryonic and larval animals to neuronal processes involved in behavior in adults (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 5</xref>). C) Venn diagram depicting the overlap between genes classified as &#x0201c;expressed&#x0201d; among embryonic and larval neurons<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> and adult neurons from our RNA-seq analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 5</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f7"/></fig><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 4</label><caption><p id="P23">A) Principal Components Analysis of the whole worm and isolated adult neuron samples obtained for this study. B) Venn diagram depicting the overlap of <italic>daf-2</italic>- and <italic>daf-16;daf-2</italic>-expressed genes with those expressed in wild-type adult neurons. C) Spearman correlation of whole-worm and isolated adult neuron samples. D) The DAF-16 cell-autonomous and cell non-autonomous targets are distinct. The number of genes that overlap between neuronal DAF-16-rescued whole-worm targets (<italic>Punc-119::daf-16::gfp;daf-16;daf-2 vs daf-16;daf-2</italic>) and isolated neuron IIS targets <italic>(daf-2 vs daf-16;daf-2)</italic> is shown (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 8</xref>). Hypergeometric distribution analysis (p-values) shows that the extent of overlap between the gene categories is not significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f8"/></fig><fig id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 5</label><caption><p id="P24">A) The different classes of neuronal IIS/FOXO genes shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref> were analyzed for DBE and DAE sequences in the 1kb upstream promoter regions. The genome-wide % of DBE and DAE occurrences across the 1kb promoters of all gene-encoding regions is reported. Comparison of whole-worm (Class I)<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> vs neuronal-IIS/FOXO-regulated targets. P-values: hypergeometric distributions. B) GO terms of Class I whole worm<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> vs. neuronal-IIS up-regulated genes (left) and Class II whole worm<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> vs neuronal-IIS down-regulated genes (right) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 5</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f9"/></fig><fig id="F10" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 6</label><caption><p id="P25"><italic>daf-2</italic> is required for various forms of <italic>C. elegans</italic> associative learning<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. <italic>daf-16</italic> is required for <italic>daf-2&#x02019;s</italic> improvements and extensions of abilities with age<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. <italic>daf-2</italic> mutants are defective for salt chemotaxis learning<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>, and <italic>daf-16</italic> is not involved in salt chemotaxis learning<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. Furthermore, salt learning utilizes a unique <italic>daf-2c</italic> isoform<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> in a <italic>daf-16</italic>-independent manner<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>, suggesting a learning mechanism distinct from the associative memory paradigms studied here. We are specifically interested in understanding how activation of DAF-16 results in the improved and extended abilities of <italic>daf-2</italic> mutants to carry out olfactory associative learning<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, short-term associative memory<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>, and long-term associative memory<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, all of which require <italic>daf-16</italic>. A) Chemotaxis index profile of wild type (N2) and <italic>daf-2</italic> animals at time points following memory training. B) RNAi knockdown of <italic>sod-3</italic>, a non-neuronal DAF-16-regulated target that influences lifespan, has no effect on the extended short-term associative memory (STAM) of <italic>daf-2</italic> mutants when treated with RNAi-feeding bacteria throughout the whole life (B) or only the post-developmental (adult-only) period (C, D) of the animal. <italic>daf-2</italic> worms treated with <italic>daf-16</italic> RNAi have defective STAM, as previously reported<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. E) Knockdown of the neuronal IIS candidate genes <italic>zip-5</italic> and <italic>best-23</italic> does not affect STAM. Time-courses showing the chemotaxis index for each time point are shown in D and E. Learning indices are shown in B, C, F, and G. B&#x02013;E) Two-way repeated measures ANOVA, Bonferroni post hoc tests. F) Treatment of <italic>daf-2</italic> worms with neuronal DAF-16 target RNAi does not affect short-term associative learning. G) Neuronal-RNAi sensitive worms (<italic>Punc-119::sid-1</italic>) in a wild-type background were treated only during adulthood with RNAi targeted against the neuronal DAF-16 target genes. (0h) Learning and 1 h short-term associative memory time points are shown. A&#x02013;G) Mean &#x000b1; SEM, *p &#x0003c; 0.05, **p &#x0003c; 0.01, ***p &#x0003c; 0.001, ****p &#x0003c; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f10"/></fig><fig id="F11" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 7</label><caption><p id="P26">A) Six adult mechanosensory neurons labeled by <italic>mec-4p::GFP</italic> were isolated for RNA-seq. B) Axon length from the cell body to the site of injury was measured in &#x000b5;m immediately after axotomy and 24 hours later. Regenerative capacity of wild-type PLM axons declines from day 1 to day 5 of adulthood. C) Day 5 wild-type animals regrow axons that are significantly shorter than in Day 1 animals. D) Axotomies of <italic>daf-2</italic> mutants grown on vector control, <italic>sod-3</italic>, or <italic>daf-16</italic> RNAi demonstrate that <italic>sod-3</italic>, a lifespan-regulating DAF-16 target, does not influence the axon regeneration capacity of <italic>daf-2</italic> worms at Day 5 of adulthood. E) <italic>fkh-9</italic> does not affect the regenerative capacity of <italic>daf-2</italic> axons on Day 1 of adulthood. F) <italic>fkh-9</italic> is not required for axon regeneration in Day 1 adults. B&#x02013;F) Mean &#x000b1; SEM, Fisher&#x02019;s exact test, *p &#x0003c; 0.05. G) Overexpression of the a and b isoforms of <italic>fkh-9</italic> in wild-type animals causes axonal structural defects. Rescuing <italic>fkh-9</italic> activity in the mechanosensory neurons of <italic>daf-2;fkh-9</italic> mutants results in severe beading and degeneration of axons.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f11"/></fig><fig id="F12" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 8</label><caption><p id="P27">Wormbase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org">www.wormbase.org</ext-link>) gene models for (A) <italic>fkh-9</italic> and (B) <italic>sod-3</italic> are shown with modENCODE data for DAF-16 ChIP-seq experiments. A) Primer sets for ChIP-qPCR are depicted. C) Posterior intestinal FKH-9::GFP expression is only modestly increased in <italic>daf-2</italic> compared to wild-type animals expressing <italic>fkh-9p::fkh-9::gfp</italic>. N= 25 animals.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f12"/></fig><fig id="F13" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 9</label><caption><p id="P28">A, B) Whole-life RNAi of <italic>fkh-9</italic> reduces <italic>daf-2</italic> STAM. C) RNAi knockdown of <italic>fkh-9</italic> exclusively during adulthood results in reduced <italic>daf-2</italic> STAM comparable to <italic>daf-16</italic> RNAi-treatment. D, E) <italic>daf-2;fkh-9</italic> mutants have reduced learning (tested immediately following STAM training) and STAM compared to <italic>daf-2</italic>. Mean &#x000b1; SEM, *p &#x0003c; 0.05, **p &#x0003c; 0.01, ***p &#x0003c; 0.001, ****p &#x0003c; 0.0001. Mean &#x000b1; SEM, *p &#x0003c; 0.05, **p &#x0003c; 0.01, ***p &#x0003c; 0.001, ****p &#x0003c; 0.0001. Time-courses showing the chemotaxis index for each time point are shown in B and E. Learning indices are shown in A, C, and D.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f13"/></fig><fig id="F14" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Fig 10</label><caption><p id="P29">Adult-only (A) or whole-life (B) <italic>fkh-9</italic> RNAi treatment increases matricide in <italic>daf-2</italic> worms. The cumulative % of animals dead as a result of bagging and/or exploding was recorded every other day. Two biological replicates were performed, with a representative experiment shown. C) Neuronal rescue of <italic>fkh-9</italic> in <italic>daf-2;fkh-9</italic> animals does not diminish the rate of vulval protrusions with age. N &#x02265; 60 per conditions for each experiment. D) Neuronal rescue of <italic>fkh-9</italic> does not restore longevity of the <italic>daf-2;fkh-9</italic> double mutant. <italic>daf-2</italic> median lifespan: 41 days, <italic>daf-2;fkh-9</italic> 20 days, <italic>daf-2;fkh-9;Punc-119::fkh-9</italic> 20 days. p &#x0003c; 0.0001 for <italic>daf-2</italic> vs. both <italic>daf-2;fkh-9</italic> and <italic>daf-2;fkh-9;Punc-119::fkh-9</italic>. N=112 worms per strain. Censor rate for <italic>daf-2</italic> 19%, <italic>daf-2;fkh-9</italic> 51%, <italic>daf-2;fkh-9;Punc-119::fkh-9</italic> 56%.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f14"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>1</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS741417-supplement-1.docx" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1325" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S6"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="P30">We thank the <italic>C. elegans</italic> Genetics Center for strains and Wormbase (WS250); L. Parsons for RNA-seq data support; J. Wiggins and the Lewis-Sigler High Throughput Sequencing Core Facility for RNA-seq support; C. DeCoste and the Flow Cytometry Facility for assistance; V. Yao for tissue prediction analysis; R. DiLoreto for chemotaxis assay analysis; Z. Gitai, the Murphy lab, and W. Mair for discussion. Funding was provided by a Keck Scholars Program fellowship (CTM), NIH Cognitive Aging R01 (CTM), and NRSA (RK), NRSA (RA), NSF (JL), and NJCBIR (VL) fellowships.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p id="P31"><bold>Author Contributions.</bold> CTM, RK, VL, and JL designed experiments. RK, VL, RA, JL, JA, and CTM performed experiments and analyzed data. RK, VL, and JL performed tissue isolation and RNA-seq. AW, RK, VL, and JL performed bioinformatics analysis. RK, VL, and RA performed short-term memory experiments. VL performed axon regeneration experiments. RK, VL, and CTM wrote the manuscript.</p></fn><fn id="FN3" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P32">The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genes that act downstream of DAF-16 to influence the lifespan of Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>424</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12845331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Corces-Zimmerman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin signaling and dietary restriction differentially influence the decline of learning and memory with age</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e1000372</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20502519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insulin/IGF1 signaling inhibits age-dependent axon regeneration</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2014</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24440228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sj&#x000f6;berg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanje</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin-like growth factor (IGF-1) as a stimulator of regeneration in the freeze-injured rat sciatic nerve</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1989</year><volume>485</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2720394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolkow</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvkun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of C. elegans life-span by insulinlike signaling in the nervous system</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11021802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Libina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tissue-specific activities of C. elegans DAF-16 in the regulation of lifespan</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14622602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleemann</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGF-&#x003b2; and insulin signaling regulate reproductive aging via oocyte and germline quality maintenance</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20946987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tepper</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PQM-1 complements DAF-16 as a key transcriptional regulator of DAF-2-mediated development and longevity</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2013</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23911329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Judy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct and indirect gene regulation by a life-extending FOXO protein in C. elegans: roles for GATA factors and lipid gene regulators</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><year>2013</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23312285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessinger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aging-dependent and -independent modulation of associative learning behavior by insulin/insulin-like growth factor-1 signal in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>J. Neurosci. Off. J. Soc. Neurosci</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>10894</fpage><lpage>10904</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tank</surname><given-names>EMH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spontaneous age-related neurite branching in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>J. Neurosci. Off. J. Soc. Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>9279</fpage><lpage>9288</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neurite sprouting and synapse deterioration in the aging Caenorhabditis elegans nervous system</article-title><source>J. Neurosci. Off. J. Soc. Neurosci</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>8778</fpage><lpage>8790</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chikina</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Huttenhower</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Troyanskaya</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global prediction of tissue-specific gene expression and context-dependent gene networks in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e1000417</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19543383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ewald</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dauer-independent insulin/IGF-1-signalling implicates collagen remodelling in longevity</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and culture of larval cells from C. elegans</article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e19505</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21559335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolation of specific neurons from C. elegans larvae for gene expression profiling</article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e112102</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25372608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IFTA-2 is a conserved cilia protein involved in pathways regulating longevity and dauer formation in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>J. Cell Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>4088</fpage><lpage>4100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apfeld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of lifespan by sensory perception in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>402</volume><fpage>804</fpage><lpage>809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10617200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>A-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New genes tied to endocrine, metabolic, and dietary regulation of lifespan from a Caenorhabditis elegans genomic RNAi screen</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2005</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16103914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The C. elegans TGF-beta Dauer pathway regulates longevity via insulin signaling</article-title><source>Curr. Biol. CB</source><year>2007</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1635</fpage><lpage>1645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17900898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lakhina</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide Functional Analysis of CREB/Long-Term Memory-Dependent Transcription Reveals Distinct Basal and Memory Gene Expression Programs</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2015</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25611510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Axon regeneration pathways identified by systematic genetic screening in C. elegans</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2011</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21943602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foxg1 regulates retinal axon pathfinding by repressing an ipsilateral program in nasal retina and by causing optic chiasm cells to exert a net axonal growth-promoting activity</article-title><source>Dev. Camb. Engl</source><year>2008</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>4081</fpage><lpage>4089</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rapid induction of genes associated with tissue protection and neural development in contused adult spinal cord after radial glial cell transplantation</article-title><source>J. Neurotrauma</source><year>2009</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19257808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CASY-1, an ortholog of calsyntenins/alcadeins, is essential for learning in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>5260</fpage><lpage>5265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18381821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoerndli</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A conserved function of C. elegans CASY-1 calsyntenin in associative learning</article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e4880</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19287492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of synaptic phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase in a behavioral learning response in C. elegans</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2014</year><volume>345</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25035490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ewald</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pan-neuronal expression of APL-1, an APP-related protein, disrupts olfactory, gustatory, and touch plasticity in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>J. Neurosci. Off. J. Soc. Neurosci</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>10156</fpage><lpage>10169</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammarlund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nix</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastiani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Axon regeneration requires a conserved MAP kinase pathway</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>323</volume><fpage>802</fpage><lpage>806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19164707</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ref-list><title>Extended Data References</title><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomioka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The insulin/PI 3-kinase pathway regulates salt chemotaxis learning in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2006</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16950159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insulin-like signaling and the neural circuit for integrative behavior in C. elegans</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2955</fpage><lpage>2960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17079685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessinger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aging-dependent and -independent modulation of associative learning behavior by insulin/insulin-like growth factor-1 signal in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>J. Neurosci. Off. J. Soc. Neurosci</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>10894</fpage><lpage>10904</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C. elegans positive olfactory associative memory is a molecularly conserved behavioral paradigm</article-title><source>Neurobiol. Learn. Mem</source><year>2014</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25108196</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Identification of neuronal IIS/FOXO targets requires neuronal isolation</title><p id="P33">A) Volcano plot of neuron-expressed relative to whole worm-expressed genes obtained by neuron-specific RNA sequencing of adult wild-type animals. B) Neuron-expressed and enriched genes are not influenced by cell isolation: treatment with the transcription inhibitor Actinomycin D affected only 0.22% of all neuronal genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). C) Tissue expression prediction of wild-type adult neuron-enriched genes. Mean &#x000b1; SEM. D) GO terms highlight the neuronal characteristics of both all and previously uncharacterized neuron-enriched genes. E) Embryonic<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>, larval<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>, and adult neuron-enriched genes and significant GO terms transition from developmental to neuronal and behavioral functions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 5</xref>); FDR&#x0003c;10% for all gene sets.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f1"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>RNA-seq transcriptional profile of isolated neurons reveals IIS/FOXO neuronal transcriptome</title><p id="P34">A) Volcano plot of <italic>daf-2</italic>-regulated, <italic>daf-16</italic>-dependent up- (red) and down-regulated (green) neuronal genes (p&#x0003c;0.05). B) Comparison of whole-worm (Class I)<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> vs neuronal-IIS/FOXO targets. P-values: hypergeometric distributions. C&#x02013;E) Short-term associative memory (STAM) assays. C) Schematic of STAM assay and chemotaxis profiles of <italic>daf-2</italic> treated with (C) <italic>sod-3</italic> or (D, E) neuronal IIS/FOXO target gene RNAi. D) Learning indices relative to control RNAi at 3h post-training of <italic>daf-2</italic> treated with adult-only (green) or whole life (blue) neuronal IIS/FOXO target gene RNAi. Mean &#x000b1; SEM, *p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01, ***p&#x0003c;0.001, ****p&#x0003c;0.0001, two-way repeated measures ANOVA, Bonferroni post hoc tests.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f2"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>FKH-9 is a direct target of DAF-16 and is expressed in mechanosensory neurons</title><p id="P35">A, B) <italic>daf-16</italic> is required for <italic>daf</italic>-2&#x02019;s enhanced Day 5 axon regeneration, Mean &#x000b1; SEM, *p&#x0003c;0.05, Fisher&#x02019;s exact test. C) Known larval regeneration genes are significantly enriched in the Day 1 adult mechanosensory transcriptome. 63 genes are both DAF-16 targets and expressed in mechanosensory neurons (&#x0003c;5%FDR). D) <italic>fkh-9</italic> mRNA levels are higher in aged <italic>daf-2</italic> compared to wild type in a <italic>daf-16</italic>-dependent manner. N=4 biological replicates, two-way ANOVA, Bonferroni post hoc tests. E) Chromatin immunoprecipitation of DAF-16::GFP worms with and without heat shock, which mobilizes DAF-16 into the nucleus. DAF-16 binds to the <italic>sod-3</italic> promoter but not its 3&#x02019; UTR, and to the <italic>fkh-9</italic> promoter at multiple locations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Extended Data Figure 8</xref>). Fold enrichment relative to wild-type (not expressing DAF-16::GFP) is shown (mean &#x000b1; SEM, two-tailed t-test, N=3 biological replicates). F) Neuronal FKH-9::GFP (<italic>fkh-9p::fkh-9::gfp</italic>) expression in <italic>daf-2</italic> compared to wild type. N=25 animals. Mean &#x000b1; SEM, two-tailed t-test. D&#x02013;F) *p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01, ***p&#x0003c;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f3"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>FKH-9 is required for <italic>daf-2's</italic> improved axon regeneration, short-term associative memory, and lifespan</title><p id="P36">A) <italic>fkh-9</italic> knockdown reduces axon regeneration of Day 5 <italic>daf-2</italic> mutants, as does <italic>daf-16</italic> knockdown. B, C) Neuronally-expressed <italic>fkh-9</italic> rescues Day 5 axon regeneration in <italic>daf-2;fkh-9</italic> mutants. Mean &#x000b1; SEM, *p&#x0003c;0.05, Fisher&#x02019;s exact test. D) <italic>fkh-9</italic> is required for <italic>daf-2&#x02019;s</italic> enhanced memory in adult-only RNAi-treated worms. E) Neuronally-expressed <italic>fkh-9</italic> rescues extended STAM in <italic>daf-2;fkh-9</italic> mutants with defective learning and memory. Mean &#x000b1; SEM, **p&#x0003c;0.01, ***p&#x0003c;0.001, ****p&#x0003c;0.0001, two-way repeated measures ANOVA, Bonferroni post hoc tests. F) Adult-specific <italic>fkh-9</italic> RNAi treatment reduces <italic>daf-2</italic> mutant lifespan. Median lifespan: control RNAi 42 days, <italic>fkh-9</italic> RNAi 21 days, <italic>daf-16</italic> RNAi 21 days. p&#x0003c;0.0001 for control RNAi vs. <italic>daf-16</italic> RNAi and control vs. <italic>fkh-9</italic> RNAi, log-rank test. N=144 worms per strain. G) IMP network analysis of DAF-16 neuronal target genes with STAM phenotypes (red circles).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms741417f4"/></fig></floats-group></article>