<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4465667</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26061739</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128181</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-54410</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Efficient Detection of Novel Nuclear Markers for Brassicaceae by Transcriptome Sequencing</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">NGS Primer Design for Brassicaceae</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stockenhuber</surname><given-names>Reinhold</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zoller</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu-Inatsugi</surname><given-names>Rie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gugerli</surname><given-names>Felix</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>Kentaro K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Widmer</surname><given-names>Alex</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>Martin C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label><addr-line>Institute of Evolutionary Biology and Environmental Studies, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label><addr-line>Genetic Diversity Centre, ETH Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff003"><label>3</label><addr-line>WSL Swiss Federal Research Institute, Birmensdorf, Switzerland</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff004"><label>4</label><addr-line>Institute of Integrative Biology, ETH Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Parida</surname><given-names>Swarup Kumar</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>National Institute of Plant Genome Research (NIPGR), INDIA</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AW KKS FG. Performed the experiments: RS RSI MCF. Analyzed the data: RS SZ MCF. Wrote the paper: RS SZ AW MCF.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>martin.fischer@env.ethz.ch</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e0128181</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Stockenhuber et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0128181.pdf"/><abstract><p>The lack of DNA sequence information for most non-model organisms impairs the design of primers that are universally applicable for the study of molecular polymorphisms in nuclear markers. Next-generation sequencing (NGS) techniques nowadays provide a powerful approach to overcome this limitation. We present a flexible and inexpensive method to identify large numbers of nuclear primer pairs that amplify in most Brassicaceae species. We first obtained and mapped NGS transcriptome sequencing reads from two of the distantly related Brassicaceae species, <italic>Cardamine hirsuta</italic> and <italic>Arabis alpina</italic>, onto the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> reference genome, and then identified short conserved sequence motifs among the three species bioinformatically. From these, primer pairs to amplify coding regions (nuclear protein coding loci, NPCL) and exon-primed intron-crossing sequences (EPIC) were developed. We identified 2,334 universally applicable primer pairs, targeting 1,164 genes, which provide a large pool of markers as readily usable genomic resource that will help addressing novel questions in the Brassicaceae family. Testing a subset of the newly designed nuclear primer pairs revealed that a great majority yielded a single amplicon in all of the 30 investigated Brassicaceae taxa. Sequence analysis and phylogenetic reconstruction with a subset of these markers on different levels of phylogenetic divergence in the mustard family were compared with previous studies. The results corroborate the usefulness of the newly developed primer pairs, e.g., for phylogenetic analyses or population genetic studies. Thus, our method provides a cost-effective approach for designing nuclear loci across a broad range of taxa and is compatible with current NGS technologies.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The study was funded by the Swiss National Science Foundation (Sinergia project CRSI33_127155), ProDoc PDFMP3_137084 and University Research Priority Program in Systems Biology/Functional Genomics. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="19"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>Sequence data is available at GenBank (KM403211-KM403369), raw reads of Arabis alpina and Cardamine hirsuta are available at the NCBI sequence read archive (SAMN03014707 and SAMN03014708), sequence alignments for C. hirsuta, A. alpina, as well as concatenated alignments for phylogenetic analysis are available at the Dryad repository (doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.dx.org/10.5061/dryad.63j2j">10.5061/dryad.63j2j</ext-link>).</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>Sequence data is available at GenBank (KM403211-KM403369), raw reads of Arabis alpina and Cardamine hirsuta are available at the NCBI sequence read archive (SAMN03014707 and SAMN03014708), sequence alignments for C. hirsuta, A. alpina, as well as concatenated alignments for phylogenetic analysis are available at the Dryad repository (doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.dx.org/10.5061/dryad.63j2j">10.5061/dryad.63j2j</ext-link>).</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>For decades, evolutionary biologists have relied on a limited set of marker regions for DNA sequencing-based studies in plant population genetics, phylogenetics and phylogeography. Most often, organellar DNA [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] and nuclear ribosomal DNA (nrDNA) regions [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] have been used for these purposes. The widespread use of these marker regions is primarily a consequence of the availability of conserved primers for their amplification in a wide range of species, e.g. for the chloroplast genes <italic>rbc</italic>L [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], <italic>mat</italic>K [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and for intergenic spacers, such as plastid <italic>trn</italic>L-F [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and nrDNA internal transcribed spacer (ITS) regions [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Uniparental inheritance, single-locus origin and low mutation rates, in the case of organellar DNA, allow direct sequencing of PCR products because no heterozygosity is expected in these regions. For nrDNA, concerted evolution among gene family members reduces heterogeneity and facilitates direct sequencing of PCR products [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Despite their widespread use, organellar genomes have several disadvantages for evolutionary studies. Uniparental inheritance and lack of recombination (but see [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]), as well as low mutation rates in plants [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] present major limitations for inferring evolutionary history, because even if multiple markers are sequenced, they reflect variation at only a single locus and additionally lack information about one of the parental species (i.e. the pollen donor) in hybrid or in polyploid species [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Concerted evolution of multi-copy nrDNA markers, such as the internal transcribed spacer regions (ITS), may produce pseudogenes [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], remain incomplete [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] or lead to the loss of one parental copy in hybrids [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], which may also bias results in evolutionary studies. The limitations of these markers strongly suggest that evidence from multiple and unlinked nuclear markers, which are not affected by these limitations, should be used. Using such data may provide improved resolution and phylogenetic congruence among different loci may indicate that the phylogeny represents the underlying species history, as shown e.g. by Fink <italic>et al</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>In addition to DNA sequencing, other types of molecular markers have also been used for multilocus analyses, including microsatellites and amplified fragment length-polymorphisms (AFLPs). Their specific advantages and disadvantages have been thoroughly reviewed elsewhere (see[<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]). In general, these markers cannot easily be compared among distantly related species, as is done in many phylogenetic or comparative phylogeographic studies, or harness the information content of nucleotide variation, and therefore do not alleviate the need for multiple, independent DNA sequence-based markers. Moreover, nuclear DNA markers also allow addressing more complex evolutionary questions [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], for instance the detection of hybrid speciation [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] or rapid radiation events [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>In the age of next-generation sequencing (NGS), multiple approaches can be taken for characterizing low-copy nuclear markers in a chosen group of organisms. Mining of genome sequence data, for example, has proven useful for the identification of shared single-copy nuclear genes in model organisms of the angiosperms [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. It has been shown, that the merging of newly generated and publicly available sequence information allows to design primer pairs for closely related taxa [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], as well as for highly diverged groups [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. However, for many study species or groups, no public datasets are available and existing data may be mislabeled [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] or erroneous [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Hence, it may be most valuable to generate <italic>de-novo</italic> sequence data, in combination with suitable reference genomes and the development of a dedicated bioinformatics workflow for primer or probe design, for characterizing multiple low-copy nuclear gene markers for population genetic, phylogenetic or phylogeographic analyses in a taxonomic group of interest.</p><p>We selected the mustard family (Brassicaceae) to evaluate novel approaches for the genome-wide characterization of nuclear gene markers and efficient primer design. In addition, we provide a database of the newly developed nuclear markers that are ready to use for a broad range of taxa. The Brassicaceae are ideally suited as a study group because multiple high-quality reference genomes for the model species <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> are available ([<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arabidopsis.org">http://arabidopsis.org</ext-link>). Furthermore, phylogenetic relationships in the mustard family have been extensively studied using a range of markers, including several nuclear genes (e.g. [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]).</p><p>The main goal of the present study was to characterize low-copy nuclear gene markers on a genome-wide scale in the mustard family. To reach this goal, we first developed a powerful primer design approach for the amplification of markers across this phylogenetically and ecologically highly diverse Brassicaceae family. Second, we established a large database of ready to use nuclear Brassicaceae markers. And finally we validated the suitability of a subset of markers for PCR amplification, Sanger sequencing and phylogenetic reconstruction to highlight their usefulness.</p></sec><sec id="sec002"><title>Material and Methods</title><p>To detect conserved sequence regions within the Brassicaceae, we used the available high- quality reference genome of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and additionally sequenced the transcriptomes of two divergent Brassicaceae species, <italic>Cardamine hirsuta</italic> and <italic>Arabis alpina</italic>. Sequencing reads from these two species were then aligned against the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> reference genome. These three species represent different lineages of the Brassicaceae family and hence should allow to detect shared, conserved regions suitable for designing universally applicable Brassicaceae primers. <italic>Cardamine hirsuta</italic> as well as <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> are members of lineage I according to Al-Shehbaz [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], and diverged relatively early. <italic>Arabis alpina</italic> belongs to the Arabideae, the largest tribe of Brassicaceae [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], which is part of the expanded lineage II sensu Franzke <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Dating the evolutionary history of Brassicaceae is particularly difficult, mostly due to few fossil records [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and rapid radiation events [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. A recent study [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] dated the split of lineage I and II to 27 million years ago (mya). Divergence time between <italic>Cardamine</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> has been estimated to be at least 13 mya [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Therefore, the selection of these three different taxa reflects a divergence of nearly 30 million years and hence they cover a broad evolutionary range across the Brassicaceae, which allowed us to identify conserved regions among these species. The workflow is presented in <xref rid="pone.0128181.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref> and explained in detail below.</p><fig id="pone.0128181.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128181.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Workflow for the identification of conserved nucleotide sequences in multiple Brassicaceae species and subsequent primer design.</title><p>Blue boxes refer to the three major steps in the workflow, white boxes indicate the general steps taken Explanations on the right provide specific results from this study.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128181.g001"/></fig><sec id="sec003"><title>Plant material, RNA extraction, normalization and sequencing</title><p>To gather as much of the exome as possible, 24 individuals from six populations of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>alpina</italic> and 28 individuals from nine populations of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>hirsuta</italic> were collected at different localities in Switzerland, to which we applied four growth chamber (K&#x000e4;lte 3000, Switzerland) stress treatments (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). "Drought" treated plants were harvested after seven days of water deprivation; "cold1" treated plants were exposed to 4&#x000b0;C for 24h, and "cold2" treated plants for two days to -6&#x000b0;C, while "heat" treatment involved two exposures to 40&#x000b0;C for 2h on two consecutive days. Since the localities of sampling are not nature reserves, and collected plants are neither protected nor endangered in these regions, we did not require sampling permits. This applies to all plant material used in our study.</p><p>mRNA from each species and treatment was extracted with RNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen, Netherlands) separately, and diluted to 300 ng/&#x003bc;l before they were equimolar pooled. Pooled mRNA was then reverse-transcribed with Super SMART PCR cDNA synthesis kit (Clontech, Takara Bio Europe SAS, France) in combination with Super Script III Reverse Transcriptase (Life Technologies, Invitrogen, USA). cDNA was amplified with iProof High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase (BioRad, USA) following the Super SMART protocol, normalized with TRIMMER (Evrogen, Russia) and sequenced on a Genome Sequencer FLX (GS-FLX; Roche, Switzerland) at the Functional Genomics Center Zurich (FGCZ; Zurich, Switzerland). Library synthesis was done with the GS-FLX Titanium Rapid Library Preparation Kit, and sequencing was then performed according to the Roche GS-FLX XLR70 Titanium emPCR and sequencing manuals. Each sample was sequenced twice on half a picotiter plate.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Read mapping, identification, primer design</title><p>The GS-FLX raw sequencing reads (available from the NCBI sequence read archive, accession numbers SAMN03014707 and SAMN03014708) were extracted with the sff_extract tool and quality-controlled using custom-made Perl scripts. All raw read files had acceptable quality (average phred quality score above 20 to at least read position 350) and read length distributions (few short reads, high peak towards the long read lengths), and were thus included in the analysis. Reads were mapped onto the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> chromosomes [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] with the runMapping tool included in the Roche 454 software suite. Sequence alignments for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>hirsuta</italic> and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>alpina</italic> are available at the Dryad repository doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.dx.org/10.5061/dryad.63j2j">10.5061/dryad.63j2j</ext-link>. Default mapping parameters were used except for minimum overlap length (set to 80%) and minimum overlap identity (set to 95%). The mapping output (ACE file) was converted to SAM format using the tools toAmos, bank-transact, and bank2contig from AMOS [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</p><p>Using samtools [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] and custom-made Perl scripts, we then extracted start/end position information and nucleotide sequences for mapped regions at least 20 bp long and with at least 2x coverage per species. We decided for a low coverage to make our approach also suitable for smaller datasets. The mappings for <italic>A</italic>. <italic>alpina</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>hirsuta</italic> were then compared with Perl scripts, sequences which mapped to the same locations in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> and were conserved in all three species were extracted. These sequences were subsequently filtered for sequence pairs that had a minimal distance of 300 bp and a maximal distance of 700 bp on the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> reference genome, to adjust the length to current NGS sequencing platforms. These sequences were then used as input for primer3 v2.2.3 [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], to design forward and reverse PCR primers with lengths of 18 to 27 bp and annealing temperatures between 58 and 62&#x000b0;C. The following primer3 options were changed from default: PRIMER_MIN_SIZE = 18, PRIMER_OPT_SIZE = 20, PRIMER_MAX_SIZE = 27, PRIMER_MIN_TM = 58.0, PRIMER_OPT_TM = 60, PRIMER_MAX_TM = 62.0.</p><p>Our primer pairs were not <italic>a priori</italic> targeting exonic or intronic regions but instead targeted conserved regions across the three study species suitable for primer design and sufficiently close for PCR amplification and subsequent sequencing. Primer pairs were then tested <italic>in silico</italic> for uniqueness on the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> genome, using BLAST+ v2.2.23 [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and custom-made Perl scripts using the following conditions: Primers were allowed to map to the genome with at most two nucleotide mismatches, and the maximal potential fragment size was set at 3,500 bp. Primer pairs potentially producing more than one fragment were discarded. Remaining primer pairs were annotated with the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> annotation from TAIR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arabidopsis.org">http://arabidopsis.org</ext-link>).</p><p>A gene ontology (GO) analysis was performed to infer the biological functions of the annotated genes using DAVID [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] with false discovery rate (FDR) set to &#x02264; 0.05.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Primer tests and sample selection</title><p>A subset of the primer pairs was then tested for amplification success and phylogenetic resolution in 30 Brassicaceae species covering the three major "lineages" [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</p><p>We used herbarium specimens (collection Matthias Baltisberger, ETH Zurich) complemented by freshly collected and silica-gel dried leaves of plants from the University of Zurich Botanical Garden (<xref rid="pone.0128181.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0128181.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128181.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Species and samples used in this study for primer testing and sequencing.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0128181.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0128181.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession Name</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herbarium Number</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collector and Date</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Origin</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequencing</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lineage</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aethionema saxatile</italic> (L.) R.Br.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CH0Z-20100490</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steiger P., <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Switzerland, San Salvatore TI 420 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">outgroup</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic> (L.) O'Kane et Al-Shehbaz</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fischer M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.90919&#x000b0; N 9.39207&#x000b0;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Col-0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana (</italic>L.) Heynh. in Holl. &#x00026; Heyn.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabis alpina</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14820</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2200&#x02013;2400 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabis bellidifolia</italic> Crantz s.l.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14821</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2200&#x02013;2400 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabis ciliata</italic> Clairv.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gugerli F.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabis caerulea</italic> All.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14816</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2200&#x02013;2400 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabis subcoriacea</italic> Gren.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14814</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2200&#x02013;2400 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Barbarea vulgaris</italic> R. Br.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XX0Z-19820365</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K&#x000e4;ser U., 2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Botanical Garden Jaen, France</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Biscutella laevigata</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14815</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2200&#x02013;2400 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">outgroup</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Boechera holboellii</italic> (Hornem.) &#x000c1;.L&#x000f6;ve &#x00026; D.L&#x000f6;ve</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brassica nigra</italic> (L.) W. D. J. Koch</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XX0Z-20010028</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K&#x000e4;ser U., 2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Botanical Gardens University Bonn-Germany</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Braya humilis</italic> (C. A. Meyer) B. L. Robinson</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marhold K.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cardamine alpina</italic> Willd.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14836</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2200&#x02013;2400 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cardamine amara</italic> L. s.str.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14813</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2100 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAY1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cardamine hirsuta</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shimizu-Inatsugi R.,</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">University of Zurich, Switzerland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cardamine resedifolia</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14818</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2200&#x02013;2400 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cochlearia officinalis</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XX0Z-20001358</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schneeberger E.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark, Bornholm, Teglkas, Shore</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Diplotaxis tenuifolia</italic> (L.) DC.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XX0Z-20000361</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K&#x000e4;ser U., 2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Giardino Botanico Alpino Rezia-Bormio</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Draba aizoides</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14830</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2200&#x02013;2400 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">outgroup</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Erysimum rhaeticum</italic> (Hornem.) DC.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XX0Z-19770612</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K&#x000e4;ser U., 2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Botanical Garden St. Gallen-Switzerland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hesperis matronalis</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14807</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 1600 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hornungia alpina</italic> (Siev.) O.Appel</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14817</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2300 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hornungia alpina</italic> subsp. <italic>brevicaulis</italic> (Hoppe) O.Appel</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14834</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2200&#x02013;2400 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Iberis amara</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XX0Z-20100109</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K&#x000e4;ser U., 2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EX BG Kiel; University Konstanz-Germany</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Kernera saxatilis</italic> (L.) Sweet</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14819</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davos, Switzerland, 2200&#x02013;2400 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lepidium campestre</italic> (L.) R. Br.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XX0Z-19963427</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K&#x000e4;ser U., 2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Matthiola valesiaca</italic> Boiss.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CH0Z-20060845</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Affeltranger K., 2006</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Switzerland, Binn VS 1280 m asl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rorippa pyrenaica</italic> (All.) Rchb.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shimizu-Inatsugi R., 2007</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Botanic Garden Zurich, Switzerland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Thlaspi ochroleucum</italic> Boiss. &#x00026; Heldr.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z/ZT MB 14807</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baltisberger M., 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Switzerland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02611;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02610;</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>The use of each species is divided into PCR, sequencing, family, "lineage" and genus. PCR indicates use for PCR amplification and sequencing indicates sequencing of the species, respectively. Family, "lineage" and genus refer to the application of species sequences at the three taxonomic levels that were phylogenetically tested in this study. The term "outgroup" refers to a taxon being sequenced and used as outgroup for phylogenetic analysis at a specific relationship level.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>DNA was extracted with DNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen), quantified with NanoDrop (ThermoFisher Scientific, USA) and Qubit (Invitrogen), and diluted to 50 ng/&#x003bc;l. Of the 2,334 identified primer pairs, 48 were selected (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6 Table</xref>) with a balanced number of EPIC and NPCL regions and even distribution across the reference genome.</p><p>PCR reactions consisted of 6.5 &#x003bc;l dH<sub>2</sub>O, 3 &#x003bc;l GoTaq buffer (Promega, USA), 1.5 &#x003bc;l MgCl<sub>2</sub> (25mM), 1.5 &#x003bc;l dNTPs (2.5 mM), 0.75 &#x003bc;l forward primer, 0.75 &#x003bc;l reverse primer, 0.075 &#x003bc;l GoTaq (Promega), and 1 &#x003bc;l DNA (50 ng/&#x003bc;l). PCR conditions were designed to allow both Sanger sequencing and tagging for next-generation sequencing (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). Conditions for primer pairs amplified here were 94&#x000b0;C for 3 min, followed by 32 cycles of 94&#x000b0;C for 30 s, 58&#x000b0;C for 30 s, 72&#x000b0;C for 30 s, and 72&#x000b0;C for 7 min. PCRs were performed on Labcycler Basic (Sensoquest, Germany) and GeneAmp PCR System 9700 (Life Technologies, Invitrogen, USA). PCR amplifications were checked on 1% agarose gels in 1x TBE buffer. Single bands were counted as successful amplifications, whereas double bands, complex banding patterns or lack of amplification products were counted as failed amplifications.</p><p>We tested the newly designed primer pairs at different levels of phylogenetic relationships (i.e. family, "lineage" and genus). Overall, we amplified 13 nuclear marker regions (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6 Table</xref>) to reconstruct phylogenetic relationships among selected members of the Brassicaceae family.</p><p>The target species and primers are summarized in <xref rid="pone.0128181.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0128181.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6 Table</xref>. First, for the family-wide phylogeny, we chose 15 species that represent the depth of the mustard family: species from three "lineages" (I, II, and III) accepted in Brassicaceae, several species that are not assigned to "lineages" and basal taxa <italic>sensu</italic> Al-Shehbaz [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Six NPCLs with low sequence divergence between the mapping species and two EPIC markers containing two short introns with more polymorphic sites were used. Second, we selected &#x0201c;lineage I&#x0201d; of Brassicaceae <italic>sensu</italic> Al-Shehbaz [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] for our analysis at the "lineage" level using seven species, one NPCL region, two EPIC markers with a single intron, and three EPIC markers with two introns. Here, we focused on sequencing success and divergence of different types of loci. Third, <italic>Arabis</italic> was selected for the evaluation of PCR success and phylogeny reconstruction at the genus level, using five <italic>Arabis</italic> species and <italic>Draba aizoides</italic> as outgroup, and four primer pairs (one NPCL, two EPIC markers with two introns, one EPIC marker containing three introns).</p><p>Successfully amplified PCR products were purified using Exonuclease I and Fastap (Thermo Scientific) at 37&#x000b0;C for 45 min, followed by enzyme inactivation at 80&#x000b0;C for 15 min. Sanger sequencing was performed in 10 &#x003bc;l reaction volumes using 1 &#x003bc;l purified PCR product, 0.5 &#x003bc;l BigDye v3.1 (Applied Biosystems, USA), 1.9 &#x003bc;l sequencing buffer (5x concentration), 5.6 &#x003bc;l ddH<sub>2</sub>O and 1 &#x003bc;l of the sequencing primer (10 &#x003bc;M). Cycle sequencing reactions were performed with the following conditions: 60 s at 96&#x000b0;C followed by 35 cycles of 10 s at 95&#x000b0;C, 5 s at 50&#x000b0;C, and 4 min at 60&#x000b0;C. Reactions were cleaned using the BigDye Xterminator Purification kit according to manufacturer protocol (Applied Biosystems). Samples were analyzed on an ABI 3130xl DNA Analyser (Applied Biosystems).</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Phylogenetic analyses</title><p>We used Geneious v7.0.4. (Biomatters Ltd.) for quality check, trimming and sequence analysis. Sequence data are available in GenBank (accession numbers KM403211-KM403369). Alignments were created with mafft v7.0.17b [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], with the alignment strategy set to auto in the case of NPCL regions and single-intron covering EPIC markers, whereas E-INS-i, an iterative refinement method [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], was selected for EPIC markers with more than one intron. Alignments were manually inspected and adjusted if necessary. Stretches of monomeric repeats of over 8-bp length, microsatellite regions and ambiguous intron alignments were removed before analysis. Heterozygous sites were treated as ambiguities following IUPAC-IUB [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Successfully sequenced fragments were blasted in order to confirm the amplification of correct regions.</p><p>Aligned sequences were concatenated and analyzed using Sequence Matrix v1.7.8 [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and are available at the Dryad repository (doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.dx.org/10.5061/dryad.63j2j">10.5061/dryad.63j2j</ext-link>). Phylogenetic trees were calculated in Geneious v7.0.4. using the implemented RAxML v7.2.8. [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] for maximum likelihood analyses, and the MrBayes 3.2.1. [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] tool for Bayesian inference.</p><p>All concatenated alignments were calculated with partitions and substitution models according to the single markers. Family, "lineage" and genus approaches were run with the following setup for maximum likelihood analyses: For RAxML we used the favoured GTR substitution model by the jModelTest [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] AIC criterion. 1,000 bootstrap replicates with the setting "fast bootstrap calculation with detection of best ML tree" were performed to calculate bootstrap support (BS). The MrBayes substitution model to obtain posterior probabilities (PP) was also selected via AIC criterion in jModeltest. We ran 10,000,000 generations with random seed, a burn-in of 500,000 generations and 4 MCMC chains, three heated and one cold chain. Heated chain temperature was set to the default value of 0.2. Subsampling frequency in all MrBayes runs was set to 2,000, and outgroups were selected before analysis.</p><p>We compared the markers amplified by our primer pairs with previously used loci in terms of nucleotide diversity and parsimony-informative characters (PIC), which were assessed via MEGA5 [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Nucleotide diversity was calculated using "Mean Diversity in Entire Population" and PIC content was extracted from the "Sequence Data Explorer". GenBank accessions (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5 Table</xref>) of the nrDNA marker ITS, and the cpDNA regions <italic>mat</italic>K and <italic>ndh</italic>F of species from genera also used in our study were retrieved and aligned as described above.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec007"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec008"><title>Read mapping, identification, primer design</title><p>A total of 1,084,601 and 985,013 sequencing reads were generated for <italic>A</italic>. <italic>alpina</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>hirsuta</italic>, respectively. 524,015 (48.3%) of the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>alpina</italic> reads mapped to <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> and 488,249 (93.2%) had a mapping quality above 30, for <italic>C</italic>. <italic>hirsuta</italic>, respective numbers were 578,373 (58.7%) and 553,846 (95.8%) reads. Read length was between 40 and 1,188 nucleotides (median = 352, mean = 329).</p><p>We designed 2,334 primer pairs in 1,164 genes from short conserved anchor regions that are shared between <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>hirsuta</italic> and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>alpina</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6 Table</xref>). The mean length of these loci, compared to <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic>, was 535 bp (range: 339&#x02013;787 bp) and their concatenated length equalled 1.23 Mbp.</p><p>The GO-term analysis revealed that genes amplified with our primer pairs cover many different pathways. Among the most overrepresented GO-terms were response to metal ions, response to abiotic stimuli, photosynthesis and carbohydrate biosynthesis (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Primer tests and sample selection</title><p>PCR amplification success for 48 selected primer pairs in 30 members of the Brassicaceae family was on average 79.4% and varied between 50% and 100% for the different primer pairs, and between 35% and 100% depending on the species. We observed a trend that more diverged species had lower amplification success. In six cases, corresponding to 0.4% of all 1,440 PCRs performed, we detected two amplification products (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Table</xref>), which were counted as failed amplifications. The specificity of the primer pairs in successfully sequenced products was 100%, all 236 amplicons did match the targeted genes in a BLAST search.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p>The phylogenetic tree at the family level based on eight concatenated nuclear markers (3,154 bp in total) showed good support for the three major Brassicaceae lineages (<xref rid="pone.0128181.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). "Lineages I", "II" and "III" were strongly supported (BS &#x02265; 81; PP &#x02265; 0.98), but basal nodes of "lineage II" were not well resolved with either maximum likelihood or posterior probability inferences. The obtained phylogeny was compared with Couvreur <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and with the BrassiBase phylogeny [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Overall, we obtained good support for all branches identified in these studies. Incongruences were found in the placement of <italic>Cochlearia</italic>, as well as the non-basal position of <italic>Biscutella</italic> in our results, whereas traditionally the corresponding tribe (<italic>Biscutelleae</italic>) was placed as a sister to all major lineages.</p><fig id="pone.0128181.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128181.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic inference at the family level.</title><p>Best Maximum Likelihood phylogram of concatenated gene sequences are shown. Bootstrap support values and posterior probabilities are given above or below the corresponding branches, respectively. Values below 50/0.5 are omitted. "Lineage"-brackets refer to lineages <italic>sensu</italic> Al-Shehbaz (2012). Percentage amplification success per species is given in brackets next to each species name.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128181.g002"/></fig><p>The concatenated dataset for phylogenetic analysis at the "lineage" level was 2,407 bp in length. <italic>Barbarea vulgaris</italic>, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>hirsuta</italic> and <italic>Rorippa pyrenaica</italic> formed one well-supported clade, (<xref rid="pone.0128181.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>; BS &#x02265; 99; PP = 1.00), <italic>Boechera holboelli</italic> and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> form another (<xref rid="pone.0128181.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>; BS &#x02265; 99; PP = 1.00).</p><fig id="pone.0128181.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128181.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic inference at the "lineage" level.</title><p>Best Maximum Likelihood phylogram of concatenated gene sequences are shown. Bootstrap support values and posterior probabilities are given above or below the corresponding branches, respectively. Values below 50/0.5 are omitted. Percentage amplification success per species is given in brackets next to each species name.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128181.g003"/></fig><p>At the genus level, highly variable EPIC markers with multiple introns, as well as conserved regions, were sequenced. Most of the intron alignments had to be removed from the final alignment because of ambiguities. <italic>Arabis subcoriacea</italic>, <italic>A</italic>. <italic>ciliata</italic> and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>bellidifolia</italic> were grouped together with high support (BS = 76, PP = 0.96; <xref rid="pone.0128181.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0128181.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128181.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic inference at the genus level.</title><p>Best Maximum Likelihood phylogram of concatenated gene sequences are shown. B Bootstrap support values and posterior probabilities are given above or below the corresponding branches, respectively. Values below 50/0.5 are omitted. Percentage amplification success per species is given in brackets next to each species name.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0128181.g004"/></fig><p>A comparison between markers used in this study and commonly applied markers ITS, <italic>ndh</italic>F and <italic>mat</italic>K at all three phylogenetic levels based on alignments revealed high variation in nucleotide diversity and PIC content of our markers. These values were always ranging between the levels of the compared ITS and plastid markers (<xref rid="pone.0128181.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0128181.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128181.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Details on alignments and markers used in our study as well as often-used markers at three taxonomic levels.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0128181.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0128181.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bra254</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bra264</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bra637</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bra813</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bra1258</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bra1511</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bra1693</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bra2187</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITS</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mat</italic>K</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ndh</italic>F</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Marker structure</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">e</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">e</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">e</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ii</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">e</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">e</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">e</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ii</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nrDNA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cpDNA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cpDNA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No. of sequences</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sequencing success</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.30%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.70%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.70%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.30%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.30%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.00%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.70%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alignment length (bp)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">398</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">471</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">326</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">427</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">430</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">399</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">296</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">599</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">707</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">725</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PIC</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PIC %</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.60%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.10%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.70%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.70%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.20%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.80%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.50%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.00%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.10%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Nucleotide diversity</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.147</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.154</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>GC content (%)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.40%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.20%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.60%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.90%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.60%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.50%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.90%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.00%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.00%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.70%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.50%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Outgroup</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Biscutella</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aethionema</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Biscutella</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aethionema</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Biscutella</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Biscutella</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aethionema</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aethionema</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Substitution model</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G+I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G+I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G+I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G+I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G+I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G+I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>"Lineage I"</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bra264</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bra406</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bra813</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bra1709</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bra1933</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bra2187</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ITS</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>mat</italic>K</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>ndh</italic>F</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Marker structure</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">e</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ii</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ii</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">i</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">i</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ii</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nrDNA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cpDNA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cpDNA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No. of sequences</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sequencing success</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.50%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.50%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alignment length (bp)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">470</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">449</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">480</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">515</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">599</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">725</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">651</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PIC</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PIC %</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.10%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.10%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.60%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Nucleotide diversity</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>GC content (%)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.00%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.40%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.70%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.70%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.40%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.10%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.60%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.90%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.70%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Outgroup</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Biscutella</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Biscutella</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Biscutella</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Biscutella</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Biscutella</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Biscutella</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Substitution model</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G+I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HKY+I (GTR+I)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F81 (GTR)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Genus</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bra264</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bra320</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bra813</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Bra1210</italic></bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ITS</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Marker structure</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">e</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">iiii</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ii</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ii</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nrDNA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No. of sequences</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sequencing success</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.30%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.70%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alignment length (bp)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">470</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">451</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">548</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">528</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">617</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PIC</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PIC %</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Nucleotide diversity</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>GC content (%)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.80%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.60%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.00%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.20%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.70%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Outgroup</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Draba</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Draba</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Draba</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Draba</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Substitution model</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTR+G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>Marker structure refers to structure of amplified fragment (e = exon, i = one intron in the fragment, ii = two introns in the fragment, iii = three introns in the fragment). Sequencing success is the percentage of obtained, readable sequences. PIC refers to number of parsimony-informative characters in an alignment. PIC % shows the percentage of parsimony-informative sites within alignments. Substitution model refers to the applied substitution model for phylogenetic inference; values in brackets refer to alternative substitution model used in RAxML. Asterisk indicates that information is based on TAIR10.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec011"><title>Discussion</title><p>The combination of high-throughput transcriptome sequencing in two distantly related Brassicaceae species and bioinformatics analysis in combination with the high quality <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> reference genome allowed us to identify 2,334 primer pairs for nuclear markers located in 1,164 different genic regions. A GO overrepresentation analysis (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>) revealed that responses to abiotic factors, such as responses to ions, were among the most overrepresented terms among these genes. The validation of a subset of primer pairs revealed that they can successfully be used for phylogenetic analyses at different taxonomic levels across the highly diverse mustard family. Other valuable features of the here provided new markers aside from their number are i) the possibility to choose levels of variability in amplified regions (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6 Table</xref>), and ii) to generate extensive sequence information for detailed analysis (up to 1.23 Mb length with all markers developed in this study). Thus, the published list of primer pairs may be of great value to studies of ecological genetics, adaptive trait evolution and population genetics in Brassicaceae.</p><p>Most previous studies that developed primer pairs amplifying across multiple species (cross-amplifying) focussed on specific markers, such as EPICs [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], nuclear protein coding loci NPCLs [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] or 3'UTR-anchored primers [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], depending on the scope of their scientific interest (<xref rid="pone.0128181.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Among our 2,334 primer pairs are numerous EPIC, NPCL and UTR-anchored markers that were jointly identified in a single workflow, which greatly enhances the utility of our method and the supplied primer list (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6 Table</xref>). Because of the wide range of nucleotide variation that can be detected with different markers, partly dependent on their amplification of coding versus con-coding regions, they can be used for phylogenetic analyses at various taxonomic levels, but also for phylogeographic and population genetic studies [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="pone.0128181.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128181.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Comparison of our approach and other publications with similar scopes mentioned in our study.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0128181.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0128181.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taxon range</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target loci</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of loci found</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard PCR conditions</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length (bp)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Li <italic>et al</italic>. (2007)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Order (Arctinopterygii)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">database mining</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPCL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e; 800</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Townsend <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Order (Squamata)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">database mining</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPCL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 700</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Chenuil <italic>et al</italic>. (2010)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subkingdom (Eumetazoa)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">database mining</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPIC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. A.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Li <italic>et al</italic>. (2010)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infraclass (Teleostei)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">database mining</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPIC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207&#x02013;324</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Curto <italic>et al</italic>. (2012)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family (Lamiaceae)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">database mining</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPIC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">362&#x02013;1717</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Shen <italic>et al</italic>. (2013)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subphylum (Vertebrata)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">database mining</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPCL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes (nested PCR)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">510&#x02013;1650</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Salas-Leiva <italic>et al</italic>. (2014)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Order (Cycadales)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">database mining</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPIC &#x00026; UTR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259&#x02013;1890</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tonnabel <italic>et al</italic>. (2014)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus (<italic>Leucadendron</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">database mining &#x00026; RNAseq</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPCL &#x00026; UTR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277&#x02013;796</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>This study</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family (Brassicaceae)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">database mining &#x00026; RNAseq</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPCL &#x00026; EPIC &#x00026; UTR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,334</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">339&#x02013;787</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p>Target loci indicate which fragments were targeted, standard PCR conditions indicates the availability of a uniform PCR protocol for all markers, length refers to fragment length of the regions found in a study. No. of loci found refers to the number of detected primer pairs or loci in the respective study.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A key aspect for the widespread use of the new primer pairs is their cross-species applicability. Our extensive tests revealed a PCR amplification success of 79.4% across a broad taxonomic range, and 99.6% of the amplified products showed single PCR bands, thus confirming the high specificity of the developed primers beyond the three initially sequenced taxa. As expected, amplification success varied between 100% in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic>, which was used as a reference species, and 35% in <italic>Aethionema saxatile</italic>, which is only sister to the core Brassicaceae. Across closely related taxa to the study species, a very high number of successful PCR reactions was obtained. <italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic> provided well-defined single bands in 96% of the tested primer pairs; the respective rates were 90&#x02013;98% (mean 94%) for four included members of <italic>Cardamine</italic> and 90&#x02013;98% (mean 94.8%) for the five tested species of <italic>Arabis</italic>. Overall, a limited taxon sampling can thus be sufficient to identify large numbers of conserved primer pairs suitable for studying a wide diversity of species. Moreover, the applicability of these primer pairs is not restricted to the lineages represented in the study, but may extend significantly beyond the studied species, as shown in <xref rid="pone.0128181.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>.</p><p>Lower amplification success for primer pairs in taxa that are phylogenetically distant to the studied species has also been reported by other studies, with success rates of 10.7% in the Lamiaceae [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] or 8.6% in Cycadales [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In our study, 10.4% of the tested primer pairs could be amplified in all 29 tested core Brassicaceae, and 6.25% in all 30 Brassicaceae. These percentages, if extended to the whole developed set of primer pairs would result in 244 primer pairs amplifying single PCR products in all core Brassicaceae or 147 primer pairs in all Brassicaceae.</p><p>Of further importance for the use of primers is that they amplify PCR products of suitable length for sequencing. While many studies report primers that amplify products &#x0003e; 1 kb long, we focused on relatively short amplification products in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic>. This species has a much smaller genome than many other members of the Brassicaceae, amplicon sizes, especially for regions including introns, may thus often be undersized estimates. Nevertheless, many of our relatively short PCR products can be sequenced either in part or across their entire length not only with Sanger sequencing, but also with current NGS technologies, especially when using paired-end protocols.</p><p>Furthermore, many studies starting with a limited number of sequences tend to optimize PCR conditions separately for each marker. As a consequence, these markers often cannot be combined in multiplex assays that are most economic in combination with NGS technologies, so called target-enrichment strategies [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Our approach of keeping annealing temperatures in a narrow range for all primer pairs, together with the limited size range of PCR products, facilitates the joint analysis of multiple nuclear gene markers.</p><p>Direct Sanger sequencing of PCR products was successful with the primer pairs that were tested. Although the Sanger method does not allow to distinguish different alleles directly, which appear as heterozygous sites in electropherograms, we were still able to use this method to assess the utility of marker regions for phylogenetic inference. Resulting phylogenies at the family and "lineage" levels were largely congruent with previous results [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Phylogenetic resolution at the genus level was low, which may be the consequence of the low number of included species or low phylogenetic information content of two of the four marker regions used, potentially leading to an increase in noise levels [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].</p><p>Comparing markers from our study with commonly used gene regions showed that our primer pairs are able to amplify fragments with high and low potential sequence divergence and PIC content. The nucleotide diversity and PIC number of loci from this study were found to range, depending on the studied locus and relationship levels, between low diversity values similar to the compared plastid markers <italic>mat</italic>K and <italic>ndh</italic>F, and levels that are similar to the nrDNA marker ITS, which is a fast evolving region (<xref rid="pone.0128181.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). These considerable differences in sequence evolution underline previous statements that single-gene trees may often not reflect the true evolutionary history of a taxon [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], thus it is of utmost importance to include many unlinked loci in evolutionary analyses. Nowadays NGS technologies coupled with target-enrichment methods, which have been used e.g. in phylogenetic [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] and phylogeography studies [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], may help overcome the potential mismatches of gene and species-trees. Therefore, our method and primer list may be used for such target-enrichment approaches, and present useful tools to study a large number of conserved marker regions in a cost-effective and fast manner across a broad range of taxa in the Brassicaceae family.</p><p>Available annotations for our primer list can be used to focus on specific groups of genes in targeted evolutionary, ecological or genomic studies that focus, for example, on genetic diversity and evolution of stress-responsive genes.</p><p>Altogether, we anticipate that the set of 2,334 nuclear gene markers presented here will benefit the Brassicaceae research community and facilitate future analyses of phylogenetic relationships and evolutionary processes in this highly diverse plant group [<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0128181.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Essential information, such as amplicon type, length or gene ID based on the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> reference genome, are readily available (<xref rid="pone.0128181.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6 Table</xref>) and hence ready to use for further studies. Finally, and most importantly, the large number of available nuclear gene markers will hopefully allow changing our perspective to move away from the analysis of a few genes that undergo uniparental inheritance or concerted evolution towards a truly genome-wide analysis of diversity and divergence.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec012"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0128181.s001"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Plant accessions and treatments for transcriptome sequencing of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>alpina</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>hirsuta</italic>.</title><p>Sample origin refers to sampling location, tissue type refers to sampled tissue for RNA extraction. Treatment refers to applied stress treatment with details in brackets, before tissue was collected. <sup>1</sup> Pooled samples from three populations from 8.86&#x000b0;E 47.06&#x000b0;N, 8.91&#x000b0;E 47.06&#x000b0;N and 9.05&#x000b0;E 47.09&#x000b0;N. <sup>2</sup> Pooled samples from three populations from 9.35&#x000b0;E 47.24&#x000b0;N, 9.02&#x000b0;E 47.08&#x000b0;N and 9.43&#x000b0;E 46.97&#x000b0;N.</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0128181.s001.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0128181.s002"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title>PCR protocol for Fluidigm Amplicon Tagging (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fluidigm.com/access-array-system.html">http://www.fluidigm.com/access-array-system.html</ext-link>).</title><p>Tag sequences: forward <monospace>5&#x02019;-ACACTGACGACATGGTTCTACA-3&#x02019;</monospace> and reverse <monospace>5&#x02019;-TACGGTAGCAGAGACTTGGTCT-3&#x02019;</monospace>.</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0128181.s002.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0128181.s003"><label>S3 Table</label><caption><title>GO-overrepresentation analysis of all 1,164 genes amplified (at least in part) with primer pairs developed in this study, sorted by false-discovery rate (FDR) values.</title><p>Analysis was performed by the online tool DAVID 6.7.</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0128181.s003.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0128181.s004"><label>S4 Table</label><caption><title>PCR amplification success of 48 primer pairs tested on 30 Brassicaceae species.</title><p>Numbers 0,1 and 2 refer to the number of bands obtained on agarose gels after PCR. Amplification success per marker and amplification success per species were calculated by adding all successful single product amplifications and dividing it by the overall number of tested species or markers, respectively.</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0128181.s004.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0128181.s005"><label>S5 Table</label><caption><title>Sequences retrieved from GenBank for comparisons between commonly used markers and markers amplified with primer pairs developed in this study.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0128181.s005.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0128181.s006"><label>S6 Table</label><caption><title>2,334 primer pairs developed in this study.</title><p>(XLSX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0128181.s006.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Matthias Baltisberger and the members of the Botanical Garden of the University of Zurich for granting access to herbarium and fresh specimens for DNA extraction, Andrew Tedder for valuable comments and suggestions, Claudia Michel and Beatrice Blattmann for support in the lab, and Maria Domenica Moccia and the Functional Genomics Center Zurich for help in data collection.</p><p>The study was funded by the Swiss National Science Foundation (Sinergia project CRSI33_127155 and ProDoc PDFMP3_137084) and a University Research Priority Program in Systems Biology / Functional Genomics.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0128181.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burleigh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Molecular markers and concepts of plant evolutionary relationships: progress, promise, and future prospects</article-title>. <source>Critical Reviews in Plant Sciences</source><volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Ribosomal ITS sequences and plant phylogenetic inference</article-title>. <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>434</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14615184?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14615184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Poczai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hyvonen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Nuclear ribosomal spacer regions in plant phylogenetics: problems and prospects</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology Reports</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>1897</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1912</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11033-009-9630-3">10.1007/s11033-009-9630-3</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19626457?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19626457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Les</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mishler</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetics of seed plants: an analysis of nucleotide sequences from the plastid gene <italic>rbc</italic>L</article-title>. <source>Annals of the Missouri Botanical Garden</source>
<volume>80</volume>: <fpage>528</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>580</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title><italic>mat</italic>K DNA sequences and phylogenetic reconstruction in Saxifragaceae s. str</article-title>. <source>Systematic Botany</source>: <fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Taberlet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gielly</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pautou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bouvet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Universal primers for amplification of three non-coding regions of chloroplast DNA</article-title>. <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1109</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1932684?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1932684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bruns</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Amplification and direct sequencing of fungal ribosomal RNA genes for phylogenetics</article-title>. <source>PCR Protocols: A Guide to Methods and Applications</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>322</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Utility of low-copy nuclear gene sequences in plant phylogenetics</article-title>. <source>Critical Reviews in Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>147</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12139440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12139440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ritland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Sequence-repeat polymorphisms exhibit the signature of recombination in lodgepole pine chloroplast DNA</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>2136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2138</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11606712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11606712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaal</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Organelle DNA phylogeography of <italic>Cycas taitungensis</italic>, a relict species in Taiwan</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>2669</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2681</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11883881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11883881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W-K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>C-W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C-L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>T-W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Evolutionary rates of commonly used nuclear and organelle markers of Arabidopsis relatives (Brassicaceae)</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<volume>499</volume>: <fpage>194</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gene.2012.02.037">10.1016/j.gene.2012.02.037</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22426291?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22426291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cronn</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haselkorn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Rapid diversification of the cotton genus (<italic>Gossypium</italic>: Malvaceae) revealed by analysis of sixteen nuclear and chloroplast genes</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Botany</source>
<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>707</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>725</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3732/ajb.89.4.707">10.3732/ajb.89.4.707</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21665671?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21665671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lihov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marhold</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Allopolyploid origin of <italic>Cardamine asarifolia</italic> (Brassicaceae): Incongruence between plastid and nuclear ribosomal DNA sequences solved by a single-copy nuclear gene</article-title>. <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>759</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>786</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16527494?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16527494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Excoffier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heckel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genomic scans support repetitive continental colonization events during the rapid radiation of voles (Rodentia: <italic>Microtus</italic>): the utility of AFLPs versus mitochondrial and nuclear sequence markers</article-title>. <source>Systematic Biology</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>548</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>572</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syq042">10.1093/sysbio/syq042</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20834011?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20834011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mayol</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossello</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Why nuclear ribosomal DNA spacers (ITS) tell different stories in <italic>Quercus</italic></article-title>. <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11341800?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11341800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harpke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Non-concerted ITS evolution in <italic>Mammillaria</italic> (Cactaceae)</article-title>. <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>593</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16843685?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16843685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Franzke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mummenhoff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Recent hybrid speciation in <italic>Cardamine</italic> (Brassicaceae)&#x02014;conversion of nuclear ribosomal ITS sequences in statu nascendi</article-title>. <source>TAG Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>98</volume>: <fpage>831</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>834</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guichoux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lagache</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaumeil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lepais</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Current trends in microsatellite genotyping</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>611</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-0998.2011.03014.x">10.1111/j.1755-0998.2011.03014.x</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21565126?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21565126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Meudt</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Almost forgotten or latest practice? AFLP applications, analyses and advances</article-title>. <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>117</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17303467?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17303467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cronn</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Use of nuclear genes for phylogeny reconstruction in plants</article-title>. <source>Australian Systematic Botany</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genome-enabled development of DNA markers for ecology, evolution and conservation</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2184</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2195</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2010.04650.x">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2010.04650.x</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20465588?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20465588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shimizu-Inatsugi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lihova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iwanaga</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kudoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marhold</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The allopolyploid <italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> originated from multiple individuals of <italic>Arabidopsis lyrata</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic></article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>4024</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4048</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2009.04329.x">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2009.04329.x</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19754506?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19754506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klejna</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barfuss</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rupp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Reticulate evolution in diploid and tetraploid species of <italic>Polystachya</italic> (Orchidaceae) as shown by plastid DNA sequences and low-copy nuclear genes</article-title>. <source>Annals of Botany</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/aob/mcq092">10.1093/aob/mcq092</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20525745?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20525745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edger</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Landherr</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Identification of shared single copy nuclear genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>Populus</italic>, <italic>Vitis</italic> and <italic>Oryza</italic> and their phylogenetic utility across various taxonomic levels</article-title>. <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-10-61">10.1186/1471-2148-10-61</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20181251?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20181251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tonnabel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mignot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rebelo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Justy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santoni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Developing nuclear DNA phylogenetic markers in the angiosperm genus <italic>Leucadendron</italic> (Proteaceae): A next-generation sequencing transcriptomic approach</article-title>. <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
<volume>70</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2013.07.027">10.1016/j.ympev.2013.07.027</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23948865?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23948865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Curto</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Puppo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meimberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Development of phylogenetic markers from single-copy nuclear genes for multi locus, species level analyses in the mint family (Lamiaceae)</article-title>. <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>758</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>767</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2012.02.010">10.1016/j.ympev.2012.02.010</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22387534?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22387534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ort&#x000ed;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A practical approach to phylogenomics: the phylogeny of ray-finned fish (Actinopterygii) as a case study</article-title>. <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>44</fpage>
<?supplied-pmid 17374158?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17374158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riethoven</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Exon-primed intron-crossing (EPIC) markers for non-model teleost fishes</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-10-90">10.1186/1471-2148-10-90</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20353608?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20353608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Salas-Leiva</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meerow</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Francisco-Ortega</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calonje</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Conserved genetic regions across angiosperms as tools to develop single-copy nuclear markers in gymnosperms: An example using cycads</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A versatile and highly efficient toolkit including 102 nuclear markers for vertebrate phylogenomics, tested by resolving the higher level relationships of the Caudata</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>2235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2248</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst122">10.1093/molbev/mst122</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23827877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23827877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chenuil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoareau</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Egea</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Penant</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rocher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aurelle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>An efficient method to find potentially universal population genetic markers, applied to metazoans</article-title>. <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>276</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-10-276">10.1186/1471-2148-10-276</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20836842?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20836842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salamin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dunwell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kesanakurthi</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haidar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Land plants and DNA barcodes: short-term and long-term goals</article-title>. <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source>
<volume>360</volume>: <fpage>1889</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1895</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16214746?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16214746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Funari</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Voevodski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leyfer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yerkes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tolan</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Quantitative gene expression profiles in real time from expressed sequence tag databases</article-title>. <source>Gene Expression</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>336</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 20635574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20635574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Arabidopsis Genome Initiative</collab> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Analysis of the genome sequence of the flowering plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>408</volume>: <fpage>796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>815</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11130711?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11130711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Couvreur</surname><given-names>TLP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Franzke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al-Shehbaz</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mummenhoff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogenetics, temporal diversification, and principles of evolution in the mustard family (Brassicaceae)</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msp202">10.1093/molbev/msp202</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19744998?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19744998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beilstein</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al-Shehbaz</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kellogg</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Brassicaceae phylogeny inferred from <italic>PHYTOCHROME A</italic> and <italic>ndh</italic>F sequence data: tribes and trichomes revisited</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Botany</source>
<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>1307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1327</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3732/ajb.0800065">10.3732/ajb.0800065</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21632335?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21632335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dobes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiefer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmickl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klimes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lysak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Supernetwork identifies multiple events of plastid <italic>trn</italic>F(GAA) pseudogene evolution in the Brassicaceae</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16987951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16987951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Al-Shehbaz</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A generic and tribal synopsis of the Brassicaceae (Cruciferae)</article-title>. <source>Taxon</source>
<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>931</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>954</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Franzke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lysak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al-Shehbaz</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mummenhoff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Cabbage family affairs: the evolutionary history of Brassicaceae</article-title>. <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2010.11.005">10.1016/j.tplants.2010.11.005</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21177137?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21177137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Al-Shehbaz IA (2011) Brassicaceae (Mustard Family).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lysak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lexer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Towards the era of comparative evolutionary genomics in Brassicaceae</article-title>. <source>Plant Systematics and Evolution</source>
<volume>259</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kagale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huebert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Condie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Polyploid evolution of the Brassicaceae during the Cenozoic era</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2777</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2791</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.114.126391">10.1105/tpc.114.126391</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 25035408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25035408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beilstein</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagalingum</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manchester</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Dated molecular phylogenies indicate a Miocene origin for <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>107</volume>: <fpage>18724</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18728</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0909766107">10.1073/pnas.0909766107</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20921408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20921408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Swarbreck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilks</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamesch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berardini</surname><given-names>TZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garcia-Hernandez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foerster</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Information Resource (TAIR): gene structure and function annotation</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>D1009</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D1014</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17986450?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17986450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Treangen</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Angly</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Next generation sequence assembly with AMOS</article-title>. <source>Current Protocols in Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>Unit 11</fpage><lpage>18</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/0471250953.bi1101s36">10.1002/0471250953.bi1101s36</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22161566?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22161566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wysoker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Homer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2078</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2079</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19505943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rozen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skaletsky</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers</article-title>. <source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>132</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>386</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10547847?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10547847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coulouris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Avagyan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bealer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-10-421">10.1186/1471-2105-10-421</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20003500?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lempicki</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources</article-title>. <source>Nature Protocols</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>44</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2008.211">10.1038/nprot.2008.211</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19131956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19131956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imamichi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Extracting biological meaning from large gene lists with DAVID</article-title>. <source>Current Protocols in Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>Unit 13</fpage><lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Standley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>772</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>780</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst010">10.1093/molbev/mst010</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23329690?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23329690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cornish-Bowden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Nomenclature for incompletely specified bases in nucleic acid sequences: recommendations 1984</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>3021</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3030</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 2582368?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2582368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vaidya</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lohman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>SequenceMatrix: concatenation software for the fast assembly of multi-gene datasets with character set and codon information</article-title>. <source>Cladistics</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>180</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>RAxML-VI-HPC: maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic analyses with thousands of taxa and mixed models</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2688</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2690</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16928733?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16928733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teslenko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van der Mark</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hohna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>MrBayes 3.2: efficient Bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model space</article-title>. <source>Systematic Biology</source>
<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>542</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/sys029">10.1093/sysbio/sys029</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22357727?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22357727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood</article-title>. <source>Systematic Biology</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>696</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>704</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14530136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14530136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Darriba</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taboada</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doallo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>jModelTest 2: more models, new heuristics and parallel computing</article-title>. <source>Nature Methods</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>772</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>772</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.2109">10.1038/nmeth.2109</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22847109?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22847109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MEGA5: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis Using Maximum Likelihood, Evolutionary Distance, and Maximum Parsimony Methods</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2739</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msr121">10.1093/molbev/msr121</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21546353?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiefer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>German</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al-Shehbaz</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Franzke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mummenhoff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>BrassiBase: tools and biological resources to study characters and traits in the Brassicaceae&#x02014;version 1.1</article-title>. <source>Taxon</source>
<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1001</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1009</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mamanova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kozarewa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Target-enrichment strategies for next-generation sequencing</article-title>. <source>Nature Methods</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>118</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.1419">10.1038/nmeth.1419</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20111037?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20111037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Signal, noise, and reliability in molecular phylogenetic analyses</article-title>. <source>Journal of Heredity</source>
<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>195</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1624764?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1624764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heled</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Bayesian inference of species trees from multilocus data</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>570</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>580</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msp274">10.1093/molbev/msp274</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19906793?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906793</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bybee</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bracken-Grissom</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hermansen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Byers</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Targeted amplicon sequencing (TAS): a scalable next-gen approach to multilocus, multitaxa phylogenetics</article-title>. <source>Genome Biology and Evolution</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1312</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1323</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/gbe/evr106">10.1093/gbe/evr106</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22002916?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22002916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Faircloth</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brumfield</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A phylogeny of birds based on over 1,500 loci collected by target enrichment and high-throughput sequencing</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e54848</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0054848">10.1371/journal.pone.0054848</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23382987?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23382987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bullock</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aguilar-Miguel</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Parallel tagged amplicon sequencing reveals major lineages and phylogenetic structure in the North American tiger salamander (<italic>Ambystoma tigrinum</italic>) species complex</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>129</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/mec.12049">10.1111/mec.12049</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23062080?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23062080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Good</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maricic</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stenzel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Targeted retrieval and analysis of five Neandertal mtDNA genomes</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>325</volume>: <fpage>318</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>321</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1174462">10.1126/science.1174462</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19608918?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19608918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lemmon</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lemmon</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>High-throughput identification of informative nuclear loci for shallow-scale phylogenetics and phylogeography</article-title>. <source>Systematic Biology</source>
<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>745</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>761</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/sys051">10.1093/sysbio/sys051</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22610088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22610088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128181.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lysak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny, genome, and karyotype evolution of crucifers (Brassicaceae)</article-title>. <source>Genetics and Genomics of the Brassicaceae</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>