<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">G3 (Bethesda)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>G3: Genes|Genomes|Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2160-1836</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Genetics Society of America</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3755910</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23833213</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">GGG_006742</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.113.006742</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Investigations</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Developmental Transcriptome of the Mosquito <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>, an Invasive Species and Major Arbovirus Vector</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Akbari</surname><given-names>Omar S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn2"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Antoshechkin</surname><given-names>Igor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn2"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amrhein</surname><given-names>Henry</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Diloreto</surname><given-names>Race</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>Jeremy</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>Bruce A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Division of Biology, MC 156-29, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California 91125</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="afn3"><p>Supporting information is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1">http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn id="afn2" fn-type="equal"><label>1</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>2</label>Corresponding author: California Institute of Technology, Assistant Professor, Biology, MC 156-29, 1200 East California Boulevard, Pasadena, CA 91125. E-mail: <email>haybruce@caltech.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1493</fpage><lpage>1509</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2013 Akbari <italic>et al.</italic></copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Unported License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="1493.pdf"/><abstract><p>Mosquitoes are vectors of a number of important human and animal diseases. The development of novel vector control strategies requires a thorough understanding of mosquito biology. To facilitate this, we used RNA-seq to identify novel genes and provide the first high-resolution view of the transcriptome throughout development and in response to blood feeding in a mosquito vector of human disease, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>, the primary vector for Dengue and yellow fever. We characterized mRNA expression at 34 distinct time points throughout <italic>Aedes</italic> development, including adult somatic and germline tissues, by using polyA+ RNA-seq. We identify a total of 14,238 novel new transcribed regions corresponding to 12,597 new loci, as well as many novel transcript isoforms of previously annotated genes. Altogether these results increase the annotated fraction of the transcribed genome into long polyA+ RNAs by more than twofold. We also identified a number of patterns of shared gene expression, as well as genes and/or exons expressed sex-specifically or sex-differentially. Expression profiles of small RNAs in ovaries, early embryos, testes, and adult male and female somatic tissues also were determined, resulting in the identification of 38 new <italic>Aedes</italic>-specific miRNAs, and ~291,000 small RNA new transcribed regions, many of which are likely to be endogenous small-interfering RNAs and Piwi-interacting RNAs. Genes of potential interest for transgene-based vector control strategies also are highlighted. Our data have been incorporated into a user-friendly genome browser located at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.Aedes.caltech.edu">www.Aedes.caltech.edu</ext-link>, with relevant links to Vectorbase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vectorbase.org">www.vectorbase.org</ext-link>)</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></kwd><kwd>dengue fever</kwd><kwd>yellow fever</kwd><kwd>chikungunya</kwd><kwd>malaria</kwd><kwd>population replacement</kwd><kwd>transcriptomes</kwd><kwd>Medea</kwd><kwd>gene drive</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="17"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name> DJS Export </meta-name><meta-value>v1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p><italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> is the principal vector for the flaviviruses yellow fever and dengue fever (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Barrett and Higgs 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Halstead 2008</xref>) and is also responsible for several recent outbreaks of the alphavirus chikengunya (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Ligon 2006</xref>). Approximately 2.5 billion people are at risk for dengue, with 50&#x02212;100 million cases and ~25,000 deaths each year (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Guzman and Isturiz 2010</xref>). The range of <italic>A. aegypti</italic> is expanding through tropical and subtropical zones worldwide, and the occurrence of Dengue fever has closely followed the expansion of the mosquitoes (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Guzman <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Guzman and Isturiz 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Lounibos 2002</xref>). No vaccine is available, leaving vector control the only option for prevention. The emergence and spread of insecticide resistance poses a threat to the sustainability of these efforts (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Hemingway <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). Vaccines are available for yellow fever, but there are still ~200,000 cases each year, resulting in ~30,000 deaths (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Barrett and Higgs 2007</xref>). Many <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> strains also are susceptible to infection with West Nile virus (<xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">Vanlandingham <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), the avian malaria parasite <italic>Plasmodium gallinaceum</italic> (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">James 2002</xref>), and filariatic nematodes (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Erickson <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), making this organism an important tool for the investigation of multiple mosquito-pathogen interactions. <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> is also a model organism for mosquito biology. It is easy to transition from field to laboratory culture, fertilized eggs can be stored in a diapause state for many months, and it is straightforward to transform with the use of transposons and site-directed integration systems (<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Nimmo <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Terenius <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Much of what we know about mosquito genetics, biochemistry and behavior comes from study of this species (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Clements 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Clemons <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Severson and Behura 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">Vanlandingham <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>).</p><p>To understand mosquito development, how the insect adapts to specific environments, acquires resistance to insecticides, and responds to infection by pathogens, the full genomic complement of genes, their structures, and the patterns of gene expression associated with these activities is needed. This, in conjunction with the ability to manipulate gene expression, provides a platform from which to generate and test hypotheses about the functions of specific genes. The <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements that drive gene expression in specific patterns&#x02014;the identification of which is facilitated through detailed transcriptional profiling of many states and the identification of transcription start sites&#x02014;also are needed to develop novel forms of transgenic-based vector control that involve population suppression or replacement of wild populations with individuals refractory to disease transmission (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Alphey <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Burt 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Catteruccia <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Davis <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Hay <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Sinkins and Gould 2006</xref>).</p><p>The <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> genome project identified 15,419 gene models by using a large collection of expressed sequence tags and gene structure information from other diptera (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Nene <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). These data have provided the basis for a number of transcriptional profiling experiments that use oligonucleotide probes on arrays (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Behura <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Caragata <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Colpitts <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Dissanayake <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Erickson <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Ptitsyn <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sim and Dimopoulos 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Souza-Neto <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">Xi <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">Zou <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). These have provided information on gene expression in response to a variety of stimuli and in some cases throughout portions of development. However, transcriptional profiling via the use of microarrays is limited in that arrays often contain probes for only a subset of known genes, they do not allow for the identification and characterization of new genes, and their use suffers from various technical biases such as nonspecific hybridization and insufficient signal for genes expressed at low levels. In contrast, transcriptome information generated by the use of massively parallel cDNA sequencing (RNA-seq) provides absolute measures of gene expression and can quantify the levels of known and unknown genes, facilitating annotation of the genome while identifying patterns of gene expression (<xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Mortazavi <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). RNA-seq can also be used to study differential splicing and locate precise transcription start and stop sites, all at single-base resolution (<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Ozsolak and Milos 2011</xref>). Several recent studies have used RNA-seq to characterize <italic>A. aegypti</italic> polyA+ mRNA or microRNA transcriptomes in specific contexts, and novel genes and patterns of gene expression have been identified (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Biedler <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Biedler and Tu 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Bonizzoni <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">2012a</xref>,<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">David <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Gibbons <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Hess <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Neira-Oviedo <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Paris <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Rinker <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Surget-Groba and Montoya-Burgos 2010</xref>). However, these studies focused on characterization of only a few life cycle stages, leaving much of the transcriptome yet to be explored. No comprehensive transcriptome encompassing the development of an arthropod vector of disease has been reported by the use of array-based transcriptional profiling or RNAseq, although a detailed array-based analysis of gene expression during <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> embryonic development and studies of sex- and tissue-specific gene expression have been reported (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Baker <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Goltsev <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Magnusson <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).</p><p>Here, we provide a comprehensive analysis of the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> transcriptome throughout development, sequenced at unprecedented depth using RNA-seq. These data have been incorporated into a genome browser located at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="aedes.caltech.edu">aedes.caltech.edu</ext-link>, with links to Vectorbase (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vectorbase.org">www.vectorbase.org</ext-link>) to provide easy access to genomic information.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2"><title>Mosquitoes and sample time points</title><p>Mosquitoes used for RNA extraction were from the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> Liverpool strain, which originated from West Africa, and was used to produce the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> reference genome (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Nene <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Mosquitoes were kept in incubators with a relative humidity of 70&#x02013;80%, maintained at 28&#x000ba;, and with a 12-hr/12-hr light/dark cycle. Larvae were fed with ground fish food (TetraMin Tropical Flakes, Tetra Werke, Melle, Germany) and sex-separated as pupae. Adults were maintained and fed with an aqueous solution of 30% sucrose. Females were blood-fed 3&#x02212;5 d after eclosion on anesthetized mice and then returned to normal mosquito-rearing conditions during sample collections. All animals were treated according to the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals as recommended by the National Institutes of Health.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Total RNA isolation</title><p>Samples were flash-frozen at specific time points, and total RNA was extracted by use of the Ambion mirVana mRNA isolation kit (Ambion/Applied Biosystems, Austin, TX). All sample collections were staged in the incubator at a relative humidity of 70&#x02013;80%, 28&#x000ba; with a 12-hr/12-hr light cycle until the desired time point was reached. Samples were then immediately flash frozen. The adult NBF carcass was processed at 3 d after eclosion, and the adult male carcass and testes were processed at 4 d after eclosion. After extraction, RNA was treated with Ambion Turbo DNase (Ambion/Applied Biosystems, Austin, TX). The quality of RNA was assessed using the Bioanalyzer 2100 (Aglient Technologies, Santa Clara, CA) and the NanoDrop 1000 UV-VIS spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies/Thermo Scientific, Wilmington, DE). RNA was then prepared for sequencing using the Illumina mRNA-Seq Sample Preparation Kit (Illumina San Diego, CA).</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Small RNA extraction, cloning, and sequencing</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from ovaries of NBF females, and PBM, at 24-, 48-, and 72-hr time points. RNA was also extracted from 0- to 2-hr and 2- to 4=hr embryos, female carcasses 72 hr PBM, male carcasses lacking testes and AG, and testes plus AG. Twenty micrograms of total RNA from each sample was size fractionated on 15% TBE-Urea polyacrylamide gels. For all ovary and embryo time points small RNAs between 18&#x02212;26 nt and 26&#x02212;32 nt in length were excised and sequenced separately. For the male and female carcasses and testes and AG samples small RNAs between 18&#x02212;32 nt were sequenced as a single sample. Ethanol precipitated RNA was ligated to a HPLC purified 3&#x02032; linker using T4 RNA ligase (Ambion/Applied Biosystems, Austin, TX). Ligation products were purified on a 15% TBE-Urea polyacrylamide gel and recovered by high-salt elution. A high-performance liquid chromatography&#x02212;purified 5&#x02032;RNA linker was ligated to the product using T4-RNA ligase, and the product was purified on a 15% TBE-Urea polyacrylamide gel and recovered as described previously. Reverse transcription was performed using SSIII (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), and cDNA was amplified using Phusion polymerase (Finnzymes Oy, Espoo, Finland). Amplified cDNA libraries were purified on a 2% agarose gel and sequenced using the Illumina Genome Analyzer II system. Linker and primer sequences are provided in supplementary <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/006742SI.pdf">Supporting Information</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS23.xlsx">Table S23</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Poly(A+) read alignment and quantification</title><p>Poly(A+) transcriptome reads were processed and aligned to a reference index generated for the A. aegypti genome (AaegL1, obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vectorbase.org">www.vectorbase.org</ext-link>), using TopHat v1.2.0 (<xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">Trapnell <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Reads were aligned using both default parameters allowing up to 40 alignments per read with a maximum 2-bp mismatch and also using unique mapping allowing only one alignment per read with a maximum 2-bp mismatch (both datasets are provided). The aligned read files were processed by Cufflinks v0.9.3 (<xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Trapnell <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Cufflinks uses the normalized RNA-Seq fragment counts to measure the relative abundances of transcripts. The unit of measurement is fragments per kilobase of exon per million fragments mapped (FPKM).</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Small RNA read alignment and quantification</title><p>The 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; adapter sequences for the small RNA reads were removed using custom Perl scripts that required a minimal match to the adapter sequence of 6 bp and a minimal size of 18 bp and maximum size of 32 bp (sequences for the adapter sequences supplied in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS23.xlsx">Table S23</ext-link>). The trimmed sequences were aligned to the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> reference genome using bowtie v0.12.7, allowing no mismatches and a maximum of 10 alignments/read. We determined small RNA abundance using custom in house Perl scripts in which we quantified the read count per million of mapped reads (RPM) for each genomic position for all nine libraries. To identify novel and non-annotated miRNA orthologs, we then sorted for the most abundant (&#x0003e;50 read counts) mapped reads in the size range of 19&#x02212;24 bp across all nine libraries and filtered out all the annotated miRNAs. We isolated ~60-bp flanking each mature sequence and tested its ability to fold into a miRNA stem loop structure using Mfold default settings (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mfold.rna.albany.edu/?q=DINAMelt/Quickfold">http://mfold.rna.albany.edu/?q=DINAMelt/Quickfold</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>TE expression</title><p>A bowtie index was created from all annotated TE in A. aegypti (extracted from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tefam.biochem.vt.edu/tefam/">http://tefam.biochem.vt.edu/tefam/</ext-link>) and both the long poly(A+) transcriptome reads and the adapter trimmed small RNA reads were aligned to this index using bowtie. Expression scores (RPKM) for each TE element were calculated using custom scripts in which each score was divided by the total length (in kb) of each annotated TE and this value was normalized to the total mapped reads (in millions) in that sample (instead of normalizing to just the reads which map to TE elements). The normalized expression values for each TE in each class were summed to illustrate the TE class expression values.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Discovery of new isoforms and newly transcribed regions (NTRs)</title><p>Reads from four sex-specific paired end sequenced libraries and 42 single-read sequenced libraries were aligned to the Aedes genome using tophat (v1.3.3) allowing the discovery of novel junctions. <italic>De novo</italic> transcriptome assembly was carried out for each mapping file separately using cufflinks (v1.3.0). GTF files produced by cufflinks runs were merged with the cuffmerge utility of the cufflinks package. Cuffmerge was also used to compare <italic>de novo</italic> transcriptomes to existing AAEL transcripts. The combined GTF file was parsed to identify new isoforms of AAEL genes (class code &#x0201c;j&#x0201d;) and NTRs (class code &#x0201c;u&#x0201d;). Nucleotide sequences of newly identified transcribed regions were extracted and searched against the nonredundant protein database downloaded from NCBI (on 7/23/2012) using NCBI BLAST+ (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Camacho <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Conserved protein domains and associated GO terms were identified using stand alone InterProScan package v4.9 and the database release 38.0 (June 2012) (<xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">Zdobnov and Apweiler 2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Clustering and Gene Ontology (GO) analysis</title><p>Cufflinks-produced FPKM values for 42 RNA-seq libraries were clustered using Mfuzz R software package (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Kumar and Futschik 2007</xref>). Mfuzz uses fuzzy c-means algorithm to perform soft clustering, which allows cluster overlap and has been demonstrated to perform favorably on gene expression data. The resulting clusters were analyzed for overrepresentation of GO terms using a hypergeometric test implemented using the GOstats R software package (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Falcon and Gentleman 2007</xref>). GO annotations for known genes were downloaded from VectorBase and merged with GO terms produced by the InterProScan analysis of novel genes. Hypergeometric tests were performed separately for biological process, molecular function, and cellular component ontologies.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>DEXSeq differential exon usage analysis</title><p>Differential exon usage was analyzed using DEXSeq (ver. 1.1.7) R package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/DEXSeq.html">http://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/DEXSeq.html</ext-link>) according to the package manual. In summary, annotation file in GTF format containing annotated VectorBase AAEL gene models and cufflinks-identified NTRs (AAEL-NIPS and NTRs) was processed with prepare_annotation.py script provided with DEXSeq package to define nonoverlapping exonic parts. Exon read counts for four sex-specific libraries (male carcass, male testes, blood-fed female carcass, blood-fed ovaries) sequenced as paired end 76 nt and single read 38 nt were generated from tophat-produced mapping files in BAM format using dexseq_count.py script. Counts from libraries for each sex were combined to generate two male and two female-specific counts (one for each run type). The count data were imported into the DEXSeq framework and differential exon usage was assessed using make CompleteDEUAnalysis function with default parameters. The analysis identified 2,468 differentially used exonic parts originating from 1278 loci at FDR of 0.05. HTML reports and graphics were generated using DEXSeqHTML function.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s11"><title>Results</title><sec id="s12"><title>Strategy for the characterization of <italic>A. aegypti</italic> transcriptome</title><p>To establish a comprehensive view of gene expression dynamics throughout <italic>A. aegypti</italic> development we conducted poly A(+) RNA sequencing (poly A(+) RNA-seq) using RNA isolated from 42 samples representing 34 distinct stages of development from the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> Liverpool (<italic>i.e.</italic>, LVP) strain (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Nene <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS1.xlsx">Table S1</ext-link>). These time points incorporated 26 whole animal and 16 tissue/carcass samples. For embryogenesis we collected 20 samples; the first three time points, 0&#x02212;2 hr, 2&#x02212;4 hr, and 4&#x02212;8 hr embryos, capture the maternal-zygotic transition at 2-hr intervals, whereas 17 additional samples collected through 76 hr, at 4-hr intervals, capture the rest of embryogenesis. Samples also were collected from each of the four larval instars and sex-separated male and female pupae. Sixteen additional samples were collected from adults. These include dissected whole ovaries from nonblood-fed females (NBF) and from females at 12 hr, 24 hr, 36 hr, 48 hr, 60 hr, and 72 hr postblood-meal (PBM); carcass samples (whole female bodies lacking ovaries) also were collected from these same time points. These samples cover ovarian and follicle development from previtellogenic &#x0201c;resting stage&#x0201d; NBF ovaries through the completion of oogenesis at 72-hr PBM. We also isolated samples from adult male testes and accessory glands (AG) as a single sample and male carcasses (lacking testes and AG) at 4 d after eclosion. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS1.xlsx">Table S1</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS2.xlsx">Table S2</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS3.xlsx">Table S3</ext-link> provide a summary of the complete polyA+ transcriptome.</p><p>Samples for sequencing of small RNAs were prepared from nine stages designed to characterize small RNAs through several major developmental transitions and in germline and somatic tissues. Samples from NBF ovaries, and ovaries from blood-fed females at 24 hr, 48 hr, and 72 hr span oogenesis and should be enriched in small RNAs present in the adult female germline and surrounding somatic support cells. Small RNAs from 0&#x02212;2 hr and 2&#x02212;4 hr embryos should consist of maternally expressed RNAs deposited into the egg but not include those present in ovarian support cells during oogenesis. Samples were also prepared from adult male carcasses, testes + AG, and adult female carcass 72 hr PBM, providing additional information on small RNAs that are expressed specifically in the germline, soma, or sex specifically.</p><p>To achieve single nucleotide resolution and facilitate the discovery of non-annotated genes, we used the Illumina Genome Analyzer II sequencing platform to sequence the aforementioned samples, producing a combination of single 38 nt and paired-end 76-bp reads. In total we generated 1.2 billion single 38 nt and paired 76-nt raw reads corresponding to total sequence output of 46 GB, with 89.45% of the reads (1.1 billion reads, 41.8GB of sequence) aligning to the <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> genome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS2.xlsx">Table S2</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Discovery of NTRs</title><p>The current assembly of the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> genome (AaegL1, released September 2009) contains 4758 supercontigs and is 1,310,090,344 bp in size, 4.7 times larger than the genome of the malaria mosquito <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>. The existing genomic annotation, which contains 17,346 genes (hereafter referred to as AAEL genes) and 18,760 transcripts encoding 17,402 peptides, was used as a starting point for our analysis (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Nene <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Sequence reads from four sex-specific, paired-end&#x02013;sequenced libraries, and all 42 single-end-sequenced libraries, were used to build <italic>de novo</italic> transcriptomes for each sample with the use of Cufflinks (<xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Trapnell <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Individual transcriptomes were merged to produce a combined gene set, which included 18,755 known transcripts, 20,198 novel isoform predictions (NIPs) of 6913 existing AAEL genes (hereafter referred to as AAEL-NIPs), as well as 14,238 NTRs that do not overlap AAEL transcription units or other annotated genome features potentially transcribed, such as transposable elements (TEs). These NTR transcripts are predicted to arise from 12,597 loci (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/FileS1.zip">File S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/FileS2.zip">File S2</ext-link>). Leveraging paired end and splice junction information present in our data, the transcriptome assembly aggregated 2,676 AAEL genes into 1,231 independent loci (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/FileS3.zip">File S3</ext-link>). The new transcriptome assembly confirmed 47,841 of 48,089 junctions derived from previously annotated AAEL transcripts (99.48%) and defined 29,242 novel junctions, significantly increasing potential splicing complexity of <italic>Aedes</italic> transcriptome. A total of 23,419 (80%) of the newly discovered junctions belong to AAEL-NIPs and 5823 (20%) originate from NTR transcripts.</p><p>To put these findings in perspective, the AAEL transcriptome covers 26.01 MB of genomic sequence (1.99% of the assembled genome). The AAEL-NIPs increase the genomic sequence coverage to 37.20 MB, and NTRs add another 13.27 MB. Thus, the transcripts identified from our polyA+ RNA samples result in an increase of transcribed sequence from 26.01 MB to 49.99 MB, almost doubling the fraction of the genome transcribing long polyA+ RNAs.</p><p>To get a better understanding of what the NTRs encode, we conducted homology searches against the NCBI nonredundant protein database and identified significant hits for 5351 (37.58%) NTRs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS4.xlsx">Table S4</ext-link>). For 1707 (31.90% of hit-producing NTRs) NTRs, the best blast hits were against <italic>A. aegypti</italic> proteins, suggesting that they may represent paralogs of previously annotated AAEL genes. The next most commonly identified species was <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>, producing best hits for 1173 transcripts. <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>, <italic>Anopheles darling</italic>, and <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> proteins were found to be most homologous to 528, 285, and 30 NTRs, respectively. Altogether, members of the mosquito family produced best hits for close to 70% of NTRs. Various members of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> genus produced best hits for additional 7.6% of transcripts, <italic>Drosophila willistoni</italic> being most frequently seen species with 147 hits. Of 8,886 NTRs lacking significant blastx hits, just 105 have open reading frames (ORFs) longer than 200 amino acids, and only 14 of these contain protein domains identifiable by interproscan (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS5.xlsx">Table S5</ext-link>). These results suggest that the majority of NTRs with no significant protein homology represent either noncoding RNAs or novel short protein-coding transcripts specific to <italic>Aedes</italic>.</p><p>To further explore the possibility that NTRs without significant protein homology are noncoding we analyzed them using the program Coding Potential Calculator (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Kong <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Although Coding Potential Calculator has a low false-positive rate (1%) when tested against <italic>Drosophila</italic> modENCODE protein-coding transcripts (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abedini and Raleigh 2009</xref>), the same settings gave an unacceptably high-false positive rate (25%) when tested against AAEL genes known or thought to encode proteins. As an alternative, we identified all transcripts longer than 200 nt, with an FPKM of 10 or greater in at least one sample, and that lacked an ORF of 200 amino acids or longer (<xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">Young <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), which resulted in a list of 3070 candidate highly expressed noncoding RNAs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/FileS4.zip">File S4</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS6.xlsx">Table S6</ext-link>). To visualize the major patterns of coregulated noncoding NTR expression we used a soft clustering algorithm (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Kumar and Futschik 2007</xref>). This resulted in the identification of multiple developmental expression patterns: the ovary and early embryo (cluster 1); early embryo-specific (cluster 9); mid- and later embryogenesis (clusters 2 and 3); late embryogenesis (cluster 5); pupal stages (cluster 7); adult somatic tissues (cluster 10); adult ovary and early embryo (cluster 8); adult male germline (cluster 4); male germline and nonblood-fed ovary (cluster 6; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/FigureS1.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS7.xlsx">Table S7</ext-link>).</p><p>The large number of potentially noncoding NTRs expressed relatively specifically in the nonblood-fed ovary and/or testis + AG is striking (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/FigureS1.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link>, cluster 6 and cluster 4; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS7.xlsx">Table S7</ext-link>). Roles for noncoding RNAs in insects are just beginning to be explored, but it is interesting to consider that important roles for noncoding RNAs in stem cells in mammalian systems have recently been described (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Bertani <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Loewer <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Sheik Mohamed <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). The nonblood-fed ovary contains quiescent stem cell-like populations for both germline and somatic cells of developing egg follicles, which are activated to begin proliferation and differentiation in response to a blood meal. The testes also contain somatic and germline stem cells. It will be interesting to determine the consequences of knocking out the functions of some of these on early germline development.</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Global transcriptome dynamics</title><p>To examine the dynamics of gene expression, we quantified expression changes of AAEL, NTR, and AAEL-NIP gene/transcript models across all developmental samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS8.xlsx">Table S8</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS9.xlsx">Table S9</ext-link>). NBF ovaries express the lowest number of genes (8400) with close to 1.1 isoform per gene. An increase in isoform complexity, which increases to 1.6 transcripts per gene, the highest in the dataset, is seen upon a blood meal. The number of expressed genes and isoforms gradually rises through embryogenesis, reaching a peak at 60 hr and decreasing afterward. Analysis of pair-wise correlations in expression levels of AAEL and NTR genes revealed that almost every developmental stage is most highly correlated with its adjacent stage, particularly during embryogenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). Notable exceptions to this trend occur between 36&#x02212;48 hr and 60&#x02212;72 hr ovaries, and between the 52&#x02212;56 hr and 56&#x02212;60 hr embryo stages, suggesting that these represent important points at which developmental and/or physiological transitions occur.</p><fig id="fig1" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Global dynamics of gene expression. The number of expressed (FPKM &#x0003e; 1) AAEL genes (blue) and AAEL and AAEL-NIP transcripts (red) and NTR gene (green), and NTR transcripts (purple) were plotted across all 42 developmental time points (A). Correlation matrix of all 42 poly (A+) RNA seq time points throughout development for AAEL genes and NTRs. Each developmental stage is most highly correlated with its adjacent time point across all embryogenesis. A decrease in correlation is observable in the 36&#x02212;48hr ovary and 60&#x02212;72hr ovary, 52&#x02212;56hr to 56&#x02212;60hr embryo. The scale bar indicates the coefficient of variation value between samples 0&#x02212;1 (B). The expression heat map indicates the number of AAEL genes and NTRs that are fivefold upregulated between each sample. The number of AAEL genes and NTRs that are 5 fold up-regulated can be determined by matching the criteria with respect to the sequence of the row tissue (left) to the column tissue (top). For example, there are 10,762 (yellow, highest number of expressed genes and this value is 1) genes and NTRs that have 5-fold more transcriptional activity in the 24hr BF ovary tissue (left) compared with the NBF ovary tissue (top). In addition, there are 4302 (0.399 value in chart) genes and NTRs (blue), which have 5-fold more transcriptional activity in the NBF ovary tissue (left) compared with the 24-hr BF ovary tissue (top). These two statements are mutually exclusive and therefore each cell represents a different set of genes (C). Hierarchical clustering heat map of AAEL genes and NTRs, illustrating the various patterns of gene expression across all developmental time points. Scale bar indicates the FPKM z scores (D). For A&#x02212;D, The major developmental groups are indicated by color bars and are organized left to right, as follows: M (brown, male testes, male carcass), Fc (purple, NBF Female Carcass, and multiple time points PBM: 12hr, 24hr, 36hr, 48hr, 60hr, and 72hr), O (red, NBF ovaries, and multiple ovarian time points PBM: 12hr, 24hr, 36hr, 48hr, 60hr and 72hr), E (green, embryo, 0-2hr, 2-4hr, 4-8hr, 8-12hr, 12-16hr, 16-20hr, 20-24hr, 24-28hr, 28-32hr, 32-36hr, 36-40hr, 40-44hr, 44-48hr, 48-52hr, 52-56hr, 56-60hr, 60-64hr, 64-68hr, 68-72hr and 72-76hr embryos), L (light blue, larvae, 1<sup>st</sup>, 2<sup>nd</sup>, 3<sup>rd</sup> and 4<sup>th</sup> instar larvae stages), and P (light orange, male and female pupae).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1493f1"/></fig><p>To identify general trends in expression profiles we compared the transcription count for every sample with every other sample, looking specifically at NTRs and AAEL genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>). Two of the most prominent features to emerge from this analysis are the unique transcriptional signature of the nonblood-fed ovary, which presumably reflects its biologically unique state as a repository of quiescent somatic and germline stem cells, and the large number of genes whose expression is up-regulated at least fivefold in the ovary PBM, reflecting the maternal synthesis of products required for oocyte formation. Large changes in gene expression during a gonotrophic cycle have also been noted in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Dana <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Marinotti <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>).</p><p>A global view of annotated AAEL and NTR gene expression is shown in the hierarchical clustering heat map in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>. To better visualize the major patterns of co-regulated gene expression for the AAEL genes we used a soft clustering algorithm, and identified 20 distinct patterns that included from 151 to 1293 genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS10.xlsx">Table S10</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS30.xlsx">Table S30</ext-link>). Many of these patterns correspond to specific developmental stages and transitions. For instance cluster 5 includes genes specifically expressed in the NBF ovary. It is highly enriched in genes involved in translation, including 92 tRNA and 12 rRNA genes. Seventy-one percent (n = 47) of the annotated snRNAs present in the <italic>Aedes</italic> genome also are found in this cluster, suggesting that mRNA splicing and maturation are also particularly important during this stage. Genes involved in mitochondrial biogenesis and RNA polymerase function are also over represented. Perhaps most strikingly, cluster 5 also expresses a large number of putative olfactory and gustatory receptors, raising the interesting possibility that environmental cues sensed by the ovary PBM may be important in initiating ovarian development. The dramatic switch from low to high transcriptome complexity following this life stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>), and the accumulation of genes required for response to stimuli and RNA processing, suggest that NBF ovary is poised for rapid transcriptional response and growth that occurs PBM. Cluster 6 includes genes predominantly expressed somewhat later in oogenesis. These include many genes involved in polysaccharide or carbohydrate binding, as well as peroxidases and oxireductases, which are likely involved in chorion and vitelline membrane biosynthesis. Interestingly, cluster 6 is also highly enriched in odorant-binding proteins. Other genes that are induced in response to a blood meal are grouped in clusters 7, 8, 9, and 11. Cluster 7 includes strictly ovary-specific genes, whereas the others include genes whose expression initiates PBM and extends into embryogenesis. Cluster 8 in particular, the largest cluster produced, includes maternally expressed genes deposited into the embryo, and is enriched in genes involved in response to stimuli, signal transduction, and protein modification among others. Clusters 12 through 16 identify genes with increased expression during early, mid and late embryogenesis; clusters 17, 18, and 19 include larvae-specific genes, while cluster 20 contains genes preferentially expressed in pupae.</p><fig id="fig2" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Soft clustering, principal component analysis, and totals. Twenty AAEL gene expression profile clusters were identified through soft clustering. Each gene is assigned a line color corresponding to its membership value, with red (1) indicating high association. The major developmental groups are indicated by symbols on the X axis, and are organized as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1, B</xref>&#x02212;D (A). Principal component analysis shows relationships between the 20 clusters, with thickness of the blue lines between any two clusters reflecting the fraction of genes that are shared (B, thickness of blue lines). n, the number of genes in each cluster.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1493f2"/></fig></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Sex-specific gene expression and splicing</title><p>Males and females differ in many morphologic, behavioral, and physiologic traits, largely caused by differences in gene expression. To begin to study these differences we compared transcriptomes from male and female samples. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/FigureS2.pdf">Figure S2</ext-link>, A&#x02212;E shows plots of expression level and sex bias for pupae, whole adults, and carcass and germline. We observed male biased AAEL and NTR gene expression when comparing male carcass with NBF-female carcass (8196 genes and NTRs, 23% of all detected genes and NTRs expressed), male pupae to female pupae (6265 genes and NTRs, 17.5%), male carcass to 72hr-BF-female carcass (3420 genes and NTRs, 9.5%), and male testes and AG to NBF female ovaries (218 genes and NTRs, 0.6%). In contrast, a strong female bias was observed in comparisons between 72-hr BF ovaries and testes plus AG (6165, 17.2%), presumably reflecting the large number and diversity of transcripts deposited in the mature oocyte. An overall male bias in gene expression was recently reported in Drosophila when comparing whole adults, and was proposed to be due to the transcriptional complexity of the testes (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Graveley <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Our results suggest that male biased gene expression also occurs in somatic tissues.</p><p>A number of AAEL genes and NTRs were identified from our sex-specific samples as being expressed at levels &#x0003e;20&#x000d7; in one sex or the other: 234 in males (63% NTRs, 37% AAEL) and 3783 in females (43% NTRs, 57% AAEL; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS28.xlsx">Table S28</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS29.xlsx">Table S29</ext-link>). When the sex-specific expression criteria were tightened to include only those genes expressed strictly sex-specifically (0 reads in the other sex), a much smaller number of genes are identified: 81 in males and 924 in females (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS11.xlsx">Table S11</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS12.xlsx">Table S12</ext-link>). Interestingly, NTRs accounted for the majority of these genes: 91% in females and 71% in males.</p><p>Extensive evidence for sex-specific splicing was also observed in our data from genes expressed in both sexes. We used cufflinks-derived gene models (AAEL-NIPS and NTRs), which represent a significantly more complex transcriptome than the original AAEL gene set, to identify 2468 exons, originating from 1278 loci, as sex-differentially (exon is expressed significantly more abundantly in one sex <italic>vs.</italic> the other) or sex-specifically (exon is exclusively expressed in one sex) expressed with a false discovery rate of 0.05 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS13.xlsx">Table S13</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS14.xlsx">Table S14</ext-link>). Of the genes expressed sex-specifically, or those with exons expressed sex-specifically, a modest number (22 in males and 24 in females) are expressed beginning ~4&#x02212;8 hrs into embryogenesis, suggesting that sex determination/sexual differentiation may have begun by this time. Male-specific genes with similar expression characteristics (although with no homology to those in Aedes) have also recently been identified on the Anopheles stephensi and Anopheles gambiae Y chromosomes, which are thought to be involved in sex determination in these insects (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Hall <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).</p><p>One facet of gene regulation of particular interest because of its potential use in novel vector control strategies has to do with the mechanisms underlying sex-specific expression and mosquito sex determination. <italic>A. aegypti</italic> and other culicine mosquitoes lack heteromorphic sex chromosomes, with sex being controlled by an autosomal locus in which the male-determining allele, M, is dominant (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Craig and Hickey 1967</xref>). The mechanism by which the M locus works to determine sex is unknown, but its activity presumably ultimately leads to sex-specific splicing of products of the doublesex locus, which is sex-specifically spliced in <italic>Aedes</italic> (<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Salvemini <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), and which controls somatic and gonad sexual development in many other insects (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Gempe and Beye 2011</xref>). In a number of insects sex-specific splicing of dsx is regulated by sex-specific splice forms of tra (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Gempe and Beye 2011</xref>). Interestingly, putative tra orthologs have not been identified in mosquitoes, and were not identified in our analysis, suggesting that regulation of sex-specific splicing of dsx may occur through a novel mechanism. Genes involved in sex determination may be included in the set of genes noted above with sex-specific expression or containing sex-specific exons (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS13.xlsx">Table S13</ext-link>). However, it is also possible that some relevant genes are not yet included in the transcriptome, either because of low expression level, or because they are located in regions of the genome not yet included in the Aedes genome sequence, and thus not included in our transcriptome.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>TE dynamics</title><p>Almost 50% of the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> genome consists of identifiable TEs (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Nene <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). TEs exist in a dynamic relationship with their host. They spread through mobilization in the host germline and must evade multiple host mechanisms designed to limit their amplification, which can decrease host fitness if left unchecked. To begin to understand the dynamics of TEs in <italic>A. aegypti</italic> we calculated the expression levels of transcripts derived from TEs through development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS15.xlsx">Table S15</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS16.xlsx">Table S16</ext-link>). The TE family with the greatest overall expression level is the tRNA-related SINE, members of which are expressed at especially high levels in the NBF ovaries. This family consists of three elements, including Feilai A, Feilai B (the most abundant TE in <italic>A. aegypti</italic> with ~50,000 copies per haploid genome), and gecko. There is a dramatic decrease in the expression level of all TEs, with the exception of the tRNA-related SINEs, in the late ovary (72-hr BF) and early embryo. This is followed by a pulse in expression of many TE families in the 4&#x02212;8 hr and 8&#x02212;12 hr embryo time points, followed by a progressive decrease through the completion of embryogenesis, and then an increase in expression in the late larvae and pupae, which may reflect expression in the developing germline.</p><fig id="fig3" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Developmental time course of TE expression profiles. Developmental expression profiles of different TE families, indicating RPKM values (y-axis) across all 42 developmental time points (x-axis). The top 10 TE families with the greatest expression levels are indicated from 1 (highest) to 10 (lowest). All families of TEs are indicated in the table in the lower left, with the number of elements in each family indicated in parentheses. Small numbers associated with specific boxes identify highly expressed TE families from upper plot of RPKM values (A). A circular pie chart indicating the percentage of the annotated genome occupied by each TE class (outer circle), and sublcass (inner circle) (B).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1493f3"/></fig></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Complexity of small RNAs</title><p>Three major classes of small regulatory RNAs are microRNAs (miRNAs), endogenous small interfering RNAs, and Piwi-interacting RNAs (piRNAs) (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Paroo 2010</xref>). miRNAs are initially transcribed as long RNAs containing hairpins. These can be processed through several different mechanisms, after which the released hairpin is transported to the cytoplasm, where it is cleaved by Dicer into a single short ~22 nt double-stranded RNAs. One or both of these strands are loaded into Argonaute family protein-containing complexes known as the RNA-induced silencing complex, where they act as guides for silencing of partially or completely complementary transcripts through translational repression and/or transcript degradation (<xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Yang and Lai 2011</xref>). In contrast, siRNAs are derived from long double-stranded RNAs that are processed by Dicer to produce multiple small RNAs that are also loaded into Argonaute-containing RNA-induced silencing complex complexes (<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Okamura and Lai 2008</xref>). miRNAs range in length from 21 to 23 nt, whereas most siRNAs are ~21 nt. Finally, piRNAs are ~25&#x02212;32 nt; their production does not require Dicer and is otherwise not well understood. They are defined by their association with members of the Piwi family of Argonaute proteins. piRNAs are generated from a variety of different precursors, including long single-stranded RNAs, and complex and repetitive regions, often carrying many transposons or transposon fragments (<xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Siomi <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).</p><p>Depending on the sample, between 80 and 90% of the total small RNA reads produced mapped to the genome, either to unique sites or multiple positions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS3.xlsx">Table S3</ext-link>). Expression levels were merged into a master table in which 55,303,820 reads, 64.49% of the total mapped small RNA reads, formed 291,735 clusters covering 12MB of genomic sequence. Overall, 28,534,187 reads (51.6% of the total mapped reads) aligned to 37,712 genomic positions with a cluster length of 18&#x02212;24 nt; 8,087,495 reads (14.6% of the total mapped reads) aligned to 151,806 genomic positions with a cluster length of 25&#x02212;34 nt; and 18,682,168 reads (33.8%) aligned to 102,217 genomic positions with a cluster length &#x0003e;34 nt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS17.xlsx">Table S17</ext-link>). The vast majority of clusters identified are expressed only (RPM = 0 in other tissues) in the ovary and early embryo samples (249,630; 85.56%). A much smaller number of clusters were specific to the 72-hr female carcass (2581; 0.88% of total clusters), the adult male carcass (415; 0.14% of total clusters) or the testes plus AG (13,227; 4.5% of total clusters).</p><p>Interestingly, depending on the sample, between 26.74 and 75.19% of the total clustered mapped reads, corresponding to 23.88 and 59.85% of the total reads respectively, mapped to regions of the genome with no other annotated features (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). For those clusters that did map to annotated features, miRNAs, small RNA corresponding to sense or antisense fragments of transposons, polyAplus NTRs, and protein-coding mRNAs were the most abundant classes, with tRNAs, rRNAs, snRNAs, snoRNAs and miscRNAs making up the remainder (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Small RNA distribution and clustering. Length distributions for small RNAs that map to the genome are indicated as percentages of the total reads mapping to the genome, for each library. Results from both unique and multimapping are shown. Samples are indicated to the right. Dotted line corresponds to the length distribution for previously annotated Aedes miRNAs included in mirBase (A). Heat map representation of all previously annotated miRNAs in <italic>A. aegypti</italic>, and 38 newly discovered miRNAs. Scale bar indicates FPKM Z-scores (B). Genome browser snap shot of a 54,727-bp genomic region, dense in 27&#x02212;32bp mapped fragments, on supercontig 1: 1,174,222-1,228,948. All small RNA libraries are uniquely mapped (C). Color bar graph depicting the log<sub>2</sub> RPM (reads per million) of each miRNA expressed in the 9 samples indicated to the right, organized in order from most to least abundant (D). The sample color scale for (A&#x02212;C) is identical, as depicted in C, and is as follows: male testes and AG (red), male carcass (orange), 72-hr BF-F-carcass (blue), 2&#x02212;4 hr embryo (green), 0&#x02212;2 hr embryo (brown), 72-hr BF-ovary (purple), 48-hr Bf-ovary (light green), 24-hr BF-ovary (light red), and NBF ovary (black).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1493f4"/></fig></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Small RNA distributions</title><p>Small RNA libraries from different samples also have distinct size distributions. Male and female carcasses have a narrow distribution of lengths centered at 22 nt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). As expected, most of these (~90%) are miRNAs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). In contrast, miRNAs comprise a much smaller fraction of the reads that map to known features in the germline and early embryo libraries, with many reads mapping to TEs, NTRs, and AAEL genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>). This shift in features to which the small RNAs map is particularly striking for libraries from 0&#x02212;2 and 2&#x02212;4 hr embryos, from which miRNAs comprise less than 25% or 10% of uniquely mapped reads, respectively. In addition to a peak of small RNA abundance centered around 22 nt, these libraries show a second broader peak RNA length centered around 27&#x02212;28 nt. Most small RNAs mapping to TEs, which are known to be important sources of piRNAs in other organisms, fall within the size range 25&#x02212;30 nt, suggesting that these are piRNAs. The RPM values for small RNAs mapping to specific TE element classes are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS20.xlsx">Table S20</ext-link>). The general trend of small RNA abundance associated with specific TE families is consistent across the time points assayed, with the most abundant class mapping to Ty3-Gypsy, followed by Pao_Bel, Ty1_copia, CR1 and I. Very few small RNAs mapping to TEs are found in male and female carcasses, despite the fact that transposons are expressed in these tissues at significant levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Small RNA mapping results and expression profiles to features. Percentage of reads mapping to the genome or annotated features; results are shown using multi-mapping (unlimited alignments) and unique mapping (single alignment) for the samples indicated on the X axis. The fraction of reads corresponding to novel transcribed features is indicated in red (A). Of the small RNAs that map to known features, the percent of small RNAs mapping to specific features is indicated for both multi and unique mapping (B). RPM values (y-axis) for each small RNA library (x-axis) were quantified against all annotated TE element families in <italic>A. aegypti</italic> for both multi and unique mapping. Numbers highlight the TEs for which small RNAs are most abundant across all samples (C).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1493f5"/></fig></sec><sec id="s19"><title>miRNA identification</title><p>To identify miRNAs we aligned sequenced small RNAs to the most current miRBase database v18 using BLAST and identified 101 (100%) of previously annotated <italic>A. aegypti</italic> or <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> miRNAs (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Skalsky <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). We also identified 36 novel <italic>A. aegypti</italic>&#x02212;specific miRNAs, as well as two evolutionarily conserved miRNAs not previously identified in <italic>A. aegypti</italic> or <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS18.xlsx">Table S18</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS19.xlsx">Table S19</ext-link>). Overall, 18% of the total small RNA reads mapping to the genome (25,241,117) aligned to previously annotated and newly predicted miRNAs, with an average mature miRNA size of 22 bp. The 15 most abundant miRNAs, each contributing &#x0003e;1.6% of total mapped reads, accounted for 81% of miRNA reads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>). 95% of miRNAs were expressed in the ovaries, and 21% of the miRNAs are located in introns of annotated genes.</p><p>We compared the abundance of the miRNAs across all nine developmental time points and hierarchically clustered the data in a heat map to visualize prominent patterns of expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS18.xlsx">Table S18</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS19.xlsx">Table S19</ext-link>). The clustering produced three major groups of miRNAs: those with low, moderate and high expression levels. As subclasses within these groups we find (1) developmentally uniformly abundant, (2) carcass and testes biased, (3) ovary expressed and maternally deposited, (4) carcass and testes specific, and (5) various other patterns of expression, generally weaker. To visualize miRNA abundance, we plotted the normalized RPKM values for each miRNA across all nine developmental time points in a bar graph, ordered from most to least abundant. Bantam was the most abundant miRNA overall and in the adult carcasses, mir-996 was the most abundant miRNA in embryos, and mir-989 was the most abundant miRNA in the ovaries. mir-263B was expressed almost exclusively in the male and female carcasses, whereas mir-286b-1, mir-286-b-2, mir-309b, mir-2944b, and mir-286a were specifically expressed in the female ovary and maternally deposited into the early embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>piRNAs</title><p>In <italic>Drosophila</italic>, a number of piRNAs derive from clusters composed of repeated sequences and transposon remnants that are localized in pericentromeric and subtelomeric regions (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Brennecke <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Saito <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). To search for dense regions of piRNA expression, we grouped together all regions expressing small RNAs within 1 kb of each other, with a minimum read count of three, into single superclusters. This reduced the total cluster number by 85%, producing a total of 46,631 superclusters ranging from 44 to 54,727 bp (avg. 992 bp) covering 43 MB of genomic sequence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS21.xlsx">Table S21</ext-link>). The majority of reads in these large clusters are between 24-32 nt in length, suggesting that these represent piRNA clusters. An example of a 54,727-bp region to which no known miRNAs or annotated genes align, that is dense with uniquely mapped 24-32bp small RNAs in all assayed tissues is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>. A recent analysis of small RNAs from whole <italic>A. aegypti</italic> adults also resulted in the identification of large genomic regions that express many 24-32 nt small RNAs (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Arensburger <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Our results extend these observations through analysis of both germline and somatic tissue samples.</p><p>Other piRNA clusters derive from unique positions within genes. For example, in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, traffic jam (tj) encodes a large Maf factor, which is expressed in the ovarian soma and required for gonad morphogenesis. Numerous piRNAs are produced from the sense strand of the tj 3&#x02032;UTR (<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Robine <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Saito <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Small RNAs of a similar length are also produced from the 3&#x02032;UTR of the <italic>A.aegypti</italic> tj homolog (AAEL007686), and from 7736 AAEL mRNAs with at least three small RNA reads mapping in at least one tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS22.xlsx">Table S22</ext-link>), suggesting that piRNAs regulation of protein coding genes in Aedes is widespread. Similar results were reported by <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Arensburger <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref>.</p><fig id="fig6" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>piRNA production by a single locus and RNA expression profiles for genes involved in small RNA production. (A) An example of piRNAs mapping specifically to the 3&#x02032;UTR of AAEL007686 is shown. (B) The expression dynamics across development of genes important for processing of different small RNAs, including miRNA, siRNAs, and piRNAs are shown as a heat map (log2 FPKM).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1493f6"/></fig><p>To gain a global view of the genes involved in small RNA processing we constructed a heat-map to visualize their expression dynamics across development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>). Increased expression of a number of genes occurs in the ovary in response to a blood meal. Other patterns of tissue/stage specific expression are also apparent. For example, Piwi-3 is specific to the ovary, whereas Piwi-7 is zygotically activated specifically in the early embryo. The significance of these patterns is unknown, but they suggest that small RNA processing is dynamically regulated, and that much remains to be learned about small RNA processing and function.</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Transcriptional profiling and transgenesis-based vector control</title><p>In addition to providing a tool for basic research on <italic>A. aegypti</italic>, the developmental transcriptome will facilitate the development of transgenesis-based control of vector populations through population suppression or replacement of the wild population with individuals refractory to disease transmission. For example, one class of suppression strategies involves the creation of males whose sperm express a transgene-based toxin that cause the death of all progeny (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Klein <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Windbichler <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). In a second, males are engineered to carry a transgene expressed (in a repressible manner in the laboratory) in females, causing their death or some other large fitness cost such as flightlessness (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Fu <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Promoters from genes that drive testis- or female-specific expression are needed for these approaches, and several have been identified in <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> using candidate gene approaches (reviewed in <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Catteruccia <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS11.xlsx">Table S11</ext-link> (female specific) and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS12.xlsx">Table S12</ext-link> (male specific) identify a number of additional genes with similar expression patterns that may also prove useful. Exons of genes expressed in both sexes that have strict sex-specific splicing of particular exons can also be used to bring about sex-specific phenotypes (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Fu <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Examples of these are found in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS13.xlsx">Table S13</ext-link>. A third population suppression strategy involves driving a engineered homing endonuclease into a population, with the insertion site for the homing endonuclease being located within gene whose product is required for female viability or fertility (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Burt 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">Windbichler <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Homing endonucleases have very long target sites and are highly specific in their insertion site preference. Although number of novel homing endonucleases have recently been identified (<xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">Takeuchi <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), and some progress has been made in creating homing endonucleases with altered target specificity (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Ashworth <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Ulge <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), many genes lack sequences that would make them targets for cleavage by currently available homing endonucleases. In addition, cleavage followed by nonhomologous end joining (in the absence of homing) can potentially result in destruction of the target site without loss of gene function (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Burt 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Deredec <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Therefore, it is important to have many potential target genes available. Good candidates are likely to be found among those genes expressed only in the female (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS24.xlsx">Table S24</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS11.xlsx">Table S11</ext-link>). Modeling studies suggest that ideal targets would be genes whose loss-of-function results in recessive, but not dominant fitness costs, in somatic tissues, but not the germline (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Deredec <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). For such genes, homing in the germline of a heterozygous female (which creates homozygous mutant germ cells) does not compromise transmission of the HEG to the next generation (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Deredec <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Genes expressed specifically in female somatic tissues are indicated in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS24.xlsx">Table S24</ext-link>.</p><p>Several strategies have also been proposed for driving genes for disease refractoriness into wild mosquito populations, including the use of engineered homing endonucleases (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Burt 2003</xref>), engineered zygotic underdominance (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Davis <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>), male meiotic drive (<xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Sinkins and Gould 2006</xref>), <italic>Medea</italic> (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), and a Medea-related gene drive system known as UD<sup>MEL</sup> (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Akbari <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Here we focus on <italic>Medea</italic> and UD<sup>MEL</sup> as these have been successfully implemented in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Akbari <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). A <italic>Medea</italic> selfish genetic element consists of two linked genes: a toxin that is expressed only in the female germline, with effects that are passed to all progeny, and a neutralizing antidote, expressed under the control of an early zygote-specific promoter. As implemented in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, the toxin consists of maternally-expressed miRNAs that silence the expression of a maternally expressed gene whose product is required for embryogenesis, thereby creating a maternal-effect lethal phenotype in all progeny. The antidote is a zygotically expressed version of the maternally silenced gene, resistant to miRNA-dependent silencing, able to provide the missing maternal product, thereby restoring normal development (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Akbari <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). <italic>Medea</italic> spreads because when present in females, it causes the death of all progeny that fail to inherit it, thereby promoting its spread at the expense of homologous chromosomes that lack it (<xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">Wade and Beeman 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Ward <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). In the UD<sup>MEL</sup> system, which has a higher introduction threshold, and is therefore more easily recalled from the population, similar components are used, but they are located on different chromosomes. miRNAs expressed and processed at high levels in the ovary and early embryo are good candidates to function as backbones for toxin expression in both systems (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS18.xlsx">Table S18</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS19.xlsx">Table S19</ext-link>).</p><p>Transcripts found in the ovary and early embryo are likely to derive from genes that are expressed in the maternal germline, with their products being dumped into the oocyte and persisting for some time following fertilization. To identify genes expressed specifically in the female germline whose promoters could be used to drive the expression of toxins, we filtered the developmental transcriptome to identify genes expressed only in the ovary and early embryo (RPKM = 0 in other samples), with the embryonic expression trending only downward following fertilization. Many AAEL genes and NTRs with these expression characteristics were identified (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS25.xlsx">Table S25</ext-link>). Transcripts found only in the ovary and not in the early embryo are likely to derive from genes expressed in ovarian somatic tissues such as the follicle cells, which die before egg laying. Filtering of the transcriptome to identify genes strictly expressed in the ovary but not elsewhere (RPKM = 0 in female and male carcass, testes plus AG and 0&#x02212;2 hr embryo) identified several genes with this expression characteristic (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS26.xlsx">Table S26</ext-link>). These genes and their promoters would not be useful for generation of Medea elements, but their transcription units could be interesting targets for homing endonucleases designed to impair female fertility.</p><p>Genes that are expressed ubiquitously, specifically in the early zygote, can provide promoters to drive the expression of antidotes. In <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> zygotic transcription is first seen ~2&#x02212;4 hrs post oviposition, and two kinesin light chain genes, AaKLC2.1 and AaKLC2.2, have been shown to be expressed specifically from 2 to 8 hrs, although whether these genes are expressed ubiquitously in space is unknown (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Biedler and Tu 2010</xref>). Several other genes with early zygotic expression in Aedes have also been recently identified, though the results of our sequencing would suggest that some of these are also expressed at significant levels in stages not sampled (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Biedler <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). To provide a comprehensive list of genes expressed only in the early zygote we filtered the <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> developmental transcriptome to identify genes that were not expressed (FPKM = 0) in the 7 ovarian samples or 0&#x02212;2hr embryos, that were expressed in the 2-4hr time window, and that then decreased in intensity, as expected for transcripts expressed transiently and then degraded. This analysis discovered 40 strictly early zygotic AAEL genes and NTRs, validating the expression patterns of the kinesin light chain genes and identifying 38 additional genes and NTRs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/TableS27.xlsx">Table S27</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s22"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study we used RNA-seq to provide the most comprehensive description to date of the transcriptome of a mosquito vector of disease, <italic>A. aegypti</italic>. Our analysis of polyA plus libraries revealed an unanticipated complexity to the <italic>Aedes</italic> transcriptome. Our results provide confirmation for 99% (15,941/15,988) of previously annotated AAEL genes. However, they also provide evidence for extensive transcription in other areas of the genome. Approximately11.19 MB of this is associated with genomic sequence overlapping the AAEL genes (AAEL-NIPs). Some of this may reflect the identification of new genes inside or overlapping with AAEL genes, while other new sequence may reflect the identification of novel transcribed AAEL exons. NTRs that show no overlap with AAEL genes or AAEL-NIPs provide expression evidence for another 13.27 MB of transcribed DNA. The validity of these new predictions will need to be confirmed using other techniques, but the fact that many of these novel transcripts and NTRs were observed in multiple samples suggests that many new splice forms of previously annotated genes and new genes have in fact been identified. In addition, our analysis is almost certainly an underestimate of the fraction of the genome transcribed as long RNA, since rare transcripts found only in specific tissues may not have been identified. Transcripts will also have been missed if they are only expressed in specific contexts&#x02014;such as during stress, aging, exposure to toxins or pathogens&#x02014;that were not sampled, or if they are not polyadenylated.</p><p>Roughly 21.5% of the NTRs were identified as being potentially noncoding, based on having a size greater than 200 nt, an FPKM of 10 or greater, and the lack of an ORF of 200 amino acids or greater. This set of cutoffs is somewhat arbitrary as it will incorrectly call as noncoding transcripts encoding small peptides or proteins generated through stop codon readthrough (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Jungreis <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Ladoukakis <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), and it will exclude short noncoding NTRs. However, it has been used as a part of search strategies for high confidence noncoding NTRs in other systems (<xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">Young <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). The structures of these NTRs are quite distinct in that their transcript lengths are on average shorter than AAEL genes and AAEL-NIPs (NTRs = 1132 bp; AAEL = 1514 bp; AAEL-NIPs = 4051 bp), and have fewer exons (NTRs = 1.58; AAEL = 3.79; AAEL-NIPs = 7.65) in addition to their genomic length being shorter (NTRs = 9250 bp; AAEL = 14,888 bp; AAEL-NIPs = 72,828 bp). Some NTRs may simply represent exons of coding genes that have not been linked to AAEL or AAEL-NIPs because of sequencing depth. However, a number are expressed at high levels, making this explanation unlikely as a general conclusion. It is also possible that some represent contamination by genomic DNA. Although it is difficult to exclude this possibility in the case of single exon transcripts, we note that a number of these NTRs are expressed differentially, during the lifecycle, making this also unlikely as a general explanation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.113.006742/-/DC1/FigureS1.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link>). A more rigorous identification of noncoding RNAs among the <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> NTR set will be facilitated by use of comparative genomics methods (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Lin <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Washietl <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), once RNAseq-based transcriptomes are available for closely related species such as <italic>A. albopictus</italic>, and more distantly related species such as <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> and <italic>Anpheles stephensi</italic>.</p><p>Our cluster analysis and characterization of sex-differential and sex-specific expression of AAEL genes, AAEL-NIPs and NTRs identified a number of patterns of co-regulated gene expression. Analysis of these patterns will help to uncover <italic>cis</italic>-acting regulatory elements, the genetic circuits underlying specific developmental transitions, biology specific to adult males and females, and parts needed to engineer transgene-based mechanisms capable of bringing about population suppression or replacement. The patterns observed are likely to often represent changes in the transcription and splicing of the genes involved. However, differential regulation of transcript stability by <italic>trans</italic>-acting factors such as microRNAs and RNA-binding proteins will also undoubtedly be important in some cases. In addition, recent work has shown that adults of Aedes strains differing in a number of ways, including place of origin, number of generations in the lab, and susceptibility to dengue infection, show significant differences in their transcriptional responses to sugar feeding or a blood meal (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Bonizzoni <italic>et al.</italic> 2012b</xref>). Thus, the observations presented here should be taken to constitute only a broad-brush overview of the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> developmental transcriptome, albeit of a strain (Liverpool) used as a model by many researchers. An important future goal will be to characterize patterns of gene expression from many strains, with the goal of identifying developmental and adult signatures that predict important life history traits such as longevity, ecotype, resistance to agents that might be used in larval or adult vector control, and susceptibility to dengue infection. The pathways identified by these genes may provide new targets for transgenesis-based strategies of vector control and/or vector competence.</p><p>One of the most remarkable features of the Aedes aegypti genome is its large TE content (~50% of the genome), and overall size, 1.37 Gigabases, almost five times that of the malaria vector Anopheles gambiae. Our analysis highlights the dynamic nature of TE expression throughout the Aedes lifecycle. Changes in the levels and relative abundance of specific TEs during adult ovarian development in response to blood feeding are particularly striking. Because the female germline is a target for transposon spread, it will be particularly interesting to determine if TEs with abundant transcripts are undergoing active expansion in Aedes. Related to this last point it is also noteworthy that some of the TEs with the highest levels of expression (tSINE, mTA, m8bp, and m3bp) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>) have very low numbers of corresponding small RNAs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). This is particularly obvious for the tRNA-related SINEs. These are expressed at very high levels in the nonblood-fed ovary, and are abundantly expressed in other samples as well. Yet small RNAs corresponding to these elements make up only between 0 and 0.004% of the total TE-associated small RNAs. MITES also have low levels of small RNAs, despite having high expression levels, and high copy numbers in the genome. Low levels of piRNAs targeting these TE classes were also noted by Arensburger <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Arensburger <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). These authors suggested lack of coding potential as one possible explanation for such a pattern and noted relatively more siRNAs targeting these elements. Although we also see a modest bias toward siRNAs the fact remains that these elements are simply not targeted at high frequency, or do not act as sources of small RNAs, in all samples tested. One possibility is that these invaded only recently, and have not yet been captured by piRNA-generating loci. More detailed studies of the evolutionary history of these elements will be required to test this hypothesis, but initial characterization of the Feilai family of tRNA-related SINE elements shows significant sequence diversity, suggesting they are unlikely to be of very recent origin (<xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Tu 1999</xref>). Overall, our analysis highlights the dynamic nature of TE expression throughout development.</p><p>Our results show that the Aedes small RNA transcriptome is dynamically regulated. Depending on the sample, we observed that between 24.81 and 65.58% of small RNA reads mapped to annotated features. Of those that map to features there are dramatic shifts in the nature of the features targeted depending on the sample. miRNAs predominate in somatic carcass tissues, with NTRs making up the next highest category. In the ovary and embryo samples, 71.01&#x02013;82.19% of reads that do not map to features are of size range 26&#x02212;32 bp, suggesting they are piRNAs. Similar observations were made by Arensburger <italic>et al.</italic>, in samples from whole adults (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Arensburger <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>); our work refines these observations to multiple tissues, both germline and somatic. Some piRNAs that do not map to features may be degenerate remnants of past battles with extinct transposons. Alternatively, and/or in addition, some may arise simply because specific regions of the genome are predisposed to generate piRNAs, with whatever is inserted into the locus becoming a substrate for piRNA production. In such a model, these regions would act to sample and respond to TEs (and other sequences) that happen to insert into them in a manner similar to the Crispr loci in prokaryotes, which generate small RNAs for genome defense from sequences that become inserted into them (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Barrangou 2013</xref>). It will be particularly interesting to compare the Aedes piRNA system with that of anopheles mosquitoes to see if this sheds light on the mechanisms leading to the massive expansion of the Aedes TE content and genome size.</p><p>We have incorporated the data from our analysis into a web-based genome browser structured using the UCSC browser format (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Kent <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). We include the current AAEL annotations as well as new AAEL-NIPs, NTRs and transcript models predicted using Cufflinks and Tophat. Each transcript and gene model is linked to Vectorbase, which provides reference genome sequences and other information on the most important disease vectors (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Lawson <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Researchers can view <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> gene expression data for every time point, explore transcript and gene models, and compare sequence conservation with several Drosophila species and Anopheles gambiae and <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>. Data can also be imported into the genome browser for viewing and comparison. As an example, we incorporated recent RNA-seq data describing patterns of gene expression observed 5 hr PBM in whole <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>, a time point not included in our data set (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Bonizzoni <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). This browser can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Aedes.caltech.edu">http://Aedes.caltech.edu</ext-link>. The transcriptome data presented will facilitate study of Aedes basic biology. It will also facilitate the development of transgenesis-based strategies of population suppression or population replacement.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supporting Information</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_3_9_1493__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_006742SI.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_FigureS1.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_FigureS2.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application"
mime-subtype="x-zip-compressed"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_FileS1.zip"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application"
mime-subtype="x-zip-compressed"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_FileS2.zip"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application"
mime-subtype="x-zip-compressed"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_FileS3.zip"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application"
mime-subtype="x-zip-compressed"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_FileS4.zip"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS1.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS2.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS3.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS4.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS5.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS6.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS7.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS8.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS9.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS10.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS11.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS12.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS13.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS14.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS15.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS16.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS17.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS18.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS19.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS20.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS21.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS22.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS23.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS24.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS25.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS26.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS27.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS28.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS29.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_g3.113.006742_TableS30.xlsx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Alexei Aravin and Katalin Fejes Toth for providing small RNA cloning protocol and expertise. We thank Lorain Schaeffer and Vijaya Kumar for help with library preparations and sequencing. This work was supported by grants to B.A.H. by the National Institutes of Health (DP1 OD003878) and the Weston Havens Foundation, the Bren foundation to Barbara Wold, the Caltech Beckman Functional Genomic Center, and the Millard and Muriel Jacobs Genetics and Genomics Laboratory at California Institute of Technology. Brian Williams and Henry Amrhein were supported by grants to Barbara Wold.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn2"><p>Communicating editor: S. Celniker</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abedini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raleigh</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A critical assessment of the role of helical intermediates in amyloid formation by natively unfolded proteins and polypeptides.</article-title>
<source>Protein Eng. Des. Sel.</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19596696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akbari</surname><given-names>O. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antoshechkin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A synthetic gene drive system for local, reversible modification and suppression of insect populations.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23541732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alphey</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nimmo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alphey</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Insect population suppression using engineered insects.</article-title>
<source>Adv. Exp. Med. Biol.</source>
<volume>627</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18510017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arensburger</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hice</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The mosquito <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> has a large genome size and high transposable element load but contains a low proportion of transposon-specific piRNAs.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>606</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22171608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashworth</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Havranek</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quadri</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoddard</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Computational reprogramming of homing endonuclease specificity at multiple adjacent base pairs.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>5601</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20435674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinder</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crisanti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A comprehensive gene expression atlas of sex- and tissue-specificity in the malaria vector, <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>296</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21649883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barrangou</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>CRISPR-Cas systems and RNA-guided interference.</article-title>
<source>Wiley Interdiscip Rev RNA</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23520078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgs</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Yellow fever: a disease that has yet to be conquered.</article-title>
<source>Annu. Rev. Entomol.</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16913829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behura</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Machorro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harker</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>deBruyn</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovin</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Global cross-talk of genes of the mosquito <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> in response to dengue virus infection.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Negl. Trop. Dis.</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1385</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22102922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolotin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The noncoding RNA mistral activates Hoxa6 and Hoxa7 expression and stem cell differentiation by recruiting MLL1 to chromatin.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Cell</source>
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>1040</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21925392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biedler</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Evolutionary analysis of the kinesin light chain genes in the yellow fever mosquito <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>: gene duplication as a source for novel early zygotic genes.</article-title>
<source>BMC Evol. Biol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>206</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20615250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biedler</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tae</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Identification of early zygotic genes in the yellow fever mosquito <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and discovery of a motif involved in early zygotic genome activation.</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e33933</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22457801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimon</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>RNA-seq analyses of blood-induced changes in gene expression in the mosquito vector species, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>82</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21276245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marinotti</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year><comment>a</comment>&#x02003;<article-title>Complex modulation of the <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> transcriptome in response to dengue virus infection.</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e50512</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23209765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marinotti</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year><comment>b</comment>&#x02003;<article-title>Strain variation in the transcriptome of the dengue fever vector, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>.</article-title>
<source>G3 (Bethesda)</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22384387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brennecke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aravin</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dus</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Discrete small RNA-generating loci as master regulators of transposon activity in Drosophila.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>128</volume>: <fpage>1089</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17346786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2003</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Site-specific selfish genes as tools for the control and genetic engineering of natural populations.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Biol. Sci.</source>
<volume>270</volume>: <fpage>921</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12803906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulouris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Avagyan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications.</article-title>
<source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caragata</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poinsignon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Improved accuracy of the transcriptional profiling method of age grading in <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> mosquitoes under laboratory and semi-field cage conditions and in the presence of Wolbachia infection.</article-title>
<source>Insect Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21114562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Catteruccia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crisanti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wimmer</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transgenic technologies to induce sterility.</article-title>
<source>Malar. J.</source>
<volume>8</volume>(<issue>Suppl 2</issue>): <fpage>S7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19917077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>L. V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A synthetic maternal-effect selfish genetic element drives population replacement in Drosophila.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>316</volume>: <fpage>597</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17395794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1999</year>&#x02003;<source>The Biology of Mosquitoes</source>. <publisher-name>CABI</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxon, UK</publisher-loc></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clemons</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haugen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flannery</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomchaney</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kast</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Aedes aegypti: an emerging model for vector mosquito development.</article-title>
<source>Cold Spring Harb. Protoc.</source>
<volume>2010</volume>: <fpage>pdb emo141</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20889691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colpitts</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlandingham</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feitosa</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Alterations in the <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> transcriptome during infection with West Nile, dengue and yellow fever viruses.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002189</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21909258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1967</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Current status of the formal genetics of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Bull. World Health Organ.</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5299452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dana</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillenmeyer</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harker</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2005</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Gene expression patterns associated with blood-feeding in the malaria mosquito <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15651988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coissac</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melodelima</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poupardin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riaz</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcriptome response to pollutants and insecticides in the dengue vector <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> using next-generation sequencing technology.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>216</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20356352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bax</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grewe</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2001</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Engineered underdominance allows efficient and economical introgression of traits into pest populations.</article-title>
<source>J. Theor. Biol.</source>
<volume>212</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11527447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deredec</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The population genetics of using homing endonuclease genes in vector and pest management.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>179</volume>: <fpage>2013</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18660532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dissanayake</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>aeGEPUCI: a database of gene expression in the dengue vector mosquito, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>.</article-title>
<source>BMC Res. Notes</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20920356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayhew</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aliota</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Mosquito infection responses to developing filarial worms.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Negl. Trop. Dis.</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e529</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19823571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falcon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Using GOstats to test gene lists for GO term association.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17098774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nimmo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aw</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Female-specific flightless phenotype for mosquito control.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>107</volume>: <fpage>4550</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20176967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gempe</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beye</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Function and evolution of sex determination mechanisms, genes and pathways in insects.</article-title>
<source>Bioessays</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21110346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Janson</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hittinger</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbot</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Benchmarking next-generation transcriptome sequencing for functional and evolutionary genomics.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19706727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goltsev</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezende</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vranizan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanzaro</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Developmental and evolutionary basis for drought tolerance of the <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> embryo.</article-title>
<source>Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>330</volume>: <fpage>462</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19298808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graveley</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duff</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landolin</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The developmental transcriptome of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>471</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21179090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isturiz</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Update on the global spread of dengue.</article-title>
<source>Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>S40</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20833000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Artsob</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchy</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Dengue: a continuing global threat.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>S7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21079655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Timoshevskiy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharakhova</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharakhov</surname><given-names>I. V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Six novel Y chromosome genes in Anopheles mosquitoes discovered by independently sequencing males and females.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23617698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Dengue virus-mosquito interactions.</article-title>
<source>Annu. Rev. Entomol.</source>
<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17803458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Engineering the genomes of wild insect populations: challenges, and opportunities provided by synthetic Medea selfish genetic elements.</article-title>
<source>J. Insect Physiol.</source>
<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20570677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hemingway</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vontas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>&#x02003;<article-title>An overview of insecticide resistance.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>298</volume>: <fpage>96</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12364782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ptitsyn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebel</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Small RNA profiling of Dengue virus-mosquito interactions implicates the PIWI RNA pathway in anti-viral defense.</article-title>
<source>BMC Microbiol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21356105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Engineering mosquito resistance to malaria parasites: the avian malaria model.</article-title>
<source>Insect Biochem. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12225922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jungreis</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spokony</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Negre</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Evidence of abundant stop codon readthrough in Drosophila and other metazoa.</article-title>
<source>Genome Res.</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>2096</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21994247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugnet</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Furey</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roskin</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2002</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The human genome browser at UCSC.</article-title>
<source>Genome Res.</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>996</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12045153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Windbichler</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deredec</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedict</surname><given-names>M. Q.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Infertility resulting from transgenic I-PpoI male Anopheles gambiae in large cage trials.</article-title>
<source>Pathog Glob Health</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22595271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S. Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>CPC: assess the protein-coding potential of transcripts using sequence features and support vector machine.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>W345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17631615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Futschik</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Mfuzz: a software package for soft clustering of microarray data.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformation</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18084642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ladoukakis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magny</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyre-Walker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Couso</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Hundreds of putatively functional small open reading frames in Drosophila.</article-title>
<source>Genome Biol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>R118</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22118156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arensburger</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Besansky</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruggner</surname><given-names>R. V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>VectorBase: a data resource for invertebrate vector genomics.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>D583</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19028744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Direct sequencing and expression analysis of a large number of miRNAs in <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and a multi-species survey of novel mosquito miRNAs.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>581</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19961592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ligon</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Reemergence of an unusual disease: the chikungunya epidemic.</article-title>
<source>Semin. Pediatr. Infect. Dis.</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16822471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jungreis</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>PhyloCSF: a comparative genomics method to distinguish protein coding and non-coding regions.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>i275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>i282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21685081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paroo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Biochemical principles of small RNA pathways.</article-title>
<source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>
<volume>79</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20205586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loewer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabili</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guttman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Large intergenic non-coding RNA-RoR modulates reprogramming of human induced pluripotent stem cells.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21057500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lounibos</surname><given-names>L. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Invasions by insect vectors of human disease.</article-title>
<source>Annu. Rev. Entomol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11729075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Windbichler</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papathanos</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcription regulation of sex-biased genes during ontogeny in the malaria vector <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>.</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e21572</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21738713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marinotti</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>Q. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dissanayake</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genome-wide analysis of gene expression in adult <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Insect Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16469063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Mapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-Seq.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Methods</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18516045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neira-Oviedo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsyganov-Bodounov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lycett</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokoza</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raikhel</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The RNA-Seq approach to studying the expression of mosquito mitochondrial genes.</article-title>
<source>Insect Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20958808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nene</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wortman</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodira</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genome sequence of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>, a major arbovirus vector.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>316</volume>: <fpage>1718</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17510324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nimmo</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alphey</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggleston</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>High efficiency site-specific genetic engineering of the mosquito genome.</article-title>
<source>Insect Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16640723</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Endogenous small interfering RNAs in animals.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>673</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18719707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozsolak</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milos</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>RNA sequencing: advances, challenges and opportunities.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21191423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paris</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melodelima</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coissac</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetreau</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynaud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcription profiling of resistance to Bti toxins in the mosquito <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> using next-generation sequencing.</article-title>
<source>J. Invertebr. Pathol.</source>
<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22115744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ptitsyn</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes-Solis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saavedra-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Betz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchman</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Rhythms and synchronization patterns in gene expression in the <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> mosquito.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21414217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinker</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Blood meal-induced changes to antennal transcriptome profiles reveal shifts in odor sensitivities in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>110</volume>: <fpage>8260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23630291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robine</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A broadly conserved pathway generates 3&#x02032;UTR-directed primary piRNAs.</article-title>
<source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2066</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2076</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20022248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Specific association of Piwi with rasiRNAs derived from retrotransposon and heterochromatic regions in the Drosophila genome.</article-title>
<source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2214</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16882972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mituyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A regulatory circuit for piwi by the large Maf gene traffic jam in Drosophila.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>461</volume>: <fpage>1296</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19812547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salvemini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zazzaro</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genomic organization and splicing evolution of the doublesex gene, a Drosophila regulator of sexual differentiation, in the dengue and yellow fever mosquito <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>.</article-title>
<source>BMC Evol. Biol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21310052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Severson</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Behura</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Mosquito genomics: progress and challenges.</article-title>
<source>Annu. Rev. Entomol.</source>
<volume>57</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21942845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheik Mohamed</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaughwin</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipovich</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Conserved long noncoding RNAs transcriptionally regulated by Oct4 and Nanog modulate pluripotency in mouse embryonic stem cells.</article-title>
<source>RNA</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>324</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20026622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimopoulos</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Dengue virus inhibits immune responses in <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> cells.</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e10678</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20502529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinkins</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Gene drive systems for insect disease vectors.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16682981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siomi</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pezic</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aravin</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>PIWI-interacting small RNAs: the vanguard of genome defence.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>246</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21427766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skalsky</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlandingham</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgs</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Identification of microRNAs expressed in two mosquito vectors, <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> and <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>.</article-title>
<source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20167119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souza-Neto</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimopoulos</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>An evolutionary conserved function of the JAK-STAT pathway in anti-dengue defense.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>17841</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17846</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Surget-Groba</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montoya-Burgos</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Optimization of de novo transcriptome assembly from next-generation sequencing data.</article-title>
<source>Genome Res.</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1432</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20693479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacoby</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Tapping natural reservoirs of homing endonucleases for targeted gene modification.</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<volume>108</volume>: <fpage>13077</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13082</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21784983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terenius</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marinotti</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieglaff</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Molecular genetic manipulation of vector mosquitoes.</article-title>
<source>Cell Host Microbe</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18996342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>&#x02003;<article-title>TopHat: discovering splice junctions with RNA-Seq.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19289445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation.</article-title>
<source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>511</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1999</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Genomic and evolutionary analysis of Feilai, a diverse family of highly reiterated SINEs in the yellow fever mosquito, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>760</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10368954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ulge</surname><given-names>U. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monnat</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Comprehensive computational design of mCreI homing endonuclease cleavage specificity for genome engineering.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>4330</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21288879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanlandingham</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klinger</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vessey</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fredregillo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2007</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Relative susceptibilties of South Texas mosquitoes to infection with West Nile virus.</article-title>
<source>Am. J. Trop. Med. Hyg.</source>
<volume>77</volume>: <fpage>925</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17984355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beeman</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1994</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The population dynamics of maternal-effect selfish genes.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>138</volume>: <fpage>1309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7896109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Medea selfish genetic elements as tools for altering traits of wild populations: a theoretical analysis.</article-title>
<source>Evolution</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>1149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21062278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Washietl</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Findeiss</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalkhof</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>von Bergen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>RNAcode: robust discrimination of coding and noncoding regions in comparative sequence data.</article-title>
<source>RNA</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>578</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21357752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Windbichler</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menichelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papathanos</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thyme</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>A synthetic homing endonuclease-based gene drive system in the human malaria mosquito.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>473</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21508956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Windbichler</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papathanos</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crisanti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Targeting the X chromosome during spermatogenesis induces Y chromosome transmission ratio distortion and early dominant embryo lethality in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Genet.</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000291</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19057670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimopoulos</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>&#x02003;<article-title>The <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> toll pathway controls dengue virus infection.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000098</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18604274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Alternative miRNA biogenesis pathways and the interpretation of core miRNA pathway mutants.</article-title>
<source>Mol. Cell</source>
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>892</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21925378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibbit</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haerty</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassett</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Identification and properties of 1,119 candidate lincRNA loci in the <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> genome.</article-title>
<source>Genome Biol. Evol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22403033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2001</year>&#x02003;<article-title>InterProScan&#x02014;an integration platform for the signature-recognition methods in InterPro.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>847</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11590104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busche</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Identification of juvenile hormone target genes in the adult female mosquitoes.</article-title>
<source>Insect Biochem. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20018242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza-Neto</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokoza</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>&#x02003;<article-title>Transcriptome analysis of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> transgenic mosquitoes with altered immunity.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002394</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22114564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>