<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">mSystems</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">mSystems</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">msys</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">msys</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mSystems</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>mSystems</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2379-5077</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology</publisher-name><publisher-loc>1752 N St., N.W., Washington, DC</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5069739</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">mSystems00038-15</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00038-15</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology and Physiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Comprehensive Transcriptome Profiles of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> UA159 Map Core Streptococcal Competence Genes</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Competence Networks in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic></alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short-authors">Khan et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rukke</surname><given-names>H. V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000f8;vik</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c5;mdal</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Oral Biology, Faculty of Dentistry, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>The Forsyth Institute, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Biological Sciences, University of Illinois at Chicago, Chicago, Illinois, USA</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>McFall-Ngai</surname><given-names>Margaret J.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><aff>University of Hawaii</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Address correspondence to F. C. Petersen, <email>f.c.petersen@odont.uio.no</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1" fn-type="present-address"><label>*</label><p>Present address: H. V. Rukke, Nordic Institute of Dental Materials (NIOM), Oslo, Norway.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Citation</bold> Khan R, Rukke HV, H&#x000f8;vik H, &#x000c5;mdal HA, Chen T, Morrison DA, Petersen FC. 2016. Comprehensive transcriptome profiles of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> UA159 map core streptococcal competence genes. mSystems 1(2):e00038-15. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/mSystems.00038-15">10.1128/mSystems.00038-15</ext-link>.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Mar-Apr</season><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e00038-15</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Khan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khan et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="sys002162010001.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> has the hard surfaces of the oral cavity as its natural habitat, where it depends on its ability to form biofilms in order to survive. The comprehensive identification of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> regulons activated in response to peptide pheromones provides an important basis for understanding how <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> can transition from individual to social behavior. Our study placed 27 of the 29 transcripts activated during competence within three major regulons and revealed a core set of 27 panstreptococcal competence-activated genes within the SigX regulon.</p></abstract><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>In <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>, an oral colonizer associated with dental caries, development of competence for natural genetic transformation is triggered by either of two types of peptide pheromones, competence-stimulating peptides (CSPs) (18&#x000a0;amino acids [aa]) or SigX-inducing peptides (XIPs) (7&#x000a0;aa). Competence induced by CSP is a late response to the pheromone that requires the response regulator ComE and the XIP-encoding gene <italic>comS</italic>. XIP binds to ComR to allow expression of the alternative sigma factor SigX and the effector genes it controls. While these regulatory links are established, the precise set of effectors controlled by each regulator is poorly defined. To improve the definition of all three regulons, we used a high-resolution tiling array to map global changes in gene expression in the early and late phases of the CSP response. The early phase of the CSP response was limited to increased gene expression at four loci associated with bacteriocin production and immunity. In the late phase, upregulated regions expanded to a total of 29 loci, including <italic>comS</italic> and genes required for DNA uptake and recombination. The results indicate that the entire late response to CSP depends on the expression of <italic>comS</italic> and that the immediate transcriptional response to CSP, mediated by ComE, is restricted to just four bacteriocin-related loci. Comparison of the new data with published transcriptome data permitted the identification of all of the operons in each regulon: 4 for ComE, 2 for ComR, and 21 for SigX. Finally, a core set of 27 panstreptococcal competence genes was identified within the SigX regulon by comparison of transcriptome data from diverse streptococcal species.</p><p><bold>IMPORTANCE</bold>
<italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> has the hard surfaces of the oral cavity as its natural habitat, where it depends on its ability to form biofilms in order to survive. The comprehensive identification of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> regulons activated in response to peptide pheromones provides an important basis for understanding how <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> can transition from individual to social behavior. Our study placed 27 of the 29 transcripts activated during competence within three major regulons and revealed a core set of 27 panstreptococcal competence-activated genes within the SigX regulon.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEYWORDS:</title><kwd>CSP</kwd><kwd><italic>Streptococcus</italic></kwd><kwd>XIP</kwd><kwd>genetic competence</kwd><kwd>natural transformation systems</kwd><kwd>pheromone</kwd><kwd>quorum sensing</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="award1"><funding-source>National Science Foundation (NSF)
<named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000001</named-content></funding-source><award-id>MCB-1020863</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Donald A. Morrison</principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>This work received funds from the Faculty of Dentistry, University of Oslo.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="103"/><page-count count="27"/><word-count count="15548"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>March/April 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="h0.0"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The acquisition of new genes through horizontal transfer among the prokaryotes plays an important role in ecological diversification and adaptation (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The first evidence of such horizontal gene transfer was the recognition that virulence determinants can be transferred between pneumococci in infected mice, a phenomenon defined as natural transformation (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Natural genetic transformation refers to the active uptake of exogenous DNA, followed by heritable incorporation of its genetic information, a capacity that is widespread but not universal in both Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria and in the archaea (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). In the Gram-positive genus <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, some members of the <italic>Streptococcus mitis</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;anginosus</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;salivarius</italic>, and <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> groups are recognized as naturally transformable (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Recently, competence was also reported in <italic>S.&#x000a0;suis</italic> and members of the <italic>S.&#x000a0;bovis</italic> group (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). In the remaining members of the genus, the presence of regulatory and effector homologs of proteins involved in competence for natural transformation indicates that competence development may be a general trait of streptococci (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>Competence in streptococci is often expressed as a transient developmental state in which bacteria exhibit a capacity for natural genetic transformation (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The competent state is triggered by autoinducing peptide pheromones, leading to increased expression of the alternative sigma factor SigX (also known as ComX), which is the master regulator of competence (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The genes differentially expressed during competence, reported as corresponding to 6% or more of the genome (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), include genes required for DNA uptake and recombination and genes required to scavenge DNA by killing other bacteria without causing self-damage. Some of the competence-specific genes are, however, not directly involved in these processes, indicating that the system may have evolved to control additional functions, such as adaptation to acid stress, biofilm formation, and virulence (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p><p>The streptococcal competence-inducing pheromones are unmodified linear peptides produced as propeptides (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Competence development is coordinated within a culture by a positive feedback loop linking pheromone production to the external concentration of the secreted mature peptide. The competence-stimulating peptides (CSPs), which belong to the double-glycine family of peptides (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), are sensed on the outside of cells upon binding to the ComD histidine kinase of the ComED two-component signal transduction system (TCSTS) (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), whereas SigX-inducing peptides (XIPs) are sensed by ComR intracellular regulators of the Rgg family, upon internalization by the oligopeptide permease complex Opp (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The propeptides belong to either the double-glycine CSP family, as in the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mitis</italic> group, or to a distinct class of peptides associated with Rgg regulators, as in the <italic>S.&#x000a0;salivarius</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, pyogenic, and <italic>S.&#x000a0;bovis</italic> groups (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p><p>In <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, a human oral colonizer associated with dental caries, the competence regulatory network is somewhat more complex than the analogous networks in other streptococci. While the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> network shares with them the alternative sigma factor SigX, it employs two peptide pheromones, not one, in upstream circuits for coordination of entry into the competent state. Furthermore, its regulatory behavior in rich media differs from that in chemically defined media (CDM). Although the reasons for such differences remain unclear, it is possible that the lack of peptides in the CDM used in different studies may be a relevant factor, since addition of assorted peptides to CDM eliminates the activity of XIP (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Each peptide pheromone circuit in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> encompasses genes for peptide synthesis, processing, and secretion, a peptide receptor regulating the transcription of additional genes, and a set of <italic>cis</italic>-acting sites targeted by the pheromone receptor to create a peptide-specific regulon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). In recent years, the links between these regulons have emerged as a set of reasonably well-defined interactions organized in a different order during competence development in the two classes of culture media (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;1&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Competence regulatory networks in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>. Regulatory links are organized into two pheromone response networks acting in peptide-rich media such as THB (A) or in peptide-free CDM (B). (A) In rich media, extracellular CSP induces the expression of bacteriocin and immunity proteins (red) through the ComED TCSTS pathway. Other genes are possibly induced by direct or indirect activation by phosphorylated ComE. The bacteriocins are thought to create pores that allow internalization of the competence pheromone XIP. XIP binds to ComR to activate the expression of at least two genes (green), <italic>comS</italic> (encoding XIP) and <italic>sigX</italic> (encoding the alternative sigma factor &#x003c3;<sup>x</sup>). Induction of <italic>comS</italic> creates a positive feedback loop that increases the production of XIP and &#x003c3;<sup>x</sup>, while &#x003c3;<sup>x</sup> activates the expression of genes (blue) involved in DNA integration (e.g., <italic>comGA</italic>, <italic>comEC</italic>, and <italic>dprA</italic>). (B) In peptide-free CDM, extracellular XIP is internalized via the Opp permease and binds to ComR, activating the expression of at least two genes, <italic>comS</italic> (encoding XIP) and <italic>sigX</italic>. Induction of <italic>comS</italic> creates a positive feedback loop, while elevated &#x003c3;<sup>x</sup> activates the expression of genes involved in DNA integration (e.g., <italic>comGA</italic>, <italic>comEC</italic>, and <italic>dprA</italic>). Bacteriocin and immunity proteins are upregulated as a result of <italic>comED</italic> induction by &#x003c3;<sup>x</sup>. Uncertainties about the regulon assignment for the full range of genes that change expression in response to the pheromones are represented by question marks, and genes upregulated but not exemplified are represented by ellipses.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sys0021620100001"/></fig><p>Assignment of genes to the ComE, ComR, and SigX regulons has been supported by analysis of shared sequence motifs at <italic>cis</italic>-acting sites and three types of evidence showing that (i) gene expression depends on a nearby regulon-specific promoter site, (ii) gene expression depends on the cognate regulator, or (iii) elevated expression of the gene can be driven by overexpression of the regulator. The supporting experimental evidence focused principally on a limited subset of induced genes (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS1">Table&#x000a0;S1</xref>&#x000a0;in the supplemental material). Despite these extensive studies, some of the links drawn in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref> are still incompletely understood. For example, the suggestion that CipB potentiates XIP by creating pores in the membrane, allowing XIP internalization in Todd-Hewitt broth (THB) (but not CDM) (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) has not been directly tested. It also remains unknown whether CSP is the signal that binds to ComD to promote ComE phosphorylation and activation in CDM (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). More broadly, it is unclear exactly which genes are in each regulon or how numerous additional inputs to competence regulation are effected.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="tabS1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00038-15.1</object-id><label>Table&#x000a0;S1&#x000a0;</label><p>Overview of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> genes upregulated by competence-inducing pheromones and their expression in deletion mutants. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="tabs1" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="sys002162010st1.pdf" content-type="local-data">Table&#x000a0;S1, PDF file, 0.3 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Khan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khan et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><p>With the broad pattern of these pathways of signal transduction outlined, it is a suitable time to refine the definition of the network by identifying genes and operons in each of the three known regulons more comprehensively, as well as by asking whether the genes that are upregulated specifically in competent cells are restricted to these three regulons. We report here six new transcriptome data sets obtained by the use of an improved tiling microarray that clearly distinguishes, on a genomic scale, the early responses to CSP from the late responses triggered by XIP. Detailed mapping of the transcriptomes allowed the comprehensive prediction or confirmation of start sites for the induced transcripts, enabling us to refine the assignment of transcripts to specific regulons and to identify new regulon members. The results also provide experimental evidence supporting early suggestions that upregulation of genes distal to competence regulator recognition sites often arises from readthrough past transcriptional terminators, accounting, in large part, for the wide intra- and interspecies variations in the number of genes assigned to the competence regulons. Finally, comparison of these data sets with existing competence transcriptome profiles in several other streptococcal species reveals a core set of streptococcal competence-specific genes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="h1"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s1.1"><title>Probe design and sampling strategy.</title><p>Published transcriptome surveys provide valuable views into the breadth of streptococcal competence-specific genes; however, for most species, including the competence model <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, transcriptome data for competence development have come mostly from early techniques of microarray analysis that have technical limitations, such as the use of probes that are often restricted to annotated open reading frames (ORFs), the use of probes with low spatial resolution, and the use of cDNA preparations that result in artifactual antisense signals. In <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, newer high-density tiling arrays and RNA-sequencing methods have already been used in transcriptome surveys of the competence response, but none of them was designed specifically to distinguish the different regulons that are activated in response to CSP. The tiling array study was restricted to responses resulting from long exposure to CSP and lacked full coverage, including probes for the <italic>comS</italic> gene (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), whereas in the RNA-sequencing study, short exposure to CSP was investigated in a medium that does not support activation of competence by CSP (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Therefore, to capture a more complete picture of competence regulation in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, we chose a strategy of probe design and sample collection and preparation that would allow comprehensive mapping of transcripts in both the early and late phases of the CSP response under conditions in which CSP induces competence.</p><p>We employed six strategies to minimize confounding errors known to affect transcriptional profiling. (i) To improve the specificity of hybridization signals, we employed 385,000 overlapping 50-mer oligonucleotide tiling probes optimized for uniqueness, <italic>T<sub>m</sub></italic>, and probe length, with a resolution of approximately 10&#x000a0;bp, as described previously (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). (ii) To minimize the artifactual &#x0201c;antisense&#x0201d; signals that arise during cDNA preparation, RNA was instead directly chemically labeled (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). (iii) To maximize mRNA signals, the RNA was depleted of rRNA. (iv) To minimize loss of sRNAs and possible short transcripts coding for small peptides such as ComS and ComC, microRNA purification protocols were employed. (v) To minimize signals from irrelevant metabolic changes that might occur during the experiment, we limited cultures to the early log phase. (vi) Finally, we chose to use the mature CSP18 pheromone (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), instead of the precursor CSP-21 peptide used in previous transcriptome surveys (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), in order to minimize any response delay due to peptide processing steps (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>).</p><p>RNA preparations were made from cultures of the wild type (WT) in the early and late stages of the response to CSP and from cultures of a <italic>comS</italic> mutant in the late stage. The most appropriate times to distinguish the early and late global responses during competence development were selected on the basis of measurements of growth, DNA incorporation dynamics, and expression of selected early and late genes after CSP supplementation of cultures in tryptone soya broth (TSB) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). TSB was chosen because this medium supports competence development stimulated by synthetic CSP, but endogenous competence development is absent or restricted to low levels and is independent of <italic>comC</italic> (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). During the first 120&#x000a0;min of incubation, cultures with and without CSP grew at equal rates and remained far from stationary phase. The culture treated with CSP became capable of rapid DNA uptake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2A</xref>), while competence remained very low in the parallel culture without added CSP throughout 4&#x000a0;h. Transformation was first detected at 100&#x000a0;min after CSP addition, reached maximal levels at 3&#x000a0;h, and declined by 4&#x000a0;h. Using a gene fusion reporter, we found that <italic>cipB</italic> expression, used as an indicator of early gene expression, was strongly dependent on CSP and increased as an immediate response, replicating previous findings (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). In contrast, expression of <italic>sigX</italic> (also CSP dependent) began only after a delay of approximately 50&#x000a0;min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2B</xref>). Thus, (i) the strong dependence of both the early expression of bacteriocin genes and the late development of competence on CSP in TSB and (ii) the time difference between the two responses established optimal conditions for study of the temporally specific effects of CSP on the transcriptome. Because endogenous competence induction was absent within the first 3&#x000a0;h and CSP-induced DNA incorporation was robust by approximately 2&#x000a0;h, at a time when growth had not been inhibited by CSP, we further evaluated the use of CSP exposure times of 10 and 100&#x000a0;min. Reverse transcription (RT)-PCR assays confirmed that the early and late transcriptional responses were activated at 10 and 100&#x000a0;min, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.&#x000a0;2C</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">E</xref>). Expression of the ComE-regulated gene SMU.1914 (<italic>cipB</italic>, <italic>nlmC</italic>) had already increased dramatically at 10&#x000a0;min compared with that in the culture without CSP, but there was only a slight increase in the expression of the SigX-dependent genes <italic>comGA</italic> and <italic>comEC</italic>. By 100&#x000a0;min, <italic>comGA</italic> and <italic>comEC</italic> expression had increased by more than 200-fold, while expression of SMU.1914 continued at an elevated level. Thus, 10 and 100&#x000a0;min were selected as the earliest suitable sampling times for studying the immediate and delayed transcriptional responses to CSP in the absence of any gross effect of CSP on the growth rate.</p><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;2&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Effect of CSP18 on induction of competence and expression of <italic>cipB</italic>, <italic>sigX</italic>, <italic>comGA</italic>, and <italic>comEC</italic> during growth in TSB. (A) During growth of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> UA159 in the presence (&#x025cf;) or absence (&#x025cb;) of CSP, transformation efficiency (solid line) and OD<sub>600</sub> (broken line) were determined at the times indicated. Exposure to pVA838 was for 20&#x000a0;min and was followed by further incubation with DNase I for 40&#x000a0;min before plating. Arrows show the times of sample harvesting for microarray analysis. (B) Luciferase reporters were used in parallel cultures to measure the effect of CSP on the expression of <italic>cipB</italic> (<italic>nlmC</italic>, SMU.1914) (triangles) and <italic>sigX</italic> (squares). The strains were grown in the presence of 50&#x000a0;nM CSP (filled symbols) or without CSP (empty symbols). CSP was added at <italic>t</italic> = 0. Relative light units (RLU) and OD<sub>600</sub> were measured in a 96-well plate with a multidetection microplate reader (SynergyHT; BioTek). Expression levels are relative to the highest value of each reporter (100%). Error bars indicate standard deviations of triplicate assays. (C to E) Relative expression of selected early responsive gene <italic>cipB</italic> (C) and late responsive genes <italic>comGA</italic> and <italic>comEC</italic> (D and E). Real-time PCR data were normalized to the expression values of the respective genes in the WT strain at 5&#x000a0;min without CSP. Mean values and standard errors for three replicates at 5, 10, and 100&#x000a0;min without CSP (red bars) and with CSP (blue bars) are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sys0021620100002"/></fig><p>RNA was extracted from cultures under the six conditions selected (UA159 for 10 or 100&#x000a0;min and the <italic>comS</italic> mutant for 100&#x000a0;min, with and without CSP) in duplicate experiments and analyzed for strand-specific genome-wide gene expression as described in Materials and Methods. Inspection of the resulting profiles gives several indications that the sampling strategy yielded expression patterns of significantly improved quality. Using directly labeled RNA to exclude the artifactual antisense signals often observed with conventional cDNA preparations offered clear benefits, as it revealed that several of the genes previously classified as upregulated in response to CSP were indeed upregulated, but only in the antisense direction. We also observed mRNAs of short length in our preparations, including that for the CSP-encoding gene <italic>comC</italic> (approximately 190&#x000a0;bp), indicating successful isolation of short transcripts. Moreover, by carefully matching the CSP-treated and untreated samples in relation to the incubation time and culture density, we could clearly distinguish changes specific to CSP exposure from nonspecific changes occurring during growth. We found that in the control samples without CSP, the expression of 98 genes differed between cultures grown for 10&#x000a0;min and those grown for 100&#x000a0;min (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS2">Table&#x000a0;S2</xref>&#x000a0;in the supplemental material). None of the genes required for competence, such as those for DNA uptake and recombination, were identified in this group, indicating that the changes were not competence related. To determine whether this information would contribute to a better definition of the overall response to the CSP pheromone, we investigated whether genes previously defined as CSP induced include the group of genes identified here as nonspecific to the CSP response. In fact, 26 of the genes showing changes associated with growth were among genes previously defined as part of the CSP response (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS2">Table&#x000a0;S2</xref>) (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="tabS2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00038-15.2</object-id><label>Table&#x000a0;S2&#x000a0;</label><p>Gene expression dynamics during culture growth. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="tabs2" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="sys002162010st2.pdf" content-type="local-data">Table&#x000a0;S2, PDF file, 0.4 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Khan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khan et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><p>Among the 1,961 protein-encoding genes annotated in the UA159 genome sequence, a subset of 83 were represented by a &#x0003e;2-fold expression increase during a 100-min CSP exposure (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS3">Table S3</xref> in the supplemental material). Only five genes exhibited downregulation, but all in the low range between &#x02212;2.1- and &#x02212;2.3-fold changes. The CSP induction ratios were, in general, similar to those previously observed in a transcriptome survey examining a competent subfraction of the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> population (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) and higher than in surveys using mixed populations exposed to CSP for 120&#x000a0;min (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS1">Fig.&#x000a0;S1</xref> in the supplemental material) (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Approximately 160 genes that were reported as differentially regulated in response to CSP in one of the mixed-population studies (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) were not confirmed in either this study or in the study using sorted competent cells (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS1">Fig.&#x000a0;S1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS4">Table&#x000a0;S4</xref>&#x000a0;in the supplemental material). We conclude that such genes are unlikely to be reproducible parts of the late CSP response and may represent experimental error, indirect effects of competence, or metabolic changes unrelated to the response to CSP. This interpretation is strengthened by the observation that the induction levels of most genes were uniformly higher in the present data and in the previous study using sorted cells and by the fact that the former transcriptome did not provide information on direction of transcripts and had a limited set of probes for each of the ORFs. Finally, the induced genes encoding bacteriocin and bacteriocin immunity proteins were generally induced at higher ratios here than in the previous studies using mixed or sorted populations of CSP-stimulated cells. This was particularly valuable in view of our aim to differentiate early and late responses associated with the activation of distinct regulons during the CSP response.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="tabS3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00038-15.3</object-id><label>Table&#x000a0;S3&#x000a0;</label><p>Effect of CSP on gene expression (ORFs). Download <inline-supplementary-material id="tabs3" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="sys002162010st3.pdf" content-type="local-data">Table&#x000a0;S3, PDF file, 1.9 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Khan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khan et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="tabS4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00038-15.4</object-id><label>Table&#x000a0;S4&#x000a0;</label><p>Comparison of transcriptome results from four studies. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="tabs4" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="sys002162010st4.pdf" content-type="local-data">Table&#x000a0;S4, PDF file, 0.6 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Khan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khan et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figS1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00038-15.8</object-id><label>Figure&#x000a0;S1&#x000a0;</label><p>Correlations between gene expression changes induced by CSP in this study and in previous transcriptome studies. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="figs1" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="sys002162010sf8.pdf" content-type="local-data">Figure&#x000a0;S1, PDF file, 0.4 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Khan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khan et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE&#x000a0;1&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Global temporal profile of responses to CSP in TSB<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.1"><sup>a</sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Gene ID<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.2"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Mean fold change<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.3"><sup>c</sup></xref><hr/></th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Annotation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.4"><sup>d</sup></xref></th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">UA159<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>comS</italic> mutant, 100&#x000a0;min</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#x000a0;min</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">100&#x000a0;min</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early response</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.150</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, NlmA, mutacin IV A</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.151</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, NlmB, mutacin IV B</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, mutacin IV immunity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.153</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.423</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, NlmD, mutacin VI</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.424</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CopY</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.426</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Copper-transporting ATPase, CopA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.427</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative copper chaperone, CopZ</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.925</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, ImmB, immunity protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1902c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, putative bacteriocin, BsmK</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1903c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1904c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1905c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative bacteriocin secretion protein, BsmL</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1906c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, BsmB</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1908c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1909c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, immunity protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1910c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1912c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1913c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative immunity protein, BlpL like, ImmA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1914c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, NlmC, CipB, mutacin V</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Late response</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02003;comS</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ComS, pheromone</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holliday junction DNA helicase RuvB</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative protein tyrosine phosphatase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative acyltransferase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Permease (efflux protein)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.166</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.168</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative transcriptional regulator</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deoxyuridine 5&#x02032;-triphosphate nucleotidohydrolase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.326</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.327</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA repair protein RadA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.352</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribulose-phosphate 3-epimerase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.353</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.354</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, Ccs50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.355</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative CMP-binding factor, CBF1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.356</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pur</italic> operon repressor</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.498</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative late competence protein, ComFA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.499</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative late competence protein, ComFC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative ribosome-associated protein, YflA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.505</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative adenine-specific DNA methylase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.506</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative type II restriction endonuclease</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.507</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DeoR family transcriptional regulator</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.508</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.539c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal peptidase type IV, CilC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.625</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative competence protein, CilE, DelA, ComEA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.626</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative competence protein, CelB, ComEC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.627</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.644</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative competence protein, CoiA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.645</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative oligopeptidase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.646</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative phosphatase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.769</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.772</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative glucan-binding protein D, BglB-like protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.836</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, CHAP domain</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.837</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative reductase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.838</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutathione reductase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.926<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.5"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTP pyrophosphokinase, PsrR, RelP</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.927<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.5"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative response regulator</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.928<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab1.5"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative histidine kinase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative DNA-processing Smf protein, DprA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA topoisomerase I</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA (uracil-5-)-methyltransferase, Gid</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA repair protein, RadC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1400c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1916</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histidine kinase of competence regulon, ComD</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1917</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ComE, response regulator of sakacin A production</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1965c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative histidine kinase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1966c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative periplasmic sugar-binding protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1967</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single-stranded-DNA-binding protein, SsbB</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1978</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative acetate kinase</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1979c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1980c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, ComGG, CglG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1981c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein, ComGE, CglE</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1982c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1983</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative competence protein ComGD, CglD</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1984</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative competence protein ComGC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1985</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transporter ComGB</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1987</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative ABC transporter, ATP-binding protein ComGA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.1997</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ComX, SigX</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.2076c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.2085</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recombinase A, RecA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SMU.2086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Competence damage-inducible protein A, CinA</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ngtab1.1"><label>a</label><p>Genes upregulated in response to CSP under at least one of the conditions tested (mean change, &#x0003e;2-fold).</p></fn><fn id="ngtab1.2"><label>b</label><p><italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> gene locus tag as in GenBank (<italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> UA159, accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AE014133">AE014133</ext-link>), except for <italic>comS</italic>, which is not annotated in the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> genome.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab1.3"><label>c</label><p>Mean fold change in gene expression in two independent biological experiments comparing CSP-treated and untreated parallel cultures.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab1.4"><label>d</label><p>Annotation as in GenBank (accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AE014133">AE014133</ext-link>) plus common gene names used in the literature.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab1.5"><label>e</label><p>TAR initiated by early gene SMU.925.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A comparison of the expression levels of individual upregulated genes in samples treated with CSP for 10 and 100 min is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>. The induced genes form two classes with different temporal patterns of expression; one class was induced at both times, and a second, larger, class was upregulated at 100&#x000a0;min but was not perceptibly affected at 10&#x000a0;min. For convenience in discussion, we designate the former early genes and the latter late genes. As they are likely to have different modes of regulation, transcriptionally active regions (TARs) in the two classes are described separately below.</p></sec><sec id="s1.2"><title>In the early phase of the CSP response, increases in expression were restricted to 20 genes in four distinct TARs.</title><p>All five genes previously reported individually to be upregulated in the early phase of the CSP response (<italic>nlmAB</italic>, <italic>nlmD</italic>, <italic>immB</italic>, and <italic>cipB</italic>), either by means of reporter constructions or by RT-PCR (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), were among the early upregulated genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). The genes in the early induction class clustered in four chromosomal regions. One locus contains the genes for bacteriocin NlmAB and the cognate bacteriocin immunity protein SMU.152 (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), with transcription continuing past a predicted terminator and through SMU_153, encoding a hypothetical protein. The three intergenic sequences among these genes were also upregulated, suggesting that the four genes are part of a single transcript. Two TARs, encoding the bacteriocin NlmD (BsmC, SMU.423) and the ImmB immunity protein (SMU.925), appear to be essentially monocistronic, with readthrough past terminator elements into a total of six downstream neighboring genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). For <italic>nlmD</italic>, the induction of the downstream genes was already evident at 10&#x000a0;min, whereas for <italic>immB</italic>, the induction of downstream ORFs SMU.926 to SMU.928 was seen only at 100&#x000a0;min. Although they were late genes, they form a single TAR initiated at the early gene <italic>immB</italic>, thus appearing to be part of the same regulon as <italic>immB</italic> and other early genes, as discussed below. The fourth early upregulated region comprises a 13-kb island, including genes for four bacteriocins (BsmB, -L, and -K and CipB), two immunity proteins (ImmA and SMU.1909), five proteins of unknown function, and an unusually large proportion of apparent intergenic regions. Analysis of expression changes in the antisense direction reveals that a marginally upregulated region extends through SMU.1902 to SMU.1897, apparently as a result of transcriptional readthrough.</p><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;3&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Genetic organization of TARs assigned to ComE, ComR, and SigX regulons. Operons (gray boxes) and terminators (black pins) are indicated as predicted by DOOR (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). The arrow borders of the genes in the ComE, ComR, and SigX regulons are red, green, and blue, respectively. The four TARs induced at 10&#x000a0;min in the WT and at 100&#x000a0;min in the <italic>comS</italic> mutant belong to the ComE regulon and comprise genes encoding bacteriocins (red), bacteriocin immunity proteins (yellow), and hypothetical proteins (gray). The 25 TARs induced only in the WT at 100&#x000a0;min (late response) belong to the ComR regulon (2 TARs), the SigX regulon (21 TARs), or unassigned regulons (others; 2 TARs). These include genes with products acting in autolysis (red), DNA transport (sky blue), recombination (green), and DNA methylation (orange) and genes that encode hypothetical proteins (gray). Three late genes encode key regulatory elements in the CSP response pathway (dark blue), SigX, ComS (ComR activator), and ComED. Binding site consensus elements are indicated by pennants for ComE (E), ComR (R), and SigX (X). Genes upregulated in the antisense direction are black. The mean fold changes in the expression of ORFs (black numbers) and intergenic regions (red umbers) for the WT at 10&#x000a0;min (ComE regulon) and 100&#x000a0;min (ComR, SigX, and other regulons) are shown above the black arrows indicating the directions of the transcripts. The images shown were drawn with Easyfig (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sys0021620100003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s1.3"><title>In the late phase of the response to CSP, a total of 83 genes organized into 29 TARs were upregulated.</title><p>Comparative analysis of the RNA harvested from CSP-treated cells at 100&#x000a0;min to that isolated from parallel untreated controls reveals that the four TARs of the early CSP response comprising 20 genes continued to be upregulated at this time. The TAR initiated at <italic>immB</italic> was extended to include three other genes (SMU.926 to SMU.928) at this time. In addition, 60 other genes organized in 22 TARs were induced in the sense direction and another three TARs were induced exclusively in the antisense direction by at least 2-fold (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). Among these, one TAR was initiated at the 3&#x02032; end of the SMU.60 gene, upstream of <italic>comR</italic>, and extended to the start of <italic>comR.</italic> Five others included regions of antisense transcription (initiated at <italic>comS</italic>, <italic>cilC</italic>, <italic>pilC</italic>, <italic>radC</italic>, and <italic>comE</italic>), and at six loci, TARs (initiated at SMU.325, SMU.351, SMU.504, <italic>lytF</italic>, <italic>comE</italic>, and <italic>ssbB</italic>) extended past terminators in the sense direction, as predicted by DOOR (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), to include downstream ORFs. The three TARs induced only in the antisense direction of the ORFs start at SMU.691, SMU.1853, and rl16. Over half of the TARs comprise genes upregulated by 10- to 132-fold.</p><p>Three of the late upregulated genes encode known regulators of competence-specific transcription in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> (ComS, SigX, and ComED). Consistent with a positive feedback loop mediated by XIP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>), there was strong induction of the XIP-encoding gene <italic>comS</italic> at 100&#x000a0;min. The TAR initiated at <italic>comS</italic> is 8&#x000a0;kb long, comprising six other ORFs, one of them transcribed in the antisense direction (SMU.63). SigX, long known as part of the response to CSP in streptococci (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), is represented by a one-gene TAR upregulated by 16-fold. Finally, the <italic>comED</italic> genes are among the late genes and are part of a TAR that extends in the 3&#x02032; direction to include the transcription of <italic>comC</italic> in the antisense direction. No induction of <italic>comC</italic> in the sense direction was observed. Of the remaining 19 late-induced TARs initiated by genes transcribed in the sense direction, 12 include at least one gene known to be involved in competence; 4 encode proteins for DNA transport, 6 encode proteins for DNA recombination, 1 encodes a protein for DNA methylation, and 1 encodes a protein for autolysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s1.4"><title>Deletion of <italic>comS</italic> abrogates the entire late response to CSP.</title><p>ComR and ComS form a positive feedback circuit that enhances the synthesis of ComS and concomitantly upregulates <italic>sigX</italic> (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Although only two copies of the complex ComR box recognition motif have been detected in the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> genome, the inference that ComR acts only at those two sites has not been experimentally tested in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>. To test this inference and investigate the place of ComS in the CSP response more thoroughly, transcriptome analysis of a <italic>comS</italic> deletion mutant was performed in parallel with the analysis of WT UA159 described above (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS4">Tables&#x000a0;S4</xref> and S5 in the supplemental material). During CSP treatment of the <italic>comS</italic> mutant for 100&#x000a0;min, none of the late-phase genes identified in the WT were upregulated, but the profile of expression seen at 10&#x000a0;min in the WT was closely recapitulated (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). This pattern supports the inference made from previous studies of several late genes that <italic>comS</italic> is an integral link between the early response and all elements of the late response.</p><p>The single gene that was upregulated in the <italic>comS</italic> culture but not in the 10-min WT sample was SMU.926. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>, SMU.926 most probably represents a readthrough from the early gene SMU.925 (<italic>immB</italic>) rather than a distinct late-activated promoter. Similarly, the single gene upregulated in the 10-min sample but not upregulated in the &#x00394;<italic>comS</italic> mutant culture is SMU.1902c (<italic>bsmK</italic>). This had the lowest degree of upregulation (2.1-fold) among the early genes and is located at the 3&#x02032; end of a long TAR extending from the early gene <italic>cipB</italic>, which was induced by 16-fold, again indicating a possible readthrough past a cryptic terminator site. In fact, the transcripts at all four early loci extended across predicted terminators and operon borders, indicating readthrough as a result of strong activation or incorrect terminator predictions.</p></sec><sec id="s1.5"><title>Assignment of regulon members.</title><p>For a comprehensive identification of the members of each of the three principal competence regulons, we combined information on the temporal responses to CSP and on the effect of <italic>comS</italic> deletion described above with a thorough analysis of the transcriptome map in the vicinity of conserved sequences recognized by ComE, ComR, and SigX (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4"> to </xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>). We then compared this information with the transcriptome data from five previous surveys investigating competence in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> to search for conserved responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>). Two of the transcriptomes compared long exposure times (120&#x000a0;min) of strain UA159 to CSP with nontreated samples (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>); the third transcriptome was also for strain UA159, but the comparison was between the WT and a CSP response-defective <italic>cipB</italic> mutant also exposed to CSP for 120&#x000a0;min (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>); the fourth one was for strain UA140 comparing the WT to an <italic>hdrR</italic> overexpression strain that shows induction of late competence genes in the absence of CSP supplementation (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>); and the fifth one used short (up to 30&#x000a0;min) exposure of UA159 to CSP or XIP in a defined medium in which CSP responses are not linked to competence (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;4&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Correlations between gene expression changes induced by short (10&#x000a0;min) or long (100&#x000a0;min) exposure to CSP in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> UA159 or by long exposure to CSP in the <italic>comS</italic> mutant. Fold changes are shown as log<sub>2</sub> values for all induced ORF sequences in the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> UA159 genome (accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AE014133">AE014133</ext-link>) and represent mean values for comparisons of CSP-treated and untreated samples from two independent biological experiments. (A) Correlation of ratios of short CSP exposure of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> UA159 to long CSP exposure of the <italic>comS</italic> mutant. The same genes were upregulated under the two conditions, with two exceptions (inner dashed circle). These are grouped as early genes. (B) Same correlation as for panel A but for changes in antisense transcripts. (C) Correlation of ratios of long CSP exposure of the <italic>comS</italic> mutant to long CSP exposure of the <italic>sigX</italic> mutant in reference 15 reveals candidate genes for the ComR regulon (dashed circle). (D) Correlation of induction ratios of long CSP exposure of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> UA159 to the <italic>comS</italic> mutant formed two groups. Early genes, as in panel A, were induced in both transcriptomes, and late genes were those induced only in UA159 upon long CSP exposure. (E) Correlations as in panel D but for antisense transcripts. Early genes are defined as those induced by short CSP exposure in WT UA159 and by long CSP exposure in the <italic>comS</italic> mutant (red borders), and late genes are defined as those that showed induction in the WT only upon long CSP exposure (green borders for putative genes of the ComR regulon and blue borders for the remaining genes). Circles corresponding to genes encoding upregulated bacteriocins are filled in red, circles corresponding to bacteriocin immunity proteins are filled in yellow, circles corresponding to proteins involved in DNA uptake are filled in light blue, and circles corresponding to proteins involved in DNA recombination are filled in green. The points corresponding to <italic>comE</italic>, <italic>comD</italic>, <italic>comS</italic>, and <italic>sigX</italic> are indicated by name (D; dark blue). Light-gray-filled circles correspond to other genes. Multiplot v.2 was used to draw the scatterplots (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/cancer/software/genepattern/modules/docs/multiplot/2">http://www.broadinstitute.org/cancer/software/genepattern/modules/docs/Multiplot/2</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sys0021620100004"/></fig><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;5&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Putative regulatory sites at early and late CSP-induced loci. (A, top) Alignment of DNA sequences upstream of clusters of early genes. The presumptive canonical promoter &#x02212;10 site is blue, bases corresponding to the DR consensus sequences are underlined, and the putative transcription start site is red (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The previously suggested SigX box of SMU.925 is boxed (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). (A, bottom) Transcriptome map showing predicted ComE binding sites (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Vertical arrows show the ComE DR sites that appeared to be active (orange DR) and sites that did not appear as active (black DR). Conditions A and B are 10&#x000a0;min of CSP and 10&#x000a0;min of no CSP, respectively. (B, top) Alignment of DNA sequences upstream of <italic>sigX</italic> and <italic>comS</italic>. These are late CSP-induced loci upregulated by ComRS. The presumptive canonical promoter &#x02212;10 site is blue, and conserved IRs known as the ComR box are bold (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). (B, bottom) Transcriptome maps at <italic>comS</italic> and <italic>sigX</italic>. Vertical arrows indicate the ComR IR sites (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Conditions A and B are 100&#x000a0;min of CSP and 100&#x000a0;min of no CSP, respectively. Probe intensities for the <italic>comS</italic> region were above the threshold used in the visualizer program. (C, top) Alignment of DNA sequences with putative SigX boxes. The SigX boxes are in bold. Superscript letters: a, SigX box within SMU.60; b, induction in the antisense direction; c, putative SigX boxes (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) not confirmed in our transcriptome. (C, bottom) Transcriptome map showing locations of predicted SigX boxes. Vertical arrows show the sites of SigX boxes that appeared to be active. Conditions A and B are 100&#x000a0;min of CSP and 100&#x000a0;min of no CSP, respectively. Changes in gene expression are presented as log<sub>2</sub> ratios (condition A/condition B), with ratios of &#x0003e;0 in green and ratios of &#x0003c;0 in red. The signal intensity of each probe (50-mer) is presented as a horizontal line in green for condition A and in orange for condition B. <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> locus tags are as in the sequence with GenBank accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AE014133">AE014133</ext-link> (&#x0003e;, transcript in the forward strand showing probe intensities above the locus tag boxes; &#x0003c;, transcript in the reverse strand showing probe intensities below the locus tag boxes). The vertical lines are separated by a distance of 100&#x000a0;bp. The complete maps are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.forsyth.org/mtd/dataset=RNAseq_smut_comS">http://bioinformatics.forsyth.org/mtd/dataset=RNAseq_smut_comS</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sys002162010005a"/><graphic xlink:href="sys002162010005b"/><graphic xlink:href="sys002162010005c"/></fig><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;6&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Comparison of gene expression maps from available <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> competence transcriptome studies. The directions of the activated TARs (arrows) from <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> exposed for 100&#x000a0;min to CSP are indicated by arrows as follows: red, TARs of the ComE regulon; green, the ComR regulon; blue and black, TARs of the SigX regulon with 5&#x02032; ends starting in the sense and antisense directions, respectively. The genes proximal to the ComE DR are red, those proximal to the ComR indirect repeat are green, and those proximal to the SigX box are blue. Gene numbers are as in the sequence with GenBank accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AE014133">AE014133</ext-link>. Gene expression data for corresponding regions are indicated for five transcriptome studies, as indicated at the left. The top row is UA159 (100&#x000a0;min). The transcriptomes in studies 1, 3, and 5 used traditional microarrays with probes limited to annotated ORFs (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). The transcriptome in study 2 used a tiling microarray covering most of the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> genome (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Study 4 used RNA sequencing in the analysis of the response to CSP and XIP in CDM (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). The CSP response in this medium does not support activation of competence but is included for comparative analysis of early responses. The transcriptome for XIP in CDM used a 30-min exposure to XIP, which was probably too short to detect the full range of core genes regulated by SigX. The <italic>comS</italic> gene was not represented in the arrays for the transcriptomes in studies 1, 2, 3, and 5 (empty space).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sys0021620100006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s1.6"><title>The ComE regulon.</title><p>To delimit the ComE regulon, we first compared the transcriptome profiles of the early response of the WT to CSP and of the <italic>comS</italic> mutant exposed for 100&#x000a0;min to CSP, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig.&#x000a0;4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">B</xref>. The expression pattern at 10&#x000a0;min is expected to reveal the immediate response of genes transcribed via ComE activation, before regulons dependent on ComR are upregulated, whereas data from the late response of a <italic>comS</italic> mutant, in which downstream regulons remain silent because of a lack of the linking XIP peptide, would potentially reveal direct targets of ComE with a slower response, as well as other downstream regulons independent of the ComR-ComS link. We found near identity between the early response in the WT and the late response in the <italic>comS</italic> mutant. All four early-induced TARs initiated at <italic>nlmA</italic>, <italic>nlmD</italic>, <italic>immB</italic>, and <italic>cipB</italic> are preceded by the direct repeat (DR) identified previously as a putative ComE binding site required for CSP-dependent bacteriocin expression (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and subsequently identified (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) as a tight binding site for purified ComE protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>). Other DR sites that bind purified ComE have been suggested to be functional, but they appeared to be nonfunctional under the conditions examined here, including the sites distal to <italic>bsmB</italic> (SMU.1906), <italic>comC</italic> (sense direction), and <italic>cslAB</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.&#x000a0;5A</xref>). The results indicate that all of the targets of ComE respond immediately to CSP and establish for the first time that ComE has no additional targets activated at late times independent of the ComR-ComS link.</p><p>We further examined the conservation of the CSP response by comparing the set of genes within the induced TARs with genes within or in the vicinity of these regions showing changed expression in previous studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>). Although the one published transcriptome study evaluating the early CSP response (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) was conducted under conditions of culture in CDM that do not support induction of competence by CSP, it did identify 19 of the 23 genes within the ComE regulon, as determined here (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>). Notably, similar to our results, in that study, <italic>comED</italic> and <italic>comC</italic> expression was only slightly or not induced by CSP, a finding also corroborated by a previous transcriptome study using a <italic>sigX</italic> mutant (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Despite the methodological limitations of the latter study, including lack of information on the direction of the transcripts and low levels of induction by CSP, all of the 23 early genes induced in the sense direction in this study were identified among the induced genes reported there (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig.&#x000a0;4C</xref>). We conclude that the UA159 genome contains only four TARs that are directly regulated by ComE, defining the ComE regulon. A total of 23 genes are transcribed in the sense direction, but direct experimentation is needed to assess the biological significance of distal genes or of the antisense transcripts in all four TARs, which are the source of the greatest variation among the different transcriptome studies.</p></sec><sec id="s1.7"><title>The ComR regulon.</title><p>Genes transcribed directly via activation of ComR in the CSP response can be identified from transcription differentials between a <italic>sigX</italic> mutant and a <italic>comS</italic> mutant in the late phase of the CSP response. Both data sets would reflect upregulation of genes of the ComE regulon, which is an early response, but only the <italic>sigX</italic> mutant would allow increased late expression of the transcripts of the ComR regulon. Although the information derived from a previous survey of gene expression in a <italic>sigX</italic> mutant (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) did not address transcript polarity or intergenic sequences, we can nonetheless use the ORF expression information available there to uncover candidate members of the ComR regulon. The scatterplot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig.&#x000a0;4C</xref> compares the genes that were upregulated in the 100-min <italic>comS</italic> mutant culture in this study to those previously reported as upregulated in a <italic>sigX</italic> mutant after a similar period of CSP exposure. The genes listed as upregulated in both transcriptomes represent the ComE regulon, as described above. The remaining seven genes, which were upregulated in the <italic>sigX</italic> mutant but not in the <italic>comS</italic> mutant or within a 10-min CSP exposure, are thus candidates for the ComR regulon. Of these, we exclude three (SMU.2037, SMU.2038, and SMU.799c) that, although induced to low levels in the <italic>sigX</italic> mutant, were not upregulated in the late response of the WT in either of the transcriptomes here (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS6">Table&#x000a0;S6</xref>&#x000a0;in the supplemental material) or in two other previous transcriptomes (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) and are not preceded by the ComR box inverted repeat (IR). The remaining candidate genes, SMU.63, SMU.64, SMU.65, and SMU.66, are contiguous with <italic>comS</italic>, which was not itself represented in the microarray used for analysis of the <italic>sigX</italic> mutant. These four genes were also upregulated in the 100-min WT transcriptome, along with the downstream genes SMU.67 and SMU.68, forming a single TAR with <italic>comS</italic>. The present data reveal that SMU.63, immediately downstream of <italic>comS</italic> but in the inverse orientation, was transcribed only from the noncoding strand, indicating strong readthrough past <italic>comS</italic> and suggesting that the entire upregulated region downstream of <italic>comS</italic> represents a single readthrough mRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). Examination of the transcription map for the WT at 100&#x000a0;min reveals that this TAR starts close to the ComR box IR that has been described as the binding site for ComR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.&#x000a0;5B</xref>) (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), further supporting a role for ComR in driving the transcription of this region.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="tabS5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00038-15.5</object-id><label>Table&#x000a0;S5&#x000a0;</label><p>Effect of CSP on the expression of intergenic sequences. Mean fold changes and <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;values for all intergenic regions are shown. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="tabs5" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="sys002162010st5.pdf" content-type="local-data">Table&#x000a0;S5, PDF file, 2.7 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Khan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khan et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="tabS6"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00038-15.6</object-id><label>Table&#x000a0;S6&#x000a0;</label><p>Initial selection of candidate genes of the ComE and ComR regulons. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="tabs6" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="sys002162010st6.pdf" content-type="local-data">Table&#x000a0;S6, PDF file, 0.4 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Khan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khan et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><p>The final member of the ComR regulon is <italic>sigX</italic>, which was expressed as a late gene, but not in the <italic>comS</italic> mutant (and was not probed in the <italic>sigX</italic> mutant). As for <italic>comS</italic>, the transcription start site at <italic>sigX</italic> mapped to a ComR box IR motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.&#x000a0;5B</xref>), providing support for a direct regulatory role for ComR in the expression of both <italic>comS</italic> and <italic>sigX</italic>. A previous transcriptome study of CSP-induced competence in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> reported a TAR extending downstream of <italic>sigX</italic> that, given its position and the general variation observed in the expression of the 3&#x02032;-terminal genes in several of the induced TARs in different transcriptomes, may represent a readthrough (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>). We conclude that just two TARs make up the ComR regulon, one initiated at <italic>comS</italic> but often extending downstream to encompass two to five additional genes and the second encompassing <italic>sigX</italic>, with an occasional downstream readthrough.</p></sec><sec id="s1.8"><title>The <italic>sigX</italic> regulon.</title><p>Because <italic>sigX</italic> is expressed late in the CSP response, genes restricted to late expression and not expressed in a <italic>sigX</italic> or <italic>comS</italic> mutant are candidates for the SigX regulon. The late class of genes is easily distinguished from the early class, as illustrated in the scatter plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig.&#x000a0;4D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">E</xref>. Discounting the genes belonging to the ComE and ComR regulons identified above (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig.&#x000a0;4A</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">C</xref>), 23 TARs comprising a total of 78 ORFs transcribed in either the sense or the antisense direction are candidate members of the SigX regulon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>, bottom). To distinguish direct from indirect regulation by SigX, we focused on the apparent presence of the highly conserved noncanonical &#x02212;10 promoter element recognized by SigX polymerase, the SigX box, near the start of these TARs. Twenty-one of the 23 candidate TARs are preceded by a SigX box, as illustrated in the transcriptome maps in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig.&#x000a0;5C</xref>. Of these, 7 represent SigX boxes not previously described and the remaining 16 include mostly SigX boxes that have been predicted in previous <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> studies and that were confirmed here by transcriptome mapping. Five other SigX boxes have been suggested in regions preceding competence-induced genes (SMU.431, SMU.504, SMU.507, SMU.925, and SMU.1904) (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), but these boxes were not confirmed in our study. At least one gene in each of these TARs (those in the sense direction) has been previously reported as upregulated in transcriptome surveys of the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> response to CSP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>). In the cases where there was some variation among the different transcriptomes regarding the set of genes that were induced within the SigX-controlled TAR regions, these usually involved genes in the 3&#x02032; termini of the TARs. Only two TARs, one for SMU.109 (possibly initiated at SMU.108) and another extending from SMU.166 to SMU.168, were upregulated in multiple transcriptomes but lack an apparent upstream SigX box (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>). These two are thus the only candidates for indirect regulation by SigX. We conclude that the SigX regulon comprises 23 TARs, with conserved upregulation of genes toward the 5&#x02032; ends of the TARs and a certain level of variation among different transcriptome surveys toward the set of genes activated in the 3&#x02032;-terminal regions of the TARs.</p></sec><sec id="s1.9"><title>A core <italic>sigX</italic> regulon.</title><p>During their evolution from a common ancestor, the streptococci became specialized for survival in diverse hosts and diverse sugar-rich niches, diverging not only by accumulation of mutations but also by gains and losses of many genes and by extensive shuffling within the genome (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Throughout this evolution, competence for genetic transformation has been a conserved trait dependent on the alternative sigma factor SigX and the SigX regulon (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The maintenance of the SigX regulon amid pervasive genetic change provides a natural genus-wide survey that can be used to distinguish conserved from variable components of the regulon. To mine the data provided by this natural experiment, we compared the competence-specific transcriptome data sets that are available for six species, representing five of the six major groups of species in this genus. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig.&#x000a0;7</xref>, we display alignments of competence-specific TARs in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> with homologous regions that are upregulated in response to CSP in <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;gordonii</italic>, and <italic>S.&#x000a0;sanguinis</italic> or by XIP in <italic>S.&#x000a0;pyogenes</italic> and <italic>S.&#x000a0;thermophilus</italic> (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Since induction levels are apparently low in <italic>S.&#x000a0;pyogenes</italic> (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>) and transformation is observed only under particular biofilm conditions (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), the absence of core induced genes in their transcriptomes was not used as evidence for the lack of a core response. However, induction of <italic>S.&#x000a0;pyogenes</italic> genes within core regions strengthened the classification of genes into the SigX core response. Inspection of the alignments reveals a broad pattern of synteny adjacent to the SigX box motifs but also variation in both gene presence and the observed length of associated TARs. Overall, the streptococcal SigX regulons contain a minority of genes invariably subject to SigX regulation, organized into three groups, (i) core genes induced in more than four streptococcal species (<italic>dut</italic>, <italic>radA</italic>, <italic>ccs50</italic>, <italic>cbf1</italic>, <italic>comFA</italic>, <italic>comFC</italic>, <italic>yfiA</italic>, <italic>cilC</italic>, <italic>comEA</italic>, <italic>comEC</italic>, <italic>coiA</italic>, <italic>pepB</italic>, <italic>pilC</italic>, <italic>dprA</italic>, <italic>radC</italic>, <italic>ssbB</italic>, <italic>comGA</italic> to <italic>comGH</italic>, <italic>ack</italic>, <italic>cinA</italic>, and <italic>recA</italic>), (ii) core genes in the DpnII group of strains (<italic>dpnA</italic> and <italic>dpnB</italic>), and (iii) core genes that have a domain in common but are not necessarily orthologs (<italic>lytF</italic> in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;gordonii</italic>, and <italic>S.&#x000a0;sanguinis</italic> and <italic>cbpD</italic> in <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;thermophilus</italic>, and <italic>S.&#x000a0;pyogenes</italic>), which we define as the core SigX regulon. This information was used to delineate a model of the transcriptional organization of the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> response to CSP in peptide-rich medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig.&#x000a0;8</xref>). A larger number of accessory genes found in SigX-dependent transcripts in some species but not in others are exemplified in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="tabS7">Table&#x000a0;S7</xref>&#x000a0;in the supplemental material. A notable feature of the core regulon is that core genes are usually at the 5&#x02032; extremity of a TAR, which immediately suggests that transcription of the accessory genes may reflect variation in terminator presence and efficacy. Indeed, in no case that we are aware of has an accessory gene downstream of a core gene been shown to provide a function in transformation. Additional accessory SigX-dependent genes are found in TARs that lack any core gene, but these are few in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, as only 4 of 22 TARs initiated by genes transcribed in the sense direction are not induced in the other species (3&#x02032; end of SMU.60, <italic>comED</italic>, SMU.1400, and possibly SMU.2076).</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="tabS7"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00038-15.7</object-id><label>Table&#x000a0;S7&#x000a0;</label><p>Comparison of transcriptome results for late genes in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, and <italic>S.&#x000a0;thermophilus</italic>. Download <inline-supplementary-material id="tabs7" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="sys002162010st7.pdf" content-type="local-data">Table&#x000a0;S7, PDF file, 0.7 MB</inline-supplementary-material>.</p><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Khan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khan et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This content is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions></supplementary-material><fig id="fig7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;7&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Core genes of the SigX regulon. Conservation of synteny to <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> SigX-induced TARs (top row) in <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;gordonii</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;sanguinis</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;pyogenes</italic>, and <italic>S.&#x000a0;thermophilus</italic>. Red pentagons correspond to genes immediately downstream of a SigX box. Competence-induced genes, black border; upregulated genes oriented antisense to the gene proximal to the SigX box, dashed black border; no change in gene expression, borderless faded colors; orthologs in each of the 15 groups, similar colors; no orthologs in the regions analyzed, gray. Core genes in the DpnII group are shown within dashed squares. The induced <italic>lytF</italic> gene in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> is also induced in <italic>S.&#x000a0;gordonii</italic> and <italic>S.&#x000a0;sanguinis</italic> and encodes a CHAP domain found in CbpD, an induced nonortholog in <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;thermophilus</italic>, and <italic>S.&#x000a0;pyogenes</italic>. LytF and CbpD have conserved lytic functions in the different species. Three other transcripts induced in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> are not shown, as they have no matches in the other species (SMU.1400, <italic>comE</italic>) or are internal to an ORF (3&#x02032; end of SMU.60). Orthology is as annotated at KEGG (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/</ext-link>). Note that for all of the transcriptomes compared with <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, there is no information on TAR polarity or length. SP<sup>1</sup>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> Rx (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>); gene locus tag as in GenBank (<italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> TIGR4, accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AE005672">AE005672</ext-link>). SP<sup>2</sup>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> R6 (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>); gene locus tag as in GenBank (<italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> TIGR4, accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AE005672">AE005672</ext-link>). SP<sup>3</sup>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> G54 (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>) DpnII restriction-methylase group (competence transcriptome not available); gene locus tag as in GenBank (<italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> G54, accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/CP001015">CP001015</ext-link>). SGO<sup>4</sup>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;gordonii</italic> Challis (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>); gene locus tag as in GenBank (accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/CP000725">CP000725</ext-link>). SSA<sup>5</sup>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;sanguinis</italic> SK36 (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>); gene locus tag as in GenBank (accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/CP000387.1">CP000387.1</ext-link>). SPy<sup>6</sup>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;pyogenes</italic> MGAS315 (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) and derivative strain D471 (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>); gene locus tag as in GenBank (<italic>S.&#x000a0;pyogenes</italic> M1 GAS SF370, accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AE004092.2">AE004092.2</ext-link>). Shown are <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> induced genes in one or both studies. STER<sup>7</sup>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;thermophilus</italic> LMD-9 (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>); gene locus tag as in GenBank (accession no. GCA_000014485.1). <sup>a</sup>SMU.354 is homologous to <italic>ccs50</italic>, but the SigX box is distal to SMU.352. <sup>b,c,d</sup>Upregulation of <italic>comFC</italic>, <italic>cilC</italic>, and <italic>coiA</italic> was not detected in the <italic>S.&#x000a0;sanguinis</italic> transcriptome but is essential for competence (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). <sup>e</sup>SSA.2233 is distal to the SigX box but not homologous to SMU.2076.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sys0021620100007"/></fig><fig id="fig8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG&#x000a0;8&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Model of the transcriptional organization of the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> response to CSP in peptide-rich medium. In step 1, extracellular CSP activates the two-component system ComED, which then induces the expression of four operons comprising several bacteriocin and bacteriocin immunity genes. The bacteriocins are suggested to create pores in the membrane that allow the entrance of the XIP pheromone into the cells. In step 2, XIP binds to ComR, which then assumes a conformation that activates the expression of two operons, one initiated at <italic>comS</italic>, creating a positive feedback loop, and the other initiated at <italic>sigX</italic>, activating the competence response. In step 3, SigX activates the expression of 22 operons, including 4 sense transcripts that are not seen in other streptococcal transcriptomes (noncore), 3 transcripts in the antisense direction (not yet investigated in other streptococci), and 15 operons encoding genes that are in the core of the streptococcal SigX response. Three groups of core genes were identified: (i) core orthologs found in at least four of the available transcriptomes, (ii) core orthologs found only in strains that belong to the DpnII group of restriction-modification systems, and (iii) core nonorthologs that have in common a conserved domain associated with similar functions (in this class are CbpD of <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>S.&#x000a0;thermophilus</italic> and LytF of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;gordonii</italic>, and <italic>S.&#x000a0;sanguinis</italic>, both of which have the lytic CHAP domain in common).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sys0021620100008"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="h2"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>A common theme among the pathways controlling competence for genetic transformation in the scores of species within the diverse genus streptococcus (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) is the use of the labile and dispensable alternative sigma factor SigX to drive the transcription of genes for DNA-processing functions. Our identification of a core of just 27 to 30 genes that are consistently placed under the control of SigX in representative streptococcal species draws attention to three classes of genes, (i) upstream regulators of <italic>sigX</italic> and genes they regulate in parallel with <italic>sigX</italic>, (ii) the core SigX regulon genes themselves, and (ii) coregulated genes beyond the core that depend on SigX for expression in species-specific patterns.</p><p>The links of SigX to upstream regulators and pheromone communication systems are found in species-specific arrangements, but in all of the cases characterized so far, <italic>sigX</italic> expression is coordinated by the activity of a pheromone peptide-dependent quorum-sensing system. In <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, competence development can be provoked through two alternative but convergent regulatory pathways initiated by alternative intercellular peptide signals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>) and regulators of both classes. Although these quorum-sensing systems vary, they both coordinate bacteriocin production with upregulation of <italic>sigX</italic>. Bacteriocin production accompanying competence development has been proposed as a mechanism to scavenge DNA from target cells that can then be used for genetic exchange (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Indeed, in mixed cultures, <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> UA140 can use bacteriocin induction to facilitate an attack on <italic>S.&#x000a0;gordonii</italic> and increase gene transfer between the species (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Other regulators also feed into one or the other of these pathways to modulate their activities at unknown points upstream of SigX, including, for instance, ScnC/R/K, HdrRM, and BsrRM in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) and CiaRH and StkP in <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>).</p><p>The LytR family response regulator that mediates the response to CSP in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, ComE, is among the most-studied regulators in this species, yet its regulatory targets have not been fully defined (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). The present results support the resolution of these uncertainties in favor of only four significant sites of ComE action. Their location uniquely at mutacin loci is consistent with the phylogeny placing &#x0201c;ComED&#x0201d; of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> in the BlpRH family of bacteriocin regulators, distinct from the ComED competence regulators that are shared by the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mitis</italic> and <italic>S.&#x000a0;anginosus</italic> groups (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>).</p><p>The core SigX regulon genes identified in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig.&#x000a0;7</xref> are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>, grouped according to the known roles of their protein products and information now available about their potential roles. Of the 27 core genes with orthologs in more than 4 of the different species analyzed, 2/3 have been characterized to some extent as important for genetic transformation in <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> or other species. Twelve are absolutely required for DNA uptake in <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, and six are important for subsequent recombination. The remaining nine genes have unknown roles in competence and include four orthologs of well-characterized proteins and five proteins with unknown function, some with domains that fall into known broad functional categories. All nine of these are dispensable for transformation in <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> but may play a role in competence in other species (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Two core genes are specific for the DpnII group of streptococci (<italic>dpnA</italic> and <italic>dpnB</italic>). In this group, methylation by DpnA protects incoming heterologous DNA from digestion by DpnII restrictases (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). A third class of core genes is represented by <italic>lytF</italic> and <italic>cbpD</italic>, of which the former is found in <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;sanguinis</italic>, and <italic>S.&#x000a0;gordonii</italic> and the latter is found in <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;thermophilus</italic>, and <italic>S.&#x000a0;pyogenes</italic>. Although the two genes are not orthologs, they both have a CHAP domain with conserved lytic activity that is important in promoting DNA release during competence (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE&#x000a0;2&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Roles of the genes of the core SigX regulon in transformation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Function and locus tag<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.1"><sup>a</sup></xref><hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gene</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Role or activity (reference[s])</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Transformation of mutants (reference[s])<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.2"><sup>b</sup></xref><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMU no.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SP no.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSA no.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMU</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SP</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSA (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recombination</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;327</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2157</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>radA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA repair protein RadA (<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;644</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0978</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0749</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>coiA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recombination</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1266</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1185</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dprA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA-processing protein, mediates RecA (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>) loading onto internalized single-stranded DNA, competence shutoff (<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74&#x02013;76</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1967</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1908</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0214</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ssbB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single-stranded DNA binding, DNA protection (<xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79&#x02013;81</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;2085</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1940</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2245</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>recA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recombinase A, strand exchange (<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>, <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recombination (core in DpnII group)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;505</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1734</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1717</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dpnA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single-strand methylase (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.7"><sup>g</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;506</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1733</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1716</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dpnB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DpnII restrictase targeting unmethylated double-stranded DNA (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uptake</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;498</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2208</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1836</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>coMFA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP-dependent DNA/RNA helicase, translocase involved in single-stranded DNA uptake (<xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;499</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2207</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1835</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>comFC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Late competence protein (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;539</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1808</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0642</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cilC</italic>, <italic>pilD</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal peptidase type IV, pilin cleavage (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;625</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0954</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0715</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>comEA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membrane protein with DNA-binding motif (double-stranded DNA receptor) (<xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;626</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0955</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0716</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>comEC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membrane channel (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.3"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1979</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0191</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adenine-specific DNA methylase (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.4"><sup>d</sup></xref> (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1980</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2047</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0190</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>comGG</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor pilin (<xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92&#x02013;94</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1981</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0189</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>comGF</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor pilin (<xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92&#x02013;94</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1982</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0188</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>comGE</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor pilin (<xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92&#x02013;94</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1983</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0187</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>comGD</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor pilin (<xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92&#x02013;94</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1984</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2051</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0186</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>comGC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major pilin (<xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>, <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>, <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1985</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2052</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0185</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>comGB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Competence protein, ABC transporter subunit (<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1987</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2053</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0184</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>comGA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pilus assembly ATPase (<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>, <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lysis (CHAP domain conserved)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;836</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>lytF</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murein hydrolase (39, 61, 77, 95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2201</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cbpD</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murein hydrolase (<xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown functions in competence<sup><italic>h</italic></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dut</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deoxyuridine 5&#x02032;-triphosphate nucleotidohydrolase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;354</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1981</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rmuC</italic>, <italic>ccs50</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA recombination protein RmuC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;355</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1980</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2116</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>yhaM</italic>, <italic>cbf1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMP-binding factor 1, 23S RNA maturation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2206</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1834</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>yfiA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribosome hibernation-promoting factor (Hpf), sigma factor (&#x003c3;<sup><xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup>) modulation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;645</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0979</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0751</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pepB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligopeptidase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;769</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0782</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1537</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pilC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membrane protein of pilus assembly</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.5"><sup>e</sup></xref><italic/> (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>radC</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA repair protein RadC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193; (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;1978</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2044</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0192</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ackA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bifunctional acetaldehyde-coenzyme A/alcohol dehydrogenase (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;2086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1941</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2246</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cinA</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Competence damage-inducible protein A (<xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab2.6"><sup>f</sup></xref> (<xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (<xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ngtab2.1"><label>a</label><p>Gene locus tag as in GenBank (SMU, <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> UA159, accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AE014133">AE014133</ext-link>; SP, <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic>, TIGR4 accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AE005672">AE005672</ext-link>; in bold, <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> G54, accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/CP001015">CP001015</ext-link>; SSA, <italic>S.&#x000a0;sanguinis</italic> SK36, accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/CP000387.1">CP000387.1</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.2"><label>b</label><p>Yes, deletion mutants not affected in transformation; &#x02193;, &#x0003e;2-fold reduction.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.3"><label>c</label><p>Unpublished data.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.4"><label>d</label><p>70% of WT.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.5"><label>e</label><p>Results with CSP showed a &#x0003c;2-fold reduction, but in one of the studies without CSP, there were no transformants (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.6"><label>f</label><p>Deletion of <italic>cinA</italic> affected the expression of the downstream gene <italic>recA</italic>, which was not fully restored by <italic>cinA</italic> complementation from a plasmid.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.7"><label>g</label><p>Transformation with unmethylated DNA was reduced in the deletion mutant.</p></fn><fn id="ngtab2.8"><label>h</label><p>Annotation at KEGG (<xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The predominance of transformation functions in the core SigX regulon suggests that this is an ancient regulon maintained because of its value in promoting genetic flexibility and maintaining ready access in each species to a large pangenome. Consistent with this view is its frequent linkage to production of lysins and bacteriocins, which can facilitate access to DNA from living cells. The question that arises concerns the functions of the remaining third of the core regulon. Although competence is suggested to be a stress response and these genes might act to relieve some stresses, it is our working hypothesis that they support horizontal gene transfer and that the absence of a phenotype in a standard transformation assay may reflect some redundancy in their activities, activities important under circumstances not yet tested, or simply functions in some aspect of the natural transformation process not yet appreciated. It is interesting, for example, that two of the nine core genes with unknown function in competence appear to have targets in the ribosome and puzzling that one of these is known in other species to inactivate ribosomes under stress (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>).</p><p>The noncore genes of the SigX regulons vary among species, but direct evidence connecting any of them to a SigX-controlled phenotype is rare. In a few cases, a species- or group-specific role in transformation is already known. One such case is that of ComE, the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> bacteriocin regulator that links XIP-stimulated competence to the expression of bacteriocins by induction of ComED (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). In other species, such as <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>S.&#x000a0;gordonii</italic>, SigX establishes a direct link to bacteriocin production by recognizing the SigX box in the promoters of bacteriocin genes (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). However, in the majority of cases, a role related to transformation is simply unknown. The frequent occurrence of apparent readthrough transcripts observed here suggests that pervasive transcription is a general feature of the competence response, which probably contributes to the list of noncore genes. Pervasive transcription represents a widespread phenomenon, as recently reviewed by Wade and Grainger (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>) and as exemplified by findings that in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> approximately 13% of the TARs seem to lack efficient termination signals (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Bacteria have apparently developed mechanisms to minimize pervasive transcription, but these are mostly unknown in streptococci.</p><p>The comprehensive identification of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> regulons activated in response to peptide pheromones provides an important basis for understanding how <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> can transition from individual to social behavior. <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> is an inhabitant of the oral cavity, where its ability to form biofilms is thought to be crucial for colonization. Biofilm formation by <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> in rich medium is enhanced by CSP (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), whereas XIP in a defined medium has an inhibitory effect (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Thus, it is clear that both pheromones may influence the <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> biofilm mode of growth. Once in biofilms, both XIP and CSP pheromones may provide <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> with a competitive advantage by activating the production of bacteriocin, which is used to attack competitors, and by increasing their ability to take up exogenous DNA and therefore adapt to the environment. It is also known that CSP may increase the ability of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> to tolerate acid stress (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) and that competence is repressed under acidic conditions (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). These effects are particularly relevant in view of the association of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> with dental caries, where the abilities to produce acids and survive under acidic conditions create an environment that favors tooth demineralization. Unraveling of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> signaling pathways will improve the focus of efforts to develop signaling interference strategies for modulating its behavior to reduce biofilm formation or reduce its ability to promote acidic conditions within dental biofilms that may contribute to caries.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="h3"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s3.1"><title>Bacteria and growth conditions.</title><p><italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> UA159 and the isogenic mutants used in this study are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab3">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>. Cultures of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> were grown in TSB (Oxoid) at 37&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C in TSB supplemented with 15% glycerol.</p><table-wrap id="tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE&#x000a0;3&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Strains and plasmid used in this study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain or plasmid</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="ngtab3.1"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source or reference(s)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> strains</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;UA159</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT, transformable strain; Spc<sup>s</sup> Erm<sup>s</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100, 101</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SM065</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UA159 &#x00394;<italic>comS::spc</italic>; Spc<sup>r</sup> (from strain MW05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6, 102</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SM068</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UA159::&#x003c6; (P<italic><sub>sigX</sub>-luc</italic>); Spc<sup>r</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;SM059</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UA159<italic>::</italic>&#x003c6; (P<italic><sub>1914</sub>-luc</italic>); Spc<sup>r</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid pVA838</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erm<sup>r</sup>; replicative streptococcal plasmid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ngtab3.1"><label>a</label><p>Spc, spectinomycin; Erm, erythromycin.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3.2"><title>Synthetic peptide.</title><p>CSP was used in the form of CSP18 (NH<sub>2</sub>-SGSLSTFFRLFNRSFTQA-COOH), synthesized by GenScript (GenScript Corporation, NJ), with a purity of &#x0003e;95%. The lyophilized peptide was reconstituted in distilled water at 175&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g&#x000b7;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and stored in small aliquots at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="s3.3"><title>Transformation.</title><p>Transformation experiments were performed in the absence or presence of CSP18 (50&#x000a0;nM). Cultures grown overnight at 37&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub> were diluted to an optical density at 600&#x000a0;nm (OD<sub>600</sub>) of 0.04. From this point, incubation proceeded at 37&#x000b0;C in ambient air. Upon reaching an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.065, the cultures were distributed into Eppendorf tubes (1.2&#x000a0;ml) and CSP was added to a final concentration of 50&#x000a0;nM. At different times, a 100-&#x000b5;l aliquot was used for OD<sub>600</sub> measurements, and a 100-&#x000b5;l sample was pelleted and frozen for RNA extraction as described below. Another 100-&#x000b5;l portion was diluted 1:2 in fresh TSB containing replicative plasmid pVA838 DNA (final concentration of 1&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g&#x000b7;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). After a 20-min incubation with plasmid DNA, recombinant DNase I (Roche) was added at a final concentration of 10&#x000a0;U&#x000b7;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and incubation proceeded for 40&#x000a0;min before dilution and plating on THB agar with or without erythromycin at a final concentration of 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g&#x000b7;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 48&#x000a0;h before the counting of visible colonies.</p></sec><sec id="s3.4"><title>Real-time PCR.</title><p>Bacterial samples for real-time PCRs were collected at 10 and 100&#x000a0;min after the addition of CSP as described above. Total RNA was extracted with the High Pure RNA isolation kit (Roche, Mannheim, Germany) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendation, except that the cells were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20&#x000a0;min in 200 &#x000b5;l of lysis buffer containing 10&#x000a0;mM Tris (pH&#x000a0;8), 20&#x000a0;mg of lysozyme ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and 100&#x000a0;U of mutanolysin ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. DNase I was used during RNA extraction to remove the remaining DNA. Complementary DNA templates were prepared from RNA with the Transcriptor First Strand cDNA synthesis kit (Roche Diagnostics GmbH, Mannheim, Germany) in accordance with the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Controls without reverse transcriptase were included. Expression of <italic>cipB</italic> and <italic>comGA</italic> was examined by real-time PCR with primer pairs FP156 (TGCTCTAGGTGCTGGGCAAG)-FP157 (GAGCTCCTCCGATTCCTCCA), FP166 (ATTGGCAACAAGAGGGAATG)-FP167 (TCTTGCTGACGCAAAACATC), and FP128 (AGAAACCGCCAGAGCTGTTA)-FP129 (CCACGCAAAGCATTTTGTAA), respectively. To normalize the data, primer pair FP299 (CCATGACCATCAACCAACAT)-FP300 (ATCAGCGCGTATTACAGGTG) was used to amplify a portion of <italic>gyrA</italic>. Assays were carried out with quantitative PCR master mix for SYBR green I. Data were collected and compared with the software and graphics program MxPro (Stratagene).</p></sec><sec id="s3.5"><title>RNA preparation for microarrays.</title><p>RNA samples were from the WT UA159 and the <italic>comS</italic> deletion mutant, grown in the presence or absence of CSP in 100-ml volumes of TSB as described for the transformation assay. WT cultures were collected by centrifugation at 10 and 100&#x000a0;min after CSP addition, and <italic>comS</italic> deletion mutant cultures were collected at 100&#x000a0;min. At each time, samples without CSP were included as controls. Two independent biological replicates were obtained for each condition, giving a total of 12 samples. Immediately after centrifugation (9,000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>, 2.5&#x000a0;min, 4&#x000b0;C), the pellets were frozen in liquid nitrogen. RNA was prepared as previously described, with a few modifications (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Briefly, the pellets were lysed with mutanolysin-lysozyme, followed by RNA extraction with the mirVana miRNA isolation kit (Ambion). This kit was used to enhance the rate of recovery of short transcripts (down to 10 nucleotides). The samples were then treated with Turbo DNase (Ambion) and analyzed for quality with a Bioanalyzer. Samples with remaining DNA, as determined by PCR with primers for <italic>ccpA</italic> (FP297, [GTAGGTGTGGTTATCCCTAATATTGC] and FP298 [ATAAATCGGCTGACTGATAGATGTC]), were retreated with Turbo DNase, and repurified until no DNA was detected. The MICROBExpress kit (Ambion) was then used for mRNA enrichment. RNA was then fragmented and Cy3 labeled (Mirus Label IT &#x000b5;Array Cy3 labeling kit; Mirus); this was followed by hybridization to the microarray probes. UA159 genomic reference DNA was purified with the DNeasy Blood and Tissue kit (Qiagen), with mutanolysin-lysozyme treatment for the lysis step, followed by fragmentation and labeling (Mirus Label IT &#x000b5;Array Cy3 labeling kit).</p></sec><sec id="s3.6"><title>Microarray signal detection, data normalization, and analysis.</title><p>The genomic tiling microarray was constructed with probe sets designed from both forward and reverse complement strands of the entire target genome of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mutans</italic> UA159 as described by H&#x000f8;vik and Chen (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). A total of 385,000 optimized probes covered the entire genome, including ORFs and intergenic regions. The probes were printed on high-density microarrays by Roche NimbleGen. To block nonspecific binding of RNA molecules, RNase-free bovine serum albumin (500&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g&#x000b7;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was added to the prehybridization solution and salmon sperm DNA (100 to 700&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g&#x000b7;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was included in both prehybridization and hybridization solutions. Hybridization was conducted at a temperature of 42&#x000b0;C in the presence of 25% formamide. NimbleScan v2.5 software was used for spot feature extraction from the scanned images, followed by normalization and analysis as previously described (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Briefly, the nonspecific background was estimated from the intensity of the intergenic sequence probes and of the genomic DNA reference and used for corrections due to sequence-specific factors (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Normalization between arrays was done with the vsn algorithm (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The log<sub>2</sub> means of the normalized signal intensities from each condition were used for downstream processes.</p><p>A Hidden Markov support vector machine (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>) was used to identify the boundaries of TARs on the basis of a set of training data derived from both ORFs and intergenic regions. The expression level of annotated genes was determined by averaging the nucleotide intensities of probe signals within the length of the gene (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Differential expression at the ORF level was measured as the difference between the log<sub>2</sub> mean probe signal intensities of the control and CSP-treated samples from two independent biological experiments, except for the 10-min sample without CSP, in which one of the hybridizations failed. The <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;values were calculated with the SAM software (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>) at default settings by performing 10 permutations for the inclusion of two sets of repeats. Genes that exhibited a &#x0003e;2-fold mean signal intensity difference (with a <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;value of &#x0003c;0.05) were registered as differentially expressed.</p></sec><sec id="s3.7"><title>Microarray data and nucleotide sequence accession numbers.</title><p>Original and normalized microarray data used in this study were deposited in the NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo</ext-link>) under accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE70067">GSE70067</ext-link>. The transcriptome profiles are also available for browsing at the Microbial Transcriptome Database website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinformatics.forsyth.org/mtd/dataset=RNAseq_smut_comS">http://bioinformatics.forsyth.org/mtd/dataset=RNAseq_smut_comS</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>We thank Todd O. Kitten, Justin Merritt, and Pascal Hols for helpful comments on the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiedenbeck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohan</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Origins of bacterial diversity through horizontal genetic transfer and adaptation to new ecological niches</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>957</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>976</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2011.00292.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21711367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1928</year>
<article-title>The significance of pneumococcal types</article-title>. <source>J Hyg (Lond)</source>
<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>159</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20474956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnsborg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eldholm</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e5;varstein</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Natural genetic transformation: prevalence, mechanisms and function</article-title>. <source>Res Microbiol</source>
<volume>158</volume>:<fpage>767</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>778</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resmic.2007.09.004</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17997281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnsborg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e5;varstein</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Regulation of natural genetic transformation and acquisition of transforming DNA in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>642</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2009.00167.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19396959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontaine</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boutry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Frahan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delplace</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fremaux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyaval</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hols</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>A novel pheromone quorum-sensing system controls the development of natural competence in <italic>Streptococcus thermophilus</italic> and <italic>Streptococcus salivarius</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>192</volume>:<fpage>1444</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1454</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01251-09</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20023010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mashburn-Warren</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Federle</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>A novel double-tryptophan peptide pheromone controls competence in Streptococcus spp. via an Rgg regulator</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>606</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07361.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20969646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu&#x000e9;don</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Competence for natural genetic transformation in the <italic>Streptococcus bovis</italic> group streptococci <italic>S</italic>. <italic>infantarius</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>macedonicus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>195</volume>:<fpage>2612</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2620</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00230-13</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23543718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaccaria</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Baarlen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Greeff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Control of competence for DNA transformation in Streptococcus suis by genetically transferable pherotypes</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e99394</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099394</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24968201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mashburn-Warren</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Federle</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>The cryptic competence pathway in <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic> is controlled by a peptide pheromone</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>194</volume>:<fpage>4589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4600</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00830-12</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22730123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontaine</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fl&#x000e9;chard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mignolet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hols</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Regulation of competence for natural transformation in streptococci</article-title>. <source>Infect Genet Evol</source>
<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>360</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2014.09.010</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25236918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Identification of a new regulator in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> linking quorum sensing to competence for genetic transformation</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>181</volume>:<fpage>5004</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5016</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10438773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fichant</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Bacterial transformation: distribution, shared mechanisms and divergent control</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3199</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24509783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snesrud</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mintz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsegaye</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Do</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fleischmann</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Identification of competence pheromone responsive genes in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> by use of DNA microarrays</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>1051</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1070</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03907.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14763980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vickerman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iobst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jesionowski</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide transcriptional changes in <italic>Streptococcus gordonii</italic> in response to competence signaling peptide</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>189</volume>:<fpage>7799</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7807</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01023-07</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17720781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cvitkovitch</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000e9;vesque</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Peptide alarmone signalling triggers an auto-active bacteriocin necessary for genetic competence</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>905</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>917</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06693.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19400789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinmoen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teigen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e5;varstein</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Competence-induced cells of <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> lyse competence-deficient cells of the same strain during cocultivation</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>185</volume>:<fpage>7176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7183</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.185.24.7176-7183.2003</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14645278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenderska</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lukenda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cordova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magarvey</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cvitkovitch</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Senadheera</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>A novel function for the competence inducing peptide, XIP, as a cell death effector of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>
<volume>336</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2012.02660.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22900705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Ploeg</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Regulation of bacteriocin production in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> by the quorum-sensing system required for development of genetic competence</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>187</volume>:<fpage>3980</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3989</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.187.12.3980-3989.2005</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15937160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Svens&#x000e4;ter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellen</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cvitkovitch</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Cell density modulates acid adaptation in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>: implications for survival in biofilms</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>183</volume>:<fpage>6875</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6884</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.183.23.6875-6884.2001</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11698377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aspiras</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellen</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cvitkovitch</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>A quorum-sensing signaling system essential for genetic competence in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> is involved in biofilm formation</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>184</volume>:<fpage>2699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2708</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.184.10.2699-2708.2002</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11976299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e5;varstein</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coomaraswamy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>An unmodified heptadecapeptide pheromone induces competence for genetic transformation in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>11140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11144</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.92.24.11140</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7479953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e5;varstein</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diep</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nes</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>A family of bacteriocin ABC transporters carry out proteolytic processing of their substrates concomitant with export</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.1995.tb02295.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7565085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e5;varstein</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaustad</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nes</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Identification of the streptococcal competence-pheromone receptor</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>869</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1996.521416.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8878047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pestova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e5;varstein</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Regulation of competence for genetic transformation in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> by an auto-induced peptide pheromone and a two-component regulatory system</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>853</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>862</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1996.501417.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8878046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Federle</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Peptide pheromone signaling in Streptococcus and Enterococcus</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>492</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1574-6976.12046</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24118108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burne</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Microfluidic study of competence regulation in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>: environmental inputs modulate bimodal and unimodal expression of comX</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2012.08187.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22845615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomasch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner-D&#x000f6;bler</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The alternative sigma factor SigX controls bacteriocin synthesis and competence, the two quorum sensing regulated traits in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e1005353</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005353</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26158727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemme</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gr&#x000f6;be</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomasch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner-D&#x000f6;bler</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Subpopulation-specific transcriptome analysis of competence stimulating peptide induced <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>193</volume>:<fpage>1863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1877</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01363-10</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21317319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000f8;vik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Dynamic probe selection for studying microbial transcriptome with high-density genomic tiling microarrays</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-11-82</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20144223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000f8;vik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Strand-specific transcriptome profiling with directly labeled RNA on genomic tiling microarrays</article-title>. <source>BMC Mol Biol</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2199-12-3</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21235785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fimland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheie</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Purification and functional studies of a potent modified quorum-sensing peptide and a two-peptide bacteriocin in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>1322</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1334</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05312.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16925560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cordova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cvitkovitch</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000e9;vesque</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Regulation of the competence pathway as a novel role associated with a streptococcal bacteriocin</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>193</volume>:<fpage>6552</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6559</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.05968-11</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21984782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>An extracellular protease, SepM, generates functional competence-stimulating peptide in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> UA159</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>194</volume>:<fpage>5886</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5896</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01381-12</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22923597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burne</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Bidirectional signaling in the competence regulatory pathway of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>
<volume>362</volume><comment/> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femsle/fnv159</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheie</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>DNA binding-uptake system: a link between cell-to-cell communication and biofilm formation</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>187</volume>:<fpage>4392</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4400</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.187.13.4392-4400.2005</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15968048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Co-ordinated bacteriocin production and competence development: a possible mechanism for taking up DNA from neighbouring species</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>392</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>404</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2005.04695.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15978073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>SMU.152 acts as an immunity protein for mutacin IV</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>194</volume>:<fpage>3486</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3494</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00194-12</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22505686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>DOOR 2.0: presenting operons and their functions through dynamic and integrated views</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>D654</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D659</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1048</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24214966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okinaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Examination of the <italic>hdrRM</italic> regulon yields insight into the competence system of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Oral Microbiol</source>
<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>177</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2041-1014.2010.00574.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20536745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayala</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kreth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mair</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Senadheera</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cvitkovitch</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Characterization of DNA binding sites of the ComE response regulator from <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>193</volume>:<fpage>3642</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3652</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00155-11</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21602345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontaine</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goffin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubout</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delplace</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baulard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lecat-Guillet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chambellon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hols</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Mechanism of competence activation by the ComRS signalling system in streptococci</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>1113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1132</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.12157</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23323845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavinski Bitar</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weinstock</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Highlander</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Town</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burne</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stanhope</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Phylogenomics and the dynamic genome evolution of the genus streptococcus</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>741</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>753</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evu048</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24625962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delplace</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clippe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fontaine</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hols</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Adaptor protein MecA is a negative regulator of the expression of late competence genes in <italic>Streptococcus thermophilus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>194</volume>:<fpage>1777</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1788</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.06800-11</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22287513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dagkessamanskaia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moscoso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e9;nard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guiral</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Overweg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Interconnection of competence, stress and CiaR regulons in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>: competence triggers stationary phase autolysis of <italic>ciaR</italic> mutant cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>1071</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1086</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2003.03892.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14763981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fawcett</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitten</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Physiological and molecular characterization of genetic competence in <italic>Streptococcus sanguinis</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Oral Microbiol</source>
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2041-1014.2011.00606.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21375701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodbury</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>CP</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Sigma X induces competence gene expression in <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic></article-title>. <source>Res Microbiol</source>
<volume>157</volume>:<fpage>851</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>856</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resmic.2006.07.002</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16963231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mashburn-Warren</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Federle</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hakansson</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title><italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic> biofilm growth <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> and its role in colonization, virulence, and genetic exchange</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>210</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiu058</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24465015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guiral</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Competence-programmed predation of noncompetent cells in the human pathogen <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>: genetic requirements</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>8710</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8715</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0500879102</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15928084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stanhope</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burne</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Core-gene-encoded peptide regulating virulence-associated traits in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>195</volume>:<fpage>2912</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2920</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00189-13</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23603743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Genetic characterization of the <italic>hdrRM</italic> operon: a novel high-cell-density-responsive regulator in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>2765</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2773</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.2007/007468-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17660440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okinaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The <italic>hdrRM</italic> operon of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> encodes a novel regulatory system for coordinated competence development and bacteriocin production</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>192</volume>:<fpage>1844</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1852</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01667-09</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20118256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okinaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Identification of a novel bacteriocin regulatory system in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>1431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1447</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07417.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21143316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Echenique</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kadioglu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trombe</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Protein serine/threonine kinase StkP positively controls virulence and competence in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>2434</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2437</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.72.4.2434-2437.2004</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15039376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halfmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kov&#x000e1;cs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hakenbeck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Br&#x000fc;ckner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Identification of the genes directly controlled by the response regulator CiaR in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>: five out of 15 promoters drive expression of small non-coding RNAs</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2007.05900.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17725562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guenzi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gasc</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sicard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hakenbeck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>A two-component signal-transducing system is involved in competence and penicillin susceptibility in laboratory mutants of <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>505</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.1994.tb01038.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8065267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granadel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Programmed protection of foreign DNA from restriction allows pathogenicity island exchange during pneumococcal transformation</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e1003178</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003178</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23459610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quentin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fichant</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Independent evolution of competence regulatory cascades in streptococci?</article-title>
<source>Trends Microbiol</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>345</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2006.06.007</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e5;varstein</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Competence-induced fratricide in streptococci</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>1423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1433</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2007.05757.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17555432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moscoso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prudhomme</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Uptake of transforming DNA in Gram-positive bacteria: a view from <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>421</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2002.03013.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12123453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi&#x000f8;rnstad</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohnstad</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e5;varstein</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Deletion of the murein hydrolase CbpD reduces transformation efficiency in <italic>Streptococcus thermophilus</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>158</volume>:<fpage>877</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>885</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.056150-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22241050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000e9;vesque</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Cell death of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> induced by a quorum-sensing peptide occurs via a conserved streptococcal autolysin</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>195</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>114</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00926-12</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polikanov</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaha</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>How hibernation factors RMF, HPF, and YfiA turn off protein synthesis</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>336</volume>:<fpage>915</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>918</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1218538</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22605777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heng</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tagg</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tompkins</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Competence-dependent bacteriocin production by <italic>Streptococcus gordonii</italic> DL1 (Challis)</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>189</volume>:<fpage>1468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1472</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01174-06</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17012395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grainger</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Pervasive transcription: illuminating the dark matter of bacterial transcriptomes</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>653</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3316</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25069631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>M&#x000e4;der</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dervyn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rochat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leduc</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pigeonneau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bidnenko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marchadier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoebeke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aymerich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bisicchia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Botella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delumeau</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denham</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fogg</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fromion</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goelzer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Homuth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jarmer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jules</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klipp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Chat</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lecointe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liebermeister</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>March</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mars</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nannapaneni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noone</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pohl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rinn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rugheimer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sappa</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwikowski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steil</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stulke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wiegert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devine</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Dijl</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hecker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Volker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bessieres</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noirot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Condition-dependent transcriptome reveals high-level regulatory architecture in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>335</volume>:<fpage>1103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1106</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1206848</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sisson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Global transcriptional analysis of acid-inducible genes in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>: multiple two-component systems involved in acid adaptation</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>3322</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3332</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.031591-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19608608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghoreishi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burne</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Sharply tuned pH response of genetic competence regulation in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>: a microfluidic study of the environmental sensitivity of <italic>comX</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>5622</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5631</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01421-15</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26070670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000f8;vik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Comprehensive transcriptome analysis of the periodontopathogenic bacterium <italic>Porphyromonas gingivalis</italic> W83</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>194</volume>:<fpage>100</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>114</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.06385-11</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22037400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000f8;vik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>A hidden Markov support vector machine framework incorporating profile geometry learning for identifying microbial RNA in tiling array data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1430</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq162</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20395286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petty</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beatson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Easyfig: a genome comparison visualizer</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1009</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1010</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr039</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21278367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burghout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bootsma</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kloosterman</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bijlsma</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Jongh</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuipers</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hermans</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Search for genes essential for pneumococcal transformation: the RADA DNA repair protein plays a role in genomic recombination of donor DNA</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>189</volume>:<fpage>6540</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6550</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00573-07</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17631629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>An unstable competence-induced protein, CoiA, promotes processing of donor DNA after uptake during genetic transformation in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>188</volume>:<fpage>5177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5186</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00103-06</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16816189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carrasco</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keck</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Genetic recombination in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>: a division of labor between two single-strand DNA-binding proteins</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>5546</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5559</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks173</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22373918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mortier-Barri&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Transformation of <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> relies on DprA- and RecA-dependent protection of incoming DNA single strands</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>527</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>536</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03702.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14617176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piotrowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Exit from competence for genetic transformation in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> is regulated at multiple levels</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e64197</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064197</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23717566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quevillon-Cheruel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirouze</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mortier-Barri&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boudes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soulet</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lisboa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noirot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Tilbeurgh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noirot-Gros</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Structure-function analysis of pneumococcal DprA protein reveals that dimerization is crucial for loading RecA recombinase onto DNA during transformation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>E2466</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E2475</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1205638109</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22904190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacques</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Deletion of competence-induced genes over-expressed in biofilms caused transformation deficiencies in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Oral Microbiol</source>
<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>406</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>417</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2041-1014.2010.00589.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21040514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carrasco</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hejna</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takeyasu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title><italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> DprA recruits RecA onto single-stranded DNA and mediates annealing of complementary strands coated by SsbB and SsbA</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>288</volume>:<fpage>22437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22450</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M113.478347</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23779106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Attaiech</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mortier-Barri&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soulet</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granadel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Role of the single-stranded DNA-binding protein SsbB in pneumococcal transformation: maintenance of a reservoir for genetic plasticity</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e1002156</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002156</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21738490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masure</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>A competence regulon in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> revealed by genomic analysis</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>929</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>939</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1998.00737.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9535083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mortier-Barri&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Attaiech</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Identification of the major protein component of the pneumococcal eclipse complex</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>189</volume>:<fpage>6497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6500</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00687-07</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17601792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mortier-Barri&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Saizieu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Competence-specific induction of <italic>recA</italic> is required for full recombination proficiency during transformation in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1998.00668.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9466264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quivey</surname><given-names>RG</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faustoferri</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> inactivation of the <italic>Streptococcus mutans recA</italic> gene mediated by PCR amplification and cloning of a <italic>recA</italic> DNA fragment</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1119(92)90626-Z</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1628842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><label>84.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruellan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Angulo</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devoret</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Identification of the <italic>recA</italic> gene of <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>6412</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/20.23.6412</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1475203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><label>85.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mortier-Barriere</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<source>Controle genetique de la competence chez la bacterie a Gram positif Streptococcus pneumoniae: etude de l&#x02019;operon tardif cinA</source>. <comment>Ph.D. dissertation</comment>
<publisher-name>Paul Sabatier University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Toulouse, France</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><label>86.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Londo&#x000f1;o-Vallejo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Mutation of the putative nucleotide-binding site of the <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> membrane-protein ComFA abolishes the uptake of DNA during transformation</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>176</volume>:<fpage>4642</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4645</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8045895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><label>87.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madeo</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Construction and analysis of a library for random insertional mutagenesis in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>: use for recovery of mutants defective in genetic transformation and for identification of essential genes</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>1883</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1890</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10223974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><label>88.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rimini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Francesco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gozzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faggioni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Domenici</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frandsen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polissi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Global analysis of transcription kinetics during competence development in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> using high density DNA arrays</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>1279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1292</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2000.01931.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10931279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><label>89.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inamine</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>ComEA, a <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> integral membrane-protein required for genetic transformation, is needed for both DNA-binding and transport</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>177</volume>:<fpage>3045</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3051</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7768800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><label>90.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pestova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Isolation and characterization of three <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> transformation-specific loci by use of a <italic>lacZ</italic> reporter insertion vector</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>180</volume>:<fpage>2701</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2710</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9573156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><label>91.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Draskovic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Biogenesis of a putative channel protein, ComEC, required for DNA uptake: membrane topology, oligomerization and formation of disulphide bonds</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>881</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>896</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04430.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15661011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><label>92.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurenceau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>P&#x000e9;hau-Arnaudet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baconnais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gault</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malosse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dujeancourt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chamot-Rooke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Cam</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claverys</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fronzes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>A type IV pilus mediates DNA binding during natural transformation in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e1003473</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003473</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23825953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><label>93.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balaban</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>B&#x000e4;ttig</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muschiol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tirier</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wartha</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Normark</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henriques-Normark</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Secretion of a pneumococcal type II secretion system pilus correlates with DNA uptake during transformation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>E758</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E765</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1313860111</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24550320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><label>94.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muschiol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balaban</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Normark</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henriques-Normark</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Uptake of extracellular DNA: competence induced pili in natural transformation of <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>Bioessays</source>
<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>426</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>435</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bies.201400125</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25640084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><label>95.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohnstad</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e5;varstein</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>LytF, a novel competence-regulated murein hydrolase in the genus <italic>Streptococcus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>194</volume>:<fpage>627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>635</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.06273-11</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22123253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><label>96.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnsborg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eldholm</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bj&#x000f8;rnstad</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000e5;varstein</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>A predatory mechanism dramatically increases the efficiency of lateral gene transfer in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> and related commensal species</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>253</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2008.06288.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18485065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><label>97.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>A unique nine-gene <italic>comY</italic> operon in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>166</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.27554-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15632435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><label>98.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mair</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Senadheera</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cvitkovitch</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>CinA is regulated via ComX to modulate genetic transformation and cell viability in <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>
<volume>331</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2012.02550.x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22428842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B99"><label>99.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Furumichi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>KEGG as a reference resource for gene and protein annotation</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>D457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D462</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv1070</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26476454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B100"><label>100.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajdi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McShan</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Savi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Primeaux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kenton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Najar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferretti</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Genome sequence of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> UA159, a cariogenic dental pathogen</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>14434</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14439</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.172501299</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12397186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B101"><label>101.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murchison</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cardineau</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Curtiss</surname><given-names>R III</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>Transformation of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> with chromosomal and shuttle plasmid (pYA629) DNAs</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>282</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3021626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B102"><label>102.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rukke</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ricomini Filho</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fimland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arntzen</surname><given-names>M&#x000d8;</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thiede</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Extracellular identification of a processed type II ComR/ComS pheromone of <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>194</volume>:<fpage>3781</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3788</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00624-12</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22609914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B103"><label>103.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macrina</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tobian</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clewell</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1982</year>
<article-title>A cloning vector able to replicate in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Streptococcus sanguis</italic></article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>353</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1119(82)90025-7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6295886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>