<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijms</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1422-0067</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4519886</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26151842</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms160715031</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijms-16-15031</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Differences between Mice and Humans in Regulation and the Molecular Network of Collagen, Type III, Alpha-1 at the Gene Expression Level: Obstacles that Translational Research Must Overcome</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Lishi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-16-15031">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-16-15031">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Hongchao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijms-16-15031">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-16-15031">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-ijms-16-15031">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Erjian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijms-16-15031">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>Stephen H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5-ijms-16-15031">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Postlethwaite</surname><given-names>Arnold E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af6-ijms-16-15031">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af7-ijms-16-15031">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Weikuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-16-15031">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af7-ijms-16-15031">7</xref><xref rid="c1-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijms-16-15031">3</xref><xref rid="c1-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>William Chi-shing</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ijms-16-15031"><label>1</label>Department of Orthopedic Surgery and BME-Campbell Clinic, University of Tennessee Health Science Center, Memphis, TN 38163, USA; E-Mails: <email>lwang37@uthsc.edu</email> (L.W.); <email>yjiao2@uthsc.edu</email> (Y.J.)</aff><aff id="af2-ijms-16-15031"><label>2</label>Department of Basic Research, Inner Mongolia Medical College, Inner Mongolia 010110, China</aff><aff id="af3-ijms-16-15031"><label>3</label>Integrative Research Center, the first Hospital of Qiqihaer City, Qiqihaer 161005, China; E-Mails: <email>hliu48@uthsc.edu</email> (H.L.); <email>ewang5@uthsc.edu</email> (E.W.)</aff><aff id="af4-ijms-16-15031"><label>4</label>Department of Medicine, Mudanjiang Medical College, Mudanjiang 157001, China</aff><aff id="af5-ijms-16-15031"><label>5</label>Department of Genetics and Developmental Biology, University of Connecticut Health Center, Farmington, CT 06030, USA; E-Mail: <email>sclark@nso2.uchc.edu</email></aff><aff id="af6-ijms-16-15031"><label>6</label>Department of Medicine, University of Tennessee Health Science Center, Memphis, TN 38163, USA; E-Mail: <email>apostlet@uthsc.edu</email></aff><aff id="af7-ijms-16-15031"><label>7</label>Research Service, Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Memphis, TN 38104, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-ijms-16-15031"><label>*</label>Authors to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mails: <email>wgu@uthsc.edu</email> (W.G.); <email>qsdyyych@126.com</email> (H.C.); Tel.: +01-901-448-2258 (W.G.); +86-452-242-5981 (H.C.); Fax: +01-901-448-6062 (W.G.); +86-452-247-0942 (H.C.).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>15031</fpage><lpage>15056</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Collagen, type III, alpha-1 (COL3A1) is essential for normal collagen I fibrillogenesis in many organs. There are differences in phenotypes of mutations in the <italic>COL3A1</italic> gene in humans and mutations in mice. In order to investigate whether the regulation and gene network of <italic>COL3A1</italic> is the same in healthy populations of mice and humans, we compared the quantitative trait loci (QTL) that regulate the expression level of <italic>COL3A1</italic> and the gene network of <italic>COL3A1</italic> pathways between humans and mice using whole genome expression profiles. Our results showed that, for the regulation of expression of <italic>Col3a1</italic> in mice, an eQTL on chromosome (Chr) 12 regulates the expression of <italic>Col3a1</italic>. However, expression of genes in the syntenic region on human Chr 7 has no association with the expression level of <italic>COL3A1</italic>. For the gene network comparison, we identified 44 top genes whose expression levels are strongly associated with that of <italic>Col3a1</italic> in mice. We next identified 41 genes strongly associated with the expression level of <italic>COL3A1</italic> in humans. There are a few but significant differences in the <italic>COL3A1</italic> gene network between humans and mice. Several genes showed opposite association with expression of <italic>COL3A1</italic>. These genes are known to play important roles in development and function of the extracellular matrix of the lung. Difference in the molecular pathway of key genes in the <italic>COL3A1</italic> gene network in humans and mice suggest caution should be used in extrapolating results from models of human lung diseases in mice to clinical lung diseases in humans. These differences may influence the efficacy of drugs in humans whose development employed mouse models.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>COL3A1</italic></kwd><kwd>gene network</kwd><kwd>human</kwd><kwd>mouse</kwd><kwd>lung fibrosis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Rodents, particularly mouse and rat have been widely used for biomedical research in models of human diseases since it is known that almost of all of genes in mouse and rat are similar to that of humans. However, not every genetic pathway or molecular mechanism of diseases or drugs discovered to be efficacious in these models can be extrapolated to human diseases. Thus, while much data from animal studies have been successfully applied to humans, some have not. The present study aims to explore the degrees of differences in the causal pathways for lung fibrosis between humans and mice. In spite of the tremendous development in biotechnology and the rapid accumulation of information from genome sequencing and discovery of mutations, progress in the development of therapeutic applications for human fibrotic lung diseases is slow. Most of the new selected targets and drugs developed from animal models have failed in humans. While the failures may be caused by many factors, we believe that genomic differences between humans and animal models may play an important role.</p><p>Collagen, type III, alpha-1 (COL3A1) is a major component of the extracellular matrix in a variety of internal organs in human body. COL3A1 is essential for normal collagen I fibrillogenesis in the cardiovascular system and lung. Mutations of the <italic>COL3A1</italic> gene in humans lead to type IV Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, a disease leading to spontaneous rupture of bowel or large arteries in early adult life [<xref rid="B1-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In contrast to the severe phenotype in humans, mice that are haploinsufficient for <italic>COL3A1</italic> have no identified phenotype. While most have severe disease, about 10% of the homozygous mutant mice survive to adulthood but have a much shorter life span compared with wild-type mice [<xref rid="B3-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Recently, <italic>Col3a1</italic> was suggested to play a role in the causation of the tight skin phonotype in a mouse model tight skin 2 (Tsk2/+) [<xref rid="B5-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], for systemic sclerosis (SSc). A missense mutation in the procollagen III amino terminal propeptide segment (PIIINP) of <italic>Col3a1</italic> was identified in the Tsk2/+ mouse model [<xref rid="B6-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], indicating its complex role in the different tissues and between humans and mice.</p><p><italic>Col3a1</italic> plays an important role in development and fibrosis of the lung [<xref rid="B7-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Lung malformation in the Ehlers-Danlos syndrome suggests that <italic>COL3A1</italic> plays a critical role in lung development [<xref rid="B8-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] in humans. SSc-related progressive lung fibrosis is another evidence to suggest that <italic>COL3A1</italic> plays an important role in the lung fibrosis [<xref rid="B9-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Recently, a study of <italic>Col3a1</italic> relevant molecular pathways using gene expression profiles in mouse models has shed light on the detailed function of <italic>Col3a1</italic> in lung [<xref rid="B10-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. These studies revealed the importance of the inflammasome and caspase 1 in innate immune signaling, which contributes to SSc fibrosis [<xref rid="B10-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and osteopontin in the inflammation, mucin production, and gene expression signatures in a murine model of fibrosis [<xref rid="B11-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. It is important to further study whether the regulation of <italic>COL3A1</italic> and its molecular pathways in lung is the same in the healthy populations between humans and mice, which provides the foundation of disease prevention and treatment. Thus, we need to understand which gene pathways in humans and mice are similar and different in healthy and disease states.</p><p>This study aims to explore the potential pathways of <italic>Col3a1</italic> in lung using data of whole genome expression in mouse models and humans. We will focus on the molecular pathways of <italic>Col3a1</italic> in normal lung tissues to investigate what roles <italic>Col3a1</italic> plays in the normal function of lung, which is a targeted organ in fibrotic disease. Understanding the gene network of <italic>Col3a1</italic> in normal genomic background will provide information on how <italic>Col3a1</italic>is regulated and how <italic>Col3a1</italic> regulates other genes. In this study, we will focus on the identification of the genetic loci that regulate the expression of <italic>Col3a1,</italic> construction of pathways of <italic>Col3a1</italic> under the normal genomic background, and comparing the similarity and differences of molecular pathways between humans and mice.</p></sec><sec><title>2. Results</title><sec><title>2.1. Transcriptome Mapping of Expression Quantitative Trait Loci (eQTL) that Regulates Expression Level of Collagen, Type III, alpha-1 (COL3A1)</title><p>We first mapped the expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) that regulates the expression level of <italic>Col3a1</italic> using data of the mouse model, the HZI Lung M430v2 (Apr08) RMA Database [<xref rid="B12-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The dataset has three probes of <italic>Col3a1</italic>. They are from the intron (GeneNetwork ID: 1442977_at), last two exons proximal and mid 3&#x02032; UTR (ID: 1427883_a_at) and distal 3&#x02032; UTR (ID: 1427884_at). Probe 1427883 was first used for transcriptome mapping. The transcriptome mapping located two eQTL at the suggestive level (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Figure S1</xref>A). One is located between 99 MB (million bases) and 104 MB on chromosome (Chr) 12 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f001">Figure 1</xref>A), which contains 57 genetic elements as candidates (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Table S1</xref>). The other is located on Chr 11, between 19.3 MB and 28 MB which also contain 57 genetic elements.</p><p>Using probe 1427884_at, we mapped tow loci (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Figure S1</xref>B), one is located on Chr 12, the same genomic region with that mapped by probe 1427883_a_at (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f001">Figure 1</xref>B). The other is located on Chr 9. The EQTL on Chr 12 was mapped into a small genomic region between 101.7 and 103.8 MB, which contains 24 genetic elements and 16 known genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ijms-16-15031-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Probe 1442977 from intron has a relatively low expression level. Transcriptome mapping showed that a merely suggestive locus on Chr 10 regulates the expression of this probe (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Figure S1</xref>C). Because of its nature of intron location, low expression level, and uncertainty of eQTL, we used the data from other two probes for the further analysis.</p><fig id="ijms-16-15031-f001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) that regulates the expression level of Collagen, type III, alpha-1 (<italic>Col3a1</italic>). (<bold>A</bold>) eQTL on chromosome (Chr) 12 located between 99 MB (million bases) and 104 detected with probe 1724883; (<bold>B</bold>) eQTL located on Chr 12 region between 101.7 and 103.8 MB.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="ijms-16-15031-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">ijms-16-15031-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Candidate genes for eQTL of regulation of <italic>Col3a1</italic> expression level in mice.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Index</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNPS Name</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MB</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;log(<italic>p</italic>)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Name</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Function Consequence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm-rs2585897</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.398979</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.82131</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>XPO4</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm1564625</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.925928</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.69919</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm2272985</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.047446</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.29611</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm2270333</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.344955</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04571</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRIM1</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm609871</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.811795</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.93442</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm-rs7326068</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.209512</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.69486</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>IFT88</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm-rs10506525</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.783378</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52754</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MSRB3</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm1082069</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.175038</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51385</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm1157141</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.093927</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.45730</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ZFPM2</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm2266405</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.919134</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.44515</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CCDC144A</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm2266494</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153.144983</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27992</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm-rs4380451</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.329497</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27737</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CMTM8</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm2269464</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.422051</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25987</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>PHEX</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm2271745</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.810174</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25088</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm506442</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176.637576</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21638</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>TLDC1</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm869284</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.193146</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.17341</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm2267394</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.082846</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14527</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GTPBP1</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">upstream variant 2 KB</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm2273373</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.874288</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.13365</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GPCPD1</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">missense</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm882858</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.461834</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11867</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm-rs2286720</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.448471</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10924</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>LYZL4</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">synonymous codon</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm-rs2763196</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.150951</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10885</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AKNA</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant, upstream variant 2 KB</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm-rs11073328</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.764843</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10746</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>FAM98B</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm397086</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.895308</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09675</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>MEGF10</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm1156850</td><td align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.939642</td><td align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.03829</td><td align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom: solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RP11-23B15.1</italic></td><td align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom: solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron variant</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>2.2. Initial Analysis of Candidate Genes for Regulation of Expression of Col3a1 on Mouse Chromosome (Chr) 12</title><p>Because two probes of <italic>Col3a1</italic> located the eQTL onto the same location on Chr 12, we further examined the genes within the eQTL region to identify the potential candidate genes. We first examined the association of expression levels of these genes in the eQTL with that of <italic>Col3a1</italic>. According to the map based on probe #1427883, there are 57 genetic elements within the eQTL (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Table S1</xref>), among them, 34 are known genes. (<italic>Galc</italic>, <italic>Gpr65</italic>, <italic>Kcnk10</italic>, <italic>Spata7</italic>, <italic>Ptpn21</italic>, <italic>Zc3h14</italic>, <italic>Eml5</italic>, <italic>Ttc8</italic>, <italic>Foxn3</italic>, <italic>Ttc7b</italic>, <italic>Tdp1</italic>, <italic>Kcnk13</italic>, <italic>Psmc1</italic>, <italic>Calm1</italic>, <italic>Rps6ka5</italic>, <italic>Gpr68</italic>, <italic>Ccdc88c</italic>, <italic>Smek1</italic>, <italic>Trip11</italic>, <italic>Catsperb</italic>, <italic>Tc2n</italic>, <italic>Fbln5</italic>, <italic>Atxn3</italic>, <italic>Cpsf2</italic>, <italic>Slc24a4</italic>, <italic>Gm46</italic>, <italic>Rin3</italic>, <italic>Lgmn</italic>, <italic>Golga5</italic>, <italic>Chga</italic>, <italic>Itpk1</italic>, <italic>Moap1</italic>, <italic>Btbd7</italic>, <italic>Cox8c</italic>). According to the map based on probe #1427884, the eQTL region contains only 24 genetic elements (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Table S2</xref>), from which we found 16 genes (<italic>Rps6ka5</italic>, <italic>Gpr68</italic>, <italic>Ccdc88c</italic>, <italic>Smek1</italic>, <italic>Trip11</italic>, <italic>Catsperb</italic>, <italic>Tc2n</italic>, <italic>Fbln5</italic>, <italic>Atxn3</italic>, <italic>Cpsf2</italic>, <italic>Slc24a4</italic>, <italic>Gm46</italic>, <italic>Rin3</italic>, <italic>Lgmn</italic>, <italic>Golga5</italic>, <italic>Chga</italic>). All of these 16 genes are among the list for eQTL based on the probe #1427883.</p><p>To make sure we did not miss the real candidates, we used the gene list of eQTL of #1427883 for further analysis. For the convenience of identifying genes linked to <italic>Col3a1</italic>, we used the circular layout model for the building of gene network in this case. The network showed that the expression levels of both probes of <italic>Col3a1</italic> are negatively correlated to <italic>Slc24a4</italic> and <italic>Rin3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f002">Figure 2</xref>). Because both genes are among the candidate list from two eQTLs of two probes, their likelihood of candidacy are strong. In addition, one probe (#1427883) of <italic>Col3a1</italic> showed a weak positive correlation with <italic>Zc3h14.</italic> One probe (#1427884) is negatively correlated to <italic>Cpsf2.</italic></p><fig id="ijms-16-15031-f002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Gene network between <italic>Col3a1</italic> and candidate genes on Chr 12. The 27 nodes in the graph below show the selected traits. All nodes are displayed. The 55 edges between the nodes, filtered from the 351 total edges and drawn as curves, show Pearson correlation coefficients greater than 0.35 or less than &#x02212;0.35. The graph&#x02019;s canvas is 40.0 by 40.0 cm, and the node labels are drawn with a 18.0 point font, and the edge labels are drawn with a 16.0 point font.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g002"/></fig><p>We next searched the publications that match these candidate genes with <italic>Col3a1</italic> using PGMapper [<xref rid="B13-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Our search indicated that none of these genes has been linked to <italic>Col3a1</italic> in the literature.</p></sec><sec><title>2.3. Narrowing down the Candidate Genes for Regulation of Expression of Col3a1 on Mouse Chr 12</title><p>From our initial analysis, we found that expression of four genes are associated with that of <italic>Col3a1</italic>: <italic>Slc24a4</italic> (103.367628 MB), <italic>Rin3</italic> (103.521850 MB), <italic>Cpsf2</italic> (103.214183 MB), and <italic>Zc3h14</italic> (at 99.985177 MB). From data from the gene network analysis, we surprisingly found that membrane targeting (tandem) C2 domain containing 1 (<italic>Mtac2d1</italic>) is positively correlated to the expression of <italic>Col3a1</italic>. It is located on Chr 12, starting on 102.883731 MB, the peak region of the eQTL. These data suggests that most likely the causal gene for the regulation of expression of <italic>Col3a1</italic> is located in the genomic region nearby 103 MB.</p><p>We next conducted association analysis of these five genes with the top 44 genes that correlated to the expression level of <italic>Col3a1</italic>. We assumed that if these genes are the regulator of <italic>Col3a1</italic>, they should also influence the expression of some of these top 44 genes that are downstream of <italic>Col3a1</italic>. Gene network analysis indicated that <italic>Mtac2d1, Cpsf2</italic>, and <italic>Slc24a4</italic> interact with each other while <italic>Mtac2d1</italic> influences the expression of more than 20 of these <italic>Col3a1</italic> relevant genes. <italic>Rin3</italic> and <italic>Zc3h14</italic> interact with each other and have influence on only three of the 44 genes. Thus, the candidate gene could be <italic>Mtac2d1</italic>, <italic>Cpsf2</italic>, or <italic>Slc24a4</italic>, within the genomic region between 102.883731 MB and 103.367628 MB, based on the genome information in GeneNetwork.</p><p>We then examined the polymorphism of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPS) on these genes in each C57BL/6J X DBA/2J (BXD) strain and their expression level of <italic>Col3a1</italic>. We first searched the SNPS between C57BL/6J and DBA/2J mouse strains from MGI (Mouse Genome Informatics) database, (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.informatics.jax.org">http://www.informatics.jax.org</uri>). For each gene, we searched the gene as well as 2 kb up and down stream. <italic>Mtac2d1</italic> has no SNPS. <italic>Cpsf2</italic> has 30 SNPS including five upstream and downstream. <italic>Slc24a4</italic> contains 123 SNPS. According to the Ensembl genome database, these two genes are next to each other on Chr 12. Therefore, these two genes could be acting together or individually in regulation of <italic>Col3a1</italic> expression.</p></sec><sec><title>2.4. Gene Network of Col3a1-Related Genes in Lung in Mouse Model</title><p>Using data on the expression level of Probe 1427883 and whole genome expression profiles in the recombinant inbred (RI) strains, we identified the top 100 probes of genes with expression levels most correlated to that of <italic>Col3a1</italic> from the mouse data of HZI Lung M430v2 (Apr08) RMA Database (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Table S3 and Figure S2</xref>). The expression of mouse <italic>Col3a1</italic> is most positively correlated to procollagen, type V, alpha 2 (<italic>Col5a2</italic>), procollagen, type 1, alpha 2 (<italic>Col1a2</italic>), fibrillin 1 (<italic>Fbn1</italic>), procollagen, type I, alpha 1 (<italic>Col1a1</italic>), a disintegrin-like and metalloprotease with thrombospondin type 1 motif, 12 (<italic>Adamts12</italic>), insulin-like growth factor 1 (<italic>Igf1</italic>), follistatin-like 1(<italic>Fstl1</italic>), lysyl oxidase-like 1 (<italic>Loxl1</italic>), and procollagen, type V, alpha 1(<italic>Col5a1</italic>). It negatively correlated to receptor (calcitonin) activity modifying protein 2 (<italic>Ramp2</italic>), nuclear factor of kappa light chain gene enhancer in B-cells inhibitor, alpha (<italic>Nfkbia</italic>), sphingosine kinase 1 (<italic>Sphk1</italic>), pre-B lymphocyte gene 3 (<italic>Vpreb3</italic>), and tensin like C1 domain-containing phosphatase (<italic>Tenc1</italic>). Heatmap analysis indicated that there is a large cluster effect that significantly influences the expression of these genes (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Figure S3</xref>). For example, there is a significant difference on the effect of gene expression levels between Chr 11 and Chr 12. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f003">Figure 3</xref> shows the influence of these two chromosomes. On Chr 11 expression of the first part of genes are affected by C57BL/6J (B6) and the last part of the genes are affected by DBA/2J (D2), while on Chr 12, the effect is opposite to that on Chr 11.</p><fig id="ijms-16-15031-f003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Heatmap showing regulation of genes on Chr 11 and 12 that are closely correlated to <italic>Col3a1</italic>. The influence of these two Chrs. On Chr 11 expression of first part of genes are affected by C57BL/6J (B6) and the last part of the genes are affected by DBA/2J (D2), while on Chr 12, the effect is opposite to that on Chr 11. Orange triangles are genetic elements (probes) that are correlated to the expression level of <italic>Col3a1.</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g003"/></fig><p>With probe 1427884, we obtained the second 100 probes of genes (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Table S4</xref>). Similar to that of probe 1427883, the expression of mouse <italic>Col3a1</italic> is positively correlated to <italic>Col5a2</italic>, <italic>Col1a2</italic>, <italic>Fbn1</italic>, <italic>Col1a1</italic>, <italic>Adamts12</italic>, <italic>Igf1</italic>, <italic>Fstl1</italic>, <italic>Loxl1</italic>, and <italic>Col5a1</italic>. It is negatively correlated to <italic>Ramp2</italic>, <italic>Nfkbia</italic>, <italic>Sphk1</italic>, <italic>Vpreb3</italic>, and <italic>Tenc1</italic>. Heatmap analysis also indicated that there is large cluster effect that significantly influences the expression of these genes (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Figure S4</xref>).</p><p>By comparing the gene list between probe 1427883 and 1427884, we identified 44 genes that are in both lists (<italic>Adamts12</italic>, <italic>Caskin2</italic>, <italic>Cdh11</italic>, <italic>Cds2</italic>, Cep55, <italic>Col1a1</italic>, <italic>Col1a2</italic>, <italic>Col5a1</italic>, <italic>Col5a2</italic>, <italic>Col5a3</italic>, <italic>Cpeb1</italic>, <italic>Ect2</italic>, <italic>Fbn1</italic>, <italic>Fstl1</italic>, <italic>Gja1</italic>, <italic>Gnptg</italic>, <italic>Hmmr</italic>, <italic>Igf1</italic>, <italic>Inf2</italic>, <italic>Klf15</italic>, <italic>Leftb</italic>, <italic>Lims2</italic>, <italic>Loxl1</italic>, <italic>Lpar4</italic>, <italic>Mapk12</italic>, <italic>Mcf2l</italic>, Mknk2, <italic>Mtac2d1</italic>, <italic>Nfkbia</italic>, <italic>Nid1</italic>, <italic>Otud7b</italic>, <italic>Pak4</italic>, <italic>Patz1</italic>, <italic>Pdxk</italic>, <italic>Pof1b</italic>, <italic>Ppp1r13b</italic>, <italic>Ptpla</italic>, <italic>Ramp2</italic>, <italic>Rhebl1</italic>, <italic>Sphk1</italic>, <italic>Tenc1</italic>, <italic>Tmem45a</italic>, <italic>Wdr5b</italic>, <italic>Wdt2</italic>). We used the 44 probes of these genes and two probes of <italic>Col3a1</italic> in the construction of the network of key genes in the <italic>Col3a1</italic> pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f004">Figure 4</xref>A). During the construction of the network, we selected one probe from each of these genes. In case of multiple probes, one probe with highest expression level and commonly associated with two probes of <italic>Col3a1</italic> is chosen.</p><fig id="ijms-16-15031-f004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Gene network of 44 common genes from two probes. The 46 nodes in the graph below show the selected probes. Only nodes with edges are displayed. The 866 edges between the nodes, filtered from the 1035 total edges and drawn as curves, show Pearson correlation coefficients greater than 0.35 or less than &#x02212;0.35. The graph&#x02019;s canvas is 40.0 by 40.0 cm, and the node labels are drawn with a 14.0 point font, and the edge labels are drawn with a 14.0 point font; (<bold>B</bold>) Two probes of <italic>Col3a1</italic> show their positive correlation with 22 genes in mice. The 74 nodes in the graph below show the selected genes. Only nodes with edges are displayed. The 431 edges between the nodes, filtered from the 2701 total edges and drawn as lines, show Pearson correlation coefficients greater than 0.5 or less than &#x02212;0.5. The graph&#x02019;s canvas is 40.0 by 40.0 cm, and the node labels are drawn with a 14.0 point font, and the edge labels are drawn with a 14.0 point font.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g004a"/><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g004b"/></fig><p>According to the final network of these genes, the following genes are up-regulated by <italic>Col3a1</italic>: <italic>Adamts12</italic>, <italic>Cdh11</italic>, Cep55, <italic>Col1a1</italic>, <italic>Col1a2</italic>, <italic>Col5a1</italic>, <italic>Col5a2</italic>, <italic>Col5a3</italic>, <italic>Ect2</italic>, <italic>Fbn1</italic>, <italic>Fstl1</italic>, <italic>Gja1</italic>, <italic>Hmmr</italic>, <italic>Igf1</italic>, <italic>Loxl1</italic>, <italic>Lpar4</italic>, <italic>Mtac2d1</italic>, <italic>Nid1</italic>, <italic>Pof1b</italic>, <italic>Ptpla</italic>, <italic>Tmem45a</italic>, <italic>Wdt2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f004">Figure 4</xref>B). The following genes are down-regulated by <italic>Col3a1</italic>: <italic>Caskin2</italic>, <italic>Cds2</italic>, <italic>Cpeb1</italic>, <italic>Gnptg</italic>, <italic>Inf2</italic>, <italic>Klf15</italic>, <italic>Leftb</italic>, <italic>Lims2</italic>, <italic>Mapk12</italic>, <italic>Mcf2l</italic>, Mknk2, <italic>Nfkbia</italic>, <italic>Otud7b</italic>, <italic>Patz1</italic>, <italic>Pdxk</italic>, <italic>Ppp1r13b</italic>, <italic>Ramp2</italic>, <italic>Rhebl1</italic>, <italic>Sphk1</italic>, <italic>Tenc1</italic>, <italic>Wdr5b</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f005">Figure 5</xref>). One probe of <italic>Col3a1</italic> is negatively while the other is positively correlated to that of <italic>Pak4</italic>.</p><fig id="ijms-16-15031-f005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Two probes of <italic>Col3a1</italic> show their negative correlation with 21 genes in mice. The 23 nodes in the graph below show the selected traits. All nodes are displayed. The 69 edges between the nodes, filtered from the 253 total edges and drawn as curves, show Pearson correlation coefficients greater than 0.6 or less than &#x02212;0.6. The graph&#x02019;s canvas is 40.0 by 40.0 cm, and the node labels are drawn with a 16.0 point font, and the edge labels are drawn with a 16.0 point font.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g005"/></fig></sec><sec><title>2.5. Gene Network of COL3A1 in Lung in Humans</title><p>We then analyzed the gene network of <italic>COL3A1</italic> using data in Super Series GSE23546 Whole-Genome GXD Non-Tumorous Human Lung Tissues Affy HuRSTA array (RMA Database [<xref rid="B14-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]). From the data, we found four probes for <italic>COL3A1</italic> (Probe ID: 100149328_TGI_at, 100303661_TGI_at, 100310834_TGI_at, 100312190_TGI_at). They are all located on Chr 2 in the same region (Chr 2: 189.839099). Probe 100312190_TGI_at has the lowest mean expression level. While the expression levels of other three probes are all higher than 11 (relative expression level used in GeneNetwork), the expression level of probe 100312190_TGI_at is 7.6. Correlation analysis indicated that probe 100312190 is not strongly correlated to the expression levels of other three probes (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Figure S5</xref>). Accordingly, probe 00312190 was not used in the further analysis.</p><p>By comparing the top 100 probes lists (presenting approximately 70 genes) for the association to the three probes (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Tables S5&#x02013;S7 and Figure S6A&#x02013;C</xref>), we identified 41 genes that correlate to the expression of all three probes of <italic>COL3A1</italic>, <italic>CCDC80</italic>, <italic>CD248</italic>, <italic>CERCAM</italic>, <italic>COL14A1</italic>, <italic>COL15A1</italic>, <italic>COL1A1</italic>, <italic>COL1A2</italic>, <italic>COL4A1</italic>, <italic>COL5A1</italic>, <italic>COL5A2</italic>, <italic>COL6A1</italic>, <italic>COL6A3</italic>, <italic>CPXM1</italic>, <italic>CTHRC1</italic>, <italic>DCLK1</italic>, <italic>DIO2</italic>, <italic>DOK5</italic>, <italic>FBLN2</italic>, <italic>FBN1</italic>, <italic>FKBP10</italic>, <italic>FMO1</italic>, FNDC1, <italic>GPX8</italic>, IGDCC4, <italic>IGF1</italic>, <italic>MFAP2</italic>, <italic>MOXD1</italic>, <italic>MXRA5</italic>, <italic>MXRA5</italic>, <italic>OLFML2B</italic>, <italic>P4HA3</italic>, <italic>PCOLCE</italic>, <italic>POSTN</italic>, PPIC, <italic>PTGFRN</italic>, <italic>SCG5</italic>, <italic>SULF2</italic>, <italic>THBS2</italic>, <italic>THY1</italic>, <italic>TUBB3</italic>, <italic>VCAN</italic>). Unlike mouse lung, in human lung these genes are all positively correlated to the expression of <italic>COL3A1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f006">Figure 6</xref>A).</p></sec><sec><title>2.6. Potential Difference in Regulation of Expression of COL3A1 between Human and Mice</title><p>We identified the probes of 16 candidate genes from the human gene expression data, based on the 16 genes from mouse eQTL data. We analyzed the correlation between their expression levels and that of all probes of <italic>COL3A1</italic> in humans. Data showed that none of these genes had expression levels associated to that of <italic>COL3A1</italic> (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Figure S7</xref>A).</p><p>We then examined the association between these same 16 genes with <italic>COL3A1</italic> in the data of RNAseq, which is from a different human population [<xref rid="B14-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B15-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The data again showed that the expression of <italic>COL3A1</italic> does not have correlation with the expression level of any of these 16 genes (<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-16-15031">Figure S7</xref>B).</p><p>These data suggest that potentially there is a difference in regulation of <italic>Col3a1</italic> in mice and <italic>COL3A1</italic> in humans.</p></sec><sec><title>2.7. Gene Network between Mice and Humans</title><p>Comparing data from mice and humans, we found that several key genes overlap between mice and humans including <italic>COL1A1</italic>, <italic>COL1A2</italic>, <italic>COL5A1</italic>, <italic>COL5A2</italic>, <italic>FBN1</italic>, and <italic>IGF1</italic>. However, there are apparently some significant differences. In humans, <italic>COL3A1</italic> correlates to <italic>COL14A1</italic>, <italic>COL15A1</italic>, <italic>COL4A1</italic>, <italic>COL6A1</italic>, and <italic>COL6A3</italic>, but these genes are not among the top list in mice. Therefore, we further compared the gene network of mice and humans.</p><p>We searched the probes of these 41 human genes in the mouse microarray data and examined their association with <italic>Col3a1</italic>. We obtained a total of 87 probes for these genes. Data showed that although some of these genes are not in the list of the top 100 most closely correlated probes of genes, most of them are positively correlated in mice to the <italic>Col3a1</italic> (<italic>R</italic> &#x02265; 0.5) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f006">Figure 6</xref>B). Exceptions are <italic>Sulf2</italic>, <italic>Mfap2</italic>, <italic>Scg5</italic>, and <italic>Fkbp10</italic>. These four genes are not associated with <italic>Col3a1</italic> in mice. The other difference is that <italic>Gpx8</italic> is negatively correlated to <italic>Ptgfrn</italic>, One probe of <italic>Sulf2</italic> is negatively correlated to <italic>Scg5</italic> while the other is negatively correlated to that of <italic>Fkbp10</italic>. Interestingly, one of the two probes of <italic>Col1a2</italic> is negatively correlated to one of the <italic>Col6a3</italic> and <italic>Fbn1</italic>.</p><fig id="ijms-16-15031-f006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Gene networks of common genes in mice and humans. Each subfigure shows Pearson correlation coefficients greater than 0.5 or less than &#x02212;0.5. The graph&#x02019;s canvas is 40.0 by 40.0 cm, and the node labels are drawn with a 14.0 point font, and the edge labels are drawn with a 14.0 point font. (<bold>A</bold>) Gene network of 41 common genes and <italic>COL3A1</italic> in human lung with probe 100149328. The 42 nodes in the graph below show the selected traits. All nodes are displayed. The 566 edges between the nodes, filtered from the 861 total edges and drawn as curves; (<bold>B</bold>) Correlations between the 41 common top human genes with <italic>Col3a1</italic> in mouse lung. The 89 nodes in the graph below show the selected traits. Only nodes with edges are displayed. The 289 edges between the nodes were filtered from the 3916 total edges and drawn as lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g006a"/><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g006b"/></fig><p>We then searched the probes of 44 mouse genes from human microarray data and compared them to the expression levels of probes of <italic>COL3A1</italic> in humans. We obtained 104 probes for these 44genes. We found that the majority of genes showed association with <italic>COL3A1</italic> in human lung (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f007">Figure 7</xref>A). However, <italic>PTPLA</italic> showed no connections to <italic>COL3A1</italic>.</p><p>We then further examined whether the 22 genes up-regulated or down-regulated by <italic>Col3a1</italic> in mice are the same in humans [<xref rid="B16-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. A total of 56 probes were identified for the 22 up-regulated genes. While most of these genes are positively correlated with each other, a few negative correlations were observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f007">Figure 7</xref>B). <italic>COL1A2</italic> showed a negative correlation to <italic>TC2N</italic>. <italic>LPAR4</italic> showed a negative correlation with <italic>ECT2</italic>, which is positively correlated to <italic>HMMR</italic> and <italic>CEP55</italic>. Thus, the <italic>COL3A1</italic> network down-regulates the expression of <italic>TC2N</italic> through <italic>COL1A2</italic>. The <italic>COL3A1</italic> network down-regulates <italic>ECT2</italic>, <italic>HMMR</italic> and <italic>CEP55</italic> through <italic>LPAR4</italic>.</p><p>We next analyzed the 21 genes down-regulated by mouse <italic>Col3a1</italic> in humans. A total of 48 probes were identified from gene expression profiles of human lung. Surprisingly, there is no strong connection (Pearson correlation coefficients greater than 0.5 or less than &#x02212;0.5) to these genes from any of three probes of <italic>COL3A1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f007">Figure 7</xref>C). When the criteria is lowered to the Pearson correlation coefficients greater than 0.35 or less than &#x02212;0.35, <italic>COL3A1</italic> showed a weak negative correlation with <italic>OTUD7B</italic> and <italic>CASKIN2</italic>. Combining the information with the genes that are up-regulated, it seems that the <italic>COL3A1</italic> may down-regulate these genes through the up-regulated genes. <italic>COL1A2</italic> seems to play a major role in the negative regulation of these genes. The other pathway may be through <italic>LPAR4</italic>, which is negatively correlated to INF2 and CDS2.</p></sec><sec><title>2.8. Potential Differences in Gene Network of COL3A1 between Humans and Mice</title><p>The above analyses allowed us to identify potential differences in the gene networks of mice and humans. In order to define the difference in the gene network of <italic>COL3A1</italic> between mice and humans, we further constructed a network using core genes that showed differences between humans and mice. We first used the eight <italic>COL3A1</italic> up-regulated genes in humans, <italic>SULF2</italic>, <italic>FKBP10</italic>, <italic>COL6A3</italic>, <italic>GPX8</italic>, <italic>PTGFRN</italic>, <italic>COL1A2</italic>, <italic>SCG5</italic>, <italic>FGN1</italic>, and <italic>MFAP2</italic> to construct the network in mice. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f008">Figure 8</xref>A, in mice, only collagens and <italic>Fbn1</italic> are strongly positively correlated together. The expression of <italic>Sulf2</italic>, <italic>Mfap2</italic>, <italic>Scg5</italic>, and <italic>Fkpb10</italic> are not associated to the expression of <italic>Col3a1</italic>. <italic>Gpx8</italic> is weakly positively associated with <italic>Col3a1</italic>. In humans, the expression of all of these genes is positively associated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f008">Figure 8</xref>B). We next examined the difference of 11 key genes originally from analysis of mouse expression profiles (<italic>Ect2</italic>, <italic>Hmmr</italic>, <italic>Cep55</italic>, <italic>Lpar4</italic>, <italic>Col1a2</italic>, <italic>Col3a1</italic>, <italic>Lpar4</italic>, <italic>Cep55</italic>, <italic>Ptpla</italic>, <italic>Otud7b</italic>, or <italic>Caskin2</italic>). We found a total of 23 records from the mouse data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f008">Figure 8</xref>C). Most of these genes are negatively associated to the expression level of <italic>Col3a1</italic>. Particularly, the expression of <italic>Col3a1</italic> is strongly negatively correlated to that of <italic>Caskin2</italic> and <italic>Otud7b. Col3a1</italic> is positively associated to <italic>Ptp1a</italic> and <italic>Cep55</italic>. In humans, while the core part of the gene network is similar to that of the mice, probes of <italic>OTUD7B</italic>, <italic>PTPLA</italic>, <italic>CEP55</italic> and <italic>ECT2</italic> are not or not directly associated with other genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-16-15031-f008">Figure 8</xref>D). By GeneSet analysis, we found that, among the differentially regulated genes, four genes belong to the extracellular region, <italic>COL1A2</italic>, <italic>MFAP2</italic>, <italic>CEP55</italic>, and <italic>SULF2</italic>. <italic>COL1A2</italic>, <italic>SULF2</italic>, <italic>PTGFRN</italic>, and <italic>PTPLA</italic> are also located on the endoplasmic reticulum. <italic>LPAR4</italic> and <italic>ECT2</italic> are lipid binding proteins. In summary, the pathways of <italic>Sulf2</italic>, <italic>Mfap2</italic>, <italic>Scg5</italic>, <italic>Fkpb10</italic>, <italic>Gpx8</italic>, <italic>Oud7b</italic>, <italic>Ptpla</italic>, <italic>Cep55</italic> and <italic>Ect2</italic> in relation to <italic>Col3a1</italic> are potentially different between mice and humans.</p><fig id="ijms-16-15031-f007" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Gene network of top collated genes in mice and humans. Each figure shows Pearson correlation coefficients greater than 0.5 or less than &#x02212;0.5. The graph&#x02019;s canvas is 40.0 by 40.0 cm, and the node labels are drawn with a 14.0 point font, and the edge labels are drawn with a 14.0 point font. (<bold>A</bold>) Correlation between <italic>COL3A1</italic> and 104 probes of top 44 genes in mice in human lung. The 107 nodes in the graph below show the selected traits. Only nodes with edges are displayed. The 517 edges between the nodes were filtered from the 5671 total edges and drawn as lines; (<bold>B</bold>) Gene network between <italic>COL3A1</italic> and 22 unregulated genes selected from mice in human lung tissues. The 59 nodes in the graph below show the selected traits. Only nodes with edges are displayed. The 386 edges between the nodes were filtered from the 1711 total edges and drawn as lines; (<bold>C</bold>) The gene network between <italic>COL3A1</italic> and 21 down-regulated genes selected from mice in human lung tissues. The 51 nodes in the graph below show the selected traits. Only nodes with edges are displayed. The 83 edges between the nodes were filtered from the 1275 total edges and drawn as lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g007a"/><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g007b"/><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g007c"/></fig><fig id="ijms-16-15031-f008" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Summary of the gene networks of humans and mice. Each picture shows Pearson correlation coefficients greater than 0.5 or less than &#x02212;0.5. The graph&#x02019;s canvas is 40.0 by 40.0 cm, and the node labels are drawn with a 16.0 point font, and the edge labels are drawn with a 16.0 point font. Solid lines represent strong correlation (absolute value: thick line = 0.7&#x02013;1; thin line = 0.5&#x02013;0.7), while dashed lines present weak correlation (absolute value: 0&#x02013;0.5). (<bold>A</bold>) Summary of the network of human-positive genes in mice. The 23 nodes in the graph below show the selected genes. The 30 edges between the nodes were filtered from the 253 total edges and drawn as curves; (<bold>B</bold>) Summary of the network of positive genes in human microarray data. The 33 nodes in the graph below show the selected genes. All nodes are displayed. The 288 edges between the nodes were filtered from the 528 total edges and drawn as curves. The graph&#x02019;s canvas is 40.0 by 40.0 cm; (<bold>C</bold>) Summary of network of mouse genes: the 23 nodes in the graph below show the selected genes. The 66 edges between the nodes were filtered from the 253 total edges and drawn as curves; (<bold>D</bold>) Summary of gene network genes from mice in human microarray data. The 25 nodes in the graph below show the selected genes. The 55 edges between the nodes were filtered from the 300 total edges and drawn as curves.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g008a"/><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-g008b"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>3. Discussion</title><p>Our analysis revealed key differences in the regulation of <italic>COL3A1</italic> between humans and mice. While many genetic elements may influence the expression of <italic>Col3a1</italic> in mice, the eQTL on Chr 12 is one of the genetic factors that regulates the expression of <italic>Col3a1</italic>. We found that the expression levels of at least two genes within the eQTL region are negatively associated with that of <italic>Col3a1</italic> in mice. The homologous region on human chromosome 7 does not seem to have any gene expression correlated to the expression of <italic>COL3A1</italic>. Although the eQTL is only at the suggestive level, the same genomic region was mapped by two probes, suggesting that it is a reliable locus; such a difference deserves further investigation. The opposite effect on several genes between mice and humans raises caution on the using mouse model for the study of <italic>COL3A1</italic> relevant lung diseases in humans. Among nine genes that are positively correlated to the expression of <italic>COL3A1</italic> in humans, some are not connected and others are not positively correlated to <italic>Col3a1</italic> in mice. Surprisingly, none of these genes have been studied together with <italic>Col3a1</italic>, based on searching the PubMed database. They apparently have not yet been brought to the attention of investigators studying lung diseases such as lung fibrosis. Some of these genes in fact have been linked to lung fibrosis. For example, <italic>SULF2</italic> is over expressed in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis [<xref rid="B19-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. <italic>CEP55</italic> has been reported to contain polymorphisms significantly associated with bleomycin-induced fibrotic lung disease [<xref rid="B20-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. There is a report on the developmental regulation and coordinate reexpression of <italic>FKBP65</italic> (<italic>Fkpb10</italic>) with extracellular matrix proteins after lung injury [<xref rid="B21-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In genome-wide association study and large-scale follow up, <italic>MFAP2</italic> has been identified as one of the candidate genes influencing lung function [<xref rid="B22-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>We believe that it is important to investigate whether the expression of these genes is altered by <italic>COL3A1</italic>, or other closely related collagen family members, in relevant diseases. Perhaps one of the big misleading concepts resulting from elucidation of the first human and mouse genome sequences is that genes in both are almost the same [<xref rid="B23-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="B26-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. While it is true that the majority of sequences of genes between mice and humans are similar, there are many reasons for the failure in clinic trails in humans of the majority of drugs derived from studies using animal models. One of the reasons may be the lack of awareness of the differences in molecular pathways between humans and mice when employing the animal model. Study of these differentially regulated genes is critical in the selection of molecular targets for the diseases influenced by <italic>COL3A1</italic> and its closely related collagen family members.</p><p>The difference in these genes may play essential roles in affecting differential development of lung cells between mice and humans. By their function, these differentially regulated genes are important for lung cell development. They are essential for the cellular components and organization. Particularly, <italic>MFAP2</italic> known as the microfibrillar-associated protein is important in structure and function of the extracellular matrix [<xref rid="B22-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. <italic>Sulf2</italic> mRNA is overexpressed in lung samples from human patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF), and Sulf2 protein was specifically localized to the hyperplastic type II alveolar epithelial cells (AECs) [<xref rid="B27-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Polymorphism of Cep55 has been significantly associated with bleomycin-induced fibrotic lung disease in mice [<xref rid="B20-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The differential regulation of these genes by <italic>COL3A1</italic> and <italic>COL1A2</italic> between humans and mice imposes a critical question on how these differences impact the molecular consequence and the disease phenotype.</p><p>Our study takes advantage of available data of whole genome gene expression profiles from mouse lung and human lung. These two sets of data have relatively large numbers of samples. The data reliability have been previously tested [<xref rid="B12-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B14-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In addition, the fact that we detected the close correlation between <italic>COL3A1</italic> and its collagen family members and <italic>IGF1</italic> further confirms the reliability of these data sets and these associations are well known [<xref rid="B19-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B22-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. For the mouse RI strains, evidently the data is accurate not only because of the homozygousity of the mouse strain but also for the repeatability of multiple mice within each strain [<xref rid="B12-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Most of the differences between mice and humans are very clear cut. For example, there is a significant negative correlation between <italic>Col3a1</italic> and <italic>Otud7b</italic> and <italic>Caskin2</italic> in mice. However, in humans, probes of <italic>OTUD7B</italic> and <italic>PTPLA</italic> are not associated with <italic>COL3A1</italic>.</p><p>The strength of the signal in microarrays sometimes is influenced by polymorphisms that are located within the sequences of probes. In our study, differentially expressed genes are detected by multiple probes [<xref rid="B12-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B27-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The chance of polymorphisms in multiple probes to have the same influence on the signal level is rare. Therefore, we feel confident of the results on the expression levels of these genes.</p><p>A clear limitation in our study is that the mouse RI strains are derived from two parental strains, the C57BL/6J and DBA/2J. Phenotypes of mouse models are known to be strain dependent [<xref rid="B28-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The molecular pathways from these two strains may not necessarily be the same with that of other strains. Nevertheless, these two strains are amongst the most popular strains used for the study of human diseases. For example, both Tsk1 and Tsk2/+ mouse models for study of human SSc are bred under B6 background [<xref rid="B5-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B30-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The human population included data from more than 1000 individuals. Therefore, we believe that the data from this study reflects the important difference between mouse models and humans.</p></sec><sec><title>4. Experimental Section</title><sec><title>4.1. Mouse Gene Expression Data Sets for Lung</title><p>Gene expression data from the mouse lung in recombinant inbred (RI) strains and standard inbred strains was done with Affy Mouse Genome 430 2.0 (GPL1261) [<xref rid="B12-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.genenetwork.org/">http://www.genenetwork.org/</uri>). The data set contains the whole gene expression profiles from 61 mouse strains, including 47 RI strains from BXD (derived from C57BL/6J and DBA/2J), two parents and two F1s, and 10 standard inbred strains.</p></sec><sec><title>4.2. Human Gene Expression Data for Lung</title><p>Human expression data include two sets from microarray and RNAseq. One set is the Super Series GSE23546 Whole-Genome GXD Non-Tumorous Human Lung Tissues Affy HuRSTA array (RMA Database). This set data from lung includes whole gene expression profiles of 1230 human samples of normal lung tissues processed with Affymetrix HuRSTA array. The gene expression data are available through GSE23546 at the GeneNetwork (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.genenetwork.org/">http://www.genenetwork.org/</uri>).</p><p>The whole-genome gene expression profiles of RNAseq data of human lung tissues in GeneNetwork were contributed by the Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) project [<xref rid="B14-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The data set of lung RNAseq currently includes RNA sequence data from 119 individuals from three data sets of whole-genome gene expression profiles of non-tumorous human lung tissues: Laval set (GSE23352), UBC set (GSE23529), and GRNG set (GSE23545). RNAseq was performed using the Illumina TruSeq library construction protocol.</p></sec><sec><title>4.3. eQTL Mapping</title><p>The GeneNetwork is capable of mapping the eQTL with conventional QTL methods, such as the Interval mapping in the GeneNetwork. Interval mapping is a process in which the statistical significance of a hypothetical QTL is evaluated at regular points across a chromosome, even in the absence of explicit genotype data at those points. In the case of eQTL, significance is calculated using an efficient and very rapid regression method: the Haley&#x02013;Knott regression equations [<xref rid="B15-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Differences in the expression of mRNA are treated as standard phenotypes. A simple regression method for mapping quantitative trait loci in line crosses using flanking markers [<xref rid="B16-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17-ijms-16-15031" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] in which trait values are compared to the known genotype at a marker or to the probability of a specific genotype at a test location between two flanking markers (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.genenetwork.org">http://www.genenetwork.org</uri>).</p></sec><sec><title>4.4. Gene Network Construction</title><p>The gene network was constructed using tools in GeneNetwork. The gene network was constructed based on the Network Graph in combination with the Correlation Matrix. Network graph is often used to visualize multiple sets of interactions. It consists of nodes and edges connecting nodes. In addition, the network graph can represent the strength of the interaction by the thickness of the edge&#x02014;that is, the higher the number of interactions between two nodes, the thicker the edge becomes. Different colors and lines were used to illustrate the nature and the strength of correlations between genes. Solid lines represent strong correlation (absolute value: thick line = 0.7&#x02013;1; thin line = 0.5&#x02013;0.7), while dashed lines represent weak correlation (absolute value: 0&#x02013;0.5). Red, pink and yellow colors are for positive correlations, while blue, green and black colors for negative correlations. For the Correlation Matrix, GeneNetwork provides tools to compute both Pearson product-moment correlations (the standard type of correlation) and Spearman rank order correlations. Both the Network Graph and Correlation Matrix were obtained with the same set of parameters or criteria. For example, for the Line Threshold in the Network Graph, absolute values greater than 0.35 were used across all samples. The Spring Model layout (force reduction) and circular model were used for the graphic method for all graphic samples (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.genenetwork.org/">http://www.genenetwork.org/</uri>).</p><p>In case of multiple probes, we first used all the probes in the construction of gene network. If they were all highly positively correlated, then one probe (usually the one with the highest expression level) was used for the final construction of gene network.</p></sec><sec><title>4.5. Statistical Analysis</title><p>The top genes shared by two sets of data from mice and two sets of humans on the basis of Pearson correlation, were used for plotting Network Graphs in GeneNetwork. An <italic>r</italic> absolute value &#x0003e;0.50 was considered to indicate connection line threshold (exception otherwise will be noted).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Authors thank Robert W. Williams for providing data and analytic tools in the GeneNetwork. The study was partially supported by a merit grant (I01 BX000671 to Weikuan Gu) from the Department of Veterans Affairs and the Veterans Administration Medical Center in Memphis, TN; and by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Project 81372996 to Yan Jiao). Data were provided in part by the Human Connectome Project, WU-Minn Consortium (Principal Investigators: David Van Essen and Kamil Ugurbil; 1U54MH091657) funded by the 16 National Institutes of Health and Centers that support the NIH Blueprint for Neuroscience Research; and by the McDonnell Center for Systems Neuroscience at Washington University.</p></ack><app-group><app id="app1-ijms-16-15031"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ijms-16-15031-s001"><media xlink:href="ijms-16-15031-s001.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><p>Supplementary materials can be found at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/16/07/15031/s1">http://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/16/07/15031/s1</uri>.</p></app></app-group><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Arnold E. Postlethwaite, Yan Jiao, Stephen H. Clark, Hong Chen and Weikuan Gu conceived and designed the experiments and Arnold E. Postlethwaite, Stephen H. Clark and Weikuan Gu obtained funding for the study. Lishi Wang, Hongchao Liu, Erjian Wang, Hong Chen, and Weikuan Gu performed the study, analyzed and interpreted the data. Lishi Wang and Weikuan Gu drafted the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-ijms-16-15031"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>W.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiodo</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamande</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Janeczko</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>H.-H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A base substitution at a splice site in the <italic>COL3A1</italic> gene causes exon skipping and generates abnormal type III procollagen in a patient with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome type IV</article-title>
<source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>265</volume>
<fpage>17070</fpage>
<lpage>17077</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 2145268?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2145268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2-ijms-16-15031"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarze</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schievink</surname><given-names>W.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petty</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaff</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Babovic-Vuksanovic</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Byers</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Haploinsufficiency for one <italic>COL3A1</italic> allele of type III procollagen results in a phenotype similar to the vascular form of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, Ehlers-Danlos syndrome type IV</article-title>
<source>Am. J. Hum. Genet.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>69</volume>
<fpage>989</fpage>
<lpage>1001</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/324123</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11577371?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11577371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3-ijms-16-15031"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krane</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aenisch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Type III collagen is crucial for collagen I fibrillogenesis and for normal cardiovascular development</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>94</volume>
<fpage>1852</fpage>
<lpage>1856</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.5.1852</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 9050868?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9050868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4-ijms-16-15031"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krawczyk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tae</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Talan</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Briest</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The haploinsufficient <italic>Col3a1</italic> mouse as a model for vascular Ehlers-Danlos syndrome</article-title>
<source>Vet. Pathol.</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>1028</fpage>
<lpage>1039</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0300985810374842</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20587693?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20587693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5-ijms-16-15031"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christner</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yufit</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Transcriptional activation of alpha 1(III) procollagen gene in <italic>Tsk2</italic>/+ dermal fibroblasts</article-title>
<source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>303</volume>
<fpage>406</fpage>
<lpage>412</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-291X(03)00315-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12659831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6-ijms-16-15031"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgwin</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martyanov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassi-Gaha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Earl</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eutsey</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The <italic>Tsk2</italic>/+ mouse fibrotic phenotype is due to a gain-of-function mutation in the PIIINP segment of the <italic>Col3a1</italic> gene</article-title>
<source>J. Investig. Dermatol.</source>
<year>2015</year>
<volume>135</volume>
<fpage>718</fpage>
<lpage>727</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2014.455</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25330296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25330296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7-ijms-16-15031"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hock</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thannickal</surname><given-names>V.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>Y.Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Histone deacetylase inhibition downregulates collagen 3A1 in fibrotic lung fibroblasts</article-title>
<source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>19605</fpage>
<lpage>19617</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms141019605</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24084714?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24084714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8-ijms-16-15031"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sa</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ki</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Occlusive vascular Ehlers-Danlos syndrome accompanying a congenital cystic adenomatoid malformation of the lung: Report of a case</article-title>
<source>Surg. Today</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>1467</fpage>
<lpage>1469</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00595-012-0355-x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23052746?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23052746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9-ijms-16-15031"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Antifibrotic effects of crocetin in scleroderma fibroblasts and in bleomycin-induced sclerotic mice</article-title>
<source>Clinics (Sao Paulo)</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>1350</fpage>
<lpage>1357</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6061/clinics/2013(10)10</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24212843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10-ijms-16-15031"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Artlett</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassi-Gaha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieger</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boesteanu</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feghali-Bostwick</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsikis</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The inflammasome activating caspase 1 mediates fibrosis and myofibroblast differentiation in systemic sclerosis</article-title>
<source>Arthritis Rheum.</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>3563</fpage>
<lpage>3574</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.30568</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21792841?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21792841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11-ijms-16-15031"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabo-Attwood</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos-Nino</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eugenia-Ariza</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macpherson</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Butnor</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vacek</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mossman</surname><given-names>B.T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Osteopontin modulates inflammation, mucin production, and gene expression signatures after inhalation of asbestos in a murine model of fibrosis</article-title>
<source>Am. J. Pathol.</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>178</volume>
<fpage>1975</fpage>
<lpage>1985</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajpath.2011.01.048</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21514415?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21514415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12-ijms-16-15031"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pommerenke</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilk</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Novoselova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geffers</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schughart</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Global transcriptome analysis in influenza-infected mouse lungs reveals the kinetics of innate and adaptive host immune responses</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>e41169</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0041169</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22815957?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22815957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13-ijms-16-15031"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>PGMapper: A web-based tool linking phenotype to genes</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>1011</fpage>
<lpage>1013</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn002</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18204061?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18204061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14-ijms-16-15031"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boss&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sin</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamontagne</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Couture</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaudreault</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joubert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Berge</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular signature of smoking in human lung tissues</article-title>
<source>Cancer Res.</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>72</volume>
<fpage>3753</fpage>
<lpage>3763</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-12-1160</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22659451?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22659451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15-ijms-16-15031"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lonsdale</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvatore</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) project</article-title>
<source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>580</fpage>
<lpage>585</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2653</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23715323?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23715323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16-ijms-16-15031"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knott</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A simple regression method for mapping quantitative trait loci in line crosses using flanking markers</article-title>
<source>Heredity (Edinb.)</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>69</volume>
<fpage>315</fpage>
<lpage>324</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16718932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17-ijms-16-15031"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheib</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farber</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Trps1 differentially modulates the bone mineral density between male and female mice and its polymorphism associates with BMD differently between women and men</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2014</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>e84485</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24416236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18-ijms-16-15031"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shifman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdar</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johannesson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yalcin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>High resolution mapping of expression QTLs in heterogeneous stock mice in multiple tissues</article-title>
<source>Genome Res.</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1133</fpage>
<lpage>1140</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.088120.108</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19376938?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19376938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19-ijms-16-15031"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Auduong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sides</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasky</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Overexpression of <italic>Sulf2</italic> in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title>
<source>Glycobiology</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>709</fpage>
<lpage>719</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/glycob/cwt010</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23418199?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23418199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20-ijms-16-15031"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paun</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemay</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomko</surname><given-names>T.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haston</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Association analysis reveals genetic variation altering bleomycin-induced pulmonary fibrosis in mice</article-title>
<source>Am. J. Respir. Cell Mol. Biol.</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>330</fpage>
<lpage>336</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1165/rcmb.2012-0078OC</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23239499?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23239499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21-ijms-16-15031"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolter</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenbloom</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Developmental regulation and coordinate reexpression of FKBP65 with extracellular matrix proteins after lung injury suggest a specialized function for this endoplasmic reticulum immunophilin</article-title>
<source>Cell Stress Chaperones</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>285</fpage>
<lpage>295</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1379/CSC-118R.1</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16333983?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16333983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22-ijms-16-15031"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Artigas</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loth</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wain</surname><given-names>L.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gharib</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Obeidat</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huffman</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Genome-wide association and large-scale follow up identifies 16 new loci influencing lung function</article-title>
<source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>1082</fpage>
<lpage>1090</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.941</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21946350?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21946350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23-ijms-16-15031"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstock</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodstadt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenson</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alb&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Evolutionary conservation and selection of human disease gene orthologs in the rat and mouse genomes</article-title>
<source>Genome Biol.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>R47</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2004-5-7-r47</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15239832?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15239832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24-ijms-16-15031"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kondrashov</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabalina</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Classification of common conserved sequences in mammalian intergenic regions</article-title>
<source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>669</fpage>
<lpage>674</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/11.6.669</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11912182?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11912182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25-ijms-16-15031"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swergold</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seldin</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Examination of sequence homology between human chromosome 20 and the mouse genome: Intense conservation of many genomic elements</article-title>
<source>Hum. Genet.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>113</volume>
<fpage>60</fpage>
<lpage>70</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 12644935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12644935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26-ijms-16-15031"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pevzner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Human and mouse genomic sequences reveal extensive breakpoint reuse in mammalian evolution</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>7672</fpage>
<lpage>7677</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1330369100</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12810957?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12810957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27-ijms-16-15031"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christmann</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampaio-Barros</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stifano</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Carvalho</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kairalla</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spira</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simms</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capellozzi</surname><given-names>V.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Association of Interferon- and transforming growth factor &#x003b2; regulated genes and macrophage activation with systemic sclerosis-related progressive lung fibrosis</article-title>
<source>Arthritis Rheumatol.</source>
<year>2014</year>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>714</fpage>
<lpage>725</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.38288</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24574232?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24574232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28-ijms-16-15031"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlueter</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoyle</surname><given-names>G.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Differential susceptibility of inbred mouse strains to chlorine-induced airway fibrosis</article-title>
<source>Am. J. Physiol. Lung Cell Mol. Physiol.</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>304</volume>
<fpage>L92</fpage>
<lpage>L102</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajplung.00272.2012</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23171502?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23171502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29-ijms-16-15031"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haston</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cory</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorion</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallett</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Strain-dependent pulmonary gene expression profiles of a cystic fibrosis mouse model</article-title>
<source>Physiol. Genomics</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>336</fpage>
<lpage>345</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiolgenomics.00208.2005</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16614460?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16614460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30-ijms-16-15031"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowell</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCrann</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frew</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Analysis of the tight skin (<italic>Tsk1</italic>/+) mouse as a model for testing antifibrotic agents</article-title>
<source>Lab. Investig.</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>1199</fpage>
<lpage>1209</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/labinvest.3700331</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16127425?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16127425</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>